<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Romanticism and Disaster</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
				<title level="a">Abstracts</title>
				<editor role="editor">Jacques Khalip</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<editor role="editor">David Collings</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
					<name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>abstracts</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2010-11-01">November 1, 2010</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p rend="noCount">Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
					<p rend="noCount">By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
						<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
							Circles.</item>
						<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
					</list></p>
					<p rend="noCount">Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Abstracts</title></analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Romanticism and Disaster:</title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2010-10-15">October 15, 2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p rend="noCount">All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for "," for ", ' for ', and ' for '.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p rend="noCount">Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p rend="noCount">Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p rend="noCount">&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
					<p rend="noCount">All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
				<keywords scheme="http://www.rc.umd.edu/#tags">
					<list>
						<item>keyword1</item>
						<item>keyword2</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Mike Quilligan</name>
				<date>2010-06-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="paratext">
				<head>Abstracts</head>
				<p rend="noCount"><quote rend="center"><ref target="#KhalipAbstract">Jacques Khalip and David Collings</ref> |
					<ref target="#JuengelAbstract">Scott J. Juengel</ref> | <ref target=
						"#KeachAbstract">William Keach</ref> | <ref target="#MortonAbstract">Timothy Morton</ref> | <ref target="#TeradaAbstract">Rei Terada</ref></quote></p>
				
			<!-- Authors, titles, and abstracts here -->
				<div><head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="KhalipAbstract"></anchor>Jacques Khalip and David Collings</hi>, <title level="a">Introduction: The Present Time of 'Live Ashes'</title></head>
				
					<p rend="noCount"><title level="m">Romanticism and Disaster</title> considers and responds to the timely concept of devastated life by thinking about how the capacity to read, interpret, and absorb disaster necessitates significant changes in
						theory, ethics, and common life. What if the consequences or "experience" of a disaster were less about psychic survival than an unblinking desire to face down the disaster as a challenge to normative structures? The essays in this volume attend to the rhetorical, epistemological, political, and social effects of romantic critique, and reflect on how processes of destruction and reconstitution, ruination and survival, are part and parcel of romanticism’s grappling with a negativity that haunts its corners. Put in this way, "disaster" does not signal a referential event, but rather an undoing of certain apparently prior categories of dwelling, and forces us to contemplate living otherwise. In confronting the end of things, what are the conditions or possibilities of existence amidst catastrophe? What is a crisis, and what kinds of challenges does it occasion? What can be philosophically gained or lost by analyzing disaster in its multiple sites, contexts, and instances?</p>
				
				<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2012.khalip.html">go to
					essay</ref>]<lb/></p></div>
				
				<div><head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="JuengelAbstract"></anchor>Scott J. Juengel</hi>, <title level="a">Mary Wollstonecraft's Perpetual Disaster</title></head>
				
					<p rend="noCount">This essay reads the moments in the <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark</title> (1796) in which Mary Wollstonecraft imagines future disasters and grieves for losses yet to come. Taking his cue from William Godwin's comment that her prejudices suffered a "vehement concussion" from the events of the French Revolution, Juengel argues that these moments of disastrous affect register a traumatic apprehension she cannot otherwise articulate - not even in her <title level="m">Historical and Moral View of the Origins and Progress of the French Revolution</title> (1794). Devastated by a wounding realization of revolutionary hope, Wollstonecraft is "[h]aunted by what was to have been the future," and weaves "the time of revolutionary politics with what we might call 'species time,' resulting in forms of untimeliness that figure as disaster without end." Her sense of this disaster, so threatening to the value of individual lives, is attuned to the discovery of a planetary "deep time" that took place in the decades before and after the 1790s and to the prospect, articulated two years later by Malthus, of an ongoing "disaster of sensation and feeling that paradoxically moves the species toward life rather than death." Yet all these untimely reflections may enable her to avoid confronting the disasters of the present, such as the consequences of the fire that destroyed large portions of Copenhagen just before her arrival there; the thought of disaster, she suggests, would relieve her from the task of treading on "live ashes," on ills not yet reduced to scenes in fancy. Ultimately, Juengel argues, these movements of disastrous thought may all speak of what Reinhardt Koselleck describes as the radical temporalization of revolutionary time, a temporalization to which Wollstonecraft ultimately responds with a generous passivity, with a more-than-Kantian hospitality to disaster itself.</p>
				
				<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2012.juengel.html">go to
					essay</ref>]<lb/></p></div>
				
				<div><head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="KeachAbstract"></anchor>William Keach</hi>, <title level="a">The Ruins of Empire and the Contradictions of Restoration: Barbauld, Byron, Hemans</title></head>
				
					<p rend="noCount">This essay explores how Regency ruin culture developed at once as the apogee and the ambivalently repressive (and repressed) symptom of British imperialism, articulating the nuances of “Britain’s role in determining the trajectory of the Napoleonic imperial project at moments unstably situated between triumph and catastrophe, commercial and military pre-eminence and social crisis.” Working through Walter Benjamin's comments on ruination in <title level="m">The Arcades Project</title>, Keach marks out how the difference between a “canonical” and “critical” ruin culture depends on gestures of delayed fascination tempered by an “awakening” that throws the ruin into sudden critical knowledge. For Keach, the ruin is indelibly coupled to restoration, thus producing a double movement of destruction and reconstruction that not only operates separately, but is intrinsic to the ideology of the ruin. As fragment, the ruin figures as a remainder of other cultures newly “acquired” and transmuted into the mournful excesses that haunt their reinstallment in pre- and post-Waterloo Britain. Even more, it either constitutes a celebratory surplus that hints at renovation or offers itself as unyielding matter—the debris of political and social violence.</p>
				
				<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2012.keach.html">go to
					essay</ref>]<lb/></p></div>
				
				<div><head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="MortonAbstract"></anchor>Timothy Morton</hi>, <title level="a">Romantic Disaster Ecology: Blake, Shelley, Wordsworth</title></head>
				
					<p rend="noCount">Our world appears to be on the brink of disaster, an appearance that is itself disastrous. The disaster of disaster is that disaster is everywhere, all the time: while on the one hand it appears obvious that disaster should be the exception that proves the rule of a generally non-disastrous world, in actuality no non-disastrous moment arrives. Like a deer in the headlights, thinking is paralyzed by disaster. Do Romantic texts reinforce this problematic state of affairs, or resist it, and if so, how?</p>				
				<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2012.morton.html">go to
					essay</ref>]<lb/></p></div>
				
				<div><head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="TeradaAbstract"></anchor>Rei Terada</hi>, <title level="a">Hegel's Bearings</title></head>
				
					<p rend="noCount">In her essay, Rei Terada ponders Hegel's style of "tarrying with the negative," particularly with the narrowing of political possibility in German territories both under Napoleonic liberalization and after Waterloo. In correspondence with his friend Friedrich Immanuel Niethammer, who states his wish to persist in fighting a losing cause even - or especially - if he is the "last man" to do so, as if to find sustenance in his inability to bear his dark times. Hegel bears up in another manner, seeking a middle way that "<emph>allows</emph> nothing to get too bad and nothing too good." Rather than trusting himself to a truly open history, Terada argues, Hegel protects the civic life of the middle class, but in doing so he also carries through on a philosophy in which "another middle, the middle of transition, always rules the world." Drawing on a description of a dream Hegel sends to his friend, in which "a certain realist calculation and foresight is implicit," his critique of "the mirror reifications of empiricism and idealism" in the <title level="m">Logic</title>, and his account in the <title level="m">Encyclopedia</title> of how the subject, reading every negativity that comes from outside as actually from inside, can become "a being capable of containing and enduring its own contradiction," Terada shows how Hegel becomes a "privileged figure of the new dispensation," someone capable of enduring "the horizonless condition of an antipolitical society that extends from the late Napoleonic era to our own."</p>
				
				<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2012.terada.html">go to
					essay</ref>]<lb/></p></div>
				
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
