<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">John Thelwall: Critical Reassessments</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
				<title level="a">Abstracts</title>

				<editor>Yasmin Solomonescu</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
					<name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>abstracts</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
					Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2010-11-01">September 1, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
						or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
						purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
						use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
						are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
						with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
						permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
						requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
						forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
						conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
						them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
						have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
						Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
						continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
						a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
						use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Abstracts</title>


					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">John Thelwall: Critical Reassessments</title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
								Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2010-10-15">October 15, 2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for "," for ", ' for
						', and ' for '.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
						keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
						such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
						been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
					12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
						on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>David Rettenmaier</name>
				<date>2011-05-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="paratext">
				<head>Abstracts</head>
				<p rend="noCount"><quote rend="center"><ref target="#SolomonescuAbstract">Yasmin
							Solomonescu</ref> | <ref target="#RoeAbstract">Nicholas Roe</ref> | <ref
							target="#FaircloughAbstract">Mary Fairclough</ref> | <ref
							target="#DesjardinsAbstract">Molly Desjardins</ref> | <ref
							target="#StanbackAbstract">Emily B. Stanback</ref> | <ref
							target="#PooleAbstract">Steve Poole</ref> | <ref
							target="#EsterhammerAbstract">Angela Esterhammer</ref> | <ref
							target="#O'BoyleAbstract">Patty O’Boyle</ref>
					</quote></p>

				<!-- Authors, titles, and abstracts here -->
				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="SolomonescuAbstract"/>Yasmin
							Solomonescu</hi>, <title level="a">Introduction</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">This essay introduces the Romantic-period political reformer
						and polymath John Thelwall and takes stock of his rapid critical renaissance
						over the past decade. The announcement of a new archival find, a copy of a
						seventeenth-century play owned and annotated by Thelwall, serves to
						highlight the range of his interests and activities. Presenting Thelwall as
						a leading representative of “romantic sociability,” I situate him within
						wider social and intellectual networks than have hitherto been mapped, and I
						raise questions about the coherence and continuity of his diverse
						pursuits&#8212;literary, political, and scientific&#8212;that demand further
						attention. My brief overview of the essays collected here emphasizes how
						they address those questions, engaging with one another, with existing
						Thelwall scholarship, and with Romantic studies more generally. This
						introduction also sets forth the rationale for the volume as part of the
						larger project <title level="m">John Thelwall: Recovery and
							Reassessments</title> (forthcoming) and explains why Romantic Circles is
						an especially appropriate venue for that project’s efforts to advance
						Thelwall studies by reconnecting text, voice, and image in the dynamic way
						for which Thelwall himself was renowned.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.solomonescu.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="RoeAbstract"/>Nicholas Roe</hi>, <title
							level="a">John Thelwall and the West Country: The Road to Nether Stowey
							Revisited</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">This article presents arguments for continuities in John
						Thelwall’s life and career from the early 1790s through to the new century,
						post-1800. Thelwall’s westward migration in 1797 is explored in detail, as
						is the publication of his essay "The Phenomena of the Wye" in the <title
							level="j">Monthly Magazine</title> for May and July of 1798.
						Consideration is given to Thelwall’s various identities, and to the
						political/cultural significances of England’s west country between 1797 and
						1819. Thelwall’s friendship with Coleridge is assessed in the light of
						intractable differences between the two men. </p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.roe.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="FaircloughAbstract"/>Mary Fairclough</hi>,
							<title level="a">John Thelwall and the Politics of the
							Picturesque</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">This essay explores the political significance of John
						Thelwall’s engagement with the discourse of the picturesque in his travel
						writing of the 1790s. E. P. Thompson asserted that Thelwall’s turn to travel
						writing in the immediate aftermath of his metropolitan radical career
						demonstrated the success of the authorities in driving him out of politics.
						For Thompson, Thelwall’s essays “A Pedestrian Excursion” and “The Phenomena
						of the Wye” (1798-1801) were “conventional” and “unremarkable” examples of
						the picturesque tour, in which Thelwall reneged on his reformist principles
						by failing to engage with the working people he encountered. Recent critical
						accounts have defended Thelwall against Thompson’s charge by accentuating
						the sociological emphasis of the pedestrian tours and playing down
						Thelwall’s engagement with the picturesque. This essay argues that it is
						precisely through an exploration of the picturesque that Thelwall finds a
						new medium for the articulation of his political ideals. Thelwall’s turn to
						the picturesque is not just a response to political harassment. <title
							level="m">The Peripatetic</title> (1793) demonstrates Thelwall’s
						long-held fascination with visual forms, though it expresses distrust at the
						abstracting effects of spectatorship. In <title level="m">The
							Peripatetic</title>, Thelwall begins an exploration of alternative means
						of “seeing,” namely the material exploration of both the landscape and
						social configurations. This exploration is continued and refined in the
						“Pedestrian Excursion” and “Phenomena of the Wye,” where the language of
						Thelwall’s descriptions of landscape anticipate his engagement with the
						politics of free speech in his elocutionary writings of the next decade.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.fairclough.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="DesjardinsAbstract"/>Molly
						Desjardins</hi>, <title level="a">John Thelwall and
						Association</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">John Thelwall’s elocutionary career has frequently been
						understood as a renunciation of his revolutionary politics. This essay
						questions such an assessment. I argue that once we understand the
						associationist model of mind that guides both Thelwall’s elocutionary work
						and his political philosophy, we see that throughout his career Thelwall was
						pursuing a common end: strengthening associations in the minds that
						inhabited, and created, the public sphere.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.desjardins.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="StanbackAbstract"/>Emily B. Stanback</hi>,
							<title level="a">Disability and Dissent: Thelwall’s Elocutionary
							Project</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">This essay argues for a reassessment of John Thelwall’s career
						as an elocutionary scientist in light of recent work in the history of
						medicine and Disability Studies. Traditionally understood as
						apolitical&#8212;at least in comparison to his involvement in radical
						politics and materialist science&#8212;Thelwall’s therapeutic endeavor
						should instead be recognized as significantly demonstrating his continued
						dedication to democratic ideals. Thelwall’s elocutionary texts are, in fact,
						provocatively egalitarian, and as an elocutionary scientist Thelwall
						actively resisted the normative views of disability that were beginning to
						consolidate during the era.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.stanback.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="PooleAbstract"/>Steve Poole</hi>, <title
							level="a">Gillray, Cruikshank &amp; Thelwall: Visual Satire, Physiognomy
							and the Jacobin Body</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">In the years following his acquittal for High Treason in 1794,
						John Thelwall came to personify all that English loyalists most feared about
						the plebeian democrats of the London Corresponding Society. In loyalist
						discourse, he became at one and the same time, an intemperate but horribly
						effective Jacobin orator, and a covert conspirator working quietly behind
						the scenes to ally the Foxite opposition with the LCS and some of its
						insurrectionary fellow travellers. The apparent disjuncture in Thelwall's
						character between public bluster and private plotting presented a unique set
						of problems for loyalist caricature, explicitly demonstrated in the practice
						of the best known ministerial cartoonists of the period, Rowlandson,
						Cruikshank and Gillray. This essay explores some of the ways in which this
						dichotomy was resolved in visual culture, and assesses the impact of popular
						prints like these on the manufacturing of Thelwall's political reputation. </p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.poole.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="EsterhammerAbstract"/>Angela
							Esterhammer</hi>, <title level="a">John Thelwall’s Panoramic Miscellany:
							The Lecturer as Journalist</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">From January to June 1826, Thelwall edited, wrote, and
						marketed <title level="j">The Panoramic Miscellany</title>, a monthly
						periodical that demonstrates his ongoing commitment to political causes,
						public education, elocutionary training, and literary criticism. This essay
						examines the context and contents of the little-known <title level="j"
							>Panoramic Miscellany</title>, showing that Thelwall’s editorial policy
						and discursive practice depend heavily on his experience as lecturer and
						educator and that the <title level="j">Panoramic Miscellany</title> stands
						out for its international perspective, its attention to women writers, and
						the integrity of its book reviews. The unsuccessful attempt of Thelwall the
						lecturer to become an independent journalist offers insights into the
						experimental and volatile media context of the 1820s.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.esterhammer.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="O'BoyleAbstract"/>Patty O'Boyle</hi>,
							<title level="a">'A Son of John Thelwall': Weymouth Birkbeck Thelwall’s
							Romantic Inheritance</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">This essay traces the meandering career of Weymouth Birkbeck
						Thelwall, the son of John Thelwall and his former pupil and second wife, the
						young and beautiful Henrietta Cecil Boyle. Born on the eve of reform and
						near the end of John Thelwall’s life, Weymouth followed in his father’s
						artistic, adventurous and amorous footsteps; creating his own peripatetic
						journey which led him eventually to a tragic and isolated death in colonial
						Nyasaland. His life narrative graphically illustrates how the Romantic
						idealism espoused by eighteenth- and nineteenth-century radicals; the reforms in
						education, and the civil and religious liberties which they campaigned for
						had unlooked for consequences, culminating in the late Victorian grab for
						Africa figured in Joseph Conrad’s <title level="m">Heart of Darkness</title>. In Weymouth Thelwall we
						have a true “son of John Thelwall” and a strangely prophetic model of Mr.
						Kurz: citizen, artist, journalist and romantic idealist&#8212;with an eye to the
						main chance and a defiant propensity to take one too many risks.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.oboyle.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
