<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">John Thelwall: Critical Reassessments</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">John Thelwall and the Politics of the Picturesque</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mary Fairclough</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Yasmin Solomonescu</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.fairclough</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2010-11-01">September 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">John Thelwall and the Politics of the
                     Picturesque</title>

                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Mary</forename>
                        <surname>Fairclough</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">John Thelwall: Critical Reassessments</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2010-10-15">October 15, 2010</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for "," for ", ' for ',
                  and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2011-05-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay" n="4">
            <head>John Thelwall and the Politics of the Picturesque</head>
            <byline><docAuthor>Mary Fairclough</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>University of Huddersfield</affiliation>
            </byline>



            <p>John Thelwall was, for E. P. Thompson, one of the most remarkable figures and
               “considerable theorists” of the British reform movement in the 1790s (<title
                  level="m">Making</title> 172-73). But Thompson asserts that Thelwall’s
               achievements were not sustained in the sequel to the metropolitan radical phase of
               his career, in which between 1798 and 1801 he published a series of articles in the
                  <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>,<emph> </emph>“A Pedestrian Excursion
               through Several Parts of England and Wales during the Summer of 1797” and “The
               Phenomena of the Wye, During the Winter of 1797-8.” For Thompson, Thelwall’s
               “Pedestrian Excursion” “is unremarkable, being largely devoted to conventional
               rehearsals of the ‘romantic and picturesque’” (“Hunting” 105). Thompson criticises
               Thelwall’s apparent failure to sustain the progressive social and political tenets of
               his earlier publications and lectures, reading the pedestrian tour as evidence of the
               “success” of attempts by the authorities to “drive” Thelwall “out of the reform
               business” (104). Thelwall’s love of the “romantic and picturesque” is, for Thompson,
               incompatible with his political activism, which demands interaction and co-operation,
               rather than detached contemplation. This essay will reassess the grounds of
               Thompson’s censure, and will argue that Thelwall’s engagement with the picturesque
               should be read not as a retreat from political engagement but as an attempt to
               rethink and recalibrate such engagement in the face of extreme pressure. Thelwall’s
               treatment of the picturesque demonstrates his sustained if evolving dedication
                  to<hi> </hi>his reformist principles. It also reveals the under-acknowledged ways
               in which Thelwall adapts and modifies aesthetic conventions in order to temper their
               political implications. </p>
            <p> Eighteenth-century aesthetic modes do generate certain reactionary political
               effects. Thompson’s critique of Thelwall echoes critical censure of the damaging
               results of aesthetic spectatorship. John Barrell and Ann Bermingham have argued that
               the aesthetic observer tends to mimic the position of a privileged landowner who
               disdains active intervention in the lives of the poor (Barrell, <title level="m"
                  >Dark</title> 70-76, <title level="m">Pandora</title> 96-98; Bermingham
                  68-69).<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="1">This condemnation has been revised
                  by critics who argue for the indeterminate, playful quality of the picturesque
                  (Michasiw 76-100; Jarvis 54; de Bolla 119-20).</note> Elizabeth Bohls notes that
               such spectatorship produces a “powerful abstracting impulse” which reinforces a
               “symbolic connection between material particulars and groups of people traditionally
               thought of as trapped in them, defined by their bodies, as opposed to their minds:
               the labouring classes and women” (13). The focus of Thelwall’s political activism
               during the mid-1790s had been the broadening of the intellectual franchise and the
               diffusion of knowledge to such groups, and his early scientific training had armed
               him with a sophisticated sense of the importance of material analyses of physical and
               political structures (<title level="m">Tribune</title> 102). Thelwall’s engagement
               with aesthetic forms appears to work against his own political practice. </p>
            <p> Michael Scrivener has recently defended Thelwall’s “Pedestrian Excursion” against
               Thompson’s charges, asserting that Thelwall’s frustration with the working people he
               encounters is a direct result of the political pressures under which he was
               struggling, which the text of the “Pedestrian Excursion” carefully suppresses
               (74-75). Scrivener argues that the essay is not restricted to accounts of the
               picturesque, but rather offers detailed analysis of the effects of agricultural
               monopoly and war on the condition of the poor. But in order to argue for this
               politically engaged Thelwall, Scrivener plays down the significance of his use of
               aesthetic conventions in the “Pedestrian Excursion,” noting that though it “has a
               minor aesthetic connoisseur dimension, the essay’s most distinctive feature is its
               sociological focus” (77). Thelwall’s landscape description is presented as a
               digression from rather than a component of the “sociological” work of the essay, and
               Scrivener does not engage with the reactionary implications of the picturesque
               itself.</p>
            <p>However, Thelwall’s exploration of the “romantic and picturesque” does not represent
               a marker of his disillusionment with political activism, but rather arms him with a
               new means of articulating his social and political goals of intellectual enquiry and
               sympathetic co-operation. Long before his excursion of 1797 Thelwall had explored in
               print whether aesthetic contemplation and political activism could prove productive
               partners. <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title>, Thelwall’s novel, travel
               narrative and reformist tract, published at the outset of his political career in
               1793, makes repeated use of visual conventions. However, <title level="m">The
                  Peripatetic</title>’s radically mixed mode does not lend itself to sustained
               engagement with aesthetic tropes, and the passages in which Thelwall evokes the
               picturesque are characterised by an ironic tone. Thelwall’s “Pedestrian Excursion”
               and “Phenomena of the Wye” engage in more detail with the picturesque; however, they
               are no mere “conventional rehearsals” of the discourse. In these essays Thelwall
               demonstrates a sophisticated appropriation of and deviation from aesthetic
               conventions to suit his political aims. As Judith Thompson has suggested, Thelwall
               challenges the distinction between an aesthetic and a sociological approach to
               landscape by emphasising the material basis of both (“Citizen” 79). For Thelwall the
               ideal viewing consciousness is never a disembodied, abstracting entity, but rather
               one which maintains a material connection with the landscape of which it forms a
                  part.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="2">As Lamb and Wagner suggest, an
                  interesting comparison piece to Thelwall’s “Pedestrian Excursion” is Mary
                  Wollstonecraft’s <title level="m">A Short Residence in Sweden, Norway and
                     Denmark</title> (15). Bohls describes how Wollstonecraft unsettles standard
                  aesthetic viewpoints and “works toward a corporeally and political situated mode
                  of perception” (142, 152).</note> His ongoing engagement with the picturesque
               demonstrates his gradual steps to overcoming the abstracting effects of aesthetic
               contemplation and toward synthesising the representation of landscape with his
               political activism.</p>

            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>In the preface to <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title>, Thelwall declares his
                  “design of uniting the different advantages of the novel, the sentimental journal,
                  and the miscellaneous collection of essays and poetical effusions” (72). Despite
                  the heterogeneous form of the work, structural coherence is conferred through the
                  walking tours which Thelwall’s protagonist Sylvanus Theophrastus undertakes to
                  Saint Albans in Hertfordshire, and to Rochester in Kent. So, like Thelwall’s
                  essays for the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, <title level="m">The
                     Peripatetic</title> describes the practice of “pedestrian excursion” (115).
                  Sylvanus states the advantages of such excursions, declaring that he and his
                  companion will “compare our remarks on such monuments of antiquity, and such
                  picturesque benefits of art and nature, as the road, or its environs might
                  present” (115). But Thelwall differentiates the pedestrian excursions undertaken
                  in <title level="m">The Peripatetic </title>from the practice of picturesque
                  tourism set out in the publications of William Gilpin: “It was not to be a mere
                  excursion of pleasure: for nothing is, in general, more delusive or insipid.
                  Information and improvement were to constitute the principle feature of our
                  expedition” (115). Though sensitive to its “benefits,” <title level="m">The
                     Peripatetic</title> maintains a sceptical attitude to aesthetic tourism;
                  therefore, the aesthetic value of landscape is rarely considered in isolation.
                  Sylvanus admits that his “observations” on the beauties he encounters “may perhaps
                  be neither very original nor profound,” but he insists on their social value,
                  generated by and recorded in “those conversations, that . . . stole the miles so
                  imperceptibly away” (115). For Thelwall, pedestrian travel should be the occasion
                  not for isolated spectatorship, but for conversation and interaction, prompting
                  both individual and collective “information and improvement.” As Judith Thompson
                  notes, Thelwall’s commitment to “friendly converse” is reflected in the “dialogic
                  form” of <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title>, in which contrasting discourses
                  are juxtaposed and combined to create an “intergeneric” conversational mode
                  (Introduction 38-39, 41).</p>
               <p> Thelwall’s “intergeneric” discursive method ensures that though <title level="m"
                     >The Peripatetic</title> makes many references to the picturesque, the
                  descriptions that follow are rarely purely aesthetic. Rather, Thelwall adopts a
                  topographical approach, describing the historical, economic and agricultural
                  condition of the landscape, though, as Thompson notes, <title level="m">The
                     Peripatetic</title> appropriates this discourse to “reorient” the reader’s
                  political preconceptions (Introduction 33). Descriptions of picturesque scenes at
                  Greenwich, Shooter’s Hill and Rochester thus digress swiftly to the “historical
                  allusions” or “flights of fancy” that they prompt (99, 162-64, 257-74). In several
                  episodes Sylvanus praises gothic ruins for their picturesque effect, but these
                  ruins are not pure “objects of art” as Gilpin would have it (<title level="m"
                     >Essays</title> 46). Instead they are physical reminders of the “instability of
                  grandeur” as well as relics of “ancient political institutions” (158, 199). The
                  ruins of Rochester castle “mingle” different effects to produce “one grotesque
                  picture of sylvan nature, of horticulture, and antiquities” (260). The aesthetic
                  effects of the ruins are inseparable from the intellectual stimulus prompted by
                  the castle’s antiquarian significance, and the social effects of the horticulture
                  practiced in its grounds. The picturesque is merely one component of the political
                  “information” to be derived from the peripatetic tour.</p>
               <p>
                  <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> does not seek a comfortable synthesis of
                  such diverse responses to visual scenes. Immediately after praising “the
                  picturesque varieties of a British horizon,” Sylvanus notes that “the scene is
                  changed; and the topographer must, for a while, take the place of the sentimental
                  admirer of picturesque beauty” (142). So sudden are the changes of “scene” in
                     <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> that they often serve an ironic
                  function, undercutting Sylvanus’s rhapsodic response to visual landscapes (151).
                  The enjoyment of visual scenes in <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> is
                  never a simple “pleasure.” Thelwall’s mixed mode generates ironic juxtapositions
                  which undercut the assumed authority of the aesthetic observer, and question
                  whether visual observation alone can stimulate “information and improvement.”</p>
               <p>
                  <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title>’s sceptical attitude to aesthetic
                  observation complicates those scenes which come closest to the conventions of the
                  picturesque tour. Sylvanus’s descriptions never generate the authority of a
                  commentator such as Gilpin. Rather, an ironic distance between Sylvanus’s voice
                  and Thelwall’s authorial presence is implied. At Shooter’s Hill Sylvanus praises
                  the “picturesque beauties” around him, but he actually describes a “prospect of
                  the widening Thames, the rich champaign, the villages and villas which lay before
                  me” (163). Thelwall is perhaps amusing himself at Sylvanus’s lack of aesthetic
                  connoisseurship here. But Sylvanus’s failure to distinguish between the
                  conventions of the prospect view and the picturesque has significant political
                  consequences. As Barrell has shown, the metaphor of the prospect was a means
                  through which an eighteenth-century gentleman could demonstrate his suitability
                  for a life of public virtue (Barrell, <title level="m">Pandora</title> 52; Labbe
                  xi-xii). Though a culturally powerful viewing position, the prospect view is
                  anathema to Thelwall’s participatory political agenda. The “bird’s eye prospect”
                  eradicates all specificity from the landscape, which compromises the activist
                  strain of <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> (<title level="m"
                     >Peripatetic</title> 150, 163). At times Sylvanus seems aware of the damaging
                  effects of the prospect view, and posits the picturesque as a more wholesome
                  alternative, declaring: “Let us turn, then, from this overgrown Metropolis, its
                  spreading streets and rising palaces; the trophies . . . of public misery and
                  oppression; and contemplate the picturesque home scenery with which this garden of
                  a heath abounds” (153). The intimate scale of a picturesque scene and its focus on
                  material objects mitigates the abstracting effect of the prospect. But the fact
                  that Sylvanus often fails to distinguish between these two discourses signals the
                  dangerous effects of such spectatorship. </p>
               <p>Despite its defence of the picturesque over the prospect view on political
                  grounds, <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> demonstrates clear suspicion of
                  the abstracting effects of all aesthetic tropes. Reformist sentiments are
                  articulated through the adoption of the mixed mode signalled in Thelwall’s
                  preface, rather than through a treatment of the aesthetic in isolation. Though the
                  picturesque has the potential to represent the interests of the humblest members
                  of society, Thelwall demonstrates the dangers of aestheticising the lives of any
                  group. He takes gypsies as his example, perhaps because Gilpin had asserted their
                  picturesque effect (<title level="m">Observations</title> II 44, 46). Thelwall
                  appears to agree when he notes that for “a hunter of the picturesque,” gypsies
                  “contribute, in no small degree, to the embellishment of rural scenery” (196). But
                  he interrogates this statement over a course of digressions which end with
                  Sylvanus’s recollection of encountering another group of gypsies. Sylvanus
                  declares an aesthetic appreciation of “the yellow misty light that gleamed over
                  the southern horizon,” but when describing the gypsies themselves, adopts a
                  vocabulary of social configuration: “I saw . . . the cheerful family of vagrants
                  sitting on the grass, around their crackling fire, and enjoying their repast, and
                  to me unintelligible conversation; with their rude, lowly tents in the rear . . .
                  and the patient 'mute companions of their toils' grazing in social familiarity by
                  their sides” (208). These people do not merely “embellish” the scene; indeed,
                  Thelwall rejects aesthetic appreciation altogether. The scene includes “none of
                  that marvellous novelty necessary to fix the demure, half-vacant eye of reverend
                     <emph>Gravity</emph>” (208-09). For Thelwall these “vulgar objects” do not
                  elicit aesthetic admiration but stimulate “a concatenation of ideas” encompassing
                  imaginative engagement, antiquarian investigation and social and political
                  activism (209). Thelwall rejects the distancing effect of the aesthetic gaze and
                  instead asserts the gypsies’ historic bonds with societies from which they are now
                  ostracised. Aesthetic “pleasure” is dismissed as Thelwall reiterates his aim of
                  promoting “information and improvement” in order to better the lives of
                  marginalised groups.</p>
               <p> Despite <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title>’s repeated engagement with the
                  picturesque, the models of political and social improvement that Thelwall
                  advocates often reject visual forms altogether. Thelwall is adamant that visual
                  scenes alone are not sufficient to prompt the sympathetic sociability that enables
                  social improvement (121). An important lyric declaring lavish admiration of the
                  natural landscape ends with the assertion that “nor all the pleasures of the
                  ravish’d sight, / Like <emph>friendly Converse</emph> wake the raptur’d glow!”
                  (115-16). Such “converse” is the stimulus for a material investigation of the
                  physical and by extension the social and political landscape, which does not rely
                  on the abstracting forms of visual observation but incorporates different “ways of
                  seeing” (Jarvis 44). Thelwall’s political activism and his training in physiology
                  provide the basis for his exploration of modes of vision which challenge the
                  distance between the observer and the landscape. Thelwall declares in a political
                  lecture delivered the year after the publication of <title level="m">The
                     Peripatetic</title> that “This is a season for inquiry and instruction, not for
                  pastime and jocularity; and it is therefore that I . . . stimulate you to enquire
                  into the nature of your rights as Britons and as men; and to investigate the
                  nature and causes of that unhappiness which we cannot but feel too sensibly”
                     (<title level="m">Political</title> 2). <title level="m">The
                     Peripatetic</title>, too, demands a material engagement with the conditions of
                  social life. In a “Digression for the Anatomists,” which draws on Thelwall’s
                  physiological training, though enquiry is prompted by the splendours of nature,
                  “the scientific eye” reveals “wider fields of wisdom and delight” than those
                  presented by the aesthetic gaze (146).<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="3"
                     >Several episodes in <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> which begin with
                     the contemplation of the visual landscape end with Thelwall advocating an
                     alternative “scientific view” (226-27).</note>
                  <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> reveals the limitations of the “pleasure”
                  of picturesque tourism. Rather than celebrating the picturesque in isolation,
                  Thelwall suggests that it should form part of a multifaceted critical
                  investigation of the landscape. <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> posits
                  the kind of material critique that Bohls finds in the work of Mary Wollstonecraft,
                  which establishes a “connection between aesthetic practices and the material,
                  social, and political conditions of human experience” (9). However, <title
                     level="m">The Peripatetic</title>, structured by ironic juxtaposition and
                  shifts of “scene,” has no interest in synthesising its diverse elements. As a
                  result <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> tends to regard aesthetic effects
                  as limited and potentially deceptive. The picturesque does not yet have a positive
                  political function in Thelwall’s work.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>“A Pedestrian Excursion through Several Parts of England and Wales during the
                  Summer of 1797” describes a walking tour from London to the West Country, which
                  Thelwall undertook during the summer in which his metropolitan radical career
                  seemed finally to have been crushed (Scrivener 74-75). The “Pedestrian Excursion”
                  is undoubtedly a politically engaged text, but one in which Thelwall adapts his
                  methods to a new form, the picturesque tour. In doing so, he imbues that form with
                  renewed political significance. In contrast to the mixed mode of <title level="m"
                     >The Peripatetic</title>, Thelwall’s “Pedestrian Excursion” is a sustained
                  interrogation of the picturesque which seeks to find a means to reconcile and even
                  integrate an analysis of visual forms with his political activism. While <title
                     level="m">The Peripatetic</title> makes only glancing allusions to Gilpin’s
                  work, the “Pedestrian Excursion” develops a self-conscious response to the
                  strictures of the picturesque, making reference not only to Gilpin’s schema, but
                  also those of the picturesque’s arch-theorists, Richard Payne Knight and Uvedale
                     Price.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="4">Thelwall investigates the power
                     of the picturesque to elicit “curiosity,” an important term for Price and Payne
                     Knight.</note> Thelwall declares himself one of the “pedestrian hunters of the
                  picturesque and sentimental,” but the picturesque is no mere fashionable object of
                  scorn (52). Rather, the opening of the “Pedestrian Excursion” suggests a function
                  for picturesque tourism which seems to achieve a synthesis between political and
                  aesthetic concerns. Thelwall notes that “circumstances [have] produced another
                  species of curiosity well calculated to go hand in hand with a passion for the
                  picturesque and romantic. Every fact connected with the history and actual
                  condition of the laborious classes had become important to a heart throbbing with
                  anxiety for the welfare of the human race” (17). The physiologically situated
                  fellow feeling urged in <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> recurs here, but
                  Thelwall now aligns it with “a passion for the picturesque.” In contrast with the
                  distrust of the abstracting effects of spectatorship in <title level="m">The
                     Peripatetic</title>, the “Pedestrian Excursion” advocates the appreciation of
                  landscape as a means of generating sociability. </p>
               <p> The “Pedestrian Excursion” develops <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title>’s
                  suggestion that the picturesque should be valorised over the prospect view, adding
                  a technical rigour to those conjectures. At East Knoyle in Wiltshire, Thelwall and
                  his companion are conducted to a “commanding eminence” from which “we commanded
                  one of the most pleasant views I had ever seen.” Thelwall praises the hills which
                  “dimly descried through mists, bounded the prospect and mingled with the horizon”
                  (44-45). But this “bird’s-eye prospect” cannot compare to that which follows when
                  the travellers descend from the hilltop and indulge in “the enjoyment of the
                  picturesque, and the beauty and fertility of the home-scene, in the lowlands, with
                  their embowered and scattered cottages” (45). The “home-scene” of the picturesque
                  is valued for its humble, inclusive qualities. Thelwall emphasises this point in
                  an earlier episode which praises “the solemn grandeur and shady sequestration of
                  [the] descending path” from the summit at Richmond Hill: “That pomp of scenery,
                  that expanse and publicity of prospect . . . fascinate, indeed the occasional
                  observer: but in the picturesque of nature, as in the intercourses of life, it is
                  principally in the lowly vales and shades of sober sequestration we must seek the
                  pleasures that cloy not on repetition” (18-19). Thelwall’s enthusiasm for the
                  occluded viewpoint of “lowly vales” echoes Gilpin and his successors (Gilpin,
                     <title level="m">Observations</title> 186; Price 33; Knight 30). However, his
                  alignment of “the picturesque of nature” with the social “intercourses of life” is
                  original (18-19). Thelwall uses landscape description to support his assertion
                  that the social “pleasures which cloy not on repetition” must be cherished and
                  protected from the destructive effects of political and economic monopoly. </p>
               <p>Thelwall’s preference for the picturesque over the prospect view is not merely a
                  marker of an unrealised social ideal, but forms part of his critique of actual
                  institutions. His speaker describes the “scene of fertility” visible from the road
                  from Shepperton, and notes that “from every eminence the mansions of opulence
                  overlook the prospect with exultation. But man, aggregate man, seems little
                  benefitted by this abundance . . . everything has the appearance of that
                  desolating monopoly which makes fertility itself a desert” (20). Thelwall
                  demonstrates that this “prospect” is not only myopic but deliberately
                  exploitative. He demands that the observer instead adopt the perspective of “man,
                  aggregate man” and engage with the material particularities of social
                     existence.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="5">Several critics note the
                     political implications of detail in landscape description (Bohls 13, Labbe
                     38).</note> Thelwall’s call for the recognition of “aggregate man” enlists
                  aesthetic description for a democratic cause, echoing as it does the rhetoric of
                  his 1796 tract <title level="m">The Rights of Nature</title>, in which the
                  “aggregate reason” of obscure individuals establishes a common interest, and forms
                  the basis of civil society (459-60). </p>
               <p>However, the “Pedestrian Excursion” also suggests an alteration in Thelwall’s
                  social and political objects since the high water mark of his metropolitan
                  radicalism. The term to which Thelwall returns again and again when advocating
                  picturesque “intercourses of life” is “sequestration.” This echoes the opening of
                  the “Pedestrian Excursion” in which Thelwall reveals the object of his journey to
                  be an “immediate and intimate communication of sentiment” with his friend Samuel
                  Taylor Coleridge in Somerset (17). Thelwall’s poem “Lines Written at Bridgwater,”
                  written just after his abortive stay with Coleridge during the tour described in
                  the “Pedestrian Excursion,” demonstrates the endurance of this ideal: <quote><lg>
                        <l>Ah! let me, far in some sequester’d dell, </l>
                        <l>Build my low cot; most happy might it prove,</l>
                        <l>My Samuel! Near to thine, that I might oft </l>
                        <l>Share they sweet converse, best-belov’d of friends! (<title level="m"
                              >Poems</title> 129)</l>
                     </lg></quote> Commentators have emphasised a lyric turn in the “Pedestrian
                  Excursion” which expresses Thelwall’s understandable desire for retreat in the
                  face of harassment (Jarvis 35-36; Scrivener 76). However, it is important to
                  scrutinise any critical narrative which, like E. P. Thompson’s, polarises
                  Thelwall’s engagement with the picturesque and his political activism. Another
                  poem dating from the summer of 1797 “On Leaving the Bottoms of Gloucestershire”
                  asserts that “sequester’d musings” must be “tho sylvan, yet not solitary” (<title
                     level="m">Poems</title> 136). Even in rural “sequestration,” Thelwall’s social
                  ideal and the basis of his political commitment is “converse,” which enables
                  “Culture and the Arts” and “social decoration” (136). But this community is too
                  secluded, untouched by “Factory” or associated commercial “Opulence” (137).
                  Thelwall’s preference for “sequestration” in “Pedestrian Excursion,” as in the
                  poems written during that summer, does not nullify the text’s political
                  engagement, but does complicate that engagement. Though Thelwall declares a
                  universal social sympathy as his political aim, the picturesque generates
                  intimate, rather than inclusive social relations.</p>
               <p> In certain episodes, the “Pedestrian Excursion” articulates a fully-formed
                  account of sympathetic sociability prompted by the picturesque landscape, but not
                  alienated by the distancing effect of the aesthetic gaze. Passing through a
                  village on the edge of Salisbury Plain, Thelwall’s speaker views a “range of
                  villages scattered along the valley, that opens in a long perspective to the
                  right.” He notes that “the hour was favourable to the emotions these objects were
                  calculated to inspire . . . the light was softened, and the shadows were
                  lengthening: circumstances that cherish a pensive serenity, and pre-dispose the
                  heart to the social sympathies of our nature” (39). The picturesque scene itself
                  awakens “social sympathies” in the travellers, but this state is not sustained.
                  Thelwall’s speaker then bemoans the “jealous caution” of working people he
                  encounters, which deadens any social intercourse (39). Thelwall’s sense of
                  alienation lies at the root of Thompson’s objections to the “Pedestrian
                  Excursion.” However, Thompson separates Thelwall’s treatment of the picturesque
                  from his political activities too starkly. Thelwall’s engagement with the
                  picturesque in the “Pedestrian Excursion” is itself a political move prompted by
                  the inequalities and hostility that he meets on his tour. But though Thelwall
                  finds the picturesque an effective means of articulating protest in the face of
                  political adversity, the “Pedestrian Excursion” struggles to articulate how it
                  might contribute to widespread political amelioration. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>“The Phenomena of the Wye, During the Winter of 1797-8” continues and develops
                  Thelwall’s engagement with the picturesque. Thelwall wrote the essay after the
                  completion of his pedestrian tour of summer 1797 but it appeared in the <title
                     level="j">Monthly Magazine</title> before the “Pedestrian Excursion.” Since the
                  publication of Gilpin’s <title level="m">Observations on the River Wye</title>
                  (1789), the Wye Valley had “acquired a due celebrity” as a picturesque tourist
                  destination, as Thelwall acknowledges in “The Phenomena of the Wye” (3). But
                  Thelwall clearly distinguishes his account from that of Gilpin. Thelwall writes
                  not as a tourist but as a resident of the Wye Valley, having moved with his family
                  to a riverside farm at Llyswen in Breconshire during the autumn of 1797. In his
                  memoir of 1801, Thelwall declares that the chief reason for “the election of this
                  spot” was “the wild and picturesque scenery of the neighbourhood” (<title
                     level="m">Poems</title> xxxv). Thelwall’s memoir presents Llyswen as the
                  realisation of the secluded “retreat” to which the “Pedestrian Excursion” seems at
                  times to gesture, a place in which “the agitations of political feeling might be
                  cradled to forgetfulness” (xxxvi). But “The Phenomena of the Wye” presents a very
                  different account of the picturesque at Llyswen, which complicates this narrative.
                  Thelwall’s speaker is not an isolated spectator of the landscape, but rather a
                  situated, embodied participant in the scenes that surround him. As a result of
                  this material engagement with the landscape, Thelwall adopts a new vocabulary in
                  his treatment of the picturesque. </p>
               <p>Thelwall’s speaker rejects the touring seasons of summer and autumn to recount the
                  beauties of the Wye in winter, and in doing so offers a novel account of the
                  picturesque. Thelwall’s focus is not the surfaces and shades of the landscape, but
                  rather its “anatomy,” revealed in “the leafless grove, the dismantled hill, nay,
                  the very gloom of night itself, when nothing is discernible but the mere outline
                  of surrounding mountains” (3). Such anatomical observation “is as essential to the
                  landscape painter, as that of the human form to the historical branch of the art”
                  (3). Thelwall’s “Digression for the Anatomists” in <title level="m">The
                     Peripatetic</title> had declared that the anatomical insights of the
                  “scientific eye” were vital even for “the elegant votary of the polite arts,”
                  namely portrait and historical painting (146). But here for the first time
                  Thelwall connects anatomical study with the analysis of landscape. In contrast to
                  Gilpin, who makes human figures decorative appendages to the landscape, Thelwall
                  asserts that the landscape can only be understood through analogy with the
                  investigation of the “human form.” The material analysis of physical forms
                  suggests a means of overcoming the gulf between Thelwall’s political aims and the
                  abstracting conventions of aesthetic contemplation. What this formal comparison
                  lacks is a sense of the social exchange fundamental to Thelwall’s political aims. </p>
               <p> Thelwall suggests the means to make analysis of the picturesque a socially and
                  politically engaged phenomenon in the next passage of the “Phenomena of the Wye,”
                  which sustains his assertion that the appreciation of landscape is informed by the
                  material analysis of physical forms, but also suggests that social configurations
                  might be understood in the same way. The “bold and prominent” features of the Wye
                  valley are particularly suited to examination during winter because:
                     <quote>Scenery of this description may be compared to those superior orders of
                     shape and feature which constitute the perfection of the human form; in which
                     transparent tints and the most perfect symmetry are graces of inferior
                     magnitude, and beauty itself is the smaller part of loveliness&#8212;where the
                     whole countenance beams expression, every feature has its animation and
                     character, every line is descriptive of some kind or elevated passion, and
                     every glance, every gesture, every motion is eloquent of sympathy and
                     intelligence. (4)</quote> This passage begins with a comparison between the
                  form of the landscape and that of the human figure. But the landscape changes from
                  a static object of contemplation to an active, co-responding companion. Thelwall
                  employs a vocabulary of reciprocal exchange of energy and emotions that echoes his
                  most engaged political lecturing.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="6">See for
                     example Thelwall’s lecture of 6 November 1795 (<title level="j">Tribune</title>
                     327).</note> Vitally, it not only recalls Thelwall’s investigations of
                  alternate “ways of seeing” in <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title>, but also
                  anticipates his engagement with a related form of material “inquiry” in his
                  elocutionary practice of the next decade. In his 1805 tract <title level="m">An
                     Introductory Discourse on the Nature and Objects of Elocutionary
                     Science</title> Thelwall notes that language must be incorporated into the
                  body’s physical expression: “Language alone is not sufficient: nature’s epitome,
                  like nature’s self, must sympathize through every element: motion and look and
                  attitude must manifest the inspiration of genuine feeling; and every portion of
                  the frame must be vital with expressive eloquence” (24). The “Phenomena of the
                  Wye” sustains and develops Thelwall’s critique of visual forms dating back to
                     <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title>. But here Thelwall demonstrates that a
                  formal appreciation of landscape is not separable from other kinds of material
                  analysis, of physiological, social, or political forms, and even suggests that the
                  aesthetic might encourage the conditions for political engagement rather than
                  isolated abstraction.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="7">I am sympathetic to
                     Terry Eagleton’s assertion that the later eighteenth century is a moment at
                     which the material particularity of aesthetic forms enables a “dangerously
                     radical” “ideal of compassionate community” (60).</note>
               </p>
               <p>In the close to this passage Thelwall demonstrates that such inclusive forms of
                  investigation can assimilate the distinct discourses of aesthetic contemplation
                  and social and political activism: “Such are the forms that owe not their
                  attraction to the wardrobe&#8212;the charms that never cloy&#8212;that fade not
                  even in the winter of old age&#8212;the sublime of human nature!” (4). Here
                  landscape description and social interaction are so profoundly synthesised as to
                  be inseparable. Thelwall echoes his assertion in the “Pedestrian Excursion” that
                  picturesque “sequestration” produces “pleasures that cloy not on repetition.” But
                  despite the sheltered location of his “little cottage,” Thelwall’s speaker in the
                  “Phenomena of the Wye” does not demand seclusion (5). In contrast to the often
                  isolated protagonist of the “Pedestrian Excursion,” Thelwall’s speaker exchanges
                  stories with “my predecessor in this little farm” (5). As Scrivener notes, the
                  “grand” natural phenomena that the speaker witnesses are discussed in terms of
                  their effects on the social and economic conditions in the valley (Scrivener 82;
                  “Wye” 6-7). Through the language of material analysis and sympathetic social
                  engagement, Thelwall ensures that the “romantic and picturesque” scenes of the Wye
                  do not represent pure “retreat” but rather gesture forward to Thelwall’s renewed
                  engagement in public life in the next decade.</p>
               <ab><hi rend="bold">Acknowledgment</hi></ab> 
               <p rend="noCount">This article was written during a
                  postdoctoral research fellowship funded by the Government of Canada’s Department
                  of Foreign Affairs and International Trade, and I gratefully acknowledge DFAIT’s
                  support.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>
               <p rend="noCount">Barrell, John. <title level="m">The Dark Side of the Landscape: The
                     Rural Poor in English Painting 1730-1840</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP,
                  1980. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">The Birth of Pandora and the Division of
                     Knowledge</title>. Philadelphia: U of Pennsylvania P, 1992. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Bohls, Elizabeth. <title level="m">Women Travel Writers and the
                     Language of Aesthetics</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Claeys, Gregory, ed. <title level="m">The Politics of English
                     Jacobinism: Writings of John Thelwall</title>. University Park: Pennsylvania
                  State UP, 1995. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">de Bolla, Peter. <title level="m">The Education of the Eye:
                     Painting, Landscape, and Architecture in Eighteenth-Century Britain</title>.
                  Stanford: Stanford UP, 2003. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Eagleton, Terry. <title level="m">The Ideology of the
                     Aesthetic</title>. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1990. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Gilpin, William. <title level="m">Observations, Relative Chiefly to
                     Picturesque Beauty, Made in the Year 1772, on Several Parts of England;
                     Particularly the Mountains, and Lakes of Cumberland, and Westmoreland</title>.
                  London, 1786. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Three Essays: On Picturesque Beauty; on
                     Picturesque Travel; and on Sketching Landscape: To Which Is Added a Poem on
                     Landscape Painting</title>. London, 1792. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Jarvis, Robin. <title level="m">Romantic Writing and Pedestrian
                     Travel</title>. Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1997. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Labbe, Jacqueline. <title level="m">Romantic Visualities:
                     Landscape, Gender and Romanticism</title>. Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1997.
                  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Michasiw, Kim Ian. "Nine Revisionist Theses on the Picturesque."
                     <title level="m">Representations</title> 38 (1992): 76-100. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Payne Knight, Richard. <title level="m">The Landscape, a Didactic
                     Poem. In Three Books. Addressed to Uvedale Price, Esq.</title> London, 1794.
                  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Price, Uvedale. <title level="m">An Essay on the Picturesque, as
                     Compared with the Sublime and Beautiful; and on the Use of Studying Pictures,
                     for the Purpose of Improving Real Landscape.</title> London, 1794. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Scrivener, Michael. "Jacobin Romanticism: John Thelwall's 'Wye'
                  Essay and 'Pedestrian Excursion'." <title level="m">Placing and Displacing
                     Romanticism.</title> Ed. Peter J. Kitson. Aldershot: Ashgate, 2001. 73-87.
                  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thelwall, John. “A Pedestrian Excursion through Several Parts of
                  England and Wales during the Summer of 1797.” Lamb and Wagner 15-55.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">The Peripatetic.</title> Ed. Judith Thompson.
                  Detroit: Wayne State UP, 2001. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “The Phenomena of the Wye, During the Winter of 1797-8.” Lamb
                  and Wagner 1-13.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Poems Chiefly Written in Retirement</title>.
                  1801. Oxford: Woodstock, 1989.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Political Lecture (No. 1) on the Moral
                     Tendency of a System of Spies and Informers, and the Conduct to Be Observed by
                     the Friends of Liberty During the Continuance of Such a System</title>. London,
                  1794. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “The Rights of Nature, Against the Usurpations of
                  Establishments. A Series of Letters to the People, in Reply to the False
                  Principles of Burke.” Claeys 389-500. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Selected Political Writings of John
                     Thelwall</title>. Ed. Robert Lamb, and Corinna Wagner. Vol. 3. London:
                  Pickering and Chatto, 2009. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “The Tribune, a Periodical Publication, Consisting Chiefly of
                  the Political Lectures of J. Thelwall.”<title level="m"> </title>Claeys 65-327. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">The Trident of Albion . . . To Which Is
                     Prefixed, an Introductory Discourse on the Nature and Objects of Elocutionary
                     Science</title>. Liverpool, 1805. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thompson, E. P. "Hunting the Jacobin Fox." <title level="m">Past
                     and Present</title> 142 (1994): 94-140. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">The Making of the English Working
                     Class</title>. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1968. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thompson, Judith. Introduction. <title level="m">The
                     Peripatetic</title>. By John Thelwall. Detroit: Wayne State UP, 2001.
                  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. "Citizen Juan Thelwall: In the Footsteps of a Free-Range
                  Radical." <title level="j">Studies in Romanticism</title> 48 (2009): 67-100.
                  Print.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
