<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">John Thelwall: Critical Reassessments</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">“A Son of John Thelwall”: Weymouth Birkbeck Thelwall’s Romantic
               Inheritance</title>
            <author>
               <name>Patty O'Boyle</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Yasmin Solomonescu</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.oboyle</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2010-11-01">September 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">“A Son of John Thelwall”: Weymouth Birkbeck
                     Thelwall’s Romantic Inheritance</title>

                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Patty</forename>
                        <surname>O'Boyle</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">John Thelwall: Critical Reassessments</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2010-10-15">October 15, 2010</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for "," for ", ' for ',
                  and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2011-05-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>“A Son of John Thelwall”: Weymouth Birkbeck Thelwall’s Romantic Inheritance</head>
            <byline><docAuthor>Patty O’Boyle </docAuthor><affiliation>Independent
                  Scholar</affiliation></byline>

            <epigraph>
               <quote>Unto Us a Son Is Born who looks more like a fine boy of a year and a half than
                  one of a half an hour old. You have now therefore another brother whom I hope to
                  see you in the course of the next month nursing. My dear Cecil has had an
                  excellent good time of it and appears likely to do very well&#8212;Eliza is
                  weeping for joy; and her dear affectionate heart makes her think it the most
                  wonderfully lovely babe that ever was born&#8212;I will leave it to others, when
                  they can find time, to tell you what sort of an old fool I am–</quote>
            </epigraph>
            <p> Thus a delighted John Thelwall wrote to his daughter Sara, on August 4, 1831, on the
               birth of his son Weymouth Birkbeck, who seems almost to have attempted to catch up
               with his father before he was an hour old.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="1">I
                  would like to thank Judith Thompson for sending me a transcript of this letter and
                  for the invaluable help she has given me during the preparation of this article.
               </note> As if fated to live at the same breathless, belated pace, Weymouth went on to
               recapitulate his father’s eccentric career and talents, inheriting his gift of
               oratory, realizing his thwarted artistic and theatrical ambitions, and setting forth
               on even more bizarre adventures in amorous, peripatetic and scientific discovery. His
               very life span ironically mirrors the forty-six years preceding his birth that
               had taken John Thelwall from an abandoned career in law to his trial for treason in
               1794, and to the brink of success in realising his long deferred political hopes in
               the Great Reform Bill of 1832. Forty-six years years later the new life so joyfully announced in 1831 was to end in an unmarked “white
               man’s grave,” archetypal symbol of the folly of imperialist ambitions that the elder
               Thelwall had rejected, along with the often bigoted religious institutions that
               partly inspired them.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="2">For a comprehensive
                  account of the role of missionaries in the formation of the Empire, see Cox. On
                  Thelwall’s anti-imperialism, see the chapter “Against Empire” in Scrivener
                  233-56.</note> Victim of his own romantic radical inheritance, Weymouth Thelwall
               was swallowed by the heart of darkness it led him into.</p>
            <p>Sixty-seven years old at Weymouth’s birth, John Thelwall may have felt himself an
               “old fool,” but he was still an enthusiastic political agitator and orator. In the
               letter announcing the birth, he informs Sara that “alternations of public exertions,
               a little tuition and much propensity to enjoy the long forbidden charm of quiet
               study” have preoccupied him over the previous weeks. Those public exertions included
               his work as a leader of the St. Mary le Bone and St. Pancras parish committee, in
               support of the Political Union of the Working Classes (Place sec. 23). The following
               October he was to play an important role in the successful organisation of a huge
               procession of the union’s members, involving tens of thousands of disaffected
               supporters of the first Reform Bill from all the parishes in London who marched
               through the city in protest at its defeat by the House of Lords (Place sec. 23). One
               of the reforms Thelwall had supported as early as 1795, the religious and political
               emancipation of Irish Catholics,<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="3">See, for
                  instance, Thelwall, “The Tribune. No. XXVIII” 240.</note> had just been achieved
               through the passing of the Catholic Emancipation Bill of 1829, though it was bitterly
               contested by other denominations and Irish protestants. Here the personal and the
               political were once more to meet in John Thelwall’s life and affect the lives of the
               son whose nativity he heralds and of his Catholic mother Cecil, whose father had been
                  Irish.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="4">Patrick Boyle, who died in 1808, was
                  the publisher of <title level="m">Boyle’s Court Guide and Fashionable
                     Register</title>, the long-running directory of addresses in London. His widow
                  Eliza ran it after his death.</note> It is almost as if the act itself had opened
               the way for his son to be born and enter civic life at least partly unhindered by the
               repressive Test Acts and other such legislation that had trammelled and harried his
               father’s radical generation. For, perhaps surprisingly, Weymouth was brought up as a
               Catholic.</p>
            <p>The religious toleration that had always marked the work of John Thelwall (catholic
               in the sense of liberal and broad-minded) would shape the lives of his sons in very
               different ways. Though there is little evidence that he ever converted, his marriage
               to Henrietta Cecil Boyle in 1817 indicates a softening in his earlier staunch
                  atheism.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="5">Two unattributed blank verse
                  meditations reprinted in Algernon Sydney Thelwall’s 1831 <title level="m">Thoughts
                     in Affliction</title> offer the only slim evidence that John Thelwall (by whom
                  they were likely composed) experienced a “movement towards grace” as he grew
                  older.</note> Perhaps in deference to her religious freedom, the wedding at St.
               James Westminster was preceded by the baptism of the five surviving children of his
               first marriage: Algernon Sydney, John Hampden, Manon Roland, Sara Maria and Edwin
               Northumbrian. His eldest sons, both of whom went on to take orders in the Anglican
               Church, show very different sides of the “Thelwall” personality. In 1831 Hampden had
               just begun a life of rural “poverty and seclusion personified” as the charitable
               Rector of Oving in Buckinghamshire (Kelly 181); his older brother Algernon was a
               militant evangelist who had recently returned from trying to convert the Jews of
               Amsterdam. While Hampden’s quiet social conscience found an outlet in supplying the
               poor lace-makers of his village with materials and markets, and teaching their
               children to read (Kelly 181),<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="6">Hampden sought
                  the support of his father’s old friend Birkbeck in this endeavour. </note>
               Algernon’s outspoken activism expressed itself in polemical tracts against Catholics
               and almost any dissenting Church that did not acknowledge the Trinity. As paid
               secretary of the Trinitarian Bible Society (TBS) formed in 1831, he engaged in a
               pamphlet war against the editor of <title level="m">The Christian Observer,</title> a
               supporter of the long-established British and Foreign Bible Society—a battle of words
               which rivalled any his father had fought. Even years after John Thelwall’s death his
               opponents were still calling his respectability in doubt. Algernon summons up the
               ghost of his own father by calling his well-known antagonist’s anonymity a
               “questionable shape”&#8212;a borrowing from <title level="m">Hamlet</title> that his
               father had used in his arguments against Burke (<title level="m">Statement
                  </title>12).<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="7">John Thelwall quotes the same
                  phrase several times in his published writing, most pertinently against Burke in
                  almost a mirror version of his son’s pamphlet war with Wilkes. See Thelwall,
                     <title level="m">Sober Reflections </title>345. For another occurrence see
                     <title level="m">The Rights of Nature</title> 415.</note> He is countered by
               the editor, Samuel Charles Wilkes, sneeringly referring to “sonorous vocables” and
               “oratorical vocabulary” to discredit the son by raising the same ghost (<title
                  level="m">Statement </title>29, 52); and by his lamenting the TBS’s lack of
               “fatherly authority” in not having bishops on its committee but having as its paid
               secretary “a son of John Thelwall” (50, 16).<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="8"
                  >Samuel Charles Wilkes, the editor of the <title level="m">Christian</title>
                  <title level="m">Observer</title>, wrote the first edition of <title level="m">A
                     Statement Presented to Judge Erskine</title> anonymously but inserted a signed
                  preface in the second edition after the TBS refused to answer an anonymous
                  pamphlet.</note> Curiously, the President of the TBS was the judge Thomas Erskine,
               son of the very barrister who had so ably defended John Thelwall at his trial in
               1794. One of the main charges against Algernon was that he spent more of the
               subscribers’ money on polemical pamphlets than on printing Bibles for the lost souls
               of Britain. The implied objection to him, however, was quite obviously that he was
               simply “a son of John Thelwall.”<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="9">That “a son
                  of John Thelwall” could call another man’s respectability into question was deemed
                  outrageous. </note> He had inherited all his father’s pugnacious spirit, without
               any of his redeeming humour and toleration.</p>
            <p>Growing up in the Church that his stepbrother so fiercely attacked, Weymouth
               Thelwall’s nature combined Algernon’s restlessness and Hampden’s practicality with
               the many-minded creativity of their common sire. Only three years old when his father
               died, he and his mother were left almost destitute, dependent upon Hampden and other
               relatives and friends.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="10">The novelist Barbara
                  Hofland, for instance, made an appeal for financial help for “the widow of a man
                  who for half a century was the unflinching advocate of those political principles
                  which at length obtained ascendancy” who “appears to me unaccountably neglected.”
                  See Hofland’s letter to Mr. Hale. </note> One of these, probably a Catholic,
               appears to have paid for the boy’s education at Stonyhurst, a highly regarded Jesuit
               boarding school in Lancashire that provided a route by which the sons of well-to-do
               Catholics, who were still excluded from Oxford and Cambridge, could get into London
               University or the Civil Service.</p>
            <p>The little we know of Weymouth’s schooldays comes from the drama critic Percy
               Hetherington Fitzgerald in his <title level="m">Stonyhurst Memories; or, Six Years at
                  School </title>(1895). He was one of only a half-dozen boys Fitzgerald considered
               worth noting as “characters.” Like his father, Weymouth was a good actor, an
               accomplished artist, and something of a democratic orator: <quote>And what odd types
                  there were! Such was Thelwall, son of the great Radical agitator and elocutionist,
                  the friend of Charles Lamb. There was a son of Thelwall’s “speaker” and I must say
                  he inherited the parental gift and could declaim with great tragic feeling. I
                  remember his spending weeks carving a Roman head on a piece of stone with a
                  penknife, and a clever performance it was. (Fitzgerald 41)</quote> More ominously
               in the light of later events, Weymouth was also the “money taker” for bets made on
               the students’ cricket matches, one of which was the cause of a rift between
               Fitzgerald and Thelwall when a school-wide political feud was running based on
               divisions of loyalty during the land league agitation.</p>
            <p>Upon his departure from Stonyhurst in 1847-48, Weymouth Thelwall immediately joined
               the Foreign Office. In 1859, whilst working as a clerk in the War Office, he married
               Marian Wrather, firstly in a Catholic and then in an Anglican Church; and a daughter,
               Edith Fanny Thelwall, was born in 1862.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="11">Edith
                  died unmarried in Kensington in 1942.</note> By October 1864, though, Weymouth had
               declared himself bankrupt in his own petition, with debts of between two and three
               thousand pounds owed mostly in bills. This was possibly through gambling, sign of a
               reckless streak that would contribute to Weymouth’s unfortunate fate.<note
                  resp="editors" place="foot" n="12">
                  <title level="m">The Coursing Calendar</title> for 1864 lists a Mr. Thelwall as
                  racing two dogs in March; one got through two rounds only to be beaten in the last
                  (131, 171).</note> After he promised he would pay his creditors whatever remained
               above £200 of his £375 salary, including his annual increase, the judge accepted this
               “very creditable” offer and made an order of discharge (“Court of Bankruptcy” 9). He
               is cited as living in Keppel Terrace, Windsor, at this time.<note resp="editors"
                  place="foot" n="13">According to a report of bankruptcies in <title level="m">The
                     Law Journal</title>’s “Gazette” for Tuesday, Oct. 18, 1864. </note> As a
               bankrupt there was little possibility that he could remain in the civil service
               without the support of his superior officers, and it is likely that he had been
               dismissed, leaving him with no means of support for his wife and child.</p>
            <p>Weymouth’s misfortunes were compounded by the death of his mother, announced in
                  <title level="m">The Gentleman’s Magazine</title> in 1865: <quote>At Windsor in
                  great distress, Mrs Thelwall, widow of John Thelwall, so well known for the part
                  he took in the political struggles at the end of the last century, and who was
                  tried for high treason and acquitted. (“Deaths” 529)</quote> Her death occurred in
               February, just two months after Weymouth’s bankruptcy hearing, in a squalid little
               backstreet, Grove Place, where the cost of unfurnished rooms was in the order of four
               shillings a week. This was a huge step down for the beautiful and talented woman who
               had once welcomed London literati to Thelwall’s gracious house in Lincoln’s Inn
               Fields, boasting “a capital grand piano,” fine paintings and prints, a library of
               over six thousand books and quality mahogany furniture, all of which, along with the
               valuable lease, had been put up for auction in 1820 (“Sales” 4). Cecil’s death
               certificate, signed by Weymouth, states that she died “of general decay,” which
               perhaps makes her obituary an indictment of those who had declined to offer a pension
               to John Thelwall in later life, when the fruits of the reform movement’s early
               struggles were beginning to be enjoyed by those who had often resisted them,
               including those who had caused Weymouth to be dismissed.<note resp="editors"
                  place="foot" n="14">I quote this from a certified copy of Cecil Thelwall’s entry
                  of death, registered in Windsor in 1865.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Yet with the rakish resilience of Thelwall’s genius, Incubus, in his play <title
                  level="m">The Fairy of the Lake, </title>Weymouth emulated his father’s capacity
               for regeneration through vocational (and amorous) reinvention. In 1871, the former
               war-office clerk reappeared in London as a landscape artist, aged forty, living in
               Westminster; and, according to the census record, his “wife” was a woman called
               Helena, birthplace not known, twenty-four years old and a dancer.<note resp="editors"
                  place="foot" n="15">See the entry for “Weymouth B. Thelwall” in the Census Returns
                  of England and Wales, 1871. </note> It is uncanny how Weymouth’s mid-life
               behaviour mirrored that of his father. At the age of forty-two, John Thelwall had
               returned to London after an eight-year exile, having transformed himself from a
               political lecturer into an elocutionist; and ten years later he too took up with a
               much younger woman, an actress (though, unlike his son, John waited until his first
               wife was dead before he remarried). As a painter of landscapes, Weymouth resurrected
               the thwarted ambitions of his father, gaining success, respect and even a measure of
               fame thereby, for his water colours were exhibited at the Royal Academy, and he even
               appeared at court, where he presented “drawings and sketches” of Norway to the Queen
               in 1873 (“Court Circular” 5). He also shared the theatricality which was so strong a
               feature of John Thelwall’s personality and oeuvre, as is shown by the fact that he
               was granted a patent in 1872 on a “theatrical monster device.” Such “colossal and
               other figures of men, monsters, and animals, for stage purposes” were popular in the
               pantomimes and spectacular shows of the period (Rees and Wilmore 25-26). Weymouth’s
               might almost have been intended for <title level="m">The Fairy of the Lake</title>,
               as evidenced in the play’s spectacular premiere in Halifax, Nova Scotia, in October
               2009.
               <!-- <hi>&lt;hyperlink to section “John Thelwall in Performance: </hi>
               <hi>The Fairy of the Lake</hi>
               <hi>”&gt;</hi> -->
            </p>
            <p> But it was not only in his amorous, artistic and theatrical passions that Weymouth
               revived the spirit of his father. During this same period, he travelled in Norway and
               contributed notes to the Norwegian Tourist Club, giving details of an intrepid trek
               across a glacial valley in extremely harsh weather, and an account of a visit to the
               Voring waterfall (“Notes and Suggestions” 104-06). Here the son of the Peripatetic
               has succeeded the youthful actor, and the painter of words also begins to flourish.
               His description of the valley, reached only after an heroic attempt to overcome the
               dangers of a hostile environment, recalls the mix of touristic sublime and
               socio-scientific pragmatism that characterized his father’s groundbreaking pedestrian
               excursions: <quote>The beauties of this magnificent foss are now by no means
                  appreciated, as visitors are obliged to rush at it from Viig, reaching it tired
                  and taking the chance of seeing it at its best or its worst according to the mercy
                  of the weather or the guides. I saw it with a 3/4 rainbow spanning the whole mist
                  filled chasm, and nothing could exceed its poetic grandeur. The payments &amp;c.
                  for guides ought also to be regulated . . . . (105-06)</quote> Like his father’s
               mock-heroic Peripatetic dangling from cliff tops and battlements, Weymouth presents
               himself as a bold and occasionally reckless adventurer rather than merely a tourist,
               then undercuts his heroism by drawing attention to his failures (his ascent of the
               Justedal Glacier was left unfinished because he forgot to wear nailed boots). He also
               makes practical “suggestions” for “improvements” for the benefit of tourists, such as
               chiselled-out footholds, stepping stones, and cromlech-style route markers
               (107-08).</p>
            <p> While Weymouth was in Norway, back in London Helena danced, touring much of England
               with her troupe of “Hungarian” dancers and receiving good reviews. The reason that
               this is known is rather surprising. There is a fine leather-bound folio in the
               Foreign Office archives containing over forty pages of correspondence on the <title
                  level="m">Case of Mr Thelwall and Miss Fielding, alias Girofle. </title>It
               includes a note written hastily on the back of an advertising flier with newspaper
               reviews, in reply to the British Vice Consul in Moscow, where Helena had been
               performing at the Theatre Bouffe as part of the Moscow Trade Fair. The nature of
               Helena’s performances is partly elucidated by the racy account of the dancing of
               “Mademoiselle Froufrou,” published in H. A. Munro Johnstone’s <title level="m">A Trip
                  up the Volga to the Fair </title>
               <title level="m">of Nijni-</title>
               <title level="m">Novgorod.</title> Johnstone refers to the fair’s “amusements” as a
               “Saturnalia” and describes the riotous behaviour of the theatre’s cosmopolitan
               audience of merchants in a manner which would certainly have raised alarm bells for
               Weymouth Thelwall <title level="m">if</title> it were not already known to him
               (108-09). But he seems to have had plans afoot for an adventurous journey of his
               own.</p>
            <p> Weymouth had written to the Foreign Office in September 1875, extremely worried
               about his “niece, Miss Helen Fielding” <quote>who was taken to Moscow by a Mr Becker
                  of whom I have not heard very pleasing accounts. I know her to be entirely without
                  money and therefore request that a telegram be sent to ask the Vice Consul to
                  ascertain her whereabouts and her safety and asking the assistance of the foreign
                  office in paying for her passage home and those of her troupe as may need it. (At
                  my expense of course). <note resp="editors" place="foot" n="16">See the letter of
                     Sept. 21, 1875, in <title level="m">Case</title>.</note>
               </quote> In due course a telegram and letters flew between Moscow and Nizhniy
               Novgorod, between Lord Derby and his senior civil servants, and between the said
               Helena and a special agent who was sent from Moscow to “find her out.” She refused to
               return to England as she had found “engagements for the Winter,” but two of her
               troupe wished to do so, and she said she would be obliged if they could be
               repatriated under the distressed British subjects scheme. The problem was that
               Weymouth objected to paying for the (obviously delighted) agent sent to accompany
               these “helpless girls” on their perilous winter journey to the coast, and despite the
               Vice Consul’s protests he did not pay. Eventually a court order for prosecution
               issued from the Treasury and an agreement was reached in which he promised payment of
               the £61 by a bill drawn on the proprietor of the<title level="m"> Illustrated London
                  News </title>on the basis of commissions for drawings he was to send from Lake
               Nyassa in Central Africa, “should I survive the journey.” <note resp="editors"
                  place="foot" n="17">See the letter of May 22, 1876, in <title level="m"
                     >Case</title>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the “Helena Fielding” affair and its African aftermath, we see the complicated
               conjunction of international trade and travel, colonial bureaucracy, artistic
               entrepreneurship and sheer, stubborn recklessness that would shape the final chapter
               in the curious life of Weymouth Thelwall. Though now an additional motive for his
               African journey was to pay for Helena’s expenses, he seems to have had the trip in
               mind for some time, possibly inspired in part by the heroic example of David
               Livingstone, whose immensely popular travels, themselves displaying the same mix of
               commercial and cultural enterprise, had ended with his death in 1873, followed by a
               huge state funeral at Westminster Abbey (Ross 247). In addition to his contract with
               the <title level="m">Illustrated London News</title>, Weymouth twice sought support
               from the Royal Geographical Society (where Livingstone had lain in state), banking on
               his reputation as an artist, but also stressing the philanthropic and scientific
               object of his journey (and name-dropping to imply he had contacts in high places):
                  <quote>Besides my main artistic purpose, I am fitting myself to make the most of
                  my journey in a scientific sense, by making natural history collections, taking
                  observations so I intend to lose sight of nothing, and if there is any probability
                  of my being able to communicate with and succour Stanley or Cameron, I should be
                  glad to attempt it . . . . I do not propose to do anything very great in the way
                  of exploration and travel, in this my first attempt in Africa; but I shall do all
                  I find myself able to do, and I hope to make it the foundation of further
                  systematic, and self supporting travels, of which the scientific and philanthropic
                  results may be really valuable.</quote> He closes this letter by saying he has
               just received a letter from Captain Burton, <quote>by which I see I may meet him at
                  Zanzibar and have the advantage of his council and experience. <note
                     resp="editors" place="foot" n="18">See W. B. Thelwall’s letter to Sir Harry
                     Rawlinson of Dec. 15, 1875. </note>
               </quote> To see a son of John Thelwall associating himself with Morton Stanley (the
               journalist who had done so much to create Livingstone’s heroic reputation) and
               Richard Burton (the heroic but rakish scholar-explorer who captivated the Victorian
               imagination while challenging Victorian pieties), underlines the connection between
               the romantic idealism of the early nineteenth century and the colonial and commercial
               explorations and exploitations to which it gave birth. Just as Stanley gravitated to
               Livingstone, so Thelwall intends to “succour” Stanley, one in a long line of
               peripatetic journalist-adventurers belatedly following in the footsteps of
               charismatic father/brother-figures, whose quest leads them into the moral quagmire of
               ambitions, expectations, opportunities, and disillusionments that was colonial
               Africa. </p>
            <p> The line between the Romantic peripatetic and the Victorian explorer is deepened by
               the curious coincidence that among the groups whose support Weymouth sought for his
               African adventure were Scottish dissenters whose mission was built on the same
               progressive educational foundations that John Thelwall had helped lay. Weymouth wrote
               to the Livingstonia committee of the Free Church of Scotland, which with the support
               of several wealthy Glasgow industrialists had established their first Livingstonia
               mission station at Lake Nyassa in 1875, in honour of Livingstone’s dream of educating
               and converting the African tribes he encountered, and of eradicating slavery by
               setting up “industrial” educational missions. In this endeavour, Livingstone drew on
               his own background as a working-class boy whose self-education was capped by his
               studies at Anderson’s College in Glasgow (Ross 11-13). Founded in 1796, this
               institution was the home of George Birkbeck’s famous mechanics’ classes of 1800-04,
               which after 1823 grew into the mechanics’ institute movement that did so much to
               shape the British system of colonial education and industry (Kelly 26-36). This was
               the very institution that John Thelwall visited in 1804, where he and Birkbeck
               discussed the “operations and cooperations” that led to the founding of his own
               Institute (Letter to Anderson). Indeed, Thelwall’s lifelong friendship with Birkbeck
               is honoured in the middle name of his son. Thus in his very identity, Weymouth
               embodies the principles that Victorian colonialism inherited from Romantic
               radicalism. </p>
            <p> Weymouth’s letters to the Livingstonia Committee also show the complex and morally
               ambivalent geopolitical realities, commercial interests and religious tensions in
               which this idealistic and progressive effort was tangled. For in one letter he
               proposes “to bring 20 sniders [rifles] with me, and to form a well armed little
               party, as fast as I can find trustworthy men,” adding that he has been a very
               “zealous Sergeant of volunteers, having gone through the Hythe course, and hold[s] a
               certificate of qualification as Sergeant instructor of musketry.” Moreover, he is not
               “without hope that the presence of a Roman Catholic well accredited by his own
               ecclesiastical superiors may have a valuable effect on the Portuguese there, as
               showing the united earnestness of all Britain in this business” (<title level="m"
                  >Correspondence</title> 131). The “business” was the eradication of the slave
               trade, still dominating the local economy and culture of central Africa, by the
               introduction of “honest” trade in ivory, and the creation of cotton plantations; but
               it was equally the business of men like James Stevenson, the Glasgow industrialist
               who bankrolled much of it, and was seeking new sources of trade and the opening up of
               mineral resources to his company in a territory controlled by the Portuguese.<note
                  resp="editors" place="foot" n="19">See McCracken 222. </note>
            </p>
            <p>Thelwall got the answer he was looking for from the Livingstonia Committee; urged to
               join a reinforcement party travelling to the Cape, he gladly agreed, eager to
               “acquaint himself with all the members of the party” and to “share equitably in all
               expenses of transport etc. up to the arrival at the Nyassa Station” (<title level="m"
                  >Correspondence</title> 131). He drafted a letter of introduction, which the
               committee agreed to endorse, stating that without taking any responsibility for the
               acts of an independent traveller, “they are of the opinion that my journey will be of
               valuable assistance to the object they have in view, and that they will therefore be
               glad that I shall receive all the support that I can legitimately secure” (<title
                  level="m">Correspondence </title>138). Having now had his passage paid and letters
               of introduction to suppliers provided, he planned to finance the rest of his trip by
               accepting commissions, and sent the committee a sample advertisement flier aimed at
               collectors and lovers of the fine arts, claiming that several titled dignitaries had
               already contributed, among them Lady Rothschild (<title level="m"
                  >Correspondence</title> 138). There is, as yet, no confirmation of how many
               commissions Weymouth received or executed, but given the glow that Livingstone’s
               celebrity cast over the entire decade, it is likely that a good home market existed
               for the products of Thelwall’s African enterprise.</p>
            <p> Weymouth Thelwall sailed from London on the <title level="m">Windsor Castle</title>
               in May 1876, heading for the heart of Central Africa amidst the well-reported
               excitement of adventure and missionary zeal which the expedition aroused, and with
               the rapturous good wishes extended to the party in England and Scotland supplemented
               by press reports which were picked up by colonial newspapers from Sydney to Cape
                  Town.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="20">The progress of the expedition was
                  regularly reported in the national and local press, as well as colonial papers
                  such as <title level="m">The Sydney Herald</title> and <title level="m">The Cape
                     Town Argos</title>. </note> But he had been in Africa for only six months when
               ominous cracks began to appear in the façade of cooperation between the independent
               artist-adventurer and the industrious missionaries. James Stewart, the founder of
               Livingstonia, complained that Thelwall had bought goods in Port Elizabeth using “the
               same worthless bills” that Thelwall’s original correspondent on the committee,
               Alexander Duff, had reported to Stewart in a letter. More damning, he had heard via
               his brother-in-law in England that Thelwall had left his wife and child destitute:
                  <quote>He is an agreeable, plausible man but I fear not a good one . . . . I wish
                  he could be shipped home as if he goes on ordering goods without any means of
                  paying for them he will give the place a bad name. (Stewart, Letter to
                  Duff)</quote> Stewart’s nephew, the civil engineer James Stewart, recorded in his
               published journal for January 1878 that Thelwall’s visit to the Established Church of
               Scotland’s Blantyre Mission in the Shire Highlands had made a bad impression. Stewart
               had been “distinctly told not to trust him.” According to Stewart, “Thelwall seemed
               dissatisfied about something but made no complaint. He left without saying goodbye”
                  (<title level="m">From Nyassa</title> 49). A short time later Weymouth Thelwall
               was dead. </p>
            <p>Published accounts refer merely to a hunting accident. Thelwall tried to save
               ammunition by finishing off a wounded baboon with his rifle butt. The force of the
               blow, however, discharged the second bullet into his chest. The Livingstonia mission
               journal, however, goes into more detail in a report given by the native porters who
               had been with him. It tells a tale of isolation and probable despair. Whatever funds
               Thelwall had begun with and stores he may have managed to buy initially, he was at
               this stage unable to secure porters, who worked for lengths of calico cloth. He had
               been travelling for about nine days out of the Livingstonia mission, in March 1878,
               when he camped a day’s march from a village: <quote>Further particulars from the men
                  are to the effect that all went well until Mangombi’s village was reached. From
                  that time forward Mr Thelwall appeared in a desponding state of mind. When he
                  rested he buried his face in his hands and generally kept muttering to himself.
                  His appetite seemed to fail him and he subsisted chiefly on native beer and wine.
                  He became less active than formerly seldom rising before ten o’clock. <note
                     resp="editors" place="foot" n="21">See the <title level="m">Journal of the
                        Livingstonia Mission</title> for March 26, 1878.</note>
               </quote> According to the men, he had risen shortly before noon and, not delaying to
               dress (his blood-stained shirt was submitted as evidence), had armed himself and one
               of his men with rifles and another with a fowling piece. They had then set off a
               hundred yards to the foot of a hill to hunt baboons. Reading between the lines, it
               appears that Thelwall may have been lacking stores, and from the account given by the
               two Stewarts it is possible that he was not given much assistance at Blantyre. But
               one must also suspect that Thelwall may have pondered taking his own life. </p>
            <p>After his death, his followers trekked back to “Mponda’s village” on the lake where
               they were given a canoe to return by. They transported Thelwall’s body back there
               during a storm, but were refused permission to bury it until they paid the chief,
               Mponda, with Thelwall’s supplies of gunpowder and wine. He was buried some distance
               from the village (now a town in central Malawi) under a great baobab tree. Robert
               Laws, the leader of Livingstonia, later pulled down a Union Jack marking the grave,
               saying Mponda would use it on one of his raids (Livingstone 133-34). Thus, the last
               direct descendant of John Thelwall lies in an unmarked grave, even further off the
               beaten track of British history than his father’s gravesite in Bath, itself
               long-forgotten until Steve Poole’s recent restoration campaign. It is a far cry from
               the national honours paid to Livingstone, who had profited from the reforms that John
               Thelwall, without recognition, had helped to institute.</p>
            <p> Like his father’s, Thelwall’s fate was in some part sealed by his refusal to conform
               to contemporary pieties and proprieties. None of the missionaries who mention him
               seems to have had a good word for him, and this may have been partly due to his
               Catholicism. Edward Young, the first Livingstonia expeditionary leader and captain of
               the mission’s <title level="m">Illala</title> steamboat, recounts the day they
               engaged five hundred natives to carry the reinforcement party’s goods to the head of
               the rapids in 1876. He ordered silence while they sang a hymn and conducted a service
               together <quote>&#8212;save only&#8212;must I say it&#8212;with one exception; for an
                  individual who had arrived out from England with this missionary detachment of
                  labourers in Christ’s field felt himself debarred by conscientious scruples from
                  doing as we did. (Young 238) </quote> This “individual” was obviously Weymouth,
               but Young cannot even give his name. Like his father, Weymouth is almost erased from
               history. Yet tellingly, the liberty of conscience for which the Thelwall name has
               always stood, lives on in this record.</p>
            <p>There is very little information about what actually did come out of Thelwall’s
               African expedition. There are numerous records of the specimens he sent back:
               butterflies, lizards and plants, including some listed with his name in the
               catalogues of the British Museum and several journals of the time. Some paintings too
               may survive, though it is difficult to know which, if any, of the watercolours that
               anchor his continuing reputation as a minor English artist were among the effects
               sold in the months after his death. Like his father’s, Weymouth’s archive has been
               scattered and lost (and this includes any mementoes of his father’s that he may have
               carried with him). And yet, while neither name, nor goods, nor even an epitaph lives
               on, Weymouth Birkbeck Thelwall may have had a broader influence than we realize, in
               part through his very Catholicism (in both senses of the word). </p>
            <p>While the Scottish missionaries disapproved of his manner and morals, there is some
               evidence that Weymouth Thelwall found friends or at least sympathizers among
               Catholics in Africa. He is mentioned specifically as having influenced the setting-up
               of the first Jesuit missionary station in central Africa after he had “a long
               conversation” with Bishop James Ricards in Cape Town on his way to the Lake Nyassa
               mission station in 1876. Ricards wrote to Father Alfred Weld, another old Stonyhurst
               boy, enthusing about a plan of sending missionary priests to Lake Nyassa, which had
               apparently been Thelwall’s suggestion (Dachs and Rea 17). Likewise Frederick, Baron
               Lugard, gives Thelwall a measure of sympathy in an account written ten years after
               Thelwall’s death, by which time, as one of the few and first Europeans on Lake
               Nyassa, his story must have become part of local history. Lugard probably heard of
               him from Laws, with whom he stayed whilst leading an expeditionary force of natives
               for the newly formed African Lakes Company against Arab slave traders intent on
               driving out the merchants who had settled there. The tone is almost wistful. “On
               Nyassa poor Thelwall shot one [baboon] and was immediately attacked by the drove”
               (Lugard 271). This is not what happened according to the Livingstonia Mission
               journal, but it suggests that the story had already taken on a certain romantic,
               larger-than-life allure. Lugard appears to have had little time for the missionaries
               in general, but he does extol the virtues of Laws, whose kindliness and literary
               tastes are acknowledged. Laws had been absent from Livingstonia for some time when
               Thelwall died, and he heard of his death as he passed Mponda’s village, where Miller,
               one of the station’s Scottish artisans, had gone to see to his remaining goods. As
               they approached on the steamer Miller shouted from the shore, “Thelwall shot himself
               by accident.” Laws then set off for Thelwall’s grave. These “goods,” whatever they
               were, were sold at Livingstonia for fifty-eight pounds, five shillings and five pence
               in 1878, and the money was sent to Thelwall’s widow Marian, who signed a receipt in
               1880 (<title level="m">Correspondence </title>171). </p>
            <p> Re-reading Conrad’s Marlow relating the story of Mr. Kurtz in <title level="m">Heart
                  of Darkness</title>, I was struck by the characteristics which link Weymouth
               Thelwall with Kurtz. He too is a painter, a journalist, a hunter, an idealist with
               “expansive views,” and above all an eloquent speaker. But the overriding attraction
               for the younger Marlow lay in Kurtz’s “<title level="m">imagined”</title> voice. An
               unheard yet famous and powerful voice also links Weymouth Thelwall with his father
               John. “He too could declaim,” says Fitzgerald of his schoolmate at Stonyhurst. In the
               few writings that Weymouth left behind we too can “imagine” a voice, far removed as
               it may be from his father’s fiery oratory, already turned ashen by the belatedness of
               textuality (at least if Hazlitt is to be believed).<note resp="editors" place="foot"
                  n="22">Hazlitt contrasts Thelwall’s writing unfavourably with his oratory in “On
                  the Difference Between Writing and Speaking.” </note> John Thelwall’s is always an
               imagined voice, a something missed, and it is this belatedness that Weymouth
               Thelwall, who never really knew his father, had to live with and through. It is this
               legacy, always already lost, that he carried into Africa with him. </p>
            <p>Reading Weymouth’s story and thinking of Conrad’s Kurtz, I was reminded too of
               Wordsworth’s <title level="m">Excursion,</title> and the Pastor’s depiction of a
               brutal and pagan Britain (bk. 9, lines 679-719), which has much in common with
               Marlow’s reference to England as a once “dark place of the earth” in the opening
               paragraphs of <title level="m">Heart of Darkness</title> (33)<title level="m">.
               </title>“He was a seaman but he was a wanderer too,” the frame narrator says, as
               Marlow directs his listeners to <quote>think of a citizen in a toga&#8212;perhaps too
                  much dice, you know&#8212;coming out here in the train of some prefect, or
                  tax-gatherer, or trader, even, to mend his fortunes. Land in a swamp, march
                  through the woods, and in some inland post feel the savagery, the utter savagery
                  had closed around him. (33) </quote>
               <title level="m">The Excursion</title> concludes with the colonial zeal of the
               Wanderer’s “discourse,” the same kind of “discourse” that characterises the fatal
               attraction of Kurtz for Marlow and for his Intended, who listens like the unnamed
               “gentle lady” to Wordsworth’s Wanderer: <quote><lg>
                     <l>So the wide waters open to the power,</l>
                     <l>The will, the instincts, and appointed needs</l>
                     <l> Of Britain, do invite her to cast off</l>
                     <l> Her swarms, and in succession send them forth;</l>
                     <l> Bound to establish new communities</l>
                     <l> On every shore whose aspect favours hope</l>
                     <l> Or bold adventure; promising to skill</l>
                     <l> And perseverance their deserved reward. (9.375-82)</l>
                  </lg></quote> This is one of the passages highlighted in John Thelwall’s own copy
               of <title level="m">The Excursion</title>, part of the lifelong dialogue between
               himself and Wordsworth that had so strong an influence on both men’s work.<note
                  resp="editors" place="foot" n="23">I am grateful to Judith Thompson for her
                  transcriptions of Thelwall’s heavily-annotated copy of Wordsworth’s <title
                     level="m">Excursion</title> (in the collection of Paul F. Betz) and for
                  discussion of the ongoing dialogue between Thelwall and Wordsworth.</note>
               Thelwall’s <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title>,<title level="m"> </title>in
               particular, has long been recognised as an important influence on Wordsworth’s poem,
               but how much influence may Wordsworth’s poem have had on men like Livingstone, and
               through him Weymouth Thelwall? We may never know, but as scholars continue to explore
               Romanticism’s colonial legacies, we may discover that both Thelwall and Wordsworth
               had more influence than we have ever suspected upon the modernist novelist who draws
               us into to a deeper understanding of that heart of darkness that lurks in all
               “civilized” beings, romantics and radicals alike.<note resp="editors" place="foot"
                  n="24">See particularly Thorburn on the influence of Wordsworth<title level="m"
                  > </title>on Conrad’s work. Thorburn does not refer to <title level="m">The
                     Excursion </title>but details many of Conrad’s uses of Wordsworthian themes and
                  narrative techniques.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <title level="m">Heart of Darkness</title> was published in 1902, two years before
               Charles Cestre bought John Thelwall’s papers at a Sotheby’s sale. In May 1903,
                  the<title level="m"> New Zealand Tablet</title> published an article that provides
               an apt epitaph for Weymouth Birkbeck Thelwall, and a fitting summary of the
               circuitous route which this essay has taken: <quote>An interesting conversion (says
                  The London “Tablet,” March 28) took place last week. Mrs Thelwall, widow of the
                  well-known water-colour artist, Weymouth Thelwall, was received into the church by
                  the Rev. Father Coventry O.S.M. of the Fulham Priory. Mrs Thelwall is herself a
                  connection of Sir Walter Scott’s family, and her husband was the youngest son of
                  the celebrated John Thelwall, the Reformer, who together with Horne Tooke and
                  Hardy was tried for high treason in 1795. This conversion offers a curious
                  instance of the links of history. John Thelwall, the new convert’s father-in-law,
                  was the friend of Coleridge, Lamb, Hazlitt and Condorcet, and yet here is the
                  daughter in law living and hale at the dawn of the twentieth century. No man, in
                  his time, did more to advance Catholic Emancipation than John Thelwall, and, by a
                  curious coincidence, his son died a Catholic, and his grandchild is a pious
                  Catholic, whose influence has brought her mother into the fold. (“Returning to the
                  Fold”)</quote></p>

            <div type="citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Case of Mr Thelwall and Miss Fielding, alias Girofle</title>.
                  1875-1876. MS FO65/959. National Archives, Kew.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Conrad, Joseph. <title level="m">Heart of Darkness</title>
                  <title level="m">and Other Stories</title>. Ware: Wordsworth Classics, 1995.
                  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Correspondence Relating to the Livingstonia Mission. </title>MS
                  7870/7871. Free Church of Scotland Missionary Archives. National Library of
                  Scotland, Edinburgh.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">The Coursing Calendar and Report of the Spring Season
                     1864.</title> London, 1864. <title level="m">Google Book Search</title>. Web.
                  31 May 2010.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">“Court of Bankruptcy, Basinghall-Street, Dec. 8.” <title level="m"
                     >The Times </title>9 Dec 1864: 9. <title level="m">Times Digital Archive
                     1785-1985. </title>Web. 20 Nov 2009.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">“Court Circular.” <title level="m">The Times</title> 23 July 1873:
                  5. <title level="m">Times Digital</title>
                  <title level="m">Archive 1785-1985. </title>Web. 31 May 2010. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">Cox, Jeffrey. <title level="m">The British Missionary Enterprise
                     since 1700. </title>New York: Routledge, 2008. Print. Christianity and Society
                  in the Modern World.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Dachs, Anthony J., and W. F. Rea. <title level="m">The Catholic
                     Church and Zimbabwe: 1879-1979. </title>Gwelo: Mambo, 1979. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">“Deaths.” <title level="m">The Gentleman’s Magazine and Historical
                     Review</title> 218 (ns 18) (April 1865): 523-34. <title level="m">Google Book
                     Search</title>. Web. 15 Sept. 2009.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">“Expedition to Lake Nyassa.” <title level="m">Illustrated London
                     News</title> 12 June 1875: 550-51. Web. 31 May 2010.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Fitzgerald, Percy Hetherington. <title level="m">Stonyhurst
                     Memories; or, Six Years at School</title>. London, 1895. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">“Gazette, Tuesday, October 18.” <title level="m">The Law Journal
                     Reports for the Year 1864</title> ns 33 (1864): 175-76. <title level="m">Google
                     Book Search</title>. Web. 20 Oct. 2009.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Hazlitt, William. “On the Difference between Writing and Speaking.”
                     <title level="m">The Complete Works of William Hazlitt</title>. Ed. P. P. Howe.
                  Vol. 12. London: Dent, 1930-34. 262-79. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Hofland, Barbara. Letter to Mr. Hale. 15 July [1834-35]. <title
                     level="m">William Wordsworth and the Romantic Imagination: A Scholar’s
                     Collection</title>. Comp. Paul F. Betz. Ithaca: Cornell U Lib., 2000. 12.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Johnstone, H. A. Munro Butler. <title level="m">A Trip up the Volga
                     to the Fair of Nijni-Novgorod</title>. Oxford, 1875. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Journal of the Livingstonia Mission</title>. MS 7909. National
                  Library of Scotland, Edinburgh.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Kelly, Thomas. <title level="m">George Birkbeck: Pioneer of Adult
                     Education.</title> Liverpool: Liverpool UP, 1957. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Livingstone, W. P. <title level="m">Laws of Livingstonia: A
                     Narrative of Missionary Adventure and Achievement. </title>3rd ed. London:
                  Hodder and Stoughton, 1923. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Lugard, Frederick John Dealtry. <title level="m">The Rise of Our
                     East African Empire: Early Efforts in Nyasaland and Uganda</title>. Vol. 1.
                  Edinburgh, 1893. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">McCracken, John. “Livingstone and the Aftermath: The Origins and
                  Development of Livingstonia Mission.” <title level="m">Livingstone: Man of
                     Africa.</title> Ed. Bridglal Pachai. London: Longman, 1973. 218-34. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Place, Francis. <title level="m">London Radicalism 1830-1843: A
                     Selection of the Papers of Francis Place</title>. Ed. D. J. Rowe. London:
                  London Record Soc., 1970. British History Online. Web. 30 May 2010. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">Rees, Terence, and David Wilmore, eds. <title level="m">British
                     Theatrical Patents, 1801-1900.</title> London: Soc. for Theatre Research, 1996.
                  Print. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">“Returning to the Fold.” <title level="m">New Zealand
                     Tablet</title> 28 May 1903: 3. <title level="m">Papers Past</title>. The
                  National Library of New Zealand. Web. 12 Dec. 2009. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">Ross, Andrew C. <title level="m">David Livingstone: Mission and
                     Empire</title>. London: Hambledon &amp; London, 2002. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">“Sales by Auction.” <title level="j">The Times</title> 21 April
                  1820: 4. <title level="m">Times Digital Archive 1785-1985.</title> Web. 29 March
                  2010. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">Scrivener, Michael. <title level="m">Seditious Allegories: John
                     Thelwall and Jacobin Writing</title>. University Park: Pennsylvania State UP,
                  2001. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Statement Presented to Judge Erskine: A Statement Presented to
                     the Right Hon. Mr. Justice Erskine, President of the “Trinitarian Bible
                     Society,” Relative to Certain Most Extraordinary Circumstances Connected with a
                     Letter Addressed by the Rev. A. S. Thelwall, Secretary of that Society, to
                     Arthur Stanley, Esquire, President of the Bath Auxiliary Trinitarian Bible
                     Society</title>. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. with additions. London, 1840.
                     <title level="m">Google Book Search</title>. Web. 29 May 2010. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">Stewart, James. <title level="m">From Nyassa to Tanganyika: The
                     Journal of James Stewart CE in Central Africa, 1876-1879</title>. Ed. Jack
                  Thompson. Blantyre: Central Africana, 1989. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Stewart, James. Letter to Alexander Duff. 28 May 1877. MS
                  PPMS1/IBEA/1/2/1877. School of African and Oriental Studies Archives, University
                  of London, London.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thelwall, Algernon Sydney. <title level="m">Thoughts in Affliction.
                  </title>London, 1831. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thelwall, John. Letter to Dr. Anderson. 9 Feb. 1804. MS
                  Adv.MSS.22.4.14. National Lib. of Scotland, Edinburgh.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. Letter to Sara Thelwall. 4 Aug. 1831. MS Coleridge. Berg
                  Collection. New York Public Lib., New York. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">The Politics of English Jacobinism: Writings
                     of John Thelwall</title>. Ed. Gregory Claeys. University Park: Pennsylvania
                  State UP, 1995. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “The Rights of Nature, Against the Usurpations of
                  Establishments.” 1796. Claeys 389-500.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “Sober Reflections on the Seditious and Inflammatory Letter of
                  the Right Hon. Edmund Burke, to a Noble Lord.” 1796. Claeys 329-87.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “The Tribune. No. XXVIII. Report on the State of Popular
                  Opinion, and Causes of the Increase of Democratic Principles. Part the Fifth.”
                  1795. Claeys 232- 45.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thelwall, W. B. Letter to the Foreign Secretary. 21 Sept. 1875. MS
                  FO65/059. National Archives, Kew.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. Letter to Sir Harry Rawlinson. 1 Nov. 1875. MS CB6/2160. Royal
                  Geographical Soc. Archives, London.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. Letter to Sir Harry Rawlinson. 15 Dec. 1875. MS CB6/2160.
                  Royal Geographical Soc. Archives, London.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “Notes and Suggestions.” <title level="m">Den Norske
                     Turistforenings Årbog for 1871</title>. 104-08. Print. <title level="m">Årbok:
                     Norske Turistforenings, Oslo</title>. Kristiania, 1869-72. <title level="m"
                     >Google Book Search</title>. Web. 16 Sept. 2009.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">“Thelwall, Weymouth B.” Census Returns of England and Wales, 1871.
                  The National Archives, Kew. <title level="m">Ancestry.com</title>. Web. 13 May
                  2010.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thorburn, David. <title level="m">Conrad’s Romanticism</title>.
                  1974. New Haven: Yale UP, 1975. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Wordsworth, William. <title level="m">Poetical Works</title>. Ed.
                  Thomas Hutchinson and Ernest de Selincourt<title level="m">. </title>London:
                  Oxford UP, 1967. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Young, E. D. <title level="m">Nyassa: A Journal of Adventures
                     whilst Exploring Lake Nyassa, Central Africa, and Establishing the Settlement
                     of “Livingstonia.”</title> Rev. Horace Waller. London, 1877. Print.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
