<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">John Thelwall: Critical Reassessments</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">Gillray, Cruikshank &amp; Thelwall: Visual Satire, Physiognomy and the
               Jacobin Body</title>
            <author>
               <name>Steve Poole</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Yasmin Solomonescu</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.poole</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2010-11-01">September 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Gillray, Cruikshank &amp; Thelwall: Visual Satire,
                     Physiognomy and the Jacobin Body</title>

                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Steve</forename>
                        <surname>Poole</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">John Thelwall: Critical Reassessments</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2010-10-15">October 15, 2010</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for "," for ", ' for ',
                  and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2011-05-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>Gillray, Cruikshank &amp; Thelwall: Visual Satire, Physiognomy and the Jacobin
               Body</head>
            <byline><docAuthor>Steve Poole</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>University of the West of England, Bristol</affiliation></byline>
            <p>This essay examines the role of loyalist visual satire in the making and shaping of
               political notoriety during the period 1795-1825. Its subject is John Thelwall, the
               first non-elite English radical to be caricatured with reference to a recognisable
               physiognomy in the 1790s and, by contemporary reputation at least, the most
               influential and politically dangerous of the English Jacobins. It will be argued that
               Thelwall presented loyalist caricature with a particular set of problems. First,
               Thelwall enjoyed a particularly high public profile as a platform orator and lecturer
               in the 1790s, which meant that his face was well enough known to justify
               representation in more precise terms than those customarily used to depict the
               anonymous “Jacobin beast.” Even those that had never seen him might still recognise
               an accurate caricature because at least two engraved portraits and one bust on a
               commemorative conder coin were in circulation by the time of the 1794 Treason Trials
               and these likenesses share many physiognomical features in common. Second, much of
               Thelwall’s notoriety derived from his animated manner and volatility on the platform,
               which, taken together with his relatively small physical stature, offered
               caricaturists a vehicle for attitudinal, rather than simply facial, representation;
               but if Thelwall’s energetic manner was a subject for derogatory satire, it was also,
               conversely, the very thing that made him attractive to audiences. Third, Thelwall’s
               physiognomy was not remotely bestial. As contemporary biographers like John Aiken
               well understood, the heavy facial characteristics of a famously swarthy target like
               Fox, or Pitt, a man who “possessed no advantages of person or physiognomy, the first
               of which was ungraceful, the second repulsive” (200), were far more easily
               exaggerated and lampooned by caricaturists. In Thelwall’s case, the most likely
               effect of the sort of grotesque or sub-human representation commonly afforded in
               caricature to stock Jacobin figures would be personal anonymity rather than
               recognition, while faithful portraiture ran the equally undesirable risk of flattery.
               It will therefore be argued here that strategies are identifiable in the practice of
               James Gillray and Isaac Cruikshank by which Thelwall’s physiognomy and bodily energy
               were (differently) negotiated and accommodated within a broadly loyalist discourse,
               although neither artist found the assimilation particularly easy. Only when Thelwall
               announced his retirement from public life and retreated to Llyswen at the end of 1797
               did caricaturists settle upon a common form of unambiguous representation and, from
               this moment on, Thelwall became a cartoon signifier of radical defeat and
               deflation.</p>
            <p>Since most plebeian English Jacobins of the 1790s were unrecognisable to the wider
               public, caricature representations tended to adopt a familiar visual language.
               Jacobins, like Frenchmen, were invariably ragged, ignorant, unkempt, ungainly and
               cowardly with poor complexions, Neanderthal brows and gaping mouths. In both attitude
               and physiognomy, they were unprepossessing. Although the relatively respectable
               reformers Horne Tooke and Joseph Priestley had both been the subject of likeness
               caricatures prior to Thelwall’s rise to prominence in 1794, the only plebeian English
               Jacobin deemed worthy of personal attention between 1792 and 1793 was Tom Paine. But
               Paine was a writer, not an orator, and since most people had no idea what he looked
               like, caricaturists did not trouble themselves with his likeness. Consequently, Paine
               was recognisable in caricature only by his proximity to objects with which he was
               associated, most commonly a copy of <title level="m">Rights of Man</title>, an excise
               book, or a pair of stays.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="1">Paine’s portraiture has been discussed by
                     John Barrell in an unpublished paper, “Portraits and Caricatures of Paine.”
                  </note>
                Besides Thelwall, the London Corresponding Society’s best known public figure
               in 1795 was John Gale Jones, another radical whose fame was dependent upon his
               oratory. But, perhaps because he was not tried for treason in 1794, Jones’s profile
               never appeared on commemorative tokens, and no engraved portrait is known before
               1798. Consequently, when occasional reference was made to him in anti-Jacobin
               caricatures he was no more identifiable from his features than Paine had been. </p>
            <p>The pseudo-science of physiognomy reached the height of its popularity in England at
               precisely the same time that Thelwall was honing his oratorical style and Gillray,
               Cruikshank and Thomas Rowlandson were fully developing the art of political
               caricature. Johann Caspar Lavater’s <title level="m">Essays on Physiognomy</title>,
               originally published in German some twenty years earlier, were available to English
               readers in twelve versions and in five different translations during the 1790s.
               Lavater’s theories linking the body and the structure of the face to standards of
               morality and intellect were extraordinarily influential, not only among artists and
               their teaching academies, but among popular radicals seeking rational and scientific
               pathways to social and political virtue on the one hand and physiology on the other.
               Thelwall, who had signalled his interest in definitions of vitality by publishing a
               controversial essay on the subject in 1793, was an advocate and so too was Godwin.
               Indeed, the most popular of the 1790s editions of Lavater’s <title level="m"
                  >Essays</title> was translated by the playwright Thomas Holcroft, a member of the
               Society for Constitutional Information and, like Thelwall, indicted and committed to
               Newgate for treason in 1794.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="2">See Graham 562; Karr 431-33; and Thelwall,
                     “An Essay Towards a Definition of Animal Vitality.” </note>
                Nor did the popularisation of Lavater occur in a vacuum. A related attempt to
               “scientifically” measure intelligence and beauty against such material variables as
               head shape, nose length or the depth of the forehead was first published by the
               Dutchman Petrus Camper in 1791, for instance, and then translated for an edited and
               popular English edition in 1794. Camper’s work, moreover, was specifically concerned
               with the replication of these physiological ideas in the arts. Given public
               familiarity with both Thelwall’s physiognomy and his explosive bodily performance,
               caricaturists had every opportunity to adopt a more personal approach in their
               handling of Thelwall than they had deployed against Paine, and every encouragement to
               fully pursue it. As Gillray’s elderly friend, the one-time Tory MP Viscount Bateman,
               would later remind him, “It is in your hands to lower the opposition. Nothing
               mortifies them so much as being ridiculed and exposed in every window” (qtd. in
               Donald 170). However, although the two most prominent print satirists of the period,
               Gillray and Cruikshank, both made use of physiognomical likeness in dealing with
               Thelwall, they addressed the problem of his physical energy in diverging ways.</p>
            <figure n="1">
               <graphic url="../images/gillray_copenhagen_houseThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>James Gillray, Copenhagen House (1795). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1851,0901.759].
               </figDesc>
               
            </figure>
            <p>Thelwall’s first appearance in caricature is also his best known. Gillray’s <title
                  level="m">Copenhagen House </title>(1795) depicts the mass outdoor LCS meeting of
               12 November 1795 and was published four days after it. Thelwall is not named in the
               print, nor is he identified from speech bubbles or rolls of paper with “lectures”
               written on them, as he would sometimes be in later efforts. But he is clearly
               identifiable from his physiognomy and from what we might term his oratorical
               attitude. Gillray, who had studied physiognomy in the Royal Academy schools, was,
               like any trained artist of the period, well acquainted with the contents of Lavater’s
                  <title level="m">Essays</title>, and in 1798 would make direct reference to them
               in a satire entitled <title level="m">Dublures of Characters or Striking Resemblances
                  of Physiognomy</title>, in which members of the Foxite Opposition were made to
               reveal a series of satanic alter-egos. The association made by Gillray between face,
               expression and body in his depiction of Thelwall for <title level="m">Copenhagen
                  House</title> closely echoed Lavater’s assertion that “the affections of the mind
               should express themselves by the voice, the gestures, but especially by the
               countenance, and man should thus communicate to man his love, his resentment and the
               other emotions of his soul by a language perfectly infallible and universally
               understood” (Lavater 51). Thelwall understood platform performance in these cohesive
               terms too, for as he saw it, it is “uniformity and animation which should give life
               to [these] lectures” (<title level="m">Tribune</title> 3: 137). Only a month before
               the Copenhagen House meeting, he had apologised to an audience when poor health
               inherited from prison forced him, “a shattered feeble remnant of a man” (3:137), to
               deliver lectures reduced to “a statement of facts and principles and the conclusions
               that result from them,” rather than “enter into digressions that would arouse my
               passions and feelings and occasion me to speak with particular warmth and animation”
               (3: 17). Without the uniform engagement of heart and body with mind and voice, he
               feared, a lecture lost its capacity to inspire. This uniform engagement is deeply
               embedded in Gillray’s representation of Thelwall, accentuated by a profound
               separation from both the collective grotesquerie<title level="m"> </title>of his
               dullard audience and the more prosaic attitudes of the less accomplished orators on
               the other two platforms. While the lowly status of his platform colleagues is
               indicated by their shabby clothing and trades (butcher, dissenting minister and
               barber), Thelwall appears dressed as a gentleman of sorts, elevated materially and
               figuratively from the LCS and its audience, in a greatcoat and a ruffled stock. </p>
            
            <figure n="2">
               <graphic url="../images/cool_argumentsThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Isaac Cruikshank, Cool Arguments!!! (1794). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1851,0901.759].
               </figDesc>
           </figure>
            <p>If we are invited to read a degree of irrational anger in the clenching of his fists,
               and uncouthness in the gaping of his mouth, it remains a considerably kinder
               portrayal than the oddly twisted form given to Thomas Erskine, Thelwall’s principal
               defender a year earlier during the Treason Trials, by Isaac Cruikshank in <title
                  level="m">Cool Arguments!!!</title> (1794). Gillray’s Thelwall retains a degree of
               balance and self-possession that Cruikshank’s Erskine has almost lost, the
               barrister’s awkward body satirically betraying the “cool argument” of the title, and
               rendering him in the process considerably more comic than the <title level="m">bête
                  noir</title> of Jacobinism. Thelwall was no stranger to the political dynamics of
               empiricism and distortion in the manufacture of “likeness,” or the delicate balance
               between truth, poetic licence and caricature, and wrote about it at some length. In
               the course of his pedestrian tour from London to the West Country to visit Coleridge
               in 1797, he studied the classical busts at Wilton House and noted discrepancies
               between the recorded features of various Roman heroes and villains and their
               historical reputations. He was fascinated by the conflicting messages suggested by
               Seneca’s “open mouth and the mixture of voluptuousness and intellectual power blended
               in the lines and solid parts of the face” because he regarded Seneca as a genius too
               flawed “to live with the purity of a philosopher.” But two busts of Brutus, whose
               love of liberty and virtue Shakespeare and a great many historians had been so
               careful to record, presented a physiognomy that was “assassination personified.” Here
               was cause for thought. “What shall we say to this? Are the portraits fictitious? Or
               have we been imposed upon by legendary panegyrics?” The latter, he decided, was the
               more likely answer. The politically motivated distortions of history might always be
               exposed by returning to the evidence of the face itself. “Perhaps our admiration of
               Brutus or Cassius may have been carried too far,” he reflected. “For my own part,
               establish the authenticity of the likeness and I will believe the testimony of a
               man’s countenance in preference to his historian” (“Pedestrian” 30-32). </p>
               
            <figure n="3">
               <graphic url="../images/portrait-richterThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Henry Richter, John Thelwall (1794). Photo by S. Poole.
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="4">
               <graphic url="../images/ridley-richter_thelwallThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>William Ridley (after Henry Richter), John Thelwall (1794).
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            <p>By the time of the Copenhagen House meeting, Gillray had at least two serious
               portraits of Thelwall upon which to draw, both derived from sketches taken in the
               Tower by Henry Richter, the brother of Thelwall’s co-defendant, John. These two
               engravings are equally careful in their recording of Thelwall’s slim body, long nose,
               strong chin, slight pinching of the brow (both this and the rolled scroll recalling
               classical representations of Demosthenes), thin, fashionably cropped hair cut back
               from the forehead but just over the ears, and an elaborately ruffled stock. It is
               fair to assume that this is a close enough approximation to Thelwall’s actual
               appearance at the age of thirty, and as portraits they correspond quite convincingly
               with the sharp featured bust of Thelwall that appeared on commemorative conder
               tokens at roughly the same time.
            
            <figure n="5">
               <graphic url="../images/thelwall_tokenThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Conder token with head of John Thelwall (1796). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum # SSB,237.70].
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="6">
               <graphic url="../images/John_Thelwall_by_John_HazlittThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>William Hazlitt (attributed), Portrait of John Thelwall (c. 1800-05). © <ref target="http://www.npg.org.uk">National Portrait Gallery, London</ref>.
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="7">
               <graphic url="../images/thelwall-public-charactersThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Anon., Head of John Thelwall from 
                  Public Characters, 1800-1801. Photo by S. Poole, from a copy of Public Characters in the Library at Downside Abbey, Somerset.
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
             To these we can add John Hazlitt’s portrait in oils, and
               the miniature profile line drawing that accompanied his appearance in <title
                  level="m">Public Characters</title>, both made about six years later when Thelwall
               had “retired” from politics. These various portraits may be read as self-conscious
               attempts to emphasise physical signs, not of oratorical enthusiasm or of reason lost
               but of reason secured. They emphasise the performative element of Thelwall’s public
               persona as transitory and self-controlled, and provide a balance both to the <title
                  level="m">appearance </title>of spasmodic excitability on the platform and to some
               of the crude representations of the diseased and emaciated Jacobin body so
               characteristic of the visual language of loyalism.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="3">For a fuller discussion of radical
                     attitudes to visual propaganda, see Barrell, “Radicalism.”</note>
                Although Gillray made no attempt in this print to miniaturise his subject,
               Thelwall was the first to admit his own “want of figure” and “feeble constitution”
               (“Prefatory” 64), for as we learn from his second wife, Cecil, “his chest was narrow;
               part of his pleura had firmly adhered to his ribs” (Mrs. Thelwall 40). Thomas Noon
               Talfourd regarded Thelwall as “small” and “compact” (298), and the Bow Street Officer
               James Walsh concurred; he was “a little stout man with dark cropt hair,” quite unlike
               the dominant figure in <title level="m">Copenhagen House</title>. This smallness of
               stature did not make him <title level="m">appear</title> feeble, however, for he was
               strongly built and held himself well. Talfourd, in fact, also remembered Thelwall as
               “muscular,” with a body sturdy enough to support “a head denoting indomitable
               resolution, and features deeply furrowed by the ardent workings of the mind” (298). </p>
            <p>The perception of balance between passion and reason was of particular concern for
               public speakers like Thelwall for, as Godwin would have it, every orator was prone to
               “a due mixture of spices and seasoning” in his delivery, since “quiet disquisition
               and mere speculative enquiry will not answer his purpose” (20). Bombastic enthusiasm,
               Godwin feared, led to exaggeration and over-emphasis and risked a counter-productive
               incitement to irrational acts of violence. It is well known that Thelwall challenged
               Godwin over these allegations during the public debates over Pitt’s Gagging Bills in
               1795, and it is clear that Godwin felt his case proven by the intemperate nature of
               Thelwall’s rebuttals, and the “angry temper” that gave rise to them. “It is
               impossible for me to answer the farrago of abusive language you send me,” Godwin
               retorted (Cestre 203-04). Godwin was not alone among Thelwall’s political
               sympathisers in airing his misgivings about the orator’s volcanic temper. Talfourd
               put it this way: “Thelwall spoke boldly and vehemently at a time when indignation was
               thought to be a virtue . . . . [S]peech was, in him, all in all, his delight, his
               profession, his triumph, with little else than passion to inspire or colour it”
               (296). More than once Thelwall intimated that the passions of the heart should not be
               held accountable to the reasonings of the head, but rather the two should be
               Socratically harmonized, though few thought he had achieved it. An inevitable
               consequence of oratorical passion, it was argued in one anti-Jacobin tract, was that
               “the multitude echo the variable will of the demagogue, he wields their dreadful
               caprice and hurls it at whatever opposes his own interests. The multitude is the
               unenlightened part of a Nation; and the multitude is the tool of the demagogue”
                  (<title level="m">Rights of Citizens</title> 116).</p>
            <p>If the representation of Thelwall’s features in Richter and Hazlitt’s portraits was
               intended to invoke a calm and intellectual counterpoint to platform energy, it was
               nevertheless subject to alternative readings by loyalist writers who saw in it less a
               revelation of the self than a concealment. The anti-Jacobin novelist George Walker,
               for example, who used Thelwall undisguisedly as a model for his sinister and
               classically minded democratic orator in <title level="m">The Vagabond</title> (1799),
               considered these same features to reveal “a little dark-complexioned man with a most
               hypocritical countenance and a grin of self-applause mingled with contempt”
                  (79).<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="4">The character alludes to ancient Rome
                  as a cipher for England.</note> Physiognomical interpretation was, unsurprisingly,
               of considerable interest to Thelwall, who confirmed his belief in Lavater’s
               strictures on more than one occasion, and took more than a passing interest in the
               facial and cranial peculiarities of his own family. To Peter Crompton of Liverpool he
               assessed his son Algernon in 1798: “I have a thousand Shandean notions about him&#8212;the peculiar form of his head, the remarkable cast of his features, and the thousand
               antic forms into which he is every now and then distorting them fill me with many a
               proud and many an anxious thought.” In fact, Thelwall was confident enough of his own
               features to seek comment from Coleridge on a now lost self-portrait, either written
               or drawn in 1796, and the satisfaction with which he regarded the strong lines of his
               own nose and chin may be judged from the rude remarks he would later make about the
               supposed weaknesses of his literary adversary Francis Jeffrey’s.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="5">Coleridge was “interested” in Thelwall’s
                     self description, but confined his response to a series of observations about
                     the inadequacies of his own physiognomy (Letter to Thelwall). Of Jeffrey, whose
                     critical reviews of the <title level="m">Poems</title> of 1801 hugely irritated
                     Thelwall, he wrote, “To all the advantage to be derived from the shortness of
                     his chin, Mr Jeffrey is most certainly entitled, and it may perhaps be of some
                     importance to those whose <title level="m">forwardness</title> is more
                     conspicuous than their <title level="m">understanding</title>, that their
                        <title level="m">chins</title> as well as their <title level="m"
                        >noses</title>, should not be over prominent” (<title level="m"
                        >Reply</title> 163).</note>
               
            </p>
            <p>Since Jacobin self-representation was partly to be a balancing act between base
               demagoguery and Demosthenian assertion, Thelwall was careful to embrace and improve
               upon Lavater’s unification of voice, gesture and countenance in the construction of
               his own public self as well as in the advice he later gave to his elocution students.
               There was an important distinction to be made between histrionic excess or the
               “theatrical elocution” of the stage, and the sort of expressive oratory that arose
               from “the <title level="m">harmony</title> of features, voice and action.” Controlled
               gesticulation, moreover, was natural to the “deportment of all persons when excited,”
               a “natural part of eloquence” in fact, and its “habitual restraint the chief cause of
               graceless and extravagant action” (<title level="m">Selections</title>-York 2).
               Thelwall’s students were lectured on physiognomy and encouraged to cultivate facial
               expression as a natural accompaniment to vocal inflection and bodily stance. The
               “fashionable insipidity” of an “inexpressive countenance,” Thelwall told them,
               suggested only a “vacancy of mind” (<title level="m">Selections</title>-Hull).
               Moreover, insipid oratory was the consequence of a conspiracy amongst modern
               elocutionists “to reduce almost all public speaking but that of the stage to one
               sympathetic monotony of tone and look and attitude” so that “all expression of
               attitude and feature . . . ought to be confined to the mummeries for which they are
               supposed to have been invented” (<title level="m">Vestibule</title> 20).</p>
            <p>A holistic approach to vitality and character is a constant trait in Thelwall’s
               writing. From our introduction to his imaginary companion and virtual alter-ego,
               Ambulator, in <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> of 1793, with his “small, but
               erect and manly form, his open brow, his strong but softened features, and his
               forward-darting eye, which reveal to the physiognomist the internal graces and
               dignity of his mind” (88-89), to the manifesto-like appeals of the <title level="m"
                  >Vestibule of Eloquence</title> seventeen years later, Thelwall consistently
               linked the science of physiognomy with improving elocution, deportment and intellect.
               Language alone would not suffice; on the contrary, “nature’s epitome, like nature’s
               self, must sympathise through every element: motion and look and attitude must
               manifest the inspiration of genuine feeling; and every portion of the frame must be
               vital with expressive eloquence” (<title level="m">Vestibule</title> 21). Gillray,
               whose own practice was largely based upon an appreciation of exaggerated animation
               and physiognomical distortion, was clearly fascinated by Thelwall and his attitude
               towards him remained characteristically ambiguous. In <title level="m">Copenhagen
                  House</title>, the dynamic contrast between Gillray’s Thelwall and Gillray’s crowd
               is not intended to confer much credit upon the latter; indeed, the argument of the
               print is dependent upon the accentuation of distance between the two. Understandably,
               Thelwall rejected any association between his crowd and Burke’s swinish multitude,
               and used physiognomy once again to refute the charge. “I am not speaking to an
               unenlightened and uninformed auditory,” he declared, “I can perceive countenances,
               many of which I know, and in many of which, though I do not know them, I can read the
               lines of intelligence and education” (<title level="m">Tribune</title> 3: 248).
               Gillray may not have been prepared to accept that but, like Coleridge, he was not
               unaware that “Thelwall is the voice of tens of thousands” (Coleridge, <title
                  level="m">Plot</title> 20-21), and the clear evidence of Thelwall’s personal
               magnetism did not present obvious strategies for hostile loyalist caricature. </p>
            <p>Thelwall certainly felt his own persuasive genius, “for he had the satisfaction of
               seeing persons filling considerable stations in society who had at first gone to hear
               him with every hostile intention, become his warmest approvers; and very frequently,
               in after life, he was greeted by men of first-rate intellect and staunch reformers,
               with their acknowledgement that he was their political father” (Mrs. Thelwall
               405-06).
            <figure n="8">
               <graphic url="../images/billys_hobby_horseThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Anon., Billy’s Hobby Horse (1795). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1876,1014.30].
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="9">
               <graphic url="../images/cruikshank_royal_extinguisherThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Isaac Cruikshank, The Royal Extinguisher (1795). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1868,0808.6487].
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            The exceptionalism implicit in Gillray’s image can be demonstrated by comparing it to
               the only previous attempt by a caricaturist to represent LCS oratory, the anonymous
                  <title level="m">Billy’s Hobby Horse</title> (1795) in which the St. George’s
               Fields meeting of 29 June 1795 forms part of the background. The only speaker that
               day was John Gale Jones, visible in the print with his arm raised, but no attempt has
               been made at likeness or oratorical posture and the meeting’s marginal position
               behind the principal figures of Pitt and John Bull reduces its role to one of
               commentary and context rather than argument and agency. We might also note the
               immediate and wholesale plagiarism of Gillray’s figure by Cruikshank in <title
                  level="m">The Royal Extinguisher</title> (1795), published a few days after <title
                  level="m">Copenhagen House</title>, and avoiding the political ambiguity
               underpinning Gillray’s print. In Cruikshank’s hands, Thelwall, though bodily
               identical, has become ridiculously Lilliputian; railing punily against Pitt’s
               towering Gulliver while the shelter of Gillray’s sun umbrella has been replaced by
               a gigantic candle snuffer. By contrast, Gillray’s ambivalent refusal to treat the LCS
               as a serious threat was not particularly helpful to ministerial arguments for the
               suppression of free speech and public assembly in the wake of the attack on the
               King’s coach a few weeks earlier. Indeed, some of the most diminutive and ineffectual
               figures in <title level="m">Copenhagen House</title> are the central representations
               of Fox and Pitt as children chancing their luck on an EO table while an unrestrained
               Thelwall thunders above their heads. Perhaps to avoid the ambiguity of presenting the
               public with the sort of irrepressibly energetic Thelwall they might actually
               recognise, therefore, Cruikshank changed tack after the passage of the Two Acts,
               divorced the orator from his popular constituency and re-fashioned him as a dupe of
               the Foxite Whigs.</p>
            <p>Rumours of a closer working relationship between the Fox and the LCS began to
               circulate publicly late in 1795. Cruikshank had already placed Fox, Sheridan and
               Stanhope in the Lilliputian crowd surrounding Thelwall in the <title level="m">Royal
                  Extinguisher</title>, and Gillray had made them leaders of the mob that attacked
               the King’s coach on October 29th in his highly ambiguous <title
                  level="m">Republican Attack</title>. These rumours gathered pace, however, after
               Fox and several of his parliamentary allies attended Thelwall’s speech against the
               Gagging Bills at the last mass outdoor meeting of the Society on 7 December (<title
                  level="m">Morning Post</title> 8 Dec. 1795). This was followed by a series of
               debates on “the most probable means left of saving the country from the despotism of
               the minister” in the Westminster Forum at which John Gale Jones claimed he had been
               waited upon by prominent Whigs and invited to join a general coalition against Pitt
               (Thale 330). In fact, according to Cecil Thelwall’s account, “Thelwall was the means
               of this union which now took place between the Whig Club and the London Corresponding
               Society,” for each had become “necessary to the preservation of the other,” although
               the LCS officially denied having anything to do with it (Mrs. Thelwall 399). Rumours
               circulated during the general election campaign of 1796 that Thelwall was intending
               to contest war minister William Windham’s seat at Norwich, but in fact he busied
               himself in supporting Fox at Westminster, where the Whig leader and the Pittite
               Admiral Allan Gardner were involved in a three-cornered contest with Thelwall’s first
               political mentor, John Horne Tooke. Thelwall had quarrelled with Tooke after the
               Treason Trials, but hoped now to see him elected with Fox at Gardner’s expense. He
               used the campaign to make a number of speeches calling for cross-party radical unity
               to defeat the ministry, but although Fox was returned, Gardner forced Tooke into
               third place.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="6">For reports of these developments, see
                        <title level="m">Telegraph</title> 23 May 1796; <title level="m">True
                        Briton</title> 28 May 1796; <title level="m">Morning Post</title> 9 and 14
                     June 1796. Thelwall shared Tooke’s philological interest in creating a devolved
                     non-elite language of politics and, like Tooke, was frequently taken to task by
                     the loyalist press for dangerously addressing plebeian audiences in non-elite
                     language. On this subject, see Jenks. For Thelwall’s relationship with Tooke,
                     see Mrs. Thelwall 343-44. William Windham was notorious for referring to
                     Thelwall and his fellow treason trial defendants of 1794 as “acquitted
                     felons.”</note>
                Despite appearances, Tooke and Fox had not in fact entered into a coalition,
               but government supporters made capital from it and were quick to point out that,
               “among the worthy electors in the interest of our senator were to be numbered Citizen
               John Thelwall, Citizen John Gale Jones, and not a few members of the Corresponding
               Society” (Bisset 3: 381). This too was the theme of Thomas Rowlandson’s <title
                  level="m">Sir Alan Gardiner at Covent Garden</title> (1796) in which, not for the
               last time, Thelwall’s unwise associations left him headless, along with both Hardy
               and Tooke. This was the first caricature print to use the verbal joke “tell-well,” a
               nick-name for the lecturer that first surfaced in <title level="m">The Times</title>
               in 1794.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="7">See <title level="m">New Times</title> 6
                     Sept. 1794. This was a satirical edition of <title level="m">The Times</title>,
                     imagining life in England after a French invasion.</note>
               
            </p>
            <figure n="10">
               <graphic url="../images/rowlandson_gardiner_coventThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Thomas Rowlandson, Sir Alan Gardiner at Covent Garden (1796). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1935,0522.4.70].
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            <p>Shortly after this, Thelwall left London for his first provincial lecture tour and
               ceased for a time to be of interest to the capital’s satirists. However, when Fox
               found himself as without influence in the reconstituted parliament as he had been in
               the previous one, he led his party into a symbolic secession from the House, citing
               as causes Pitt’s retreat into cabinet government and the intransigence of the
               ministry over reform and the continuation of the war. Instead, he proposed
               co-operation with the extra-parliamentary reform movement who would otherwise be
               either “too weak to resist the Court” or, more ominously, prone to dangerous
               “excesses” (<title level="m">Public Advertiser</title> 8 Aug. 1797). Unsurprisingly,
               Fox’s loyalist critics suspected darker motives, for “telling the People that their
               parliament will not listen to reason” was “little short of an invitation to civil
               war” (Wells 65-66). The suspicion that radicals like Thelwall and Tooke were secretly
               plotting with disaffected parliamentarians like Fox, Stanhope, Sheridan and the Duke
               of Bedford to overthrow the State proved irresistible to satirists and in June,
               Thelwall reappeared as a pivotal figure in a series of critical prints by
               Cruikshank.
            
            <figure n="11">
               <graphic url="../images/cruikshank_purleyThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Isaac Cruikshank, The Diversions of Purley (5 June 1797). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1868,0808.6637].
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="12">
               <graphic url="../images/cruikshank_delegatesThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Isaac Cruikshank, Delegates in Council (9 June 1797). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1868,0808.6641].
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            These prints do not address Thelwall’s bodily energy, however, partly perhaps because
               other ministerial propagandists were emphasising the success of the Gagging Acts in
               stopping his mouth. “It is all over with me,” he is made to lament in one pamphlet, 
            <quote><lg><l>Where shall I sedition roar</l>
            <l>In what room my tribune place</l>
            <l>Thelwall’s business is no more</l>
            <l>Stopp’d for ever is his race. (<title level="m">Decline</title> 17-18)</l></lg></quote>
            For Cruikshank, however, Thelwall was more dangerous without his lectern than with
               it. In these prints, he may be recognised from his likeness and from textual
               allusions to lecturing, but he is otherwise unremarkable as he consorts privately
               with his influential new allies. In the first of them, <title level="m">The
                  Diversions of Purley</title>, Thelwall appears as part of the secessionist
               coalition with Erskine, Fox, Sheridan, Stanhope and Grey. He is no longer the orator
               but the secretive plotter, in a busy nursery, scissoring “old fashioned” aristocratic
               ermine to make swaddling for Fox’s monstrous offspring, master Revolution and miss
               Sedition. Should his profile be insufficient to identify him, he addresses a figure
               who breaks into the frame from the left with a query, “Did you hear my last lecture?”
               This figure is Horne Tooke, whose best known work provides the satire with its title,
               and who answers Thelwall with another question, “Have you heard from Sheerness”?
               Together, Tooke’s question and his peripheral position provide a commentary on
               Thelwall’s role as intermediary between Fox and Tooke on the one hand and between
               Jacobinism and the naval mutinies on the other. The mutiny at the Nore, close to the
               Kent coast at Sheerness, had broken out simultaneously with the second mutiny at
               Spithead, Portsmouth. John Gale Jones had been sent on a lecturing mission to the
               Kentish dockyards in 1796 and the LCS had gone to some trouble to encourage radical
               societies at Portsmouth. They were now widely suspected in the loyalist press of
               agitating amongst the sailors and schooling them in political and democratic demands.
               In May, <title level="m">The True Briton</title> had claimed Thelwall was on the Isle
               of Wight, “not an indifferent spectator, doubtless, of the late proceedings at
               Spithead,” and Cruikshank’s allusion is not unpredictable (12 May 1797). <title
                  level="m">Diversions of Purley</title> was followed four days later by a second
               comment on the mutinies, <title level="m">The Delegates in Council</title>. Thelwall,
               having flitted from his Janus-like role between Fox and Tooke to the lower deck HMS
               Sandwich at the Nore, was now placed in a more sinister position as familiar,
               prompter and grog-server to the mutineers in the negotiation of terms with Admiral
               Buckner. Tooke resumes his rightful position under the table with the Foxite
               parliamentarians, but Thelwall stands openly beside his grotesquely drawn plebeian
               associates, fixes the Admiral squarely in the eye and issues instructions: “Tell him
               we intend to be masters,” he says, “I”ll read him a lecture.” Here, Cruikshank
               persuades his audience, was a man uniquely comfortable in both Opposition and
               insurrectionary circles and apparently able not only to move between them with ease
               but to direct operations from an assumed position of authority. 
            
            <figure n="13">
               <graphic url="../images/cruikshank_watchmanThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Isaac Cruikshank, Watchman of the State (20 June 1797). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1868,0808.6644].
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            Later in the month, Cruikshank produced a third related image, <title level="m"
                  >The</title>
               <title level="m">Watchman of the State</title>. As in <title level="m">Diversions of
                  Purley</title>, Fox is the central figure, this time in the character of an
               absconding watchman, deserting his post and abdicating his responsibility to keep the
               more extreme wing of the democratic coalition under control. Lauderdale and Bedford
               watch and applaud while Horne Tooke, Sheridan, and Stanhope lay gunpowder trails to
               destroy the constitution, the Commons and the Lords. A diminutive Thelwall, with a
               paper marked “Norwich lectures” in his pocket, once again provides the link with
               extra-parliamentary mischief making, this time lighting a taper from Stanhope’s
               lantern in a bid to destroy aristocracy. </p>
            <p>In all three of these prints, Cruikshank’s approach is different from Gillray’s.
               Thelwall’s physiognomy is reproduced with sufficient accuracy to make him
               recognisable, and his features do not undergo even the slight comedic distortions
               made use of by Gillray. But no allusion is made to his oratorical voice or to his
               bodily energy. He is in fact quite unremarkable, and this, perhaps, is Cruikshank’s
               point. What makes Thelwall dangerous is not the bluster and posturing of his high
               profile public performances but his chameleon-like ability to flit between various
               reform parties, belonging to none but at ease in any. Given Thelwall’s self-evident
               personal attractions and his polymathical intellectual dabblings in science,
               philosophy and the arts, some loyalist approaches to Jacobinism identified a
               framework of fluidity, sophistry and adaptability in the belly of the beast. As the
               arch-loyalist Robert Bisset put it, seemingly with Thelwall in mind: 
            <quote>One prominent feature often mentioned in Jacobinism is its versatility . . . . He is at
               one time a pamphleteer . . . we have him next as a novel-monger . . . next the Jacobin tries
               his hand at play-writing . . . the Jacobin now changes himself into the form of a
               lecturer, and from his tub his nightly nonsense pours . . . dabbling a little in
               metaphysics which are too deep for being fathomed by his line of understanding, he
               next comes upon us as a political philosopher . . . he turns critic next, and as a
               reviewer attempts to spread the beneficial doctrines and precepts of the various
               works he brings out in his other manifold capacities . . . he is a Socinian, a Methodist,
               a Seceder, a Presbyterian, a Roman Catholic, or a Mahometan; he has projected to be a
               Hindoo; he has been seen in the mosque and on his way to the pagoda, he struts at the
               school desk, he pops upon us in the conventicle, and assails us on the roadside.
               (Bisset 2: 242-43)</quote>
            Duplicity of this kind is rarely betrayed by low appearance or bad physiognomy; on
               the contrary, when understood on these terms, the Jacobin may be anonymous, prosaic,
               unnoticed. The Jacobin was not the first folk-devil to be constructed in this way for
               it had also been the fate of the eighteenth-century sodomite, another sinister figure
               variously imagined to be recognisable from his posture, speech and clothing, or
               alternatively concealed by outward shows of the ordinary. Sodomites did not always
               conform to the popular stereotype, lamented the pamphleteer Emanuel Collins in 1756;
               on the contrary, their insidious posturing as something they were not made them
               doubly dangerous. They “fly generally to large cities to hide themselves in the
               multitude, and seek security in the crowd . . . . Undaunted and upright they crowd our
               publick walks, unaw’d by guilt, and unappal’d by the fears of any impeachment” (1,
               7). Like Jacobins, they were masters of facade and pretence, “lurking,” as one
               newspaper put it in an attempt to forewarn its readers, “under the different
               characters and disguises of a solicitor, a gentleman of an estate, a steward to a
               nobleman, a cook, a tapster, and other shapes” (<title level="m">Newcastle
                  Courant</title> 24 Sept. 1737).</p>
            <figure n="14">
               <graphic url="../images/gillray_horrorsThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>James Gillray, Promis’d Horrors of a French Invasion (1796). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1851,0901.823].
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            <p>The contrast between Cruikshank and Gillray’s practice at this time was further
               demonstrated in the latter’s complex and highly finished <title level="m">Promis’d
                  Horrors of the French Invasion – or – Forcible reasons for Negotiating a Regicide Peace</title>
               (1796). In this print, Gillray’s captivation by Thelwall’s energy and his ambivalence
               towards him is clear once again. Small in body but active and highly spirited, a
               recognisably sharp-featured Thelwall takes the Great Bedfordshire Ox (his opposition
               ally, the Duke of Bedford) by the tail and, with a well-aimed kick and a wave from a
               rolled copy of his lectures, encourages him to up-end a flailing Edmund Burke at the
               doorway of Brookes’s club in St James. Like Cruikshank, Gillray uses Thelwall more as
               an abettor and instigator than a direct agent, but he is possessed by a comic <title
                  level="m">joie de vivre</title> that scarcely suggests the “promis’d horrors” of
               the design. The loyalist message of the print is compromised in any case by Gillray’s
               insistence on using dice, playing cards and an EO table in White’s Club to cloud our
               sympathies for the misfortunes of a dissolute Royal Family (the Prince of Wales and
               the Dukes of Clarence and York). 
            <figure n="15">
               <graphic url="../images/gillray_irish_invasionThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>James Gillray, End of the Irish Invasion (Jan. 1797). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1868,0808.6585].
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            Gillray was not uninterested in the Corresponding Society’s relationship with the
               seceding Foxites, but unlike Cruikshank, he used the unlikely coalition as a vehicle
               for light comedy, doomed to failure, and ultimately the cause of Thelwall’s undoing.
               He is never a threatening figure in Gillray’s work; rather, he is transformed from a
               fountain of energy in 1795-96, to the representation of Jacobin defeat by the
               beginning of 1797. In<title level="m"> The End of the Irish Invasion</title> (1797),
               a comment on the dispersal of Hoche’s invasion fleet off the coast of Ireland in
               1796, French complicity with the Foxite/Jacobin coalition founders in storm-tossed
               seas and Thelwall is figuratively shipwrecked alongside Erskine and the Whig
               secceders. With his lectures in his pocket, and a pack of playing cards bobbing on
               the water behind him, Thelwall’s political “gamble” has failed and he is, quite
               literally, out of luck and out of his depth. A few days later in another Gillray
               satire, <title level="m">The Tree of Liberty must be Planted Immediately
               </title>(1797), 
            <figure n="16">
               <graphic url="../images/gillray_treeThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>James Gillray, The Tree of Liberty Must Be Planted Immediately (Feb. 1797). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1868,0808.6594].
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            Thelwall is once again a victim of hubris. Having failed to learn the lessons of his
               own lectures on classical history, his severed head lies slightly to the side of
               those of the Whigs, meaningfully separated from them by the executioner’s axe and
               resting upon a signifier of his own folly, a notice announcing “lectures upon the
               fall of the republic.” It is true that Gillray featured a revitalised Thelwall the
               following year in <title level="m">The New Morality</title> (1798), 
               <figure n="17">
                  <graphic url="../images/new_moralityThumb.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>James Gillray, The New Morality (1798). Photograph by S. Poole, image reproduction for non-commercial purposes, courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.
                  </figDesc>
               </figure> but this was a
               directed commission for the <title level="m">Anti-Jacobin</title> magazine and prompted as
               much by a specific reference in Canning’s accompanying verse as any decision of his
               own. The revitalisation is in any case compromised once again by defeat, robbing
               Thelwall of power and influence despite his deportment. As assorted English Jacobins
               pay homage to Larevelliere Lepaux—the “High Priest,” as Canning put it, of the French
               cult of “Theophilanthropy”—Thelwall, portrayed as a railing imp on Bedford’s
               Leviathan shoulders, has become more feeble-bodied than before. In severely
               mud-spattered clothing, Thelwall is clearly no longer the “voice of thousands” and
               there is now an absurdity to his animation. The mud is an allusion to Thelwall’s
               hostile reception from loyalist mobs during recent provincial lecturing engagements
               at Derby, Norwich, Stockport and Ashby de la Zouch, and referred to in Canning’s
               verse: “Thelwall and ye that lecture as ye go, / And for your pains get pelted, praise
               Le Paux . . . .” By the time of this print’s appearance, Thelwall had in any case ceased
               to pose any significant threat because he had publicly announced his retirement to
               Llyswen, Wales, at the end of 1797. </p>
            <figure n="18">
               <graphic url="../images/rowlandson_democracyThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Thomas Rowlandson, A Charm for a Democracy (1799). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1851,0901.958].
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            <p>The <title level="m">Anti-Jacobin’s</title> prime target in 1798-99 was not the
               individual influence of the charismatic lecturer in any case, but Opposition
               newspapers and essayists. Apart from the usual Whig suspects, Thelwall’s companions
               in the <title level="m">New Morality’s</title> procession of villains include Godwin,
               Coleridge, Southey, Holcroft, and Priestley besides representations of the <title
                  level="m">Morning Chronicle</title>, the <title level="m">Courier</title>, the
                  <title level="m">Star</title> and the <title level="m">Morning Post</title>. In
                  <title level="m">A Charm for a Democracy</title> (1799), produced by Thomas
               Rowlandson for the <title level="m">Anti-Jacobin Review</title>, another motley
               procession of radicals presides over a seditious cauldron heated by a bonfire of
               Jacobin texts, including Thelwall’s <title level="m">Rights of Nature</title>, to a
               fare blown by a newsboy from the <title level="m">Courier</title>. But this is a
               print that celebrates radical defeat; it is anything but alarmist. Thelwall stands in
               line, prematurely aged, his lectures tucked under one arm but effectively silenced.
               “I’m off to Monmouthshire,” he says. In loyalist discourse, the withdrawal of voice
               left Thelwall an empty windbag, his vitality extinguished, his lectures ineffective
               when committed to print. <title level="m">The Anti-Jacobin</title> was in buoyant
               mood: 
            <quote><lg><l>Tied up, alas! Is every tongue, </l>
            <l>On which conviction nightly hung, </l>
            <l>And Thelwall looks, though yet but young, </l>
            <l> A spectre. (“The Jacobin” 135) </l></lg></quote>
               <figure n="19">
                  <graphic url="../images/thelwall_school_of_eloquenceThumb.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Samuel de Wilde, School of Eloquence and Grace (1808). Photograph by S. Poole, image reproduction for non-commercial purposes, courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.
                  </figDesc>
               </figure>
               
            As Llyswen recluse and then professional elocutionist over the subsequent twenty
               years, Thelwall received little attention from satirists. When he did, it was only to
               suggest confluence between respectable cover and Jacobin intent, and only because the
               next generation of Whigs after Fox’s death were finding it no easier to exert lasting
               political influence. In <title level="m">The School of Eloquence and Grace</title>
               (1808), a complex engraving for the <title level="m">Satirist</title>, a large party
               of washed up Whig parliamentarians, defeated in the election of 1807, have booked
               themselves into Thelwall’s Bedford Square Institute to have their inarticulacy and
               other ineptitudes examined. Thelwall opened the Institute in 1806 to “pupils who have
               impediments of utterance, of whatever description . . . who may either labour under the
               like imperfections or be desirous of improvement in the accomplishments of reading
               and recitation, conversational fluency, public oratory, and the principles of
               criticism and composition,” and in a later prospectus he made specific overtures to
               parliamentarians who, “may depend upon every attention that can be instrumental
               either to the improvement of their oratorical powers or the direction of their
               studies” (qtd. in Duchan 139).<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="8">See also Thelwall, <title level="m">Plan
                        and Objects </title>9.</note>
                Given an Opposition that still included erstwhile political colleagues of
               Thelwall’s like Erskine, Burdett, and Horne Tooke (all of whom appear in the print),
               the <title level="m">Satirist’s </title>suggestion that a little Thelwallian
               eloquence and grace wouldn’t go amiss was sharply observed. Grenville’s political
               failings, it is suggested here, were compounded by his lack of figure as much as his
               defective oratory, and it is as appropriate to Thelwall’s holistic theories of
               vitality that Grenville must submit to having extraneous flesh carved from his
               buttocks to improve his balance, as it is for Lord Henry Petty to be taught how to
               stand for dancing by Thelwall’s wife. The failure of men like these to carry
               political argument is signified most clearly by the ungainly oratorical attitude of
               Thelwall’s old adversary, William Windham, so unsuccessful in his attempts to shame
               ministers over the British bombardment of Copenhagen that a bust of Demosthenes falls
               from the wall behind him. </p>
            <p>Thelwall’s failure to recapture the political limelight when he re-emerged into
               public life at the end of the Napoleonic Wars can be measured by the indifference of
               the early nineteenth century caricature trade after the death of both Isaac
               Cruikshank and Gillray. Thelwall came out of retirement to lend support to the
               moderate reformer John Cam Hobhouse at Westminster during the election of 1818 and
               spoke on a number of platforms as a “veteran” reformer. As the newly appointed editor
               of <title level="m">The Champion</title> newspaper, he appeared occasionally in
               satirical prints as a wizened and ineffectual figure in the radical crowd, in stark
               contravention of suggestions in sympathetic journals like the <title level="m"
                  >Monthly Magazine</title> that his return to the political stage was
               “characterised by his usual eloquence and energy” (48 [1819]: 566). George Cruikshank
               included him in two caricatures during these years, <title level="m">The Funeral
                  Procession of the Rump</title> (1819), and <title level="m">Coriolanus Addressing
                  the Plebeians</title> (1820), in the first of which his sorry figure traipses
               along in the wake of Hobhouse’s election defeat, expressing itself “ashamed of [his]
               company,” who include not only Burdett but some unidentified “acquitted felons.” In
               the second, he lines up with the radical crowd’s more moderate wing (the elderly
               Cartwright, Hobhouse and Hone), and looks more inconsequential than ever. Thelwall’s
               marginalised position in the radical canon reached new heights, however, in what was
               probably the last caricature ever to feature him, <title level="m">The Reign of
                  Humbug</title> (1825). 
            <figure n="20">
               <graphic url="../images/funeral_of_the_rumpThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>George Cruikshank, The Funeral Procession of the Rump (1819). Photograph © S. Poole, image reproduction for non-commercial purposes, courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="21">
               <graphic url="../images/cruikshank_coriolanusThumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>George Cruikshank, Coriolanus Addressing the Plebeians (1820). © The Trustees of the British Museum [Museum #1859,0316.152].
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="22">
               <graphic url="../images/Reign_of_Humbug_1825Thumb.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Thomas Howell Jones, The Reign of Humbug (1825). Photograph © S. Poole, image reproduction for non-commercial purposes, courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            Uniquely, this was no loyalist print, but one composed as a frontispiece by Thomas
               Howell Jones for the radical republican William Benbow’s short-lived satirical
               journal, <title level="m">The Town</title>. The very prominent Thelwall, posturing
               once again as a gentleman elocutionist, takes his place amongst a pantheon of public
               figures regarded by Benbow as modern irritants, time-wasters and imposters. Having
               taken fright and abandoned the <title level="m">Champion</title> when the fiercely
               loyalist Constitutional Association threatened to prosecute him for seditious libel
               in 1820, and having at the same time loosened his political ties even with moderate
               men like Hobhouse, Thelwall was dismissed more readily than ever before by popular
               and less “respectable” stalwarts. In Howell Jones’s print, Thelwall has only his
               continuing association with the <title level="m">Monthly Magazine</title> to
               (literally) support his compromised political apostasy, and finds himself surrounded
               by every kind of frivolous financial speculator, corrupt politician, disingenuous
               bishop and confidence trickster (including Brougham and Burdett) in Benbow’s firing
               line. In fact, he occupies a central position in a “humbug” world characterised in
               Benbow’s prospectus by “every species of imposture, dupery and quackery” and whose
               inhabitants “shall stand exposed in their native deformity.”<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="9">See advertisement in <title level="m"
                        >Morning Post</title> 31 May 1825. I have not been able to trace a copy of
                     the journal but the print survives in the British Museum’s collection. </note>
               The wider public, to whom Thelwall had once directed his political energies,
               are shown facing away from his misdirected oratorical flourish to become dupes of the
               revived campaign against Catholic emancipation instead of making demands for reform.
               Thelwall’s irrelevant cry from atop his barrel, “My lectures on elocution . . . ,” goes,
               literally, over everyone’s head. </p>
            <p>We may conclude then not only that Thelwall’s caricatured persona stayed consistently
               true to his actual physiognomy over a thirty year period (which is interesting in
               itself), but that, during the early years when it most mattered, both Gillray and
               Isaac Cruikshank&#8212;albeit in different ways&#8212;were far too interested in the apparent
               contradictions in their subject’s persona to reduce him unproblematically to an ugly
               Jacobin signifier like Paine. Thelwall emerges instead as a complex caricature,
               either a man whose slight frame, masked expression and quiet adaptability negate the
               strength of his oratory and reveal a political chameleon who is not, perhaps, the
               one-dimensional firebrand of popular construction, or alternatively a man whose
               credentials as a firebrand are unquestionable but whose darker motives and seditious
               character are far from clear. These ambiguities were only reconciled by Thelwall’s
               running to ground in 1797-98, due largely to the concerted efforts of the
               legislature, the connivance of the judiciary and the brute force of loyalist mobs.
               More than a decade ago, E. P. Thompson persuasively traced the multi-layered
               silencing of the “Jacobin Fox” in these terms, and it has been suggested here that
               both James Gillray and Isaac Cruikshank’s satires offer a visual commentary on the
               process by which this was achieved as well as the language in which it was expressed.
               However, the success of Pitt’s ministry in engineering the silence and defeat of
               Thelwall in 1798 has yet to be measured as a factor in his relatively unconvincing
               return to politics in 1818-20. The re-embodiment of the most feared democratic orator
               of the 1790s as the patron saint of lost causes, diluted principles and political
               humbug began in visual satire with Gillray in 1797. For all of Gillray’s oft-cited
               political ambivalence, his deflated Thelwall was perhaps of greater service to
               loyalist discourse than was Cruikshank’s alarmism, an approach to the problem that defied
               any obvious solution and which tended not only to question the effectiveness of the
               Gagging Acts but to suggest they had actually prompted clandestine plotting.
               Thelwall’s portrayal in print satire as the embodiment of radical defeat remained
               current for almost two more decades and did nothing to ease his assimilation back
               into the reform pantheon. Despite the re-energised mass platform movement for the
               popular franchise in the period between the close of the French wars and the passing
               of the Great Reform Act, Thelwall had come to stand for the failure of Jacobin
               aspiration. Alienated from former allies in the LCS like John Gale Jones and
               Alexander Galloway, who both threw in their lot with the new leaders of the reform
               movement—Cobbett, Hunt and even some of the Spenceans—Thelwall took his place
               alongside middle-class advocates for a limited extension of the suffrage and remained
               easy prey to charges of apostasy. For loyalist and radical illustrators alike,
               Thelwall’s reappearance in the early nineteenth century was marked by the forging of
               political alliances, as hopeless as they were disingenuous, and in the adoption of
               uncontroversial “professional” channels for the dissipated expression of what had
               once seemed a most terrible and dangerous energy. </p>
            <div type="citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>
               <p rend="noCount">Aiken, John. <title level="m">General Biography, or Lives, Critical
                     and Historical, of the Most Eminent Persons of All Ages, Countries, Conditions
                     and Professions. </title>Vol. 8. London, 1813. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Barrell, John. “Portraits and Caricatures of Paine.” Paper prepared
                  for the Lewes Paine Festival, Sussex, England. 2009. TS.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “Radicalism, Visual Culture, and Spectacle in the 1790s.”
                     <title level="m">Romanticism on the Net</title> 46 (May 2007): n. pag. Web. 10
                  Nov. 2009. Rpt. in <title level="m">Field Day Review</title> 4 (2008): 40-61.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Bisset, Robert. <title level="m">The Historical, Biographical and
                     Literary and Scientific Magazine... for the Year 1799</title>. 3 vols. London,
                  1800. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Camper, Petrus. <title level="m">The Works of the Late Professor
                     Camper, on the Connection Between the Science of Anatomy and the Arts of
                     Drawing, Painting, Statuary etc. </title>Trans. T. Cogan. London, 1794.
                  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Cestre, Charles. <title level="m">John Thelwall: A Pioneer of
                     Democracy and Social Reform in England During the French Revolution</title>.
                  London: Swan Sonnenschein, 1906. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Coleridge, Samuel Taylor. Letter to John Thelwall. 19 Nov.
                     1796.<hi> </hi>
                  <title level="m">Electronic Text Centre</title>. Web. 25 March 2010. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">The Plot Discovered; or An Address to the
                     People, Against Ministerial Treason</title> Bristol, 1795. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Collins, Emanuel. <title level="m">The Saints Backsiding: or the
                     Remarkable Case of a Late Reverend, Holy, Anabaptistical Preacher Belonging to
                     Their Meeting in Bristol.</title> Bristol, 1756. Print. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">The Decline and Fall, Death, Dissection, and Funeral Procession
                     of His Most Contemptible Lowness, the London Corresponding Society</title>.
                  London, 1796. Print. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">Donald, Diana. <title level="m">The Age of Caricature: Satirical
                     Prints in the Age of George III</title>. New Haven:<hi> </hi>Yale UP, 1996.
                  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Duchan, Judith Felson. “The Conceptual Underpinnings of John
                  Thelwall’s Elocutionary Practices.” <title level="m">John Thelwall: Radical
                     Romantic and Acquitted Felon</title>. Ed. Steve Poole. London: Pickering and
                  Chatto, 2009. 139-45. Print. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">Godwin, William. <title level="m">Considerations upon Lord
                     Grenville’s and Mr Pitt’s Bills</title>. London, 1795. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Graham, John. “Lavater’s <title level="m">Physiognomy</title> in
                  England.” <title level="m">Journal of the History of Ideas</title> 22.4 (1961):
                     561-72.<hi> </hi>Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">“The Jacobin.” <title level="m">Anti-Jacobin</title> 22 (9 April
                  1798): 135.<hi> </hi>Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Jenks, Timothy. “Language and Politics at the Westminster Election
                  of 1796.” <title level="m">Historical Journal</title> 44. 2 (2001): 419-39.
                  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Karr, David. “Thoughts that Flash like Lightning: Thomas Holcroft,
                  Radical Theatre, and the Production of Meaning in 1790s London.” <title level="m"
                     >Journal of British Studies</title> 40. 3 (2001): 324-56. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Lamb, Robert, and Corinna Wagner, eds. <title level="m">Selected
                     Political Writings of John Thelwall</title>. 4 vols. London, Pickering and
                  Chatto, 2009. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Lavater, Johann Caspar<title level="m">. Essays on Physiognomy,
                     Designed to Promote the Knowledge and the Love of Mankind. </title>Vol 1.
                  London, 1789. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Monthly Magazine</title> 48 (1819): 566. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Morning Post</title> 9 Dec. 1795. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Morning Post</title> 9 June 1796. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Morning Post</title> 14 June 1796. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Morning Post</title> 31 May 1825. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">New Times</title> 6 Sept. 1794. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Newcastle Courant</title> 24 Sept. 1737. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Public Advertiser</title> 8 Aug. 1797. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Rights of Citizens, Being an Examination of Mr. Paine's
                     Principles, Touching Government. </title>Dublin, 1791. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Talfourd, Thomas Noon. <title level="m">Final Memorials of Charles
                     Lamb: Cons</title>
                  <title level="m">isting Chiefly of His Letters not Before Published, with Sketches
                     of Some of His Companions</title>. London, 1859. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">Telegraph</title> 23 May 1796. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thale, Mary, ed. <title level="m">Selections</title>
                  <title level="m">from the Papers of the London Corresponding Society,
                     1792-1799</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1983. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thelwall, John. “An Essay Towards a Definition of Animal Vitality.”
                  1793. Lamb and Wagner 1: 11-32.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. Letter to Peter Crompton. 3 March 1798. MS Eng 947.2 (21).
                  Houghton Lib., Harvard University, Cambridge.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Mr Thelwall’s Reply to the Calumnies,
                     Misrepresentations and Literary Forgeries Contained in the Anonymous
                     Observations on his Letter to the Editor of the Edinburgh Review</title>. 1804.
                  Lamb and Wagner 3: 157-88. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “A Pedestrian Excursion Through Several Parts of England and
                  Wales during the Summer of 1797.” 1799-1801. Lamb and Wagner 3: 15-55. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">The Peripatetic, or Sketches of the Heart, of
                     Nature and Society</title>. Vol. 1. Southwark, 1793. Print. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Plan and Objects for an Institution for the
                     Cure of Impediments.</title> London, 1813. Print. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “Prefatory Memoir.” 1801. Lamb and Wagner 3: 57-89.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Selections, &amp;c. for Mr Thelwall’s
                     Lectures on the Science and Practice of Elocution</title>. Hull, 1802.
                  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Selections, &amp;c. for Mr Thelwall’s
                     Lectures on the Science and Practice of Elocution</title>. York, 1802.
                  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">The </title>
                  <title level="m">Tribune, A Periodical Publication, Consisting Chiefly of the
                     Political Lectures of J. Thelwall</title>. London, 1795-96. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">The Vestibule of Eloquence</title>. London,
                  1810. Print. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thelwall, Mrs. [Henrietta Cecil Boyle]. <title level="m">The Life
                     of John Thelwall</title>.<title level="m"> </title>Vol. 1. London, 1837.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thompson, E. P. “Hunting the Jacobin Fox.” <title level="m">Past
                     and Present</title> 142 (1994): 94-140. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">True Briton</title> 12 May 1797. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">
                  <title level="m">True Briton</title> 28 May 1796. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Walker, George. <title level="m">The Vagabond</title>. Vol. 1.
                  London, 1799. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Walsh, James.<hi> </hi>Letter to<hi> </hi>the Duke of<hi
                  > </hi>Portland. 16 Aug. 1797. MS HO 42/41. The National Archives, Kew.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Wells, Roger. <title level="m">Insurrection: The British
                     Experience, 1795-1803</title>. Gloucester: Sutton, 1983. Print.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
