<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">John Thelwall: Critical Reassessments</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">John Thelwall and the West Country: The Road to Nether Stowey
               Revisited</title>
            <author>
               <name>Nicholas Roe</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Yasmin Solomonescu</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.roe</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2010-11-01">September 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">John Thelwall and the West Country: The Road to
                     Nether Stowey Revisited</title>

                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Nicholas</forename>
                        <surname>Roe</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">John Thelwall: Critical Reassessments</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2010-10-15">October 15, 2010</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for "," for ", ' for ',
                  and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2011-05-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>John Thelwall and the West Country: The Road to Nether Stowey Revisited</head>
            <byline><docAuthor>Nicholas Roe</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>University of St. Andrews</affiliation></byline>
            <p>Recent Thelwallian conversations have grown from and reflected back upon the essays
               in <title level="m">John Thelwall: Radical Romantic and Acquitted Felon</title>.<note
                  resp="editors" place="foot" n="1">See Poole.</note> Conversational exchange was
               congenial to Thelwall himself, as the medium of “philosophic amity” he anticipated at
               the end of his West Country tour in summer 1797 (<title level="m">Retirement</title>
               129). Both Robin Jarvis and Michael Scrivener have shown how Thelwall’s “Pedestrian
               Excursion through Several Parts of England and Wales during the Summer of 1797”
               expressed an “intellectual mobility” that combined remarks on picturesque beauty with
               “the social labor and political conflicts that also are part of the land’s meaning”
               (Scrivener 224). The “Pedestrian Excursion” and its postscript “The Phenomena of the
               Wye, During the Winter of 1797-8” are exemplary instances of what Scrivener terms
               the “social creativity” of Jacobin writing (295), a creativity also manifest in what
               Judith Thompson has noted as the democratic temper of Thelwall’s experiments with
               form and genre in <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> (11, 18, 29).</p>
            <p>“The Phenomena of the Wye” records a late stage of Thelwall’s west country excursion.
               It was published in the <title level="m">Monthly Magazine</title> for May and July
               1798, before the other instalments of the “Pedestrian Excursion” appeared between
               1799 and 1801. This arrangement is peculiar. Perhaps Thelwall intended it to distract
               attention from the missing segment of his excursion&#8212;what occurred between
               Thelwall setting-off from Bath with “solitary step” (“Pedestrian” 55) and his arrival
               in the middle of the autumn at the Wye Valley on his “first visit to [those] parts”
               (“Wye” 5). If that was indeed the design, it didn’t work. The missing section of the
               tour was in fact its principal purpose, as announced by Thelwall in his prefatory
               remarks: a visit to his “invaluable friend” Samuel Taylor Coleridge at Nether Stowey
                  (“Pedestrian”<title level="m"> </title>17). </p>
            <p>As reconstructed without reference to the “Pedestrian Excursion” the visit to Stowey
               has been seen to mark Thelwall’s retreat from metropolitan radicalism and ‘“the
               vortex of public contention” to become the “new Recluse” of Liswyn Farm, and, later,
               a Lecturer on Elocution (<title level="m">Retirement</title> xxiii, xxxviii).<note
                  resp="editors" place="foot" n="2">See for example my account in <title level="m"
                     >Wordsworth and Coleridge</title> 234-62, focusing on Thelwall’s response to
                  the spy, James Walsh, who tracked him from London to Nether Stowey.</note> That
               “turn” might summarise Thelwall’s trajectory from London in 1795 through to Liswyn in
               1801, a trajectory impelled negatively by persecution, disappointment, and
               marginalisation and positively by the wish for friendship, correspondence, and
               affection. The subsequent lapse of “philosophic amity” leads to “retreat,”
               “retirement,” and “reinvention,” from which Thelwall re-emerges with a new identity
               as an elocutionist. Several essays in <title level="m">John Thelwall: Radical
                  Romantic</title> challenge this profile, by pointing to continuities between
               Thelwall’s political lectures and his practice as an elocutionist. Simply put, as a
               political lecturer in the 1790s, Thelwall was the voice of the inarticulate; in later
               years his elocution helped the tongue-tied to speak for themselves. As the popular
               orator of the Corresponding Society Thelwall had lisped and stammered at the tribune;
               Thelwall the speech therapist lectured on “Bonaparte and the Spanish Patriots” at the
               Angel Inn, Tiverton. </p>
            <p>When in the mid-1790s the London Corresponding Society was forced underground it
               adopted the cover of the “School of Eloquence,” a school in which Thelwall&#8212;had
               he chosen to do so&#8212;might have continued his political lectures. He didn’t so
               choose. He set off first to East Anglia, and was rebuffed by riots. He then trekked
               north to Derby, to find the offer of a newspaper editorship had been foreclosed. With
               London in 1797 a no-go area for him, there was little option but to step westwards on
               a walking tour towards a correspondent, not as yet encountered in person, who
               appeared to promise all that Thelwall was denied elsewhere in England: familiarity,
               affection and intellectual fellowship. </p>
            <p>In this article I want to offer some further arguments for a continuity between
               Thelwall up to the “Pedestrian Excursion” in 1797, and the Thelwall who re-emerged
               from Liswyn Farm. I want to attend to Thelwall and the sense of place, and to ask
               what it meant at that moment to step westwards in the hope of establishing “a more
               immediate and intimate communication” with friends settled in the West Country
               (“Pedestrian” 17). Within that narrative of continuity, I want also to speculate
               about the breaks and fractures signalled by the published version of Thelwall’s
               “Pedestrian Excursion.” As presented in the <title level="m">Monthly
               Magazine</title>, the anticipated “communication” with his friend produces a
               dislocation in the “Excursion” narrative that prompted Thelwall to publish the
               “Phenomena of the Wye” first, and separately from, the “Excursion” it should have
               concluded. In this arrangement of the narrative, the episode of friendly
               communication with Coleridge is completely excised. </p>
            <div type="section" n="1"><head>*</head>
            <p>Thursday, 29 June 1797. Thelwall and his friend Wimpory set off from London between
               nine and ten o’clock in a heavy shower of rain. Their route will take them out of
               London to Windsor, Basingstoke, Andover, Salisbury, Amesbury, Stonehenge, Winterborne
               Stoke, Wylye, Fonthill, Wardour Castle, Mere, Frome, Bristol and Bath . . . and
               eventually to the Wye Valley. Broadly speaking Thelwall was following earlier
               travellers such as Thomas Gray and William Gilpin, and William Wordsworth on his 1793
               venture westwards from London, via the Isle of Wight, Salisbury and the Plain, to
               Bath and Bristol. If we include Wordsworth’s wider poetic migrations between 1793 and
               1798 we might say that Thelwall was tracking a topography of the imagination that led
               from the desolate vistas represented by an early poem like <title level="m">Salisbury
                  Plain</title> to the human landscapes of <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title>.
               Thelwall, likewise, abandoned the persecutions of London and headed westward in the
               hope of human community, and for Thelwall, too, the westward journey would produce
               significant challenges and transformations.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="3">For more on Thelwall’s and Wordsworth’s
                     West Country tours, see <title level="m">English Romantic Writers and the West
                        Country</title>, ed. Roe, especially the introduction and Carol Kyros
                     Walker’s essay, “Wordsworth’s 1793 Journey to the West Country and
                     Wales.”</note>
               
            </p>
            <p>The social, cultural and political observations that inform Thelwall’s “Pedestrian
               Excursion” have been widely noted, and comparisons have rightly been made with Arthur
               Young and William Cobbett.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="4">See, for instance,
                  E. P. Thompson 104-07; Scrivener 222-28; and Lamb and Wagner 15. </note> More can
               I think be said, and one keynote is Thelwallian diversity. Thelwall is familiar to us
               as a journalist poet, orator, lecturer, leader of popular societies, speculative
               scientist, and elocutionist. He was also a published dramatist, pamphleteer,
               autobiographer, novelist, and diarist. His other identities include Thelwall the
               political agent, songwriter, editor, pedestrian, naturalist, farmer, and collector.
               To these we can add his early years in his father’s silk business; apprentice
               to a master-tailor; epic poet; trainee lawyer; aspirant actor, and would-be
               historical painter. I wrote in “The Lives of John Thelwall” about his various
               identities as a “private citizen,” “Citizen Thelwall,” “Brother Thelwall,” Sylvanus
               Theophrastus, John Beaufort, “the new Recluse,” “Citizen John,” “Citizen Jack,” “the
               famous Thelwall,” and “the lisping orator.” And I suggested that it is possible to
               map a comparable diversity in other areas of Thelwall’s life&#8212;for example in his
               travels and tours throughout England. It’s worth emphasising these earlier selves,
               because we overhear many of their voices in the course of his “Pedestrian
               Excursion.”</p>
            <p>Who are they? A non-exhaustive list, arranged alphabetically, includes the following
               Thelwalls, all of whom we hear from in the course of the “Excursion”: 
            <list><item>Thelwall the <hi>Agriculturalist</hi>, concerned with crops, farm and land
               maintenance, and the condition of the soil.</item>
            <item>Thelwall the <hi>Antiquarian</hi>, who is intrigued by the mutilated wooden monument
               at Salisbury Cathedral, and speculates on the astronomical function of Stonehenge
                  (“Pedestrian”<title level="m"> </title>29, 37).</item>
            <item>Thelwall the <hi>Art Historian</hi>, who appears throughout the “Excursion,” comments
               on the chapel paintings at Amesbury House and finds occasion to remark on
               contemporary painters such as West, Barry, Northcote and Fuseli (34-36). </item>
            <item>Thelwall the <hi>Architect</hi>, ready with an opinion on “the fine florid
               Normo-Gothic style” of St. Mary Redcliffe at Bristol, the interior of Salisbury Cathedral and “[t]he many-shafted pillars and Saracenic (or Normo-Gothic) arches
               that divide the nave and circles . . . handsome, uniform and in excellent proportion”
               (53, 28).</item>
            <item>Thelwall the <hi>Classical Historian </hi>“nurtured with the love of Roman liberty,”
               whose appreciation of Roman busts, coloured by his knowledge of the times, gives us
               “the bloated, intemperate, licentious, effeminate, mischief-meditating countenance of
               Nero, with his pursed-up, pouting, distorted mouth, and assassin arm wrapped up in
               his cloak” (31). </item>
            <item>Thelwall the “confidential correspondent” of Samuel Taylor Coleridge (17).</item>
            <item>Thelwall the <hi>Economist</hi> prepared to expatiate on “<title level="m">National
                  Debt</title>,” “<title level="m">Circulating Medium</title>,” “<title level="m"
                  >Waste Lands</title>,” and the rural wages of labourers (“Wye” 10-12). </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Farmer</hi> Thelwall, as concerned as the agriculturalist about “the state,
               cultivation, and the fertility of pastures,” drainage, the size of farms and the
               condition of farm buildings (“Pedestrian” 22).</item>
            <item>Thelwall the <hi>Gallant</hi>, with an eye to the “mistress of the house” who is
               “somewhat handsome” (24-25).</item>
            <item>Thelwall the <hi>Industrialist</hi>, whose childhood experiences inform his remarks
               about the silk-mill near Basingstoke, and the cloth mill at Frome (26-27, 48-49).</item>
            <item>Thelwall the <hi>Journalist</hi>&#8212;the published text of the “Excursion” is a
               gleaning from his more extensive “observations” (17).</item>
            <item>Then there is Thelwall the <hi>Landscape Painter</hi> and <hi>Gardener</hi>, ready
               with comments on Poussin, Claude, and the layout of Windsor Great Park (“Wye” 3;
               “Pedestrian” 21). </item>
            <item>Thelwall the <hi>Pedestrian</hi>, the <hi>Peripatetic</hi>, and the <hi>Picturesque
                  Traveller</hi>. </item>
            <item>Thelwall the <hi>Politician</hi> who remarks briefly on liberty and justice and
               resists an “elaborate dissertation” (“Pedestrian” 32).</item>
            <item>Thelwall the <hi>Public Figure</hi> or “<hi>Celebrity</hi>” who is recognised at
               Frome and suddenly and unexpectedly finds himself “in the midst of friends” (48).</item>
            <item>Thelwall the <hi>Utopian Thinker</hi>, who “formed Utopian plans of retirement and
               colonisations” (21).</item>
            <item>And finally, to round up this list, there is Thelwall the <hi>Bon Viveur</hi> on the
               watch for his next meal: bread and milk (20); tea and rolls and cream (21); eggs,
               bacon, and ale (25); new milk (26); “animal food” (27); ham, eggs, salad, gooseberry
               pies and ale (41-42); a cold leg of lamb, lamb chops and salad (46). All of this
               country fare is sampled en route to Stowey. </item></list></p>
            <p>So Thelwall assumes diverse identities and discourses, adapts himself to occasion,
               and, except for the moment when he is recognised at Frome, travels across country
                  <title level="m">incognito</title>. And we hear accordingly little of what
               Thelwall felt in himself&#8212;the “Excursion” concerns itself with the physical,
               material detail of landscapes, buildings and contents, soil, wages, the condition of
               rivers, the cleanliness or otherwise of inns, and the palatability of food. When we
               part company from him at Bath, he is headed further west into Somerset, to meet his
               confidential correspondent “well known in the literary world” (17). We shall meet
               Thelwall again as the different creature of the “Phenomena of the Wye” articles, and
               as Thelwall himself leaves a gap in his narrative I am going to take this opportunity to
               offer a few conjectures about what it meant to step westward to Nether Stowey in
               summer 1797. </p>
            <p>Thelwall’s “eccentric ramble” westwards was exactly that: a trajectory outwards from
               the city towards a location off-centre, away from the uproar of public life towards a
               “more immediate and intimate communication” with a private friend (“Pedestrian” 17).
               The Quantock Hills, two days from London by the fastest coach, offered the
               geographical and psychological sense of remove and reassurance that had already
               attracted Coleridge from Bristol and, more recently, Wordsworth and his sister from
               London via Dorset. Here, as Richard Holmes’s biography of Coleridge showed us, were
               the provincial landscape and culture that inspired Coleridge’s early visions.</p>
            <p>One question occurs. Why the Quantocks? Wouldn’t another region of England, Wales or
               Scotland have served as well? At a period of political and social unrest the
               Quantocks might be thought to have offered shelter from political persecution such as
               Thelwall had endured, and the shaded coombs and windswept uplands both nurtured and
               disciplined literary composition. This is the landscape Coleridge celebrates in
                  <title level="m">Fears in Solitude</title> and yet, rather than offering a remove
               from the centre of unrest in London, Somerset was the historical heartland of
               rebellion&#8212;as Coleridge, a Devonshire man, certainly knew. A dozen miles from
               Nether Stowey was Taunton, a parliamentary stronghold during the Civil War and an
               important centre for Non-conformity with an academy (c. 1670-1759) linked to the
               network of dissent that criss-crossed the country. The Duke of Monmouth’s challenge
               for the throne in 1685 had gathered momentum in Dorset, only to meet defeat at “sad
               Sedge-Moor”&#8212;Thomas Hardy’s phrase (line 8). Hundreds were executed in Judge
               Jeffreys’s “bloody assizes” that followed. When the French planned an invasion
               attempt in 1797, they targeted a remote area of the Somerset coast close to
               Coleridge’s home at Nether Stowey. Was this fortuitous? A matter of wind and tide? Or
               did the French anticipate a welcome from locals whose forebears had experienced murderous
               retribution? Certainly Coleridge and Wordsworth found a like-minded friend in Thomas
               Poole, the tanner of Nether Stowey who had founded a poor man’s club in the village
               (Poole’s enemies thought of the club as a private army over which he had “intire
                  command”).<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="5">See the report from the spy James Walsh in
                     my <title level="m">Wordsworth and Coleridge </title>260-61. </note>
                For Thelwall, the excursion to Somerset was less an escape from the dangers of
               London than a homecoming in a provincial landscape long associated with
               resistance&#8212;a resistance that in the days of King Alfred had arguably led to the
               foundation of England itself. The geopolitical history of the West Country was
               unquestionably a factor in the Home Office decision to dispatch the
               spy&#8212;Coleridge’s “Spy Nosy”&#8212;to report on “the famous Thelwall” and the
               “nest of democrats” at Alfoxden, and we can see those associations continued in the
               next generation. Ten years later, in 1808, Leigh Hunt’s friend J. P. Marriott founded
               the <title level="m">Taunton Courier</title>&#8212;a liberal newspaper, modelled on
               Hunt’s London <title level="m">Examiner</title>, that circulated throughout the West
               Country. On the first page of the first issue, 22 October 1808, the <title level="m"
                  >Taunton Courier</title> carried an advertisement for Thelwall’s forthcoming
               lecture on “Bonaparte and the Spanish patriots” at the Angel Inn, Tiverton. Hunt’s
               brother John, publisher of the <title level="m">Examiner</title>, actually made his
               home in 1819 a few miles from Taunton at Cheddon Fitzpaine: it was a settlement long
               postponed, for the Hunt brothers were descendants of an ancient Devonshire family
               from South Molton. The assertive political-cultural independence of <title level="m"
                  >The Examiner</title> in which Shelley and Keats found their first readers was a
               West Country inheritance, and that inheritance is arguably why Thelwall, Coleridge
               and Wordsworth had also relocated from London to the Quantocks at a moment of
               political crisis and impending repression in the mid-1790s. Often thought of in terms
               of “retreat,” “retirement,” and “disengagement,” the road to Nether Stowey was taken
               by those, like Thelwall, who sought continuity, confidentiality, and communication at
               a time of “default” in the centre. Thelwall’s “eccentricity” signalled his refusal to
               abandon the cause: his wayward trajectory to the west was a homing-in on the one area
               of the country likely to prove receptive to his democratic campaign. If that was
               indeed his expectation, the experience proved somewhat different from what he had
               anticipated&#8212;hence the fracture in the published narrative of the
               “Excursion.”</p>
               <p>Thelwall’s “familiar and confidential correspondence” with Coleridge was the conversation of two friends whose political ideals overlay intractable differences. Thelwall was a materialist, as his <title level="m"
                  >Essay on Animal Vitality</title> and the “Pedestrian Excursion” demonstrated. The
                  <title level="m">Essay</title> argued that spirit “must be material,” possibly the
               mysterious “electrical fluid” that was simultaneously “a fine and subtle, or aeriform
               essence” that is “<title level="m">superadded to matter</title>” (116-17). In the
               “Excursion” Thelwall’s concern is “observations”&#8212;social, topographical,
               picturesque, architectural, economic, agricultural, gastronomic. Indeed, apart from
               the state of his stomach, we hear almost nothing about Thelwall himself&#8212;no
               impressions, no hint of personal feelings, no imaginative response. As a single
               suggestion of what might have been possible, Wordsworth evidently heard about or
               looked over Thelwall’s journal and noted his observation of how “tasteless
               inhabitants . . . have daubed their houses, and one in particular, the very colonnade
               before his door, with green paint” (“Pedestrian” 19). “Tintern Abbey” removes all
               inhabitants from the scene, and restores a natural continuity between the landscape
               and “pastoral farms / Green to the very door.” Thelwall is concerned with taste, or
               its lack, as materialised by “the country houses of persons long immured in large
               cities” (20). Wordsworth’s more impressionistic vision tells us of his wish to see a
               landscape in which human presences almost pass unnoticed.</p>
            <p>At Stowey Thelwall, Coleridge, and the Wordsworths talked, walked, dined, and recited
               poems and plays, and as David Fairer has recently argued, it rapidly became clear
               that Thelwall’s materialism was at odds with Coleridge’s idealism and
                  spirituality. That apparent conflict did not preclude some
               interassimilation, as I suggested in tracing “Tintern Abbey”’s conversation with
               Thelwall’s “Lecture on Animal Vitality” (<title level="m">Politics of Nature</title> 93-95). Thelwall, likewise, obliged to quit Nether Stowey, was aware of
               Coleridge’s experiments with landscapes of feeling in his recent poem “This Lime-Tree
               Bower my Prison.” That awareness is apparent in Thelwall’s own blank verse poems,
               “Lines Written at Bridgewater” and “To the Infant Hampden,” and also in “The
               Phenomena of the Wye, during the Winter of 1797-8” to which I now want to turn by way
               of concluding.</p>
            <p>There are some continuities between the narrative of the “Pedestrian Excursion” that
               in chronological terms preceded the “The Phenomena of the Wye” but, as indicated
               already, saw print rather later. As apparent are some notable differences. In
               particular, “The Phenomena of the Wye” shows us Thelwall moving towards a more
               subjective, mediated vision that discovers emblems or symbols of his own feelings in
               the landscape. The “eccentric ramble” of Thelwall’s recent past greets the “intricate
               meanders” of the Wye in a moment of self-recognition that is also an acknowledgement
               of survival amid “eternal diversity” (“Wye” 4). If we do not hear the thoughts and
               feelings of the “pensive wanderer” who saunters along the banks, the sight of
               “successive strata of sand, of gravel, and of rock” glimpsed through the “transparent
               stream” is suggestive of depth and retrospection (as in Coleridge’s sonnet “To the
               River Otter”) (4). Thelwall the materialist is now prepared to grant that a scene may
               be “enchanting” and may result in “curiosity inflamed”; the atmosphere can be “thick,” and a sky
               “sullen” (3). Here are “mingled impressions” (4), a “transparent veil” (7), “rays of
               sun tingling with transient glow” (6), and “a sort of wild and awful music”
               reminiscent of the poems of Ossian (8). Thelwall was on the way to realising how the
               language and rhythms of poetry offered the release, the response, and the “intimate
               communication” he had sought in making his “Excursion” to meet Coleridge at Stowey
               (“Pedestrian” 17). As he tapped into his own experiences and feelings in the
               post-Nether Stowey <title level="m">Poems Written in Retirement</title> of 1801,
               Thelwall was already alert to poetry’s potential to liberate those whose speech was
               as fractured as his own. Thelwall’s “road to Nether Stowey” led beyond the village
               limits, to the Wye, to Liswyn, and, ultimately, to his Institute of Elocution at
               Lincoln’s Inn Fields. </p></div>
            <div type="citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>
               <p rend="noCount">“Bonaparte and the Spanish Patriots.” 
                  <title level="m">Taunton Courier</title> 22 Sept. 1808: 1. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Fairer, David. “A Matter of Emphasis: Coleridge and Thelwall,
                  1796-7.” <title level="m">Organising Poetry: The Coleridge Circle,
                     1790-1798.</title> Oxford: Oxford UP, 2009. 236-59. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Hardy, Thomas. “A Trampwoman’s Tragedy.” 
                  <title level="m">Collected Poems of Thomas Hardy</title>. 1930. London: Macmillan,
                  1974. 182-85. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Holmes, Richard. <title level="m">Coleridge: Early Visions.</title>
                  London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1989. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Lamb, Robert, and Corinna Wagner, eds. <title level="m">Selected
                     Political Writings of John Thelwall</title>. By John Thelwall. Vol. 3. London:
                  Pickering and Chatto, 2009. Print. The Pickering Masters.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Poole, Steve. Introduction. <title level="m">John Thelwall: Radical
                     Romantic and Acquitted Felon.</title> Ed. Poole. London: Pickering and Chatto,
                  2009. 1-11. Print. The Enlightenment World 11.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Roe, Nicholas. “The Lives of John Thelwall: Another View of the
                  ‘Jacobin Fox.’” <title level="m">John Thelwall: Radical Romantic and Acquitted
                     Felon</title>. Ed. Steve Poole. London: Pickering and Chatto, 2009. 13-24.
                  Print. The Enlightenment World 11. </p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">The Politics of Nature: William Wordsworth
                     and Some of His Contemporaries</title>. 2nd ed. Basingstoke: Palgrave
                  Macmillan, 2002. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Wordsworth and Coleridge: The Radical
                     Years</title>. Oxford: Clarendon, 1988. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---, ed. <title level="m">English Romantic Writers and the West
                     Country</title>. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2010. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Scrivener, Michael. <title level="m">Seditious Allegories: John
                     Thelwall and Jacobin Writing.</title> University Park, PA: Pennsylvania State
                  UP, 2001. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thelwall, John. “An Essay, Towards a Definition of Animal
                  Vitality.” 1793. Roe, <title level="m">Politics of Nature</title> 96-119.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “A Pedestrian Excursion through Several Parts of England and
                  Wales during the Summer of 1797.” 1799-1801. <title level="m">Selected Political
                     Writings of John Thelwall</title>. Ed. Robert Lamb and Corinna Wagner. Vol. 3.
                  London: Pickering and Chatto, 2009. 17-55. Print. The Pickering Masters.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “The Phenomena of the Wye, During the Winter of 1797-8.” 1798.
                     <title level="m">Selected Political Writings of John Thelwall</title>. Ed.
                  Robert Lamb and Corinna Wagner. Vol. 3. London: Pickering and Chatto, 2009. 3-13.
                  Print. The Pickering Masters.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Poems Chiefly Written in Retirement.</title>
                  1801. Oxford: Woodstock, 1989. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thompson, E. P. “Hunting the Jacobin Fox.” <title level="m">Past
                     and Present</title> 142 (1994): 94-140. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Thompson, Judith. Introduction. <title level="m">The
                     Peripatetic</title>. By John Thelwall. Ed. Thompson. Detroit: Wayne State UP,
                  2001. 11-50. Print.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
