<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Romanticism and Biopolitics</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
				<title level="a">About this Volume</title>
				<editor role="editor">Alastair Hunt</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<editor role="editor">Matthias Rudolf</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
					<name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>about</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2012-01-24">Jan 24, 2012</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
						<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
							Circles.</item>
						<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
					</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">About this Volume </title></analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Romanticism and Biopolitics:</title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2012-01-24">October 15, 2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for "," for ", ' for ', and ' for '.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Mike Quilligan</name>
				<date>2010-01-24</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="paratext">
				<head>About this volume</head>
				<p rend="noCount">This volume of <title level="j">Romantic Circles Praxis Series</title>
					includes an editor's introduction by <ref target="#HuntAbout">Alastair Hunt and Matthias Rudolf</ref>, essays by <ref target="#RedfieldAbout">Marc Redfield</ref>, <ref target=
						"#SunAbout">Emily Sun</ref>, <ref target="#GuyerAbout">Sara Guyer</ref>, and
					<ref target="#GuelenAbout">Eva Geulen</ref>.</p>
				
			<!-- Long volume abstract goes here -->
				<p rend="noCount">This collection of articles is intended to initiate a conversation about and between biopolitics and romanticism. Its broad contention is that the study of biopolitics reanimates the question of romanticism in two senses. First, the set of conceptual resources provided in recent work on biopolitics opens up inventive lines of inquiry that enable scholars to re-think the already established awareness that the literature, philosophy, and culture of romanticism displays an obsession with life. In another sense biopolitics reanimates romanticism insofar as the current scholarly concern with life as an object of power marks the radical survival of romanticism. If romanticism responds well when examined in the light of contemporary biopolitical theory, then a constitutive part of this response is a certain resistance to biopolitical theory. The contributors to this volume demonstrate that the biopolitical intervention on life engages paradoxes, predicaments, and aporias that have been widely or fully appreciated neither by theorists of biopolitics nor by critics who take up their work. Romanticism, we suggest, is a privileged locus for the awareness that even the most assured representation of life turns upon an irreducible “literariness.”</p>
				
				<!-- Change name of encoder here -->
				<div type="section"><head>About the Design and Markup</head>
					<p rend="noCount">This volume was TEI-encoded by Michael Quilligan and Dave Rettenmaier, site managers for Romantic Circles. Laura Mandell developed the modified versions of the transforms provided by the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml">TEI</ref> that were used to convert the TEI files into HTML. TEI renders text archival quality for better preservation and future access.</p>
					
					<p rend="noCount">The image associated with this issue includes elements from the Table 17 illustration from Fritz Kahn's <title level="m">Das Leben des Menschen: Eine volkstumliche Anatomie, Biologie, Physiologie und Entwicklungsgeschichte des Menschen Vol. 2 (1922-1931)  </title>. The original image can be found at the British Library's website <ref target="http://www.bl.uk/learning/artimages/bodies/kahn/kahnmachines.html">Learning Bodies of Knowledge</ref>; more information about the text can be found in Cornelius Borck's <title level="a">Communicating the Modern Body: Fritz Kahn's Popular Images of Human Physiology as an Industrialized World</title> in <title level="j">Canadian Journal of Communication</title> 32 (2007), pp. 495-520.</p>
						<p rend="noCount">The HTML pages do not use frames but rather make extensive use
					of stylesheets for layout and presentation. The site works best when
					viewed with Mozilla Firefox v. 3, Netscape 4.0, Internet Explorer 4.0, or
					higher, or a comparable browser; earlier browsers may not display everything
					properly.</p></div>
				
				<div type="section"><head>About the Romantic Circles Praxis
					Series</head>
				
				<p rend="noCount">The <title level="j">Romantic Circles Praxis Series</title> is devoted to
					using computer technologies for the contemporary critical
					investigation of the languages, cultures, histories, and
					theories of Romanticism. Tracking the circulation of
					Romanticism within these interrelated domains of knowledge,
					<title level="j">RCPS</title> recognizes as its conceptual terrain a world
					where Romanticism has, on the one hand, dissolved as a
					period and an idea into a plurality of discourses and, on
					the other, retained a vigorous, recognizable hold on the
					intellectual and theoretical discussions of today.
					<title level="j">RCPS</title> is committed to mapping out this terrain with
					the best and most exciting critical writing of
					contemporary Romanticist scholarship.</p></div>
				
				<!-- Contributor bios here -->
				<div type="section"><head>About the Contributors</head>
				
					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Alastair Hunt<anchor xml:id="HuntAbout"></anchor></hi> is Assistant Professor of English at Portland State University in Oregon. He has published on Friedrich Schlegel, Hannah Arendt, Vercors, and the Presidential Turkey Pardon. He is completing a book titled <title level="m">Rights of Romanticism</title>.</p>
									
					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Matthias Rudolf<anchor xml:id="RudolfAbout"></anchor></hi>  received his Ph.D. in English from the University of Wisconsin, Madison in 2007, and currently teaches at the University of Oklahoma. Rudolf specializes in British and German Romanticisms, critical theory, and the question of “human.” He has published on romantic poetry, post-colonial literature and theory, and biopolitics.</p>
					
					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2012.hunt-rudolf.html">go to essay</ref>]</p>
					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Marc Redfield<anchor xml:id="RedfieldAbout"></anchor></hi> is Professor of English and holds the John D. and Lilliam Maguire Distinguished Chair in the Humanitites at Claremont Graduate University. He is the author of <title level="m">Phantom Formations: Aesthetic Ideology and the Bildungsroman</title> (1996) and of <title level="m">The Politics of Aesthetics: Nationalism, Gender, Romanticism</title> (2003); he has coedited <title level="m">High Anxieties: Cultural Studies in Addiction</title> (2002).</p>
					
					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2012.redfield.html">go to essay</ref>]</p>
					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Emily Sun<anchor xml:id="SunAbout"></anchor></hi> is Associate Professor in Foreign Languages and Literatures at National Tsing Hua University, Taiwan. She is the author of <title level="m">Succeeding King Lear: Literature, Exposure, and the Possibility of Politics</title> (Fordham UP, 2010) and co-editor of <title level="m">The Claims of Literature: A Shoshana Felman Reader</title> (Fordham UP, 2007).  She also co-edited the summer 2011 special issue, "Reading Keats, Thinking Politics," of <title level="j">Studies in Romanticism</title>.</p>
					
					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2012.sun.html">go to essay</ref>]</p>
					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Sara Guyer<anchor xml:id="GuyerAbout"></anchor></hi>  teaches in the English Department at the University of Wisconsin-Madison, where she also directs the Center for the Humanities.  She is the author of <title level="m">Romanticism after Auschwitz</title> (2007).  Her latest project focuses on Biopoetics and the case of John Clare. With Brian McGrath, she edits the Lit Z series at Northwestern University Press.</p>
					
					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2012.guyer.html">go to essay</ref>]</p>
					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Eva Geulen<anchor xml:id="GuelenAbout"></anchor></hi> studied German Literature and Philosophy at the University of Freiburg, Germany, and The Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, USA, where she received her Ph.D. in 1989 (<title level="m">Worthörig wider Willen.  Darstellungsproblematik und Sprachreflexion in der Prosa Adalbert Stifters</title>, Iudicium Verlag, 2002).  Between 1989 and 2003, she held teaching positions at Stanford University, the University of Rochester and New York University.  From 2003  to 2012  she  was  Professor for German Literature at the Institut  für Germanistik, Vergleichende Literatur-  und Kulturwissenschaft at the University of Bonn, Germany.  Since 2012 she has been Professor for German Literature at Goethe University Frankfurt am Main, Germany.  Recent publications include <title level="m">Hannah Arendt and Giorgio Agamben: Parallelen, Perspektiven, Kontroversen</title>, ed. with Georg Mein and Kai Kauffmann (Fink Verlag, 2007); <title level="m">Tiere, Texte, Spuren</title>, ed. with Norbert Eke (Erich Schmidt Verlag 2007); <title level="m">The End of Art. Readings of a Rumor after Hegel</title> (Stanford University Press, 2006); <title level="m">Giorgio Agamben zur Einführung</title> (Junius Verlag, 2005, 2nd edition 2009); essays on Nietzsche, Benjamin, Raabe, Th. Mann and others. She has been co-editor of the journal <title level="j">Zeitschrift für deutsche Philologie</title> since 2004.</p>
					
					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2012.geulen.html">go to essay</ref>]</p>
				
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
