<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Romanticism and Biopolitics</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">Response and Commentary (Sara Guyer, Marc Redfield and Emily
               Sun)</title>
            <author>
               <name>Eva Geulen</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">Alastair Hunt</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <editor role="editor">Matthias Rudolf</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2012.geulen</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-01-24">Jan 24, 2012</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded,
                  reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                  purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as
                  provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic
                  Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                  with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted
                  by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express
                  prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the
                  following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order
                  to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users
                  to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet.
                  We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis,
                  and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all
                  Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic
                  Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Response and Commentary (Sara Guyer, Marc Redfield
                     and Emily Sun)</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Eva</forename>
                        <surname>Geulen</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Romanticism and Biopolitics:</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2012-01-24">October 15, 2010</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for ","
                  for ", ' for ', and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on
                  the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been
                  indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces,
                  etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>Dave Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2012-03-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>Response and Commentary (Sara Guyer, Marc Redfield and Emily Sun)</head>
            <byline><docAuthor>Eva Geulen</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>Goethe University Frankfurt am Main</affiliation></byline>

            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>I</head>
               <p>Were one to write a history of how late twentieth-century political concepts
                  emerged, and how they changed as they migrated across fields, disciplines and
                  continents, the notion of ‘biopolitics’ would make for an interesting case
                  study—which is to say that at this point in time it is both too late and too early
                  for such a project: too late, because the term has accrued such a variety of
                  meanings and encompasses so many different aspects, from prenatal diagnostics and
                  euthanasia to the treatment of refugees, smoking bans and ecology, that
                  restricting its meaning, for example, to Foucault’s understanding of biopolitics,
                  would be beside the point; and too early as well, precisely because the term still
                  carries acute, albeit unspecific, significance and therefore lacks the historical
                  distance required for critical assessment. Hence my first obligation as
                  commentator is to determine what each contributor means by the term. To facilitate
                  this task, a few orienting remarks are in order. </p>
               <p>Even though Hannah Arendt never used the word biopolitics, she was among the first
                  to register and lament the increasing political preoccupation with the natural
                  processes of living such as sustenance and reproduction which, she believed, had
                  displaced politics and the public sphere in the pre-modern sense of classical
                  antiquity. Her diagnosis in <title level="m">The Human Condition</title> (1958) is
                  tentatively, by association more than argument, tied to her earlier investigation
                  of in <title level="m">The Origins of Totalitarianism</title> (1951). The link
                  between the decline of classical politics and the emergence of 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-century totalitarianisms is given in the concept of nature. As nature
                  and natural life moved to the center of politics, nature (as well as history
                  understood as a force of nature) became trans-legal authorities totalitarian
                  politics appealed to in order to justify their actions. At the same time, Arendt
                  is also known as an avid critic of human rights because, in her view, those rights
                  were bound to produce right-less fugitives since the very declaration of those
                  rights (at least in France) was premised on citizenship and statehood. With her
                  critique of human rights, Arendt resumed a line of argument originally suggested
                  by Karl Marx in his problematic essay <title level="a">On the Jewish Question</title> (1842), in which he
                  argued that human rights refer to the rights of property owners. </p>
               <p>In his series of books on the figure of the <emph>homo sacer</emph>, Agamben names Arendt as a predecessor for his own understanding of biopolitics (<title level="m">Homo Sacer </title>3ff). According to Agamben, Arendt had profound insights
                  into the biopolitical logic of modernity, but she failed to firmly connect her
                  critique of the ‘unnatural growth of the natural’ and the problematic parameters
                  of human rights to her investigation of modern totalitarianisms. Agamben believes
                  that Arendt was not up to the task because she lacked the concepts Michel Foucault
                  eventually provided with his notion of biopolitics some twenty years after Arendt
                  and without reference to her.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn1" place="foot" n="1"
                     >Among the most relevant texts by Michel Foucault on this subject belong the
                     following: <title level="m">History of Sexuality, Vol. 1</title>; <title
                        level="m">Security, Territory, Population</title>; <title level="m">The
                        Birth of Biopolitics</title>; <title level="m">Society Must Be
                        Defended</title>. </note> In Foucault, biopolitics signifies a particular
                  point in the development of modern governmentality when population (rather than
                  territory) became the preferred object of political and social concerns. Foucault
                  contrasts this new notion of biopower or biopolitics to the older notion of
                  sovereign power. According to the most frequently (also in the present volume)
                  quoted definition, sovereign politics was about letting live and actively
                  exercising a right to kill; by contrast, biopolitics lets die but actively engages
                  the right (of the state) to enforce life and, in this sense, "makes live" (<title
                     level="m">Society </title>241). However neatly the opposition of these two
                  paradigms appears initially, Foucault has occasionally pointed out that sovereign
                  power and biopower or biopolitics can overlap. Thus he remarked on the irony that
                  Franco, the last European political sovereign in the old sense, became subject to
                  biopolitical techniques aimed at prolonging his life when he fell ill. Nazi
                  ideology is another site where older sovereign power and modern biopower converge:
                     <quote>Nazism was doubtless the most cunning and the most naïve (and the former
                     because of the latter) combination of the fantasies of blood and the paroxysms
                     of a disciplinary power. A eugenic ordering of society, with all that implied
                     in the way of extension and intensification of micro-powers, in the guise of
                     unrestricted state control (<emph>étatisation</emph>), was accompanied by the
                     oneiric exaltation of a superior blood; the latter implied both the systematic
                     genocide of others and the risk of exposing oneself to a total sacrifice. It is
                     an irony of history that Hitlerite politics of sex remained an insignificant
                     practice while the blood myth was transformed into the greatest blood bath in
                     recent memory. (<title level="m">History</title> 149-50)</quote> The situation
                  is further complicated by the fact that Foucault introduced the term biopolitics
                  relatively late in life. He is certainly better known for his analyses of
                  disciplinary power, subject of his most famous studies on the clinic, the
                  penitentiary and the mental asylum.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn2" place="foot"
                     n="2">See <title level="m">The Birth of the Clinic</title> and <title level="m"
                        >Discipline and Punish.</title>
                  </note> While boundaries between disciplinary power and biopolitics are certainly
                  more difficult to draw than those between sovereign and biopower, it is safe to
                  say that they are not the same thing. However, the three articles under
                  consideration here tend to confound the two concepts. Their authors often use
                  biopolitics in such a way that it encompasses disciplinary strategies while the
                  latter term is eclipsed entirely. One difference between disciplinary power and
                  biopower suggested by Foucault himself concerns the different ‘materials’ and the
                  different bodies of knowledge they require. Disciplinary powers tend to work on
                  individuals who are turned into docile bodies by institutions such as schools and
                  hospitals. Biopower, however, has populations as its object. Hence biopower is
                  inconceivable without the new type of knowledge provided by Malthusian statistics
                  at the close of the eighteenth century. Later on, eugenics, social Darwinism and
                  scientific racism produce similarly structured knowledge. While the distinction
                  between individuals and larger entities is initially helpful, it is far from
                  clear-cut when issues like education or sexuality are under consideration where
                  the very relation of the individual to entities (such as nations, races or
                  populations) is at stake, as Foucault himself pointed out in the last chapter of
                  his <title level="m">History of Sexuality: An Introduction</title> from 1978. </p>
               <p>To make matters even more confusing, Foucault actually uses two different terms
                  for this phenomenon, namely biopower and biopolitics. There is scant evidence that
                  the two concepts need to be distinguished, as some believe. Given that Foucault
                  was more interested in the minutiae of particular practices than in conceptual
                  precision, it is doubtful whether biopolitics and biopower can or should be
                  distinguished. It would certainly be more desirable to explore the relations
                  between disciplinary power and biopolitics/biopower, but that would be better left
                  to a Foucault specialist. Suffice it to say that the most pertinent definition of
                  biopower and biopolitics most frequently cited by Foucault emphasizes its
                  difference from classical sovereignty. </p>
               <p>However, their opposition is not exhausted by the obvious reversal of the
                  respective positions of life and death in the sense of the definition referred to
                  above, but also extends to the respective spheres in which sovereignty and
                  biopolitics are situated. Sovereignty is, for all intents and purposes, a legal
                  discourse contingent on jurisprudence (and theology), whereas both disciplinary power 
                  and particularly biopower develop technologies based on the kind of knowledge
                  produced by newly emergent sciences such as biology and statistics in the late
                  eighteenth century (whose legal codification in racial laws, for example, is
                  secondary). This marks the very juncture where Agamben’s notion of biopolitics
                  diverges most obviously from Foucault. Agamben refuses to accept this historical
                  distinction and argues instead for a constitutive nexus of biopolitics and
                  sovereign power. According to Agamben, sovereign power has been biopolitics all
                  along. Both are essentially legal notions and the famous <emph>homo sacer</emph>,
                  briefly referred to as an archaic practice of Roman law in the fragmentary
                  compilations of Pompejus Festus, is the most significant piece of evidence in
                  Agamben’s attempt to make the case that sovereign power has always been
                  biopolitics. Their nexus unfolds in what Agamben calls the logic of the ‘ban’
                     (<title level="m">Homo Sacer </title>15-29, 104-110). Isolating, ex-cepting and
                  exempting a ‘natural’ life (however that might be defined) from the sovereign
                  sphere is said to be any sovereignty’s original and constitutive move. By banning
                  it, the ruling law delivers this outlawed life over to death with impunity. For,
                  according to Festus, the <emph>homo sacer </emph>is a person who cannot be
                  sacrificed, but whose killing also does not amount to a sacrilege and will not
                  entail any consequences, neither with respect to divine nor to any other law. For
                  Agamben then, sovereign politics is biopolitics and biopolitics is, at bottom,
                  always a politics of death and killing. That biopolitics, defined by Foucault as a
                  politics of fostering and enforcing life should turn out to have been a
                  ‘thanatopolitics’ from the start, is revealed most radically (and lethally) in the
                  concentration camps. In Agamben’s view, the death camps are permanent sites of
                  exception where the survival of the German race is produced by killing Jews. In
                  the camps, the difference between rule and exception, between life and death
                  disappears in what Agamben calls a zone of indistinction (47). Also disappearing
                  into a zone of indistinction are historical and local differences. Agamben traces
                  his idea of a lethal biopolitics at the heart of all sovereignty all the way back
                  to archaic Roman law and he extends it to encompass contemporary sites such as
                  Guantanamo Bay, European refugee camps, and airport transit zones, all of which
                  supposedly share the structure of the camps. </p>
               <p>Given the range of possible sites for <emph>homines sacri</emph> in the present
                  and throughout history, one begins to see why Agamben’s studies have had such a
                  profound impact in so many different areas of culture and politics. For those of
                  us in the business of philology and Western literature, there are two topics that
                  immediately suggest themselves as promising sites for engaging Agamben’s theory.
                  There is modernism and, with it, the various Avant-gardes which seek to abolish or
                  transform the distinction between life and art (Cf. Bachmann et al.), and there
                  is, of course, the earlier blue-print for such experiments, Romanticism, with its
                  emphatic notion of nature and its organicism, all of which co-emerged with the
                  very technologies Foucault associates with the rise of biopolitics (or biopower). </p>
               <p>All three contributors agree that re-considering Romanticism in light of
                  biopolitics is worthwhile, and, surprisingly, despite their different subject
                  matters and approaches, they all turn out to be more or less fervent defenders of
                  Romanticism. One might have expected the opposite, given that many analyses tend
                  to use the perspective of biopolitics to indict or, at least, challenge the
                  cherished icons of the Romantic tradition. One could imagine that particularly
                  those working in the field of German, who just witnessed the Schiller anniversary,
                  would seize the opportunity to question the author of the <title level="m">Letters
                     on Aesthetic Education of Man</title> and hero of the Left up to and including
                  his peculiar reception by Jacques Rancière. However, the authors collected in this
                  volume are determined to relieve Romanticism from any biopolitical charges and
                  suspicions. In fact, they seem to use the question of biopolitics and Romanticism
                  as an opportunity to rehabilitate much-maligned aesthetics. Perhaps these scholars
                  are actually fighting demons other than biopolitics. Occasional references to
                  Terry Eagleton or Paul de Man suggest dissatisfaction with the aversion against
                  aesthetics notorious in deconstructive readings as well as in older left-wing
                  ideological critique. Clearly, all three contributors perceive of biopolitics as a
                  version of that earlier charge and they rebel against it in different ways. </p>
               <p>However, considering that it was Agamben whose books ignited current discussions
                  of ‘biopolitics and X’, perhaps expectations of critical indictment of Romanticism
                  are flawed to begin with. Any reader of Agamben will not fail to notice that he is
                  not only a scathing critic of our current politics, but that he, perhaps even more
                  so then Derrida before him, is drawing on rich, often arcane, sources of
                  Old-European learnedness such as Pindar and Plato, Aristotle and Augustine, to
                  name just a few. Moreover, he is also a highly astute reader of poetry and
                  literature, as his marvelous book <title level="m">Stanzas</title> or the prose
                  vignettes collected in <title level="m">The Open: Man and Animal</title> show.
                  Even in his book on the camps, <title level="m">Remnants of Auschwitz</title>,
                  Primo Levi is his main source, while Hölderlin and other authors hover in the
                  margins. With those and additional pieces on Robert Walser, for example, and his
                  re-discovery of Max Kommerell in mind (<title level="m">Potentialities</title>),
                  positive assertions of aesthetics seem very much in line with Agamben’s own
                     interests.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn3" place="foot" n="3">Yet it is worth
                     mentioning that in his early works Agamben is very much a critic of aesthetics
                     in the tradition of Heidegger and others. Cf. <title level="m">The Man without
                        Content</title>. </note> Indeed, much of the attraction he currently exerts
                  on the intellectual (and by no means exclusively academic) imagination has to do
                  with his literary and aesthetic sensibilities which, for once, do not come at the
                  price of political stakes but appear to be in tune with them. However, even this
                  reminder could not quite dispel my initial surprise; I will return to this. </p>
               <p>In any case, from the initially unexpected consensus among them one might infer
                  that the readings, while nominally about biopolitics, actually belong to a
                  recently emerging trend to re-consider and re-evaluate aesthetics. This interest
                  might have been occasioned by discussions surrounding biopolitics, but it is
                  certainly not limited to that issue. Recall, for example, Elaine Scarry’s elegant
                  quasi-platonic defense of beauty from the late 1990s as an early instance of
                  reconsidering the role of aesthetics. The already mentioned Jacques Rancière also
                  made great efforts to rehabilitate the tradition of autonomous art since Schiller
                  from an idiosyncratic but certainly political perspective. Christoph Menke, whose
                  work offers the most significant contributions to date in reshaping our
                  understanding of aesthetics, even took on the question of biopolitics and
                  aesthetics directly, seeking to distinguish Foucault’s disciplinary power from
                  aesthetic practice in an essay aptly entitled ‘Two kinds of exercise’ (‘Zweierlei
                     Übung’).<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn4" place="foot" n="4">See also Menke
                     and Rebentisch. </note> However, none of these authors figures here. But it is
                  rather obvious that biopolitics appears to have assumed the place occupied by
                  older ideology critiques of aesthetics. At issue in all articles is aesthetics by
                  way of biopolitics and not the other way around as one might have expected. That
                  is not to say that the issues at hand—abortion in the case of Sara Guyer,
                  education in Marc Redfield and Mill’s utilitarian philosophy in Emily Sun’s
                  text—have nothing to do with biopolitics. However, the specificities of
                  biopolitics tend to be assigned lesser importance vis-à-vis the overt interest in
                  rehabilitating aesthetics. Having made this observation, I hasten to add that I
                  find this objective rather intriguing and that I certainly have no better, more
                  interesting or specific way of considering the question of Romanticism and
                  biopolitics. All I can offer in the final pages is an attempt to recast the
                  question of aesthetics and biopolitics by way of two concepts from their
                  respective spheres, namely form and life. To this end I will turn to Lukáçs’
                     <title level="m">Theory of the Novel</title> from 1916. However, having
                  isolated, for now, the re-emergence of aesthetics as the dominant motif uniting
                  the different contributions to this volume, I would like to examine each a bit
                  more closely on its own terms before considering Lukáçs in the last section. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>II</head>
               <p>Of the three contributions, Sara Guyer’s article on ‘Biopoetics’ is most obviously
                  programmatic in nature. What she proposes as ‘biopoetics’ is sharply distinguished
                  from and even opposed to its meaning and use in Brett Cooke and Frederick Turner’s
                  1999 anthology of the same name. While they profess faith in the existence of
                  artistic universals defining “our common humanity” (qtd. in Guyer), Guyer’s own
                  tentative appeal to an alternative “new humanistic method” is based on the
                  rejection of the scientific approach favored by the authors of <title level="m"
                     >Biopoetics: Evolutionary Exploration in the Arts</title>, which she associates
                  with the scientifically generated techniques of social control originally
                  described by Michel Foucault as biopolitics (or biopower, respectively).
                  Alternatively, her sense of ‘biopoetics’ relies on the power (but also: the
                  failure) of specific poetic operations—tropes of animation such as prosopopeia and
                  apostrophe. In outlining this other sense of biopoetics, she pursues a double
                  strategy. In the first part of her article, she engages various critics and
                  theoreticians to explore different ways of relating biopolitics and the lyric. In
                  the second part, she offers an elegant reading of a particular poem by John Clare
                  in which biopolitics in Foucault’s sense and the lyric come together in a way
                  obliquely suggested by Barbara Johnson, but more poignantly articulated in the
                  poem at hand. On Guyer’s reading, the poem exposes itself neither as a power over
                  life nor a power to kill but as a dissipating power, a weakness, as it were. At
                  stake in her reading is the failure of address, poetry’s failure to conjure up a
                  life no longer or not yet there but not exactly dead either. This poetically
                  performed failure of poetic sovereignty results in the insight that “sovereignty
                  and abandonment can share the same rhetoric”. In this, she finds an implicitly
                  consoling answer to the question that looms large in the first part of the essay:
                  Is literature, in particular Romantic literature, which emerges at the same time
                  as the newly devised strategies of biopolitics, analogous to those mechanisms,
                  perhaps even complicit with them? What does the biopolitical wish to wield power
                  over life have to do with the lyric modes of animating inanimate objects? Is
                  Romanticism, in fact, a secret agent of biopolitical technologies and strategies?
                  Assuming this is Guyer’s question, her answer is absolutely clear: literature
                  plays a different role with regard to life; it is neither a latent medium nor a
                  manifest agent of biopolitics. Yet literature’s chief concern is not death either,
                  as a certain reading of de Man’s deconstruction tends to suggest. Instead, poetry
                  and, by extension, biopoetics, is, for Guyer, a human and humanistic account of
                  life deeply opposed to biopolitics. </p>
               <p>With her emphatic insistence on poetry as a humanistic concern not exhausted by
                  science or technique, Guyer relieves poetry from the suspicion of being an
                  accomplice to biopolitics; at the same time she rejects the older prejudice
                  against Romanticism as organicist ideology. On her reading, biopoetics is an
                  ambivalent—but in its ambivalence unequivocally so—counter-concept and antidote to
                  biopolitics. While her position is clear, I am less certain about the motivation
                  and more uncertain still about the way she stages her questions and her answers.
                  Some of these difficulties may well have to do with the conceptual problems
                  surrounding biopolitics. The focus on abortion, as introduced by Johnson and
                  Deutscher, raises additional problems. For Guyer, abortion is per se a
                  biopolitical issue, as is the death penalty. However, this is debatable. According
                  to Foucault’s notion of biopolitics, abortion is not biopolitical because it does
                  not concern populations (or races) but individuals in relation to other sovereign
                  instances such as the state, which does or does not legalize abortion. The
                  question is more complicated when viewed from Agamben’s perspective. According to
                  him, the biopolitical goal to further, prolong, extend, and foster life was, at
                  bottom, always the desire to obtain a license to kill with impunity. The logic at
                  work here is most radically exemplified by Nazi-Racism in which the death of Jews
                  ensures the survival, the life of the Arian race. I hesitate to draw this analogy,
                  but no state will question abortion if the mother’s life is at stake. Hence
                  abortion is not biopolitical in Agamben’s sense either. (Since he harks back to
                  Roman law it is worth pointing out that one of the ways biopolitics reared its
                  head in the Roman Republic was the <emph>potestas vitae necisque</emph>, the right
                  of the father to decide whether his already born son should live or die. In his
                  analysis of this legal term, Agamben argues that this absolute power over the son
                  is the condition on which one becomes a free Roman citizen and thus a political
                  subject.) However, in another sense the issue of abortion is indeed strictly
                  biopolitical because what is legally, morally and medically at stake is the very
                  question which, according to Agamben, is the fatal problem of all politics to
                  date: what constitutes life or, more specifically, what constitutes viable life? I
                  do not know what Agamben would have to say about abortion, but one could argue
                  that the very fact that there are legal and moral debates about abortion is a sign
                  that politics has indeed been reduced to (or rather: still is) all about drawing a
                  (legal) boundary that separates life from what is not yet, or no longer, life. In
                  this perspective, abortion is indeed on par with the problematic state of comatose
                  patients who are either dead or alive depending on which legal and medical rule is
                  brought to bear on their case, and fetal life does indeed begin to look like
                  occupying a zone of indistinction similar to that of the comatose or the
                     <emph>Muselmann</emph> in the camps. Obviously, that is a highly problematic
                  line of argument, which I would rather not pursue. Suffice it to say that I am not
                  sure what to make of the notion of fetal life as introduced by Guyer via Johnson. </p>
               <p>While the biopolitics of abortion and the idea of fetal life are pertinent but
                  somewhat fuzzy (perhaps necessarily so), biopolitics moves into full view just
                  when Guyer believes to have broken its shackles and moved beyond it into the realm
                  of what she calls biopoetics. This occurs in her reading of Clare’s poem. Here the
                  notion of a fetal life in a zone of indistinction is linked to a poetic
                  sovereignty that fails to govern, a poetic power that fails to animate. This
                  failure exposes the co-existence, even dependency of sovereign rhetoric and a
                  rhetoric of abandonment, failure, and impotence. The reason why the biopoetic as
                  presented in this article could, in fact, be identified as the biopolitical itself,
                  has to do with one of Agamben’s more interesting but less cited arguments.
                  According to him, the constitutive nexus between sovereign power and biopower lies
                  in the fact that the ultimate power of the sovereign (or, for that matter: the
                  law) is its ability to withdraw and suspend itself. By surrendering its powerful
                  hold on a life, it exposes this life to death with impunity. True power is the
                  power to abandon power, as the law does when a state of emergency or exception is
                  announced. As is well known, what Agamben’s calls the ‘logic of the ban’ is
                  indebted to Carl Schmitt, who made the decision to suspend the rule of law in the
                  state of exception the cornerstone of his theory of sovereignty. Whereas Schmitt’s
                  decisionism celebrates the active act of deciding as proof of sovereign power,
                  Agamben, by contrast, emphasizes the passivity and the powerlessness of power as
                  the key element. (In part, this has to do with his reading of Aristotle as
                  developed in the essays collected in <title level="m">Potentialities</title>.)
                  When Guyer emphasizes the intertwinement of powerlessness and sovereignty, she
                  comes rather close to describing Agamben’s logic of the ban that is at the core of
                  biopolitics.</p>
               <p>Like Sara Guyer, Marc Redfield, too, is invested in literature as a site where the
                  workings of biopower are, if not resisted, then at least revealed in their
                  dependence on specifically literary operations that “compose and exceed not just
                  law or right per se, but also the sovereign exception that founds and exceeds law”
                  (6). In other words: literature is the better theory of biopolitics. After an
                  impressively succinct summary of both Foucault and Agamben, Redfield focuses on
                  ‘Bildung’, the formation of subjects, as a supposedly non-coercive model of
                  control that can also be read in a more sinister vein as a biopolitical phantasm
                  (Redfield’s measured agreement with Eagleton’s critique of Romantic aesthetics
                  evidences that he too considers the charge of biopolitics leveled against
                  Romanticism of a kind with earlier ideology critiques). His subsequent readings of
                  Schiller and Goethe are designed to demonstrate that their texts, even and
                  especially when they are not thematically concerned with biopolitical issues,
                  reflect on what Redfield with Agamben calls the “inscription of natural life in
                  the juridico-political order” (5), which Agamben (as Arendt before him) locates in
                  the Declaration of the Rights of Man. </p>
               <p>He readily concedes that Schiller’s notion of aesthetic education does indeed lend
                  itself to a biopolitical reading (although, like Guyer, he also seems to identify
                  Foucault’s biopower with his idea of disciplinary power). What concerns him most
                  is the concealed violence of aesthetic education and practice. And his point is
                  well taken. Education, considered by Kant the greatest task because the welfare of
                  the entire species depends on it [‘das Geheimnis der Gattung’] is, on the face of
                  it, a highly suggestive candidate for biopolitical interests precisely because the
                  future of the species depends on the individual and vice versa. However, in a
                  closer reading of Schiller’s famous passage on the artist and the politician from
                  the <title level="m">Letters on Aesthetic Education</title> Redfield can show that
                  things are more complicated, involving duplicities and slippages. Where Guyer
                  focuses on undecidability, Redfield emphasizes an ‘instability haunting’
                  Schiller’s text, its figures and tropes. While acknowledging peculiar and
                  suspicious convergences between the free play of the faculties in the aesthetic
                  state and the state of exception, Redfield eventually sides with (Schiller’s)
                  aesthetics against biopolitics because Schiller’s text exposes any pretensions to
                  aesthetic sovereignty as illusory. As in the case of Guyer’s reading of Clare’s
                  “To Mary,” aesthetic artifacts question the sovereignty of sovereignty. If,
                  however, sovereignty’s power resides precisely in its ability to surrender power,
                  in the power to exempt lives from its hold, then recognizing that sovereignty does
                  not govern does little to alter the operative biopolitical structure. Redfield’s
                  reading of Goethe’s as opposed to Schiller’s response to the revolution in his
                  “Unterhaltungen deutscher Ausgewanderten,” which, incidentally, is indebted to
                  Andreas Gailus’ interpretation of this text, proceeds along similar lines. </p>
               <p>While Redfield and Guyer’s respective texts offer very different perspectives,
                  they both intend to show that the texts under consideration “stage and deconstruct
                  sovereign violence” (Redfield 19). Just as Guyer, Redfield argues that art and
                  aesthetic theory expose and reveal what would otherwise remain hidden. Aesthetics
                  (not in general, but in the works of Schiller and Goethe he has chosen) is
                  heralded as a discourse capable of displaying “traces of a violence that
                  sovereigns commandeer but cannot properly command”. However, a free-floating
                  violence (as in the case of constitutionally anchored states of exception) that is
                  no longer tied to a person is no less violent and perhaps even more so, as Agamben
                  shows when he suggests that the problem of sovereignty is not person-bound (as
                  Schmitt believed) but structural. In other words: I am not sure whether an
                  ambivalence discovered, an inconsistency revealed, a delusion exposed are in
                  themselves improvements of any sort. At work in both essays is a fundamental
                  belief in the powers of enlightenment—as if the recognition and articulation of
                  instabilities and inconsistencies, which readings of literature can reveal, made
                  the operative norms any less normative. The implicit value attributed to moments
                  of undecidability and ambivalence is all the more remarkable in light of the fact
                  that Agamben’s success probably has something to do with his oedipal revolt
                  against Derrida and deconstruction where ambivalence was held in high esteem. One
                  could even speculate that Agamben’s insistence on the fatality of indistinction
                  calls the value deconstruction accorded to ambivalence into question. This much is
                  suggested by his rather explicitly anti-Derridean reading of Kafka’s parable
                  ‘Before the Law’ when Agamben writes: <quote>The prestige of deconstruction in our
                     time lies precisely in its having conceived of the entire text of tradition as
                     being in force without significance, a being in force whose strength lies
                     essentially in its undecidability and having shown that such a being in force
                     is, like the door of the Law in Kafka’s parable, absolutely impassable. But it
                     is precisely concerning the sense of being in force … that our position
                     distinguishes itself from that of deconstruction. (<title level="m">Homo Sacer
                     </title>54)</quote> Agamben interprets the figure of the man before the law as
                  a Messianic figure whose very goal is to get the open door of the Law to close.
                  With reference to deconstruction he continues: <quote>What threatens thinking here
                     is the possibility that thinking might find itself condemned to infinite
                     negotiations with the doorkeeper, or, even worse, that it might end by itself
                     assuming the role of the doorkeeper who, without really blocking the entry,
                     shelters the Nothing onto which the door opens. (54)</quote> Those are rather
                  strong words, aimed at questioning an overestimation of ambivalence and
                  undecidability. </p>
               <p>Of all three contributions, Emily Sun in her intriguing essay on John Stuart
                  Mill’s encounter with Wordsworth has the strictest conceptual sense of
                  biopolitics. She relies not on the Foucault of the lectures on Racism with their
                  famous juxtaposition of sovereign power and biopower, nor the <title level="m"
                     >History of Sexuality</title>, but draws instead primarily on Foucault’s
                  lectures in the <title level="m">Birth of Biopolitics</title> from the late 70s,
                  where biopolitics is related to the emergence of liberalism beginning in the late
                  eighteenth century. By the same token, Sun’s interesting essay is also the least
                  concerned with traces of the biopolitical within aesthetic artifacts. Rather, her
                  reading of Wordsworth’s significance for John Stuart Mill amounts to something of
                  a case study in the power of aesthetic education in Schiller’s sense. Haven fallen
                  into crisis, Mill’s turn to Wordsworth affects a turn away from the liberal
                  utilitarianism he had previously espoused. Less ambiguously than Redfield and
                  Guyer, Sun views art more straightforwardly as antidote to a notion of politics
                  reduced to managing populations. However, she also acknowledges a link between the
                  two worlds of Benthamite reasoning and Wordsworth’s poetry. As in the
                  contributions by Guyer and Redfield, (literary) rhetoric is once more at issue. In
                  her case, a rhetoric of theatricality enables and underpins the transformation of
                  Mill’s utilitarianism. Whether that implicates art in liberalism or liberalism in
                  aesthetics is of lesser concern for Sun, in part because of her very clearly
                  defined notion of biopolitics and in part because she confines herself to tracing
                  the noticeable shifts affected by Mill’s discovery of Wordsworth. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
               <head>III</head>
               <p>At one point in her article, Sara Guyer refers to Agamben’s notion of
                     <emph>forma-di-vita</emph>. While Agamben has neglected to elaborate this term
                  in greater detail, it is certainly legitimate to identify form-of-life as an
                  alternative to the bare life produced by sovereignty. Form-of-life, Guyer writes
                  with reference to a short text by Agamben of that title, entertains “a relation to
                  the indeterminate and unprogrammed” (Guyer). As <emph>forma-di-vita</emph>, life
                  is indeed about the (non-actualized or unlived) possibilities of life as opposed
                  to sovereignty’s efforts to separate and isolate a mere life. Thus the term points
                  to Agamben’s idiosyncratic ontological re-description of possibility in his
                  readings of Aristotle. All other definitions of the enigmatic concept of
                  form-of-life are based on negation. Accordingly, form-of-life is a life in which
                  no life can be abstracted or isolated from the form this life has assumed. Leaving
                  aside the general semantic overdetermination of <emph>forma-di-vita</emph>,
                  form-of-life or, in German, <emph>Lebensform</emph> (which, incidentally,
                  signifies a qualified life just as much as a life-form, i.e. species), it is worth
                  pointing out that problems of life and form are a great concern in at least two
                  spheres of thought. Since Romanticism (in the widest sense), life and form and
                  their numerous permutations have been subject to aesthetic practice and theory. In
                  addition (and, conceptually speaking, in close vicinity), the compound noun unites
                  two concepts circulating in many strands of late nineteenth- and early
                  twentieth-century <emph>Lebensphilosophie</emph>. While Agamben never refers to
                  any of the relevant authors explicitly, his proximity to Deleuze, whom we owe one
                  of the most sophisticated readings of Bergson to date, might have influenced his
                  terminological choice. More obviously, <emph>forma-di-vita</emph> is also a
                  reformulation of Heidegger’s <emph>Dasein.</emph>
                  <note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn5" place="foot" n="5">See Agamben’s essay “Form of
                     Life,” in <title level="m">Means without End</title>. Though Agamben does not
                     cite Heidegger directly, most of the essay’s diction and content, however, very
                     clearly point back to § 9 of Heidegger’s <title level="m">Being and
                        Time</title>. </note> Bringing together in some way or other the notion of
                  life as unformed flow and form as lasting shape is a central topic in authors like
                  Bergson, Simmel, and others up to and including Heidegger. However, whether the
                  nexus of life and form can or should be thought of as a <emph>relation</emph>, is,
                  in fact, at issue in all of these authors and also informs Agamben’s own
                  discussions of <emph>forma-di-vita. </emph>
               </p>
               <p>Perhaps his most sustained but also speculative and enigmatic elucidations of
                     <emph>forma-di-vita</emph> are part of the very chapter in which he offers his
                  already quoted critique of Derrida and deconstruction. In those sections, entitled
                  ‘Form of Law’, Agamben interprets Kafka’s famous parable ‘Before the Law’ as an
                  allegory of the sovereign exception or ban which includes what it excludes and
                  hence maintains a relation to it by not relating to it. What holds bare life and
                  mere form (of the law) together is nothing else than this relationship which
                  Agamben designates as ban (<title level="m">Homo Sacer </title>49-62). Borrowing a
                  phrase from the correspondence between Gershom Scholem and Walter Benjamin on
                  Kafka, the law in “Before the Law” is said to be “in force but without
                  significance” (51). In the state of exception the law is stripped of any content
                  and “the empty potentiality is so much in force as to become indistinguishable
                  from life” (51). Against this background Agamben raises the question of  whether there
                  might be a “form of life (…) that corresponds to the form of law” (52). The
                  dissolution of the ban with its peculiarly extreme relationship of relating by
                  not-relating would require, Agamben argues, to acknowledge that life and law, just
                  like Heidegger’s being and Being, do not have “the form of a relation” (60). He
                  further suggests that this “implies nothing less than an attempt to think the
                  politico-social factum no longer in the form of a relation” (60). For if one
                  thinks of life and law in terms of a relation, any relation, one has already
                  succumbed to the logic of the ban which, according to Agamben, is the most
                  extreme, most tenuous and hence most powerful form of all possible relations.
                  Agamben concludes that the mere form of law (as given in the state of exception
                  and resulting in the indistinguishability of life and law) can be countered or
                  “confronted by life that, in a symmetrical but inverse gesture, is entirely
                  transformed into law” (55) which presumably would amount to a true (Messianic)
                  state of exception rather than the permanent state of exception we are said to
                  live in. The only examples of such a form of life can be found in the bizarre
                  gallery of <emph>homines sacri</emph> at the close of Agamben’s book, featuring
                  the <emph>Muselmann</emph>, a comatose patient, the Roman priest <emph>Flamen
                     Diale</emph> and Hitler, among others. The Roman priest as well as Hitler may
                  perhaps be considered as figures whose life has been transformed into law, whereas
                  the comatose patient like the <emph>Muselmann</emph> might represent a law that
                  has become life. Disturbing as this prospect is, Agamben appears to have his hopes
                  staked on this inversion:<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn6" place="foot" n="6"
                     >Ambivalent formulations are part of Agamben’s provocations. An example of
                     deliberate ambivalence can be found in the beginning of the chapter on
                     “Sovereignty and Bare Life”: “The ‘enigmas’ that our century has proposed to
                     historical reason and that remain with us (Nazism is only the most disquieting
                     among them) will be solved only on the terrain—biopolitics—on which they were
                     formed” (<title level="m">Homo Sacer</title> 4). For a more thorough discussion
                     of this aspect, see Geulen.</note> if a life could transform itself into law as
                  its form and thus become a form of life in which law and life are inseparable,
                  there would be no room for relations and hence no room for the logic of the
                  sovereign ban that upholds the logic of relations by holding its elements in
                  permanent suspense. </p>
               <p>While it is perhaps impossible to conceive of a politics of
                     <emph>forma-di-vita</emph> or, for that matter, of any politics, without
                  recourse to the notion of relation, there exists indeed a form, an aesthetic form,
                  that is virtually indistinguishable from life, a form that does not relate to its
                  content in any way because its form, its formal law binds it directly to the
                  (discrete, heterogeneous, form- and law-less) empiricism of life; a form,
                  moreover, which for this very reason has frequently been judged to be a formless
                  form or a ‘half-art [<emph>Halbkunst</emph>]’ (Lukáçs 73). That form, a modern
                  form, is the novel. At least this is what Georg Lukáçs sought to argue in his
                     <title level="m">Theory of the Novel</title> from 1916, which remains one of
                  the most powerful and rich theoretical explorations of the novel as a form
                     <emph>sui generis</emph> (rather than a genre among others). Given the
                  prominence of the terms ‘life’ and ‘form’ in his text, it is highly instructive to
                  re-read his book in light of the question of biopolitics and aesthetics. The
                  point, however, is not to provide any answers to the question whether aesthetics
                  is complicit with biopolitics, but to reframe the very question by shifting the
                  terrain. Instead of asking about possible relations between aesthetics and
                  biopolitics, Lukáçs’ <emph>Theory of the Novel</emph> may be productively (re)read
                  as a site where the question of form and life is played out exclusively as a
                  problem of aesthetic form. Therefore, his essay may be considered a testing
                  ground, as it were, for the conceptual viability of Agamben’s enigmatic idea of
                     <emph>forma-di-vita</emph>. Before making the case for such a re-reading, an
                  obvious objection or question needs to be addressed: what are the reasons for
                  doing so? If Agamben and notions of biopolitics allow us to relate politics and
                  aesthetics in a number of different ways, should one not hold on to that
                  possibility rather than giving up on politics and, once more, withdrawing into the
                  aesthetic sphere? Indeed, but any attempt to ‘relate’ aesthetics and politics
                  upholds their distinction and separateness. If Agamben has a lesson to teach, it
                  is that distinction and relation can result in a highly problematic collapse of
                  distinctions. In other words: if there is something to Agamben’s claim that
                  relationality has proven inherently problematic with respect to law and life, it
                  might be worthwhile to pursue the non-relational idea of
                     <emph>forma-di-vita</emph> in aesthetics without relating it to politics. Of
                  course, this is bound to raise the specter of the aestheticization of politics; at
                  the very least it could be misinterpreted as an attempt to call Agamben’s
                  political stakes into question by showing that the core problems are aesthetic in
                  nature and only parade as political. Yet such an argument would also depend on
                  being able to draw the line between aesthetic forms and politics. And it is to
                  challenge this idea that I am enlisting Lukáçs. As an added benefit this might
                  also shed some light on the enigmatic idea of non-relationality associated with
                     <emph>forma-di-vita. </emph>
               </p>
               <p>Among the many terms Lukáçs’ account of the novel employs, such as law, life and
                  form, none is more dominant than that of form. Contrary to many readings
                  (including his own assertions in the later preface) and his supposed Hegelianism,
                  he is less concerned with philosophy of history than with intrinsic questions of
                  form. And it is important to note that, in a manner inconceivable for Hegel,
                  philosophy too is for Lukáçs an aesthetic form, which he places next to epic and
                  tragedy as the third of “the great and timeless paradigmatic forms of world
                  literature [<emph>Weltgestaltung</emph>]” (35). Moreover, the emergence of all
                  three forms already presupposes the loss of totality and a rupture between subject
                  and object, soul and action, life and its significance. This is true of philosophy
                  “as a form of life” (29) and it is also true of the great Homeric epics. They are
                  certainly not the adequate expression of a totality enjoyed by the Greeks and
                  forever unattainable to the moderns. On the contrary, the very existence of
                  Homer’s epics proves that life has lost its immanent significance. This is not to
                  say that there are no differences between Homer, Dante, and the modern novel, but
                  they all respond in different ways to the same problematic: “Every art form is
                  defined by the metaphysical dissonance of life which it accepts and organizes as
                  the basis of totality complete in itself” (71). Admittedly, for Homer it was just
                  a matter of lifting the meaningful forms of life to consciousness, whereas the
                  modern novel forever seeks and seeks to produce what it would rather just find.
                  This is why the novel is called the epic “of an age in which the extensive
                  totality of life is no longer given, in which the immanence of meaning in life has
                  become a problem, yet which still thinks in terms of totality [<emph>die Gesinnung
                     zur Totalität hat</emph>]” (56). Persisting through its different
                  manifestations in the epic, the novella or the novel is what Lukáçs calls “the
                  formative <emph>a priori</emph>” (44) or “formal <emph>a priori</emph>”
                     (46)—<emph>Formapriorität</emph>—shared by all epic forms. Whereas tragedy’s
                  ‘formal <emph>a priori</emph>’ consists in answering the question: “how can
                  meaning [<emph>Wesen</emph>] come to life?” all epic forms respond to the inverse
                  question: how can life transcend itself and become meaningful: “How can life
                  become essential [<emph>wesenhaft</emph>]?” (35). In Agamben’s terminology, how
                  can life become form-of-life, in Heidegger’s, how can being become Being? The
                  undeniable uniqueness of Homer’s works over and against all other ‘great epic
                  forms’, including the novel, stems from the fact that Greek epic gave an answer to
                  that question before the question arose as such (13). Its formulation was
                  philosophy’s task, which succeeded the epic and articulated the very problem to
                  which the former had already found the solution. This peculiarity of Greek epic
                  removes it forever from our grasp. In fact, the radicality with which Lukáçs
                  insists on the epos’ ultimate otherness surpasses both Nietzsche’s earlier and
                  Benjamin’s later reflections on Greek antiquity in general and tragedy in
                  particular.</p>
               <p>The rhythm of the emergence and transformations of these three forms (epic,
                  tragedy and philosophy) is indeed, if not exactly preordained by, then at least
                  synchronized with “the historic-philosophical position of the world’s clock” (91).
                  However, the conclusion that the very purpose of art and its respective forms is
                  to provide a dissonant world and fragmented life with the meaningful totality both
                  are lacking is deceptive. Instead, each form must obey its own structural logic
                  and formal law, independent of the state of affairs (which philosophy charts):
                     <quote>Each form appears positive because it fulfills its own structural laws:
                     the affirmation of life that seems to emanate from it as a mood is nothing
                     other than the resolving of its form-conditioned [<emph>formgeforderten</emph>]
                     dissonances, the affirmation of its own, form-created
                        [<emph>formgeschaffenen</emph>] substance.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn7"
                        place="foot" n="7">In an earlier passage, Lukáçs had written: “Art always
                        says ‘And yet!’ to art” (72).</note> (128) </quote> The emphasis should be
                  on “form-conditioned” and “form-created”. The dissonances and their dissolution
                  into a meaningful totality are equally functions of the internal law of forms,
                  quite independent of everything else. The historical fate of the various forms is
                  thus determined by the formal specificities in accordance with the questions a
                  particular aesthetic form attempts to answer. Hence, tragedy, which responds to
                  the question how essence can come alive, is more immune to changes in what Lukáçs
                  calls “the transcendental structure of the form-giving subject and the world of
                  created forms” (40f). The reason why tragedy survived longer and adapted better to
                  the fundamental rifts in the relationship of life and meaning is to be found in
                  its ‘formative a <emph>priori</emph>.’ In all drama, meaning is given or posited
                  and at issue is how to bring it to life. Therefore, drama is more likely to
                  produce a perhaps in many ways problematic, but nevertheless a whole world (for
                  example in the figure of the hero). Epic does not have this option because its
                  Form <emph>a priori</emph> is entirely different. What is given to the epic is not
                  any transcendent meaning of life but just life itself. All epic forms are such
                  that “the world at any given moment is an ultimate principle; they are empirical
                  at their deepest, most decisive, all-determining transcendental base“ (46). A few
                  pages later, Lukáçs adds that all epic’s empiricity is “form-demanded
                     [<emph>formgewollt</emph>]” (49).<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn8"
                     place="foot" n="8">The translation has been modified, since, unfortunately, the
                     English rendition misses the point. </note> The ‘f<emph>ormgewollte</emph>’ or
                     ‘<emph>formgeforderte</emph>’ empiricism of all epic forms resists its
                  assimilation into a meaningful whole. Whenever an epic form attempts to do so in
                  modernity, it inevitably violates its intrinsic formal law. As a consequence, the
                  epic is constantly threatened to deteriorate into lyrical subjectivity or into the
                  objectivism of drama: <quote>This indestructible bond with reality as it is, the
                     crucial difference between the epic and the drama, is a necessary consequence
                     of the object of the epic being life itself. The concept of essence leads to
                     transcendence simply by being posited, and then, in the transcendent,
                     crystallizes into a new and higher essence expressing through its form an
                     essence that <emph>should be</emph>—an essence which, because it is born of
                     form, remains independent of the given content of what merely
                        <emph>exists</emph>. The concept of life, on the other hand, has no need of
                     any such transcendence captured and held immobile as an object. (47) </quote>
                  In modernity, with its shifts in the concept of life, epic forms find themselves
                  in a very different situation than drama. Already in the epos of antiquity, this
                  form was bound to life, but the epic had only to let the essence emerge through
                  its form. But life’s stubborn resistance has grown enormously. On account of their
                  “formal a priori”, epic forms “can never of their own accord charm something into
                  life that was not already present in it” (47). It is important to bear in mind
                  that the empiricism of life that is epic’s subject is not its content or object,
                  but is itself, as Lukáçs says, demanded by form. It is therefore not a matter of
                  epic forms somehow relating to life; in the epic, being bound to life is its
                  formal requirement, the law of its form. </p>
               <p>In the course of his book, Lukáçs suggests several solutions to the dilemma epic
                  faces in modernity. The totality epic forms are to achieve by virtue of their
                  formal law can be relegated to a fragment—as in novellas, ballads or the idyllic.
                  But all those epic forms remain threatened and flawed as they transgress into the
                  lyric (by making an individual subject the bearer of totality) or into drama by
                  abstractly claiming a meaning life does not have on its own. All of these remain
                  partial and for the most part non-satisfactory solutions to a dilemma that the
                  novel as the epic’s true successor faces head-on, so to speak: “The dissonance
                  special to the novel, the refusal of the immanence of being to enter into
                  empirical life, produces a problem of form whose formal nature is much less
                  obvious than in other kinds of art” (71). The novel is an epic form and as such it
                  cannot distinguish between life and form because it is bound to empirical life qua
                  form. The bizarre solution the novel finds for its peculiar form-problem is, above
                  all, to acknowledge that its solutions must all be deficient in view of what is
                  required: “the immanence of meaning required by the form
                     [<emph>formgeforderte</emph>] is attained precisely when the author goes all
                  the way, ruthlessly, towards exposing its absence” (72). From this dialectical
                  ruse issues Lukáçs’ theory of irony: “Irony, the self-surmounting
                     [<emph>Selbstaufhebung</emph>] of a subjectivity that has gone as far as it is
                  possible to go, is the highest freedom that can be achieved in a world without
                  God” (93). But this solution too remains, as many forms of drama, too abstract and
                  “intellectualist [<emph>intellektualistisch</emph>]” (44). </p>
               <p>However, the novel also has a purely formal solution for the problems it faces as
                  an epic form. Bound to life, it takes one of life’s essential dimensions and
                  adopts it as its proper form. In the novel, time becomes process and process
                  becomes (dynamic) form: “Thus the novel, in contrast to other genres whose
                  existence resides within the finished form, appears as something in process of
                  becoming“ (72). This is why Lukáçs likes to invoke the novel as “the form of
                  mature virility” (85). It is a reminder of the fact that a life’s story is the
                  usual form of the novel and biography one of its essential possibilities. In
                  short: the form of the novel is formed life.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn9"
                     place="foot" n="9">For Lukáçs the life of the novel has to be an individual
                     life in accordance with his premises. Rüdiger Campe, taking his cue from
                     Lukáçs, has shown that there is another, older type of novel not concerned with
                     the individual’s life but with the life of institutions, which resurfaces in
                     early 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-century once the biographical novel has run its
                     course. Campe identified novels by Kafka and Robert Walser as institutional
                     novels, and perhaps Dostoyevsky—whom Lukáçs exempts from his discussion of the
                     novel as an altogether new form—could also be read along these lines. See
                     Campe, <title level="a">Robert Walsers Institutionenroman</title>. On the problem of form and the
                     novel and the emergence of life in those theories, see also Campe, <title level="a">Form und
                     Leben in der Theorie des Romans</title>. </note> The novel’s solution is thus not even
                  to try to find meaning in any particular contents; rather in adapting the
                  life-worldly fact of time as its form, the sheer becoming can now appear as
                  essential and meaningful. This is how the novel can be like life but “as form, the
                  novel establishes a fluctuating yet form balance between becoming and being; as
                  the idea of becoming, it becomes a state [<emph>Zustand</emph>]. Thus the novel,
                  by transforming itself into a normative being of becoming, surmounts itself” (73).
                  In life, time has no beginning and no end, but the novel achieves the
                  transformation of time into a process that subsequently appears as the very
                  essence of all life. This is the novel’s chance to be the old epic’s legitimate
                  successor and, at the same time, an entirely new epic form. This chance is highly
                  improbable and the ways in which Lukáçs underscores the contingency of that form
                  as a form bound to the contingencies of life is nothing less than remarkable. </p>
               <p>The highly critical form of the novel “prescribes still stricter, still more
                  violable artistic laws for itself than do ‘the closed forms,’ and those laws are
                  all the more binding because they cannot be defined or formulated” (73).<note
                     resp="editors" xml:id="ftn10" place="foot" n="10">The translation has been
                     modified since the translator elided part of the sentence. </note> Just as
                  time, which also inheres in the “sphere of mere life,” becomes the idea of process
                  when the novel adopts it as its organizing principle, the indefinable but strictly
                  binding principles governing the success of the novel also have their origin in
                  the life world: <quote>Tact and taste, in themselves subordinate categories which
                     belong wholly to the sphere of mere life and are irrelevant to an essential
                     ethic world, here acquire great constitutive significance; only then is
                     subjectivity, at the beginning of the novel’s totality and at its end, capable
                     of maintaining itself in equilibrium, of positing itself as epically normative
                     objectivity and thus of surmounting abstraction, the inherent danger of the
                     novel form. (74) </quote> Laws of tact are laws defying articulation. They are
                  in force but without significance. By entrusting each novel’s fate to the tact of
                  the aesthetic subjectivity, Lukáçs re-turns something to the novel that it
                  threatened to have lost when it found the solution of its challenges in the idea
                  of irony and the adaptation of time as a formal principle. Subjecting the novel to
                  the wholly unknowable and indefinable laws of tact, Lukáçs restores to the novel
                  the very life-worldly contingency that its formal a priori demands. The novel is
                  thus not only a critical and permanently endangered form but also highly
                  paradoxical: Its goal is to find meaning in life but whenever it succeeds in doing
                  so it has potentially betrayed the very life that it is bound to: “the great epic
                  is a form bound to the historical moment [<emph>an die Empirie des geschichtlichen
                     Augenblicks gebunden</emph>], and any attempt to depict the utopian as existent
                  can only end in destroying the form, not in creating reality” (152). For Lukáçs
                  this (form-generated) fate of the novel is mirrored in the life of this form. In
                  Dante, the epic is on the way to being supplanted by the novel; all subsequent
                  novels, from Goethe to Tolstoy, from the abstract idealist novel to the novel of
                  disillusion [<emph>Desillusionsroman</emph>], with rarest and highly improbably
                  exceptions, remain flawed. However, their very deficiencies confirm the novel as
                  the form bound to life as chance and contingency. With Dostoyevsky, finally, who
                  dawns at the end of Lukáçs’ book, the novel has disappeared: <quote>Dostoyevsky
                     did not write novels, and the creative vision revealed in his works has nothing
                     to do, either as affirmation or as rejection, with European nineteenth-century
                     Romanticism or with the many, likewise, Romantic reactions against it. Only
                     formal analysis of his works can show whether he is already the Homer or the
                     Dante of that world or whether he merely supplies the songs which, together
                     with the songs of other forerunners, later artists will one day weave into a
                     great unity. (152f) </quote> Whether Dostoyevsky did not write novels after all
                  is another question. Be that as it may, as a form bound to life, the life of the
                  novel itself has the form of life: contingent and flawed. And like its characters
                  the novel itself is always searching and never finds itself. The novel is a form
                  of life in which no bare life can be separated, whose law is life and whose life
                  is its law. If the novel is <emph>forma-di-vita, </emph>or, less emphatically, if
                  the novel as described by Lukáçs affords the possibility to make sense of
                  Agamben’s enigmatic term and its implied anti-relational logic, then one may raise
                  the question of the novel’s politics. Lukáçs could not be more concise on this
                  point. There is no politics of the novel and there can never be one, neither
                  biopolitical nor sovereign. However, the novel is the one genre least guilty of
                  the notorious “exaggeration of the substantiality of art [<emph>Überspannung der
                     Substantialität der Kunst</emph>]”, least guilty of the equally notorious
                  “hypostasy of aesthetics into metaphysics” (38) because as a form of art, and,
                  more specifically, as a genre of great epic art, the novel is not about art but
                  about life. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>
               <listBibl>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Agamben, Giorgio</author>
                        <title level="m">Stanzas: Word and Phantasm in Western Culture</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Martinez, Ronald L.</editor>
                        <edition>1977</edition>

                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Minneapolis</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>U of Minnesota P</publisher>
                           <date>1992</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                     <series>
                        <title level="m">Theory and History of Literature, 69</title>
                     </series>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Agamben, Giorgio</author>
                        <title level="m">Homo Sacer: Sovereign Power and Bare Life</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Daniel Heller-Roazen</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Stanford UP</publisher>
                           <date>1998</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Agamben, Giorgio</author>
                        <title level="m">Remnants of Auschwitz: The Witness and the Archive</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Heller-Roazen, Daniel</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Zone</publisher>
                           <date>1999</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Agamben, Giorgio</author>
                        <title level="m">Potentialities: Collected Essays in Philosophy</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Daniel Heller-Roazen</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Stanford UP</publisher>
                           <date>1999</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Agamben, Giorgio</author>
                        <title level="m">The Man without Content</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Giorgia Albert</editor>
                        <edition>1977</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Stanford UP</publisher>
                           <date>1999</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Agamben, Giorgio</author>
                        <title level="m">Means Without Ends: Notes on Politics</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Binetti, Vincenzo</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Casarino, Cesare</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Minneapolis</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>U of Minnesota P</publisher>
                           <date>2000</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Agamben, Giorgio</author>
                        <title level="m">The Open: Man and Animal</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Kevin Attell</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Stanford UP</publisher>
                           <date>2003</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Arendt, Hannah</author>
                        <title level="m">The Origins of Totalitarianism</title>
                        <edition>1951</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>San Diego</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Harcourt</publisher>
                           <date>1973</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Arendt, Hannah</author>
                        <title level="m">The Human Condition</title>
                        <edition>1958. 2nd ed</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>U of Chicago P</publisher>
                           <date>1998</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Buchmann, Sabeth</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Draxler, Helmut</editor>
                        <editor>Greene, Stephan</editor>
                        <title level="m">Film, Avantgarde, Biopolitik</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Schriften der Akademie der Künste</publisher>
                           <date>2009</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Campe, Rüdiger</author>
                        <title level="a">Robert Walsers Institutionenroman <title level="m">Jakob
                              von Gunten</title></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Die Macht und das Imaginäre: Eine kulturelle Verwandtschaft
                           in der Literatur</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Behrens, Rudolf</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Steigerwald, Jörn</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Würzburg</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Königshausen u. Neumann</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">235-251</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Campe, Rüdiger</author>
                        <title level="a">Form und Leben in der Theorie des Romans</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Vita Aesthetica: Szenarien ästhetischer
                           Lebendigkeit</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Avanessian, Armen</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Menninghaus, Winfried</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Völker, Jan</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Diaphanes</publisher>
                           <date>2009</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">193-211</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Cooke, Brett</editor>
                        <editor role="edotpr">Turner, Frederick</editor>
                        <title level="m">Biopoetics: Evolutionary Explorations in the Arts</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Lexington</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Paragon House</publisher>
                           <date>1999</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Deleuze, Gilles</author>
                        <title level="m">Bergsonism</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Tomlinson, Hugh</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Habberjam, Barbara</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Zone</publisher>
                           <date>1991</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Foucault, Michel</author>
                        <title level="m">The Birth of the Clinic: An Archaeology of Medical
                           Perception.</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Sheridan Smith, A. M.</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Vintage</publisher>
                           <date>1973</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Foucault, Michel</author>
                        <title level="m">Discipline and Punish: The Birth of the Prison</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Sheridan, Alan</editor>
                        <edition>2nd ed</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Vintage</publisher>
                           <date>1977</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Foucault, Michel</author>
                        <title level="m">History of Sexuality, Vol. 1</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Hurley, Robert</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Vintage</publisher>
                           <date>1980</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Foucault, Michel</author>
                        <title level="m">Society Must Be Defended: Lectures at the Collège de France
                           1975-1976</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Davidson, Arnold I.</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Macey, David</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Picador</publisher>
                           <date>2003</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Foucault, Michel</author>
                        <title level="m">Security, Territory, Population: Lectures at the Collège de
                           France 1977-1978</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Snellart, Michel</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Burchell, Graham</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>St. Martin’s P</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Foucault, Michel</author>
                        <title level="m">The Birth of Biopolitics: Lectures at the Collège de France
                           1978-1979</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Snellart, Michel</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Burchell, Graham</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>St. Martin’s P</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Gailus, Andreas</author>
                        <title level="a">Of Beautiful and Dismembered Bodies: Art as Social
                           Discipline in Schiller's <emph>Letters on the Aesthetic Education of
                              Man</emph></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Impure Reason</title>
                        <editor>Wilson, W. Daniel</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Holub, Robert C.</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Detroit</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Wayne State UP</publisher>
                           <date>1993</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">146-165</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Geulen, Eva</author>
                        <title level="a">The Function of Ambivalence in Agamben’s Re-Ontlogization
                           of Politics</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">A Leftist Ontology: Beyond Relativism and Identity
                           Politics</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Strathausen, Carsten</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Minneapolis</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>U of Minnesota P</publisher>
                           <date>2009</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">19-29</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Guyer, Sara</author>
                        <title level="a"><ref target="praxis.2012.guyer.html">Biopoetics, or
                              Romanticism</ref></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Biopolitics</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Hunt, Alastair</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Rudolf, Matthias</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <publisher>University of Maryland</publisher>
                           <date type="update">2012</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                     <series>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Circles Praxis Series</title>
                     </series>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Heidegger, Martin</author>
                        <title level="m">Being and Time</title>
                        <edition>1953</edition>
                        <editor role="editor">Schmit, and Rev. Dennis</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Stambaugh, Joan</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Albany</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>State U of New York P</publisher>
                           <date>2010</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Lukáçs, Georg</author>
                        <title level="m">The Theory of the Novel: A Historico-philosophical Essay in
                           the Forms of Great Epic Literature</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Bostock, Anna</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass.</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>MIT P</publisher>
                           <date>1983</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Marx, Karl</author>
                        <title level="a">On the Jewish Question</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Early Writings</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Benton, Gregor</editor>
                        <edition>1975</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Penguin</publisher>
                           <date>1992</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Menke, Christoph</author>
                        <title level="a">Zweierlei Übung. Zum Verhältnis sozialer Disziplinierung
                           und ästhetischer Existenz</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Michel Foucault. Zwischenbilanz einer Rezeption</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Honneth, Axel</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Saar, Martin</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Frankfurt a.M.</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Suhrkamp</publisher>
                           <date>2001</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Menke, Christoph</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Rebentisch,Juliane</editor>
                        <title level="m">Kreation und Depression: Freiheit im gegenwärtigen
                           Kapitalismus</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Kadmos</publisher>
                           <date>2010</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Rancière, Jacques</author>
                        <title level="m">The Politics of Aesthetics</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Rockhill, Gabriel</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Continuum</publisher>
                           <date>2004</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Redfield, Marc</author>
                        <title level="a"><ref target="praxis.2012.redfield.html">Aesthetics,
                              Sovereignty, Biopower: From Schiller’s <title level="m">Über die
                                 ästhetische Erziehung des Menschen</title> to Goethe’s <title
                                 level="m">Unterhaltungen deutscher
                           Ausgewanderten</title></ref></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Biopolitics</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Hunt, Alastair</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Rudolf, Matthias</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <publisher>University of Maryland</publisher>
                           <date type="update">2012</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                     <series>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Circles Praxis Series</title>
                     </series>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Scarry, Elaine</author>
                        <title level="m">On Beauty and Being Just</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Princeton UP</publisher>
                           <date>1999</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Schiller, Friedrich</author>
                        <title level="m">On the Aesthetic Education of Man, in a Series of
                           Letters</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Wilkinson, Elizabeth M.</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">L.A., Willoughby</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
                           <date>1967</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Sun, Emily</author>
                        <title level="a"><ref target="praxis.2012.sun.html">What is Poetry in the Theater of Biopolitics?</ref></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Biopolitics</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Hunt, Alastair</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Rudolf, Matthias</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <publisher>University of Maryland</publisher>
                           <date type="update">2012</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                     <series>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Circles Praxis Series</title>
                     </series>
                  </biblStruct>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
