<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Romanticism and Biopolitics</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">Biopoetics, or Romanticism</title>
            <author>
               <name>Sara Guyer</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">Alastair Hunt</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <editor role="editor">Matthias Rudolf</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2012.guyer</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-01-24">Jan 24, 2012</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded,
                  reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                  purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as
                  provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic
                  Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                  with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted
                  by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express
                  prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the
                  following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order
                  to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users
                  to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet.
                  We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis,
                  and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all
                  Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic
                  Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Romanticism and Biopolitics</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Sara</forename>
                        <surname>Guyer</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Romanticism and Biopolitics:</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2012-01-24">October 15, 2010</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for ","
                  for ", ' for ', and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on
                  the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been
                  indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces,
                  etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>Dave Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2010-03-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>Biopoetics, or Romanticism</head>
            <byline><docAuthor>Sara Guyer</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation></byline>

            <p>In his last lecture of 1975-76, Michel Foucault focused on “power’s hold over life”
               (239), and in particular the emergence in the nineteenth century of sovereignty as a
               power over life, rather than death, sovereignty as “the right to make live and let
               die” (241). As Foucault explains in the <title level="m">History of
               Sexuality</title>, “The old power of death that symbolized sovereign power was now
               carefully supplanted by the administration of bodies and the calculated management of
               life” (262), two “techniques” that Foucault identifies not in philosophy but “in the
               form of concrete arrangements” (262). Foucault’s insight has opened up the epoch of
               biopower, providing the terms and frames though which everything from sexuality to
               human rights can be understood as occurring in the aftermath of this shift in the
               very significance of life itself.</p>
            <p>British (and French) poets writing at more or less the same time as the planners and
               statisticians who Foucault considers, that is, from the late-eighteenth to
               mid-nineteenth centuries, might also be understood to register a new significance of
               life itself. As Denise Gigante most recently has argued in <title level="m">Life:
                  Organic Form and Romanticism</title>, a preoccupation with life—in her case,
               understood as organicism, vitality, or nature—binds the poets we typically call
               romantic. For Gigante, the romantics were writers (like the scientists who are their
               contemporaries) “committed to defining and representing the incalculable,
               uncontrollable—often capricious, always ebullient—power of vitality” (3). This is a
               power that the poets also sought to categorize, calculate, and manage, if not through
               new forms of record keeping and sanitation, then through new uses of older tropes and
               figures. In this sense, poetry can be understood as another of the “concrete
               arrangements” or “techniques” of power for the management of life, another site of
               the power over life, like vaccination or the variety of emergent forms of public
               health to which he alludes. This is true both in a thematic and a strategic sense:
               literature of the period takes the power over life as a theme, but it also takes life
               as its object. We would have to look no further than a novel like Mary Shelley’s 1818
                  <title level="m">Frankenstein</title> to find a clear example in which all of
               these senses of life and power emerge. There we find that race, the question of the
               human species, education, the threat to populations, and the emergence of new
               projects in biomedical engineering are construed as analogous to literature itself;
               and literature (formed as a novel, but figured as poetry) emerges as a kind of life.
               Indeed, Shelley famously refers to her literary fiction as a newly formed life, more
               or less substitutable with and even allegorized by the life-form whose existence the
               novel traces. Thus <title level="m">Frankenstein</title> could be read as a vivid
               example of the analogy between what Foucault calls <emph>biopower</emph>
               and literary power—or literature as a form of biopower. Yet, that what is at stake in
               this convergence is a monstrous formation whose full frontal force never can be
               grasped suggests, at least allegorically speaking, the sublime impact—on poetry and
               politics both—of this new power over life.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="1">For
                  further discussion of <title level="m">Frankenstein </title>and biopolitics, see
                  the chapter “Testimony and Trope in <title level="m">Frankenstein</title>” in my
                     <title level="m">Romanticism After Auschwitz</title>. While most examples of
                  lyric life are not concerned with the species, <title level="m"
                     >Frankenstein</title> is a notable exception, as it is precisely man as species
                  and its future that is at issue throughout the novel. Furthermore, other
                  iterations of biopolitics, notably that of Giorgio Agamben, are not focused on the
                  question of species (or human as species), but rather of the human and its
                  political possibility and impossibility. For a discussion of the difference
                  between a power <emph>of</emph> life and a power <emph
                     >over</emph> life, see Roberto Esposito. </note>
            </p>
            <p>One way of understanding this convergence—the more or less simultaneous emergence of
               life as the medium of political <emph>and</emph> poetic power, the
               emergence of biopower <emph>and</emph> romantic poetry—is as an historical
               or terminological <emph>accident</emph>, rather than a series of effects
               with a shared cause. Indeed, the romantic preoccupation with sovereignty (as lyric
               subjectivity) and poetic power as a vital force sits uneasily with Foucault’s account
               of biopower, even as it shares its constitutive terms. The lyric subject, at least as
               it is conventionally characterized, is a resoundingly individual formation, whereas
               biopower, in Foucault’s account, is administrative and neither oriented towards nor
               executed by the individual. Moreover, recent critics of biopower, including Lauren
               Berlant and Eric Santner, also have noted the flawed tendency to correlate the
               variety of conceptions of sovereignty (personal, political, and theological), a
               tendency that the correlation between romanticism and biopolitics could even be said
               to repeat.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="2"> See Berlant, “Slow Death” and
                  Santner, <title level="m">The People’s Two Bodies</title>. For an account of
                  romanticism attuned to the rhetoric of species and at odds with conventional
                  characterizations, see Alastair Hunt, <title level="m">The Rhetoric of Romantic
                     Species</title>. </note>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, following Foucault, we might go further and ask about the conditions that allow
               life at this moment to emerge as an object (both aim and concern) of poetry and
               politics, of lyric subjectivity and political sovereignty? Put another way, we might
               ask whether this is strictly a nineteenth-century formation or rather, a
               late-twentieth-century one articulated in and through a return to the nineteenth
               century texts and contexts that have been called our contemporaries?<note place="foot"
                  resp="editors" n="3"> See Cynthia Chase, Marc Redfield. </note> Does this new
               preoccupation with the power over life simply occur in the nineteenth century as an
               arbiter of modern poetry and politics or is it a retroactive formation framed by two
               competing theoretical gestures belonging to the 1970s and figured through a past that
               it recasts even as it is conditioned by it? Is this the modernity of the
               nineteenth-century or of the late-twentieth century? </p>
            <p>It is the very shape of this temporal knot that has led me, elsewhere, to conceive of
               romanticism as a <title level="m">poetics of survival</title>, that is, as
               preoccupied with and producing a condition of living on, while at the same time
               figuring and instantiating life as beyond or in excess of the opposition between life
               and death. In this essay, I wish to develop my earlier account in a somewhat
               different direction by focusing on the concurrent socio-political and
               rhetorico-lyrical preoccupations with making live. Taking seriously the shifting
               conception of life as the object of politics and poetics in the nineteenth
               century—and the initial articulation of this shift in the 1970s, the years of
               Foucault’s “Society must be defended” lectures, the publication of the first volume
               of his <title level="m">The History of Sexuality</title> [1976], and of Paul de Man’s
               essays “Autobiography as De-Facement” and “Shelley Disfigured” [1979]—I will argue
               that there is a correspondence between biopolitics and romanticism that is captured
               in this shared preoccupation with life, and that it is a conception of poetry and
               politics that is uncontained by the nineteenth century.<note place="foot"
                  resp="editors" n="4">“Uncontained” is Carol Jacobs’ term, see her <title level="m">Uncontainable Romanticism</title>. This point can be read to
                  resonate with one of Agamben’s criticisms of Foucault, that what he identifies as
                  a modern emergence, in fact has an ancient origin. </note> I will also suggest
               that this conjunction becomes an occasion to recognize life as survival, and thus to
               consider something about life that the various demographers and managers who appear
               in Foucault’s texts (and in his only cursorily formulated and digressive account of
               biopower) may not be in a position to perceive or comprehend, but nevertheless
               continue to expose.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="5">See the lecture of 17 March
                  1976, where Foucault apologizes for “this long digression on biopower” (254).
               </note> In other words, far from exhausted by Foucault’s account of biopower and the
               theoretical accounts to which it has given rise, a lyric consideration of life, one
               formulated in and through romanticism trains us to see beyond the management of
               species and populations and to recognize the excesses that biopower and its
               institutions inherently fail to contain. In other words, while it might appear from
               my opening observation that modern poets are managers, belonging to the same category
               as statisticians and public health officials, and that lyric sovereignty, insofar as
               it is focused upon making live, is a mode of administration, several examples suggest
               instead the undoing of individual formations by the very gesture that appears to
               contain it. These lyric examples show that life is always on the side of nonpower,
               and that its containment fails to sustain the newly formulated opposition between
               life and death that is at the heart of the shift that Foucault so compellingly
                  describes.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="6">Foucault is of course aware of
                  this uncontainment, and his example of Franco’s death “and the symbolic values it
                  brings into play” in the lectures on 1975-76 offers one example. <title level="m"
                     >Society Must be Defended</title>, 248. </note>
            </p>
            <p>In what follows, I will turn from Paul de Man’s formative rhetorical account of the
               lyric to Barbara Johnson’s feminist revision of de Man in order to develop my own
               analysis of <emph>biopoetics</emph>. Johnson’s consideration of a subgenre
               of abortion lyric fosters a rethinking of the modern lyric and its rhetorical
               effects, identifying a shift in its organization from aiming to overcome the
               opposition between the living and the nonliving (in other words, “making live”) to
               imagining a relation between mother and child, whether dead or alive, as two
               potentialities. This example is a clear instance of the intersection of poetics and
               politics around the question of life, and one that, like <title level="m"
                  >Frankenstein</title>, dramatizes the encounter between biopolitics and
               romanticism. Moreover, Johnson explicitly shows how lyric apostrophe can be
               understood not only as the trope of politics, but a trope that turns politics into
               biopolitics. From Johnson’s discussion of lyric animation and its political—or as I
               suggest—biopolitical—implications, I turn to a poem by John Clare that offers another
               way of imagining the lyric and its relation to biopolitics. Clare, a poet known as
               much for his lurid biography, his use of local idiom and eccentric grammar, and his
               opposition to the Enclosure Acts that divided his parish, spent a third of his life
               in a mental asylum. By focusing on questions of animation in the context of a lived
               fiction experienced as a pathology, a debilitating delusion that kept Clare from
               living among others, I propose to develop Johnson’s reading of lyric apostrophe into
               a theory that further emphasizes the lyric rhetoric at work in the politics of life
               and making live. </p>
            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>I. A Fetal Address</head>
            
            <p>Despite having written extensively on romantic lifewriting and on Percy Shelley’s <title level="m">The Triumph of Life</title>, Paul de Man seemed to have very little
               interest in the question of life itself. Indeed, life, like death, for de Man is a
               linguistic predicament, and those texts that seem most preoccupied with life (I am
               thinking here of “Autobiography as De-facement” and “Shelley Disfigured”), are not
               simply “about” death or even the undecidability between life and death (recall: “one
               moves, without compromise, from death <emph>or</emph> life to life <emph>and</emph> death [<title level="m">Rhetoric of Romanticism,</title>
               74]), but about figures and figural language. When in his essays of the late-1970s,
               later collected in <title level="m">The Rhetoric of Romanticism</title>, de Man
               apparently turns away from organicist accounts of language (that is, language as a
               vehicle of life), he does so in order to turn our attention to the ideology of
               rhetoric (or literature) as a restorative, indeed indissociably restorative and
               privative, operation. Autobiography (or lifewriting) operates through a figurative
               movement that “deprives and disfigures to the precise extent that it restores.” (And
               returning to the example I introduced above, Mary Shelley’s <title level="m"
                  >Frankenstein</title> recognizes this in all of the scenes where the encounter
               between Victor Frankenstein and his creature, involves a series of faintings and
               restorations.) Although de Man focuses on Wordsworth’s <title level="m">Essays upon
                  Epitaphs</title> and Percy Shelley’s “Triumph of Life,” privation, disfiguration,
               and restoration in his account are not matters of life and death, an assumption that
               would remain within an organicist paradigm, albeit a negative one, but rather matters
               of cognition, apparition, and image. It is sensation, and the relation between the
               visible and the knowable worlds, rather than life and death, that are at the core of
               de Man’s observations. </p>
            <p>For all of these reasons, it might seem antithetical to turn to de Man in an effort
               to track the relation of literature to life and develop a theory of <emph
                  >biopoetics</emph>, unless <emph>biopoetics</emph> is only another name
               for figure, just as it might be another name for romanticism itself. However, despite
               his own apparent allergy to questions of life and his indifference to biological
               processes or political analysis on a grand scale, de Man’s understanding of
               figuration has laid the groundwork for other accounts of lyric figures (apostrophe,
               prosopopoeia) that take place in a more explicit relation to the politics of life,
               namely those of Barbara Johnson. </p>
            <p>In her 1986 essay “Apostrophe, Animation, and Abortion,” Johnson draws upon de Man’s
               account of figure to ask whether “the very essence of a political issue—an issue
               like, say, abortion—hinges on the structure of figure,” and she goes on to wonder if
               there is “any <emph>inherent</emph> connection between figurative language
               and questions of life and death, of who will wield and who will receive violence in a
               given human society?” (<title level="m">World of Difference </title>184). The key
               word here is “inherent.” For figurative language, insofar as it relies upon a
               seemingly infinite capacity for substitution, is driven by the establishment of
               connections where there are none. Figuration is in this sense a matter of the
               non-inherent, or the inherent as mere substitutability. So, to ask about ‘inherence,’
               to consider the possibility of an essential and permanent relation between
               “figurative language” and “questions of life and death,” or to ask whether figure is
               the “hinge” that bears the essence of politics, including the politics of life and
               death, as Johnson does, is to suggest that there can be no politics of life without
               this poetics. Johnson’s task is to understand and track the meaning and shape of this
               poetics. Turning to abortion, Johnson conjoins questions of figure or poetic address
               with what Penelope Deutscher has called “one of the major nodes of biopolitics” (55):
               abortion. Johnson seems to ask, although not in quite so many words, whether
               biopolitics is essentially <emph>biopoetics</emph>. And while she will go
               on to develop her initial consideration of the inherent relation of lyric figures and
               politics into a speculative consideration of motherhood (“there may be a deeper link
               between motherhood and apostrophe” [198]), the theoretical landscape is such that she
               is not yet in a position to reflect directly upon the relation of biopolitics and
               biopoetics. In the mid-80s, when Johnson’s essay is published, Foucault’s various
               discussions of “making live” in the nineteenth century remained overshadowed by his
               much more substantial considerations of governmentality, the body, and its
               discipline. Thus, while Johnson presciently evokes the question of the relation
               between biopolitics and poetics in her discussion of abortion and lyric, it remains a
               question that still bears asking directly—one insinuated but not exhausted by the
               example of abortion and poetry addressed to unborn fetuses. It is also the question,
               I want to suggest, of the lyric itself. In other words, the question for us, as it is
               to a certain extent for Johnson, is how important—how essential or <emph
                  >inherent</emph>—is life for the discussion of literary rhetoric (or poetry), and is
               this matter of life, rather than a programmatic attachment, not only a matter of
               politics, but in fact the political nexus of literature itself? Put another way, the
               question for us is whether life is the poetic nexus of the political? For Johnson,
               insofar as politics is a matter of power and power a matter of violence, the essence
               of any political issue is the question of life and death, of <emph>the
                  power over life and death</emph>. And to suggest that politics “hinges on the
               structure of figure,” as she does here, is also to suggest that it hangs on a
               rhetorical device that <emph>makes</emph> “present, animate, and
               anthropomorphic,” a device that, recalling Foucault’s account of political power,
               makes live. This figure, apostrophe, has a particularly compelling presence in the
               late-eighteenth and early-nineteenth centuries and an afterlife in some unlikely
               places. For example, as Johnson shows, it is at work in the case of abortion, where
               the question of viability may not be altogether new, but it does become newly visible
               and, thanks to new technologies for managing the ends of life—from pills to
               respirators—newly ubiquitous. Now, as anyone even minimally familiar with the
               rhetoric around abortion in the US knows, a central claim on one side of the debate
               is the assumption of fetal life as having an unproblematic relation to human,
               speaking life, indeed of fetal life as rights-bearing life or as personhood. Hence,
               as Catherine Mills recently has shown, the use of 4D sonograms in antiabortion
               materials has as its aim the production of the fetus as a face-bearing entity—and
               person or personage. Here, political and poetic rhetoric, the rhetoric of persuasion
               and the rhetoric of tropes and figures, enter in to a heightened relationship. </p>
            <p>Johnson begins by showing how lyric apostrophes, as acts of animation that assume the
               difference between the living and the dead, turn out to undo the very distinctions
               upon which they seem to rely. Her initial examples, drawn from Baudelaire and Percy
               Bysshe Shelley, relay scenes in which a lyric subject addresses an inanimate object
               in order to endow it with the power that will retroactively animate the very subject
               responsible for the address in the first place. Johnson reads these poems in the
               romantic (and post-romantic) lyric tradition in which a (male) poet undertakes to
               obtain a voice from the outside together with poems (by women) in which “the question
               of animation and anthropomorphism is…given a new and disturbing twist,” poems that
               “textually place aborted children in the spot formerly occupied by all the dead,
               inanimate, or absent entities previously addressed by the lyric” (189). Like
               Foucault, Johnson seems to register a shift in modernity’s relation to sovereignty,
               showing that an emergent structure of animation in the nineteenth century remains at
               the core of political thinking in the late-twentieth-century; and, like Foucault,
               again, she is interested in re-reading and re-casting an earlier emergence (which we
               could in both cases call <emph>biopower</emph>) from the perspective of its
               violent future.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="7">Agamben suggests that Foucault
                  doesn’t do this sufficiently. Also, Penelope Deutscher persuasively considers the
                  reasons why Agamben never takes up the matter of abortion—in part the complexity
                  of analogizing abortion and the Holocaust, an analogy which is the
                  bread-and-butter of the anti-abortion movement and something one would not want to
                  touch. </note> It is in these poems that a new, specifically biomedical
               uncertainty about the nature and meaning of the living and the dead emerges. It is
               also here that Johnson explicitly registers a continuity—or analogy—between poetry
               (the rhetoric of animation) and biopolitics (abortion). </p>
            <p>Johnson begins her exploration of another lyric scene with Gwendolyn Brooks’ “The
               Mother,” a poem that, in her account, traces the disappearance and appearance of the
               first person subject, rendering the lyric subject an object of the abortion itself
               (“Abortions never let <emph>you</emph> forget”); the addressee of aborted
               fetuses (“I have heard in the voices of the wind the voices of my dim killed
               children”); and finally the subject addressing them, albeit through a citation (“I
               have said, Sweets, if I sinned….”). Even as a subject, she remains uncertain about
               their status (“oh what should I say, how is the truth to be said?”) and thus her own.
               Indeed, Brooks’ poem reflects a particularly complex case where in actuality she did
               not want to bring the objects of her address to life even as this animation is what
               occurs when she continues to hear the voices that sound only through her. Thus, as
               Johnson notes, “the poem can no more distinguish between ‘I’ and ‘you’ than it can
               come up with a proper definition of life” (190). This ambivalence about life and
               death is fundamental to the structure of apostrophe, and in this sense it also
               reveals what is at stake in abortion itself. Whatever our politics or rhetoric, from
               the perspective of politics or rhetoric, it is not clear whether a life that is not
               viable (an embryonic life) can be considered a life at all, just as it is not always
               clear whether a life, even if not viable, is anything other than a life. From a
               biopolitical perspective, like the one that Agamben offers at the end of <title
                  level="m">Homo Sacer</title>, the fetus also would emerge as one of those lives in
               which the political and the biological have entered into a domain of indistinction.
               For Agamben, this would be only a particularly vivid example of a quotidian
               situation. The same could be said for Johnson, insofar as this is the structure of
               lyric, a structure upon which “the essence of politics hinges.” Yet, for Johnson, who
               approaches the political scene through poetry and rhetoric, what is at stake is not
               only the indistinction between political life and biological life, but political life
               and poetic (or rhetorical) life. Poetry and rhetoric supplement the place of biology
               so that the question of species, populations, and measure, that is, the objects of
               social science become a question for literary theory and history.</p>
            <p>My point here is not to suggest that Johnson <emph>only</emph> registers
               life or death as a fundamentally linguistic (and hence nonhuman) predicament, as de
               Man does, but to show that her essay raises some highly specific questions about the
               relation of poetry <emph>to</emph> life and death, indeed the power of
               poetry (or language) <emph>over</emph> life and death, when it registers
               the poetic and biological questions of life as thoroughly indissociable. It is in
               this sense that what Agamben refers to as a “zone of indistinction” comes to involve
               poetry and lyric subjectivity; for lyric (or poetic or rhetorical), biological, and
               political notions of life emerge as indistinguishable. While Johnson considers the
               ways that the lyric, as an exemplary form of language, can repeat and re-enact the
               violence it aims to overcome, she also challenges conventional accounts of lyric
               subjectivity as they relate to life itself. Johnson not only argues that debates
               about abortion can be seen as debates about apostrophe and the rhetoric of animation
               and address, but equally that lyric poetry can be seen as part of the abortion
               debates—or construed more generally—debates within the politics of life. She goes so
               far as to suggest (while attributing this suggestion to Brooks’ poem) that “arguments
               for and against abortion are structured through and through by the rhetorical limits
               and possibilities of something akin to apostrophe.” And further that: “The fact that
               apostrophe allows one to animate the inanimate, the dead, or the absent, implies that
               whenever a being is apostrophized, it is thereby automatically animated,
               anthropomorphized, ‘person-ified’. (By the same token, the rhetoric of calling makes
               it difficult to tell the difference between the animate and the inanimate, as anyone
               with a telephone answering machine can attest)” (191). </p>
            <p>For Johnson, this “automatic animation” that occurs within a rhetoric of address
               raises questions about the relation between what Agamben has called life and
               form-of-life. Agamben describes his task as completing and correcting Foucault’s work
               on biopolitics. He insists upon the ancient origins and specifically modern
               tendencies of biopolitics by reminding us that initially two words, <foreign
                  >bios</foreign> and <foreign>zoe</foreign>, were used to designate life, and
               focuses on what he calls “form-of-life,” a life in which it is never possible to
               isolate something such as naked life, by which he means “a life for which what is at
               stake is living itself, in which the single ways, acts, and processes of living are
               never simply <emph>facts</emph> but always and above all <emph
                  >possibilities</emph> of life, always and above all power” (<title level="m"
                  >Means</title> 4). Here, Agamben understands a form of life as separate from
               automation, repetition, habit, or prescription, seeing it rather as possibility or
               potential, a relation to the indeterminate and unprogrammed. Agamben distinguishes
               between this “form-of-life,” a life of reflection, and what is translated
               alternatively as bare or naked life, although even bare or naked life is not simply a
               given, but an assumed category. Yet, when Johnson suggests that arguments about
               abortion (about biological or sacred life) are structured “through and through by
               something akin to apostrophe,” and when she suggests that apostrophe <emph>automatically</emph> animates, which is to say that it is a power over
               life without intentionality, deliberation, or control, she seems to recognize the
               separability or division within life not as something that could be gotten beyond or
               resolved, but as the very structure of life, just as it is so central to language
               fraught between performative and constative powers. The distinction essential to
               Agamben’s insight is not at all essential here. This is the parallel of de Man’s
               understanding of death as a linguistic predicament, for now <emph
                  >life</emph> emerges as a linguistic predicament; and Johnson suggests that “it
               becomes impossible to tell whether language is what gives life or what kills” (192).
               Johnson accounts for language or the lyric subject as displacing sovereignty,
               operating as a power to give or take life itself, rather than a power to kill, as
               under the older, premodern model. Yet, it is not because of this impossibility of
               determining the nature of linguistic power that there is a debate about abortion.
               Rather, what occurs in the sphere of politics shares a structure with—indeed is—a
               linguistic predicament. Johnson reveals that biopolitics, understood as this power
               over life, is indissociable from lyrical language as a power over life. Thus,
               returning to my initial questions concerning the concurrent emergence of biopower and
               romanticism as two nineteenth-century scenes of power as making live, Johnson’s
               simultaneous reading of the romantic lyric and <emph>its</emph> legacies
               with biopower and <emph>its</emph> legacies offers a clear response.
               Johnson’s reading of lyric apostrophe suggests that the poetic and political
               preoccupation with life is not merely an historical accident nor an occasion where
               poetry reflects the politics or culture of the age, but rather that this convergence,
               through Johnson’s reading, reveals the lyrical structure of biopolitics: biopolitics
               as a politics of apostrophe. In this sense, the politics that Johnson identifies
               throughout her essay is an unmarked biopolitics, which is structured like the lyric. </p>
            <p>But Johnson’s essay does not stop here, for it challenges us to consider what happens
               when this is the case, that is, when politics and poetry hinge upon apostrophe and
               when making live becomes the operative mode of poetry and politics both. Johnson not
               only perceives the conjunction of poetics and politics, but also exposes the
               implications of this conjunction on conventional accounts of subjectivity. It is not
               just that abortion poetry offers a particular case, and not only that debates about
               abortion “hinge on a structure akin to apostrophe,” but she goes further to show that
               lyric subjectivity as a variety of subjectivity more generally has hinged upon the
               assumption or production of a life akin to the one ended in an abortion <emph>or</emph> survived in birth. It is this survival that Johnson reminds
               us Baudelaire flaunts when he opens <title level="m">Les Fleurs du Mal</title> by
               representing himself as a failed abortion, as an originary survivor. Johnson’s
               insight, drawn from her reading of Baudelaire, is that something like fetal or
               embryonic life remains the life of the lyric subject—even in its most
               quintessentially sovereign form.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="8">This is a
                  prescient precursor to Agamben’s account of the indistinction between the two
                  figures of exception: the sovereign and so-called bare life. See <title level="m"
                     >Homo Sacer</title>. Also, it is worth noting that Johnson does not distinguish
                  between embryo and fetus, a distinction that is typically linked to gestational
                  age. In this analysis the distinction is not especially meaningful as what remains
                  at stake is viability or the indistinction between living and nonliving which is
                  at issue whether the being is more or less than eight weeks in utero. </note>
               Lyric apostrophe assumes and produces the subject as fetal life. This is true not
               only in poetry like Brooks’ that takes abortion as its theme, but as the reference to
               Baudelaire and more generally to romantic and postromantic lyric poets reveals,
               “fetality,” rather than sovereignty, is the position of the romantic lyric
                  subject.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="9">See Agamben on <foreign
                     >infans</foreign> and infancy. </note> Thus, just as Agamben considers the paradox
               of political sovereignty as positioning the sovereign and the exile in the same
               position of exceptionality <foreign>vis-à-vis</foreign> the law, Johnson, reading Baudelaire and Shelley
               after Brooks and Adrienne Rich, articulates a paradox of lyric sovereignty (which is
               also political sovereignty) as positioning the fetus and the (male) subject in the
               same position of fetality <foreign>vis-à-vis</foreign> apostrophe. </p>
            <p>Penelope Deutscher distinguishes this fetal life from the so-called bare life that
               Agamben associates with biopolitics. For Deutscher, the distinction is a temporal and
               categorical one: the fetus is a scene of contested life prior to loss or privation.
               As she writes: “A consideration of fetal life does not fit the series [Muselmanner,
               overcoma, etc.], as it usually is not situated at the threshold of depoliticization
               or dehumanization of previously politicized or humanized life. The fetus represents
               the zone of contested and intensified political stakes around the threshold between
               what some would consider ‘prelife’ and what is to be identified as nascent human
               life, meaningful human life, and/or rights-bearing life” (58). When Johnson reads
               Baudelaire and Brooks, she identifies poetic life as a zone of fundamentally
               contested viability. Yet the difference between Baudelaire and Brooks, on Johnson’s
               reading, is that whereas lyric life and subjectivity in Baudelaire are issued from
               the position of a failed abortion or fetal life, that of the child, for Brooks and
               Clifton and others it is the position of a mother, albeit one who is not a mother, a
               mother of aborted or miscarried children live only within the space of literature,
               and a mother whose position within that space is at once always assumed and almost
               always denied. </p>
            <p>In concluding the essay, Johnson builds upon this understanding to conceive of lyric
               expression beyond that of the fetus/subject. Spawned by Brooks’ poem as well as other
               poems of the same subgenre by Rich, Anne Sexton, and Lucille Clifton, poems in which
               the subject is figured as a mother who is both addressed by and addresses herself to
               her dead offspring, Johnson suggests that the entire history of the lyric—of poetry
               or politics, insofar as it is bound up with calling, is the repetition of a primal
               apostrophe, the entrance into language and subjection through a demand placed upon
               the mother who is called upon to make the child live. These poems that remember the
               stakes of apostrophe—poems issued in the voices of mothers addressed by children who
               may never have lived—also reveal the structure of apostrophic animation. They suggest
               that the hidden structure of the lyric and its mode of animation resembles and
               depends upon a mother who is almost always unremarked. Johnson seems to suggest that
               were we to recast our prevailing accounts of subjectivity, were we to recognize the
               place of the lyric subject as one not of infinite substitution (“men have in a sense
               always had no choice but to substitute something for the literal process of birth”
               [198]), but rather of unsubstitutability, we might find a path outside that of
               childhood (or masculine subjectivity). This suggests that we might come to recognize
               that the relation of apostrophe to animation is a relation to motherhood itself.<note
                  place="foot" resp="editors" n="10">For another account of the centrality of the
                  mother to romantic subjectivity, see Cathy Caruth, “Past Recognition: Narrative
                  Origins in Wordsworth and Freud.” </note> The risk of unsubstitutability of the
               sort that Johnson describes is not simply the loss of lyric power and the shift from
               a dyadic conception of apostrophic animation (making live) to one that recognizes
               that the lyric subject figured is a fetus is indissociable from a maternal subject.
               It is also one that opens up a space for another subject position: that of the mother
               who does not “make live” or who makes live that which she also has let die, even if
               she may nor have killed.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="11">These formulations
                  evoke Agamben’s account of homo sacer as a life that can be killed but not
                  sacrificed. See Deutscher for a speculative discussion of Agamben’s avoidance of
                  abortion in the <foreign>Homo Sacer</foreign> volumes. </note>
            </p>
            <p>On Johnson’s reading apostrophe emerges as a maternal structure: if the lyric subject
               is conventionally figured as a sovereign, and if rhetorical reading exposes instead
               that it is variously a fetus, embryo, infant, or child, Johnson aims to break the
               fetus-sovereign dyad by recognizing that what has not or cannot be said is that lyric
               animation is akin to motherhood, that we ought to begin to see the lyric subject not
               as a man or a child (which is to say a fetus), but as (or wanting to be) a
                  mother.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="12">Of course, Wordsworth had a strong
                  sense of the lyric subject as child. </note> It is as if our failure to recognize
               the lyric subject as mother has left us with a structure of animation that cannot but
               leave the subject a child whose viability and power is in question.</p>
            <p>Johnson exposes fetal life as the life of lyric subjectivity as we know it. Put
               otherwise, it is this life that she reminds us Baudelaire already recognizes as the
               life of lyric subjectivity when he refers to himself as an abortion manqué. Yet, the
               lyric subject is a fetus only because we do not see it (or him) as a mother. Rather
               than an originary split in life, we have an originary question of viability itself
               (and with it the particularly complex question of rights) at the heart of the
               subject. Rather than operating like other techniques of power over life, and rather
               than a symptom of romantic ideology, for Johnson the lyric is the structure of this
               scene of indissociable power and contestation. While Johnson sets out to revise this
               scene by focusing on the relation of apostrophe to motherhood, in what follows, I
               wish to expand our thinking of apostrophe and viability by considering a poem that
               couples the poetics of life with the history of madness, a poem written by a subject
               who, like Baudelaire, often was figured as a child, and yet whose own lyric
               productions recover not a mother, but an asylum.</p></div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>II. Apostrophe’s Inmate</head>
            
            <p>I opened with the observation that the romantic lyric emerges alongside biopower as
               two forms of a power over life. Reading Johnson, I also considered how politics might
               be seen to “hinge” on the structure of a poetic figure, and further that to recognize
               this structure is to see poetry as assuming a life at the threshold of viability, a
               situation that further conjoins poetry with biopolitics, at least in the version
               articulated by Giorgio Agamben. In this last section I want to consider how this
               conjunction of poetry and biopolitics also leads to a further development in our
               conception of poetry, and how the lyric has a particularly direct relation to the
               shift from sovereignty to biopower. For Johnson the presence of the lyric subject
               indicates the absence of the mother, an absence that Johnson’s account of the lyric
               undertakes to remedy. This recovery of the (theoretical) mother—the establishment a
               position where she can speak and be addressed and the “achieve[ment] of a full
               elaboration of any discursive position other than that of a child”—might go far in
               alleviating certain forms of personal and cultural pathology. But if we were to
               accomplish this would it be the end of the story? While, abortion—its poetry and
               politics - opens up one especially crucial case for thinking about the poetics of
               animation and politics of life, the various forms of social abandonment and
               questionable viability fostered by animating acts, whether in politics or poetry,
               reveal another.</p>
            <p>On December 28, 1841, Clare became an inhabitant of the Northampton General Lunatic
               Asylum, one of the genre of institutions that Foucault identifies with the management
               and restoration of the population.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="13">See Joanna
                  Ball’s discussion of the asylum and its commitment to a “gentle” system of care
                  and Jonathan Bate’s description of the asylum’s “liberal regime” (469). </note>
               Clare wrote extensively while in the asylum, where he went largely unmonitored. While
               much of his poetry of this period (he was there until his death in 1864) has not been
               preserved, an undated apostrophic lyric addressed “To Mary” is one of the hundreds of
               poems that survive. “To Mary” conjoins apostrophe and “lunacy,” exposing an inherent
               failure to arbitrate between the living and the dead or the self and another, as both
               rhetorical effect and medical symptom. It is this disorder that the asylum is called
               upon to manage, but like the lyric, instead sustains.<note place="foot" resp="editors"
                  n="14">On the intake form at the lunatic asylum, Clare’s condition is understood
                  as associated with and preceded by “years addicted to poetical prosing” (qtd in
                  Bate, 466). </note> Thus, if the institutions of biopower are structured like
               apostrophe insofar as they are oriented towards animation or survival, it is
               precisely survival or “making live” that leads to haunting, confusion, and enduring
               symptoms of madness. </p>
            <p>Clare, famous first for being a <emph>poor</emph> poet and later, a <emph>mad</emph> one, archives this radical privation in a poem that
               strangely, even perversely, registers the effects of making live. Like the abortion
               poems that Johnson reads, what we have here is not simply an example of a personal
               intervention or an encounter with the personal as political, but rather a poem that
               bears witness to the lyric and the asylum as two scenes of managing life that both
               house and sustain a form a madness or haunting. In fact, the relation in this case is
               even closer than first meets the eye, for this poem, like all of those that survive
               Clare’s twenty-three year internment, comes to us thanks to its transcription and
               preservation by the asylum’s steward, William Knight. There is no remaining
               manuscript, only a transcript composed in Knight’s hand. “To Mary” is therefore a
               poem whose survival is the effect of the very institution called upon to keep Clare
               alive <emph>and</emph> separate him from the living; it is a poem that
               registers not the work of “madness and civilization,” but of “madness and biopower,”
               and the apostrophic or biopoetic structure of both.</p>
            <p>Whereas Johnson’s reading focuses on the relation between political, biological, and
               poetic life, revealing the limits of the romantic figuration of the lyric subject as
               man-child, in “To Mary,” we encounter romantic animation not from the perspective of
               the mother, but of the lover who (inextricably from his persistent love) is also an
               inmate. “To Mary” is addressed to a girl that Clare loved in childhood, but whose
               father prevented their marriage because of Clare’s low social standing and fate for
                  poverty.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="15">For a psychoanalytic and rare
                  theoretical account of Clare’s love and poetry, see Sigi Jöttkandt, <title
                     level="m">First Love: A Phenomenology of the One</title>. Melbourne: Re-Press,
                  2010. Jöttkandt recalls that Clare believed he was confined in the asylum because
                  of his polygamy. </note> While Clare went on to marry and build a family with
               another woman, Patty Joyce, he remained irremediably attached to Mary, as is evident
               in the journal that he wrote during his escape from his first asylum, which concludes
               with a letter to Mary Clare whom he addresses as “My dear wife.”<note place="foot"
                  resp="editors" n="16">See the “Journey out of Essex” included in <title level="m"
                     >John Clare by Himself</title>, 265. </note> In the journal, Clare explains that
               he is told of Mary’s death, but that he simply does not believe it, complaining that
               “neither could I get any information about her further then the old story of her
               being dead six years ago which might be taken from a bran new old newspaper” (264).
               Clare remains convinced that Mary is alive and often acknowledges that he has two
                  wives.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="17">See the “Asylum Observations” from
                  Northampton, where he writes: “God almighty bless Mary Joyce Clare and her family
                  now and forever – Amen; God almighty bless Martha Turner Clare and her family now
                  and forever – Amen.” In <title level="m">John Clare by Himself</title>, 266.
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>As an apparently conventional love poem, one that assumes and reflects upon the
               communion of a living lover and his dead beloved, “To Mary” evokes tropes of
               remembrance and loss, presence and absence. As a stubborn account of survival—of life
               beyond life and death—it also indicates the poetry and the politics that produces and
               sustains a life perceived to be unfit for society. What we have here is neither a
               scene of the mourning—fulfilled or not—of a maternal poetics (in which we would have
               to include Victor Frankenstein), nor a strictly political exclusion that reveals the
               new politics of public health. Rather, we encounter an apostrophic poetics in which
               making live coincides with a denial of loss, but in which this denial, this insistent
               animation, becomes unmanageable and emerges as a form of lunacy. Here poetry and
               mental illness converge not only through the instruments of lyric, but also the
               instruments of biopower that resemble them. In other words, the symptom and the
               remedy (if not the cure) are both forms of apostrophe. </p>
            <quote><lg>
                  <head>To Mary</head>

                  <l>I sleep with thee, and wake with thee,</l>
                  <l>And yet thou art not there;</l>
                  <l>I fill my arms with thoughts of thee,</l>
                  <l>And press the common air.</l>
                  <l>Thy eyes are gazing upon mine,</l>
                  <l>When thou art out of sight;</l>
                  <l>My lips are always touching thine,</l>
                  <l>At morning, noon, and night.</l>
                  <l>I think and speak of other things</l>
                  <l>To keep my mind at rest:</l>
                  <l>But still to thee my memory clings</l>
                  <l>Like love in woman's breast.</l>
                  <l>I hide it from the world's wide eye, </l>
                  <l>And think and speak contrary;</l>
                  <l>But soft the wind comes from the sky,</l>
                  <l>And whispers tales of Mary.</l>
                  <l>The night wind whispers in my ear,</l>
                  <l>The moon shines in my face;</l>
                  <l>A burden still of chilling fear</l>
                  <l>I find in every place.</l>
                  <l>The breeze is whispering in the bush,</l>
                  <l>And the dews fall from the tree,</l>
                  <l>All sighing on, and will not hush,</l>
                  <l>Some pleasant tales of thee.</l>
               </lg></quote>
            <p>The poem opens with the chilling announcement—directed at its addressee—that while
               the subject sleeps and wakes with Mary, she is not there. The poem candidly
               acknowledges the failure of poetic address to solve the problem of absence or death
               (“and yet thou art not there”), and likewise, the failure of absence or death to
               exhaust direct address and the presence that it remarks and effects (“I sleep with
               thee and wake with thee”). Thus, Mary is at once too resilient and utterly absent. We
               could say that Mary’s presence is the effect of psychosis or delusion, <emph>this</emph> is why Clare is in the asylum, and not just the outcome of
               lyric surmise; and yet we would be hard pressed to rigorously distinguish on the
               basis of this poem, between madness and poetry. In fact this confusion comports with
               Roy Porter’s hesitations about diagnostic readings of Clare, and Porter’s suggestion
               that what we call madness in Clare might not be madness at all, just as it might
               suggest that there is a deeper link between madness and apostrophe than we have
               hitherto suspected.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="18">See the essay collected in
                     <title level="m">John Clare in Context</title>. </note> This becomes a poem of
               madness (rather than passion and allegory) because of its history, because of
               indicators outside of the poem rather than internal to it. Or, put another way, it is
               a poem that reveals the conventions of the lyric to be indistinguishable from those
               markers of mental disorder that are meaningful only outside of poetry, rather than
               within it. However, in a case like Clare’s when the lyric becomes a vehicle for
               autobiography, and indeed in any autobiographical or testimonial text that relies
               upon lyric figures for its narration, what is at stake is not only the non-opposition
               between the living and the dead, but the emergence of that non-opposition as a
               pathology. </p>
            <p>In a second episode, Clare describes an embrace that only can remain imaginary, for
               he fills his arms not with a body, but with “common air,” suggesting that it is both
               quotidian and shared, the stuff of life that signals in this case the absence of the
               living. And in a line that resonates with Wordsworth’s “A Slumber did my spirit
               seal,” admits: “I think and speak of other things/To keep my mind at rest,”
               suggesting that Mary, like Wordsworth’s Lucy, is “a thing,” that is, that she is not
               animate, even as the entire poem is organized around managing the opposite statement.
               Thus, in a third episode Clare is the object of Mary’s gaze, but a gaze that, far
               from direct or reciprocal, occurs only when she is out of sight, which is to say, <emph>always</emph>. The first stanza also concludes with an infinite kiss,
               a gesture whose possibility relies upon its impossibility and the absence of its
               recipient (or otherwise a death that it would deliver). As an exercise in the
               temporal logic of presence and absence, the infinite relation here is presented as an
               impossible one, one that we might also call literary or poetic. In other words, the
               power over life described here occurs only in and through poetry (or delusion): this
               is a life indifferent to certificates of birth and death, statistics, or populations.
               And yet, it is the very condition archived here, the very condition of a virulent
               apostrophe, that leads to the convergence of poetry and politics as two scenes of
               animation, for it is this condition that shapes Clare’s supposed inability to live
               among others and his removal in the name not only of his own survival but theirs as
               well. He is unable or refuses to distinguish between the living and the dead or, put
               another way, he is unable to choose to reside among the living, and by failing to
               choose life, by staying with Mary (or by attaching himself to the dead poets, like
               Shakespeare or Byron, whose poems he will “continue”), Clare registers a poetry in
               which the lyric subject is absorbed by a loss in the dramas of animation. And yet,
               this is precisely what all lyric poems do when they marshal the powers of apostrophe.
               What Clare’s poem then reveals is another scene in the emergence of the poetics of
               animation and the politics of life: a conjunction not only between romanticism and
               madness, but romanticism and the asylum. </p>
            <p>Returning to Clare’s poem, we can further specify its experience of apostrophe. If
               this poem assumes the presence of its addressee, it also breaks the analogy between
               life and presence, absence and death. Moreover, unlike Shelley or Brooks, Clare asks
               nothing of his addressee, he merely describes his relation to her. (The nature of
               this description nevertheless makes it seem a creepy demand.) In a move that seems
               almost to concede, finally, the absence that the act of address rejects, a move that
               also evokes some of the moments of strange concession that occur in Clare’s journals,
               the poem leaves its addressee in a position of utter non-responsiveness, or to recall
               the line I noted above, she becomes a <emph>thing</emph>, the matter of
               this address, rather than its addressee.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="19">For
                  example, in the Journey out of Essex, Clare’s account of his escape from the
                  asylum, he writes describes his entry into his village and a woman jumps out to
                  great him. He decides she’s drunk or mad, and writes: “But when I was told it was
                  my <hi rend="underline">second</hi> wife Patty I got in and was soon at
                  Northborough, but Mary was not there, neither could I get any information about
                  her further other than the old story of her being dead six years ago, which might
                  be taken from a bran new old newspaper printed a dozen years ago, but I took no
                  notice of the blarney having seen her myself about a twelvemonth ago alive and
                  well and as young as ever.” </note>
            </p>
            <p>In the poem, the solution is not to turn <emph>to</emph> the addressee.
               Recalling that other sense of apostrophe or trope as turning away, Clare turns <emph>away</emph> from her (“I think and speak of other things/To keep my
               mind at rest”), whether for his own sanity or out of fear of humiliation.<note
                  place="foot" resp="editors" n="20">In this sense, the poem can be understood not
                  only to use apostrophe, but also to theorize it. </note> Still, the permanent
               presence of the absent lover archived in the first stanza is repeated in the second
               stanza where it is the poet’s memory that remains fixated, even despite the effort to
               turn away. Here, the <emph>subject</emph> becomes the <emph
                  >object</emph> of address, but it is not Mary who speaks or whose voice he hears.
               Rather he hears <emph>of</emph> her through the whispering wind. This is
               the convention of Clare’s contemporaries, Wordsworth and Shelley, but also a
               convention that, as Johnson shows, Brooks reworks by “textually placing aborted
               children in the spot formerly occupied by all the dead, inanimate, or absent entities
               previously addressed by the lyric” (189). Still, what occurs here also differs from
               the address in the other poems, for it is not the addressee who speaks—directly or
               indirectly—through or to the wind; it is not Mary’s voice that Clare hears. Rather,
               the wind speaks to him in its “own” voice <emph>of</emph> Mary (“The night
               wind whispers in my ear…”). This apostrophe does <emph>not</emph> raise
               significant questions about the power to marshal life or death (Shelley) or about the
               sovereignty of the lyric subject as poet or as mother (Brooks), but exposes the
               subject’s impotence and haunting, rather than its ultimate power. It may be that a
               weak or triangulated apostrophe, like this one, an apostrophe that breaks the dyadic
               subjectivism of the conventional lyric reveals another poetics of life. </p>
            <p>Clare reports to Mary that he hears tales told of her. She at once inhabits the
               position of the second and third person, just as he inhabits the first and second
               persons (“All sighing on, and will not hush, / Some pleasant tales of thee”). The
               tales are also the return of what the subject attempts to repress or conceal,
               figuring yet another scene of ineffectivity. Much as he tries to say something else,
               the tale of Mary can be displaced, but not extinguished; he can voice it or hear it,
               but cannot abandon—or be abandoned by—it. Put another way, the third stanza seems to
               describe a scene that might be one of revelation—that might expose the ghostliness
               and disturbance of this relation, as if he finally were to learn the truth of her
               absence and the mistake of his assumption of her presence. However, what is revealed
               here is instead another form of haunting. Still related to Mary, it is not she, only
               stories of her; her life and voice are now displaced onto the nightscape. In a turn
               that already begins at the end of the second stanza (“But soft, the wind comes from
               the sky,/And whispers tales of Mary”), by the third stanza, the world has become
               animated once more in a speaking scene that occludes the beloved. Mary’s absence is
               replaced by the “whispering” and “sighing” of tales, what Sigi Jöttkandt calls
               Clare’s “mary-ing” of the world.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="21"> First Love
                  119.</note> While the poem initiates with a lyric address, by the end, the subject
               becomes the addressee, and the addressee, far from disappearing, has become an
               object. While this is the case in “Ode to the West Wind” and “The Mother,” here we
               are left to ask who is addressing the subject? In this case we have not a mirroring,
               a reciprocal animation, or even a crossing of lyric and maternal animation. Rather,
               when Clare thinks and speaks “of other things,” when he turns from his beloved to the
               landscape, he finds not that he has turned away, but the very resilience of this
               passionate attachment. Yet who is attached to whom and how do we decipher a scene in
               which hyperanimation has riven subject and object, person and place both? </p>
            <p>It is this excessive animation that leaves Clare writing from the asylum, and it is
               this mode of apostrophe that, like Johnson’s account of apostrophe in abortion
               poetry, and for that matter, de Man’s account of death (and life) as a linguistic
               predicament leads us to rethink the relation of lyric to life, apostrophe to
               sovereignty, for it is anything but sovereignty that apostrophe in this instance
               seems to wield. Yet, the risk of this non-sovereignty is that it remains tied to new
               institutions in which the nourishment of life and violence against the living are
               conjoined. The lunatic asylum is just one of these examples. It is the asylum that
               protects Clare from society, preserves his poetry, transcribes and archives it, and
               yet that also keeps him from seeing his family for over twenty years (from his
               commitment until his death). If this poem bears witness to a poetics of life that
               breaks with the dyadic model, it also can be seen to proliferate it, for when Clare
               describes the lyric subject as the object of address he may already, proleptically be
               describing a structure of reception in which his own voice becomes a “whisper” and in
               which is own poem comes to us in a double form, borne by a writer who is ultimately
               not the poet, and another listener who may or may not be its addressee: William
               Knight.</p>
            <p>Johnson’s reading of Brooks after Shelley and Baudelaire allows us to witness anew
               the lyric structure of sovereignty—and to see in the place of the lyric subject,
               perceived as sovereign (Mill) or as mute (de Man) before her, a subject whose very
               viability is in question. My reading of Clare proposes another iteration of lyric
               subjectivity as it relates to life. The poem seems to rely upon another dyad; no
               longer mother (living)/child (dead) nor poet (living)/breeze (nonliving); but rather
               a more familiar encounter between the lover and beloved. Yet here, the dyad, while
               utterly intense dissipates into a scene in which <emph>nothing</emph> and
               no one can be fully recovered. Here, uncertain viability is shared between the poet
               and addressee; just as the power of over life is shared between the poet, his
               steward, and the whispering breeze. This whispering also returns us to the question
               of life. It leads not only to poetic fame or posthumous life (as in the case of
               Shelley or Wordsworth), but also to what Joao Biehl has called “social abandonment”
               or actual incarceration, to a life lived in the asylum. Indeed, behind the relation
               of lover and beloved, here, there is the relation of inmate and asylum. The inmate
               who suffers from a confusion of voices, a loss of his actual loved ones, not only his
               fictional lover, and the disappearance of his manuscript. Yet, a typescript and a
               place in the archive replace the absent manuscript, a freedom of mobility and
               protection from worry and poverty substitute for the loss of family and obligation.
               If these substitutions are forms of “making live” they also bear the structure of an
               apostrophe, like the one in “To Mary,” that sustains, rather than remedies a malady. </p>
            <p>What kind of power of or over life is the lyric? Thanks to de Man and Johnson, we
               have seen how this power can be alternatively, even simultaneously restorative and
               privative, how it can refigure or transfigure the subject exposing the question of
               her very viability. Yet with Clare we see how lyric sovereignty dissipates into
               voices everywhere, and how the question of poetic power intersects with that of
               biopower, with the rise of the Victorian asylum that became this poet’s place. In
               other words, developing Agamben’s account of the structure of <foreign>homo
                  sacer</foreign> into a poetic claim, we also see how sovereignty and abandonment share
               a rhetoric; how the lyric is one manifestation of this rhetoric; and how, at least in
               this case, independent of an originary fissure in the meaning of life we have instead
               the birth of biopoetics, not a literary biopolitics or a biopolitics of literature,
               but a lyric thinking life itself. </p></div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
               <head>Coda</head>
            
            <p>In 1999, Brett Cooke and Frederick Turner published a collection of essays entitled
                  <title level="m">Biopoetics: Evolutionary Explorations in the Arts</title>. In an
               introductory essay, “Biopoetics: The New Synthesis,” Cooke outlines the theory of
               sociobiology (or evolutionary psychology) upon which the essays collected in the
               volume rely, and suggests that the aim of biopoetics is to “seek artistic universals
               and features that reflect our common humanity” (5). In establishing the term <emph>biopoetics</emph>, he explains: “I propose that we add the prefix
               ‘bio’ to the Aristotelian root ‘poetics,’ a word which describes the science of at
               least one art—there is no English term for the study of <emph>all</emph>
               the arts. Derived from the Greek word for making, ‘poetic’ also refers to our impulse
               to create beauty. We then nominate the term ‘biopoetics’” (6). Here, biopoetics is a
               name for the evolutionary account of aesthetics. This <emph
                  >biopoetics</emph>, while in no way evoking <emph>biopolitics</emph>, as
               elaborated by Foucault, Agamben, and others, nevertheless shares with these
               approaches a focus on new scenes of scientific method. For <emph
                  >biopoetics</emph>, in this sense, it is a matter of using scientific method to
               understand the emergence of art as a living thing; for <emph
                  >biopolitics</emph>, in the sense offered by Foucault, it is matter of recognizing
               how the sciences of demography and public health, among others, obtain a new power
               over life and the living. Yet, the example of another, critical biopoetics, which
               this essay has sought to isolate, begins to tell another story, one attuned to a
               rhetoric of figure and to the question of literature’s power over life. By taking
               seriously the relation of lyric animation to the politics of life, we discover the
               example, not only of a haunting that poetry fails to manage (Johnson, Brooks), but
               also a mode of subjectivity at the threshold of viability and survival. For Clare,
               this is manifest as delusion and madness, as the failure to distinguish between what
               is living and dead and the emergence of the poetic subject not merely as madman, but
               as psychiatric object. If biopoetics in this sense returns us to Foucault’s
               biopolitics, then, it does so by exposing a new humanistic method. This is the
               inverse of the biopoetics formulated by Turner and Cooke. For rather than dismissing
               literary criticism and theory—whether in the name of natural or social scientific
               method—it reaffirms literary criticism’s uncanny ability to say something about life. </p>
            <p>When E.O. Wilson, on the jacket of Cooke and Turner’s <title level="m"
                  >Biopoetics</title>, writes that he can see the methods proposed there “taking
               over from deconstruction by 2010, and permanently,” he advocates a methodological
               turn away from the linguistic and other turns that have marked humanistic method
               since the 1970s. As 2010 draws toward a close, the prediction seems not to have borne
               out. It is time therefore that we begin to recognize another biopoetics. Not the
               biopoetics of evolutionary arts, but of the conjunction of rhetorical and
               biopolitical reading. This biopoetics sets out, as this essay set out, by admitting
               two scenes of making live, and it concludes by exposing the impossibility of a
               politics of life or a science of literature that would be free from poetics.</p></div>
        
         <div type="citations">
            <head>Works Cited</head>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Agamben, Giorgio</author>
                     <title level="m">Means Without Ends: Notes on Politics</title>
                     <editor role="translator">Binetti, Vincenzo</editor>
                     <editor role="translator">Casarino, Cesare</editor>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Minneapolis</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>U of Minnesota P</publisher>
                        <date>2000</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author>Ball, Joanna</author>
                     <title level="a">'The Tear Drops on the Book I Read': John Clare's Reading in
                        the Northampton General Lunatic Asylum, 1841-1864</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">Wordsworth Circle</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol">34.3</biblScope>
                        <date>Summer 2003</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">155-58</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Bate, Jonathan</author>
                     <title level="m">John Clare: A Biography</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>FSG</publisher>
                        <date>2003</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Caruth, Cathy</author>
                     <title level="m">Empirical Truths and Critical Fictions: Locke, Wordsworth,
                        Kant, Freud</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Johns Hopkins UP</publisher>
                        <date>1991</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Chase, Cynthia</author>
                     <title level="m">Romanticism</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Essex</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Longman</publisher>
                        <date>1992</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Clare, John</author>
                     <title level="m">John Clare by Himself.</title>
                     <editor role="editor">Robinson, Eric</editor>
                     <editor role="editor">Powell, David</editor>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Manchester</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Carcanet</publisher>
                        <date>1996</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Clare, John</author>
                     <title level="m">The Later Poems of John Clare 1837-1864</title>
                     <editor role="editor">Robinson, Eric</editor>
                     <editor role="editor">Powell, David</editor>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                        <date>1984</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Cooke, Brett</author>
                     <author>Frederick Turner</author>
                     <title level="m">Biopoetics: Evolutionary Explorations in the Arts</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>St Paul, MN</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Paragon House</publisher>
                        <date>1999</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author>Culler, Jonathan</author>
                     <title level="a">Apostrophe</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="m">The Pursuit of Signs: Semiotics, Literature,
                        Deconstruction</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Ithaca, NY</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Cornell UP</publisher>
                        <date>2002</date>
                        <date>135-54</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>De Man, Paul</author>
                     <title level="m">The Rhetoric of Romanticism</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Columbia UP</publisher>
                        <date>1984</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Derrida, Jacques</author>
                     <title level="m">The Beast and the Sovereign. </title>
                     <editor>Lisse, Michel</editor>
                     <editor role="editor">Mallet, Marie-Louise</editor>
                     <editor role="editor">Michaud, Ginette</editor>
                     <editor role="translator">Geoffrey Bennington</editor>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>U of Chicago P</publisher>
                        <date>2009</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author>Deutscher, Penelope</author>
                     <title level="a">The Inversion of Exceptionality: Foucault, Agamben, and
                        'Reproductive Rights'</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">South Atlantic Quarterly</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol">107.1</biblScope>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">55-70</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Foucault, Michel</author>
                     <title level="m">History of Sexuality</title>
                     <editor role="translator">Robert Hurley</editor>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Vintage</publisher>
                        <date>1980</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Foucault, Michel</author>
                     <title level="m">'Society Must be Defended': Lectures at the Collège de France:
                        1975-1976</title>
                     <editor role="editor">Bertani, Mauro</editor>
                     <editor role="editor">Fontana, Alessandro</editor>
                     <editor role="translator">David Macey</editor>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Picador</publisher>
                        <date>1997</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Gigante, Denise</author>
                     <title level="m">Life: Organic Form and Romanticism</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New Haven</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Yale UP</publisher>
                        <date>2009</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Haughton, Hugh</author>
                     <author>Phillips, Adam</author>
                     <author>Summerfield, Geoffrey</author>
                     <title level="m">John Clare in Context</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                        <date>1994</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Jacobs, Carol</author>
                     <title level="m">Uncontainable Romanticism: Shelley, Brontë, Kleist</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Johns Hopkins UP</publisher>
                        <date>1989</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author>Johnson, Barbara</author>
                     <title level="a">Apostrophe, Animation, and Abortion</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="m">World of Difference</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Johns Hopkins UP</publisher>
                        <date>1987</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">184-99</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Jöttkandt, Sigi</author>
                     <title level="m">First Love: A Phenomenology of the One</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Melbourne</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Re-Press</publisher>
                        <date>2010</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Redfield, Marc</author>
                     <title level="m">The Politics of Aesthetics: Nationalism, Gender,
                        Romanticism</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Stanford UP</publisher>
                        <date>2003</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>


         </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
