<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Robert Bloomfield: The Inestimable Blessing of Letters</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
				<editor role="editor">John Goodridge</editor>
				<editor role="editor">Bridget Keegan</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
					<name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>abstracts</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
					Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p rend="noCount">Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be
						downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
						unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching,
						and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
						amended.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on
						Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only
						in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as
						expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in
						any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors
						and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization
						should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
					<p rend="noCount">By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the
						following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p rend="noCount">Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in
						order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that
						of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
						elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
						resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the
						only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of
						course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our
						conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Abstracts</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Robert Bloomfield: The Inestimable Blessing of
							Letters</title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
								Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2011-08-01">November 1, 2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p rend="noCount">All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for
						"," for ", ' for ', and ' for '.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p rend="noCount">Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been
						typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p rend="noCount">Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been
						indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p rend="noCount">&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound
						sign</p>
					<p rend="noCount">All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces,
						etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
					12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
						on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Mike Quilligan</name>
				<date>2010-06-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="paratext">
				<head>Abstracts</head>
				<p rend="noCount"><quote rend="center"><ref target="#GoodridgeAbstract">John
							Goodridge and Bridget Keegan</ref> | <ref target="#FulfordAbstract">Tim
							Fulford</ref> | <ref target="#DenneyAbstract">Peter Denney</ref> | <ref
							target="#HaywoodAbstract">Ian Haywood</ref> | <ref
							target="#KeeganAbstract">Bridget Keegan</ref></quote></p>

				<!-- Authors, titles, and abstracts here -->
				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="GoodridgeAbstract"/>John Goodridge and
							Bridget Keegan</hi>, <title level="a">Introduction</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">This introduction argues for the importance of a scholarly consideration of Robert Bloomfield's interesting and extensive correspondence. It then offers a brief overview of the four essays including in this special number.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.goodridge-keegan.html">go to
							essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="FulfordAbstract"/>Tim Fulford</hi>, <title
							level="a">Bloomfield in his Letters: The Social World of a London
							Shoemaker Turned Suffolk Poet</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">This essay places Bloomfield in his social world—the world of
						Georgian London and of rural Suffolk and Wales. It makes extensive use of
						his correspondence to offer new insights into such issues as patronage and
						publishing, the book market, radical politics, Cockney London, and the
						picturesque tour. It shows Bloomfield to be a witty commentator on his time
						as well as an astute reader of the poetry of his contemporaries.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.fulford.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="DenneyAbstract"/>Peter Denney</hi>, <title
							level="a">The Talk of the Tap-Room: Bloomfield, Politics and Popular
							Culture</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">This article takes as its point of departure Bloomfield’s
						repeated and insistent claim that he was a poet, not a politician. Drawing
						on the fascinating recently published correspondence of Bloomfield and his
						circle, it examines how the dissociation of poetry and politics in the
						post-revolutionary decades affected the poet’s public and private
						identities. In the first instance, the article explores how the ideology of
						natural genius exerted pressure on Bloomfield and other laboring-class poets
						to think about poetry as a cultural form that was incompatible with the
						public sphere of politics, especially the combative world of artisan
						radicalism. But the article also shows that the polarization of political
						culture in the aftermath of the French Revolution debate had the effect of
						politicizing even the most private aspects of Bloomfield’s life and literary
						productions. Much to the poet’s profound vexation, his public persona was
						appropriated by radicals, liberals, and loyalists alike, depriving him of
						the privacy the theory of natural genius assumed he should embrace.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.denney.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="HaywoodAbstract"/>Ian Haywood</hi>, <title
							level="a">The Infection of Robert Bloomfield: Terrorising <title
								level="m">The Farmer's Boy</title></title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">This article argues that Robert Bloomfield’s seminal text
							<title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> is a much darker and more
						troubled poem than has been appreciated. Although recent criticism has begun
						to explore some of the poem’s ideological complexities, there is still a
						prevailing tendency to locate its imaginative resources and strengths in its
						depiction of a lost pastoral world of rural English labor. Haywood aims to
						break out of this pastoralist mold by reading the poem as a
						psycho-biographical allegory of Bloomfield’s unresolved feelings about
						separation, loss, social mobility, patronage, and success. By intensifying
						and magnifying the more violent conventions of the georgic, Bloomfield
						converts the poem into what John Barrell (writing about De Quincey) calls
						“narratives of trauma and narratives of reparation” (22). The pain, terror,
						and guilt of these “narratives” reflect not only Bloomfield’s troubled
						poetical formation but also capture the counter-revolutionary paranoia and
						repression of the late 1790s. Although Haywood's interpretation uses the
						text to speculate about Bloomfield’s memories of his early life, his
						conclusions are supported by copious illustrations and supportive evidence
						from Bloomfield’s letters. </p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.haywood.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="KeeganAbstract"/>Bridget Keegan</hi>,
							<title level="a">Bloomfield's Writing for Children</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">Robert Bloomfield twice wrote works explicitly for a juvenile
						audience. <title level="m">Little Davy’s New Hat</title> was first published
						in 1815 and went through three separate editions by 1824. <title level="m"
							>The Bird and Insects’ Post Office,</title> which Bloomfield was writing
						with his son Charles at the time of his death, was published posthumously in
						his <title level="m">Remains</title> (1824). With these texts, Bloomfield
						tried his hand at what was, in the early nineteenth century, a relatively
						new genre. In addressing a juvenile audience, Bloomfield joined some of the
						most important authors of the age. A re-examination of the works for
						children demonstrates how Bloomfield fully participates in his Romantic
						cultural moment. While differing in style and in audience, these two texts
						are also very much of a piece with Bloomfield’s other core moral and
						artistic concerns. Although celebrating Bloomfield’s children’s books could
						be seen as inviting the risk of once again relegating Bloomfield to the
						status of naïf—a writer capable only of simple works and observations
						because of his laboring-class background—if we understand them in relation
						to the rest of Bloomfield’s achievements they appear less anomalous and less
						simplistic. Both works are unafraid to contend with life’s harsher realities
						even as they perform the typical moral function of children’s literature and
						extol the virtues of charity and kindness to the poor and to animals. </p>
					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.keegan.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
