<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Robert Bloomfield: The Inestimable Blessing of Letters</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">The Talk of the Tap-Room: Bloomfield, Politics, and Popular
               Culture</title>
            <author>
               <name>Peter Denney</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">John Goodridge</editor>
            <editor role="editor">Bridget Keegan</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.denney</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2010-11-01">March 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">The Talk of the Tap-Room: Bloomfield, Politics, and
                     Popular Culture</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Peter</forename>
                        <surname>Denney</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Robert Bloomfield: The Inestimable Blessing of Letters</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-03-01">March 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#226;&#8364;&#339;,"
                  for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
            <keywords scheme="http://www.rc.umd.edu/#tags">
               <list>
                  <item>Robert Bloomfield's letters document one artist’s struggles (and sometimes
                     his victories) to share his unique voice and vision; the online publication of
                     his extant letters (a companion to this collection of essays) reveals new and
                     exciting insights into Bloomfield the artist and the man. The essays included
                     in this collection highlight and draw attention to aspects of Bloomfield's
                     literary production that would likely not be possible without the full access
                     to his letters that the edition provides, and make a strong case for why
                     Bloomfield continues to be worthy of study. They suggest how much more remains
                     to be said about this prolific poet. </item>
                  <item>Robert Bloomfield</item>
                  <item>pastoral</item>
                  <item>labouring-class poetry</item>
                  <item>rural labour</item>
                  <item>psychopathology</item>
                  <item>shoemaker</item>
                  <item>London</item>
                  <item>Honiton</item>
                  <item>Capel Lofft</item>
                  <item>James Thomson</item>
                  <item>The Seasons</item>
                  <item>Romantic poetry</item>
                  <item>literary biography</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>Michael Quilligan</name>
            <date>2010-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>
               <title level="a">The Talk of the Tap-Room: Bloomfield, Politics, and Popular
                  Culture</title>
            </head>

            <byline><docAuthor>Peter Denney</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>Griffith University</affiliation></byline>
            <div type="section">
               <head> </head>
               <p>The tendency to associate the value of a particular literary work with the
                  personal probity of its author had characterized the polite reception of
                  laboring-class poetry ever since Oxford professor Joseph Spence wrote his
                  influential account of Stephen Duck in the early eighteenth century. Emphasizing
                  his industriousness, contentment, and piety, Spence praised the way that Duck
                  displayed “so many Merits, and so much Humility join’d together,” evincing, for
                  example, a preference for the religious and moral writings of Addison rather than
                  the low burlesques of street literature (27). From Stephen Duck to John Clare, the
                  laboring-class poet was expected by the polite to conform to a model of exemplary
                  private virtue, diligent, dutiful, and suitably distanced from what were perceived
                  to be the vulgar elements of collective plebeian life.<note n="1" place="foot"
                     resp="author">For the polite reception of plebeian poetry in these terms, see
                     Christmas 48-49.</note> But this image acquired a new urgency with the growth
                  of popular radicalism in the late eighteenth century, and especially amidst the
                  counter-revolutionary climate that witnessed, with the publication of <title
                     level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> in 1800, the transformation of Robert
                  Bloomfield from anonymous shoemaker to literary celebrity. </p>
               <p>Indeed, shortly after Bloomfield’s death in 1823, the editor of his <title
                     level="m">Remains</title>, his friend Joseph Weston, sought to establish the
                  poet’s posthumous reputation by commending not only the excellence of his verse,
                  but also the spotlessness of his character. And it was precisely to counter
                  damaging rumors concerning his allegedly irregular religious beliefs, at a time
                  when such beliefs were regarded as potential accessories of insurrection, that
                  Weston set about to defend the poet’s personal morality. “The virtues . . . of
                  this excellent man,” proclaimed Weston, “did not protect him from the shafts of
                  calumny; on a point too, which . . . must have wounded his sensitive heart, for it
                  chilled the affection of his earliest friends. The world will learn with
                  astonishment, that Bloomfield has been traduced on the subject of religion!—Robert
                  Bloomfield!—whose life was one pure and gentle stream of overflowing kindness;—in
                  whose meek and quiet spirit there was ‘<emph>indeed</emph> no guile;’ whose
                  conversations and writings were ever filled with incentives to piety” (1: xx-xxi). </p>
               <p>As several contributors to this issue point out, among those friends most troubled
                  by rumors of Bloomfield’s dangerous religious and political views was T. J. Lloyd
                  Baker. In a series of letters of 1821, Lloyd Baker demanded that the poet, then
                  experiencing severe poverty and ill health, clarify his beliefs for the peace of
                  mind of his supporters. The letters implied that Bloomfield’s wife’s devotion to
                  the provincial servant-prophetess, Joanna Southcott, had somehow rubbed off on the
                  poet, leading him to forgo church attendance, as if religious heterodoxy were a
                  natural stepping stone to infidelity. Worse still, Lloyd Baker had heard rumors
                  that Bloomfield had got into the habit of reading radical periodical publications,
                  which aimed to overthrow the established government. And from these “two
                  circumstances,” Lloyd Baker concluded, “the idea” had spread that Bloomfield had
                  “imbibed Deistical &amp; Republican principles”—beliefs “frequently united in the
                  same persons” (letter 351, 23 May 1821). Such rumors had apparently led many of
                  Bloomfield’s polite friends—and it was only the friendship of the affluent that
                  Lloyd Baker thought it was worthwhile preserving—to withdraw their support,
                  respect, and financial aid. But although professing to write with the intention of
                  restoring the goodwill of his polite friends, this was conditional on an
                  appropriately conservative response, and Lloyd Baker later conceded that it would
                  be “highly wrong in any person . . . to associate with, &amp; to give countenance
                  to a man” desirous of undermining the “Church or Government of this country”
                  (letter 353, 29 May 1821). Understandably, Bloomfield was offended by the letter,
                  not least because none of these supposed friends were presently providing any
                  financial assistance whatsoever. He was also clearly incensed at the assumption
                  that his personal life was the proper object of surveillance by people of a
                  superior social class, a feeling that had plagued him throughout his literary
                  career, whether he was regarded as a “curiosity” or, as in this instance, a
                  “dangerous man” (letter 351). But perhaps what infuriated Bloomfield most of all
                  was the fact that the letters forced him to compromise his independence by
                  explicating his views on two subjects, religion and politics, which, in the year
                  he first entered the polite literary scene, he had resolved not to discuss either
                  in his intimate letters or in his public writings.</p>
               <p>This essay takes as its point of departure Bloomfield’s repeated and strenuous
                  claim in his correspondence that he saw himself as a poet, not a politician. It
                  should be stressed that this was a position Bloomfield maintained to people of all
                  political persuasions: radical, liberal, and conservative. As he wrote in 1804 to
                  the bookseller, poet and republican, Thomas Clio Rickman, “I . . . have four years
                  past made a determination to be nutral in Politicks and Religion . . . <emph>I
                     must and will</emph> be as <emph>private</emph> a Man as pastoral poetry will
                  permit me to be, or subjects that involve not creeds and systems of which all the
                  world knows I have had small means of judging” (letter 129, 29 May 1804). Such a
                  comment apparently endorsed the age-old dictum that those engaged in manual work
                  did not possess the leisure necessary for formulating accurate political
                  judgments, an idea endlessly repeated in loyalist propaganda from the 1790s
                  onward. “How can we expect to receive pure instruction,” asked one clergyman, “if
                  we . . . draw our notions of national policy from the lips of a labourer or
                  mechanic?” (Hurdis 41). But Bloomfield had a deep respect for the intellectual
                  capacity of rural and urban workers, and he was contemptuous of the tendency of
                  the rich and polite to denigrate the experiences, expressions, and aspirations of
                  laboring people. “I have heard more sense and truth in a tap-room, than I have
                  sometimes heard in better company; and there is nothing more striking to me . . .
                  than that <emph>total</emph> ignorance of the <emph>manner of living</emph> among
                  the poor . . . of what they talk, and of what they think! Nothing to me has
                  appeared more strange or more disgusting, than finding amongst those ranks, raised
                  above the mechanic and labourer, such a mean opinion of the poor!” (<title
                     level="m">Remains</title> 2: 71-72). Furthermore, as this comment attests,
                  Bloomfield did express strong beliefs on a range of social and economic questions,
                  though these did not fit neatly into the polarized political culture
                  characteristic of the post-revolutionary period. </p>
               <p>All this seems to support the view that Bloomfield pandered to the conservative
                  impulses of the polite reading public by disingenuously representing himself as an
                  exclusively pastoral poet, as unconcerned with political subjects as the rural
                  laboring people he idealized in his poetry (Sales 18-22). And it is true that
                  throughout Bloomfield’s career, both detractors and sympathizers often described
                  him simply as “the Farmer’s Boy.” For William Hazlitt, for example, this
                  appellation aptly reflected the fact that “his Muse has something not only rustic,
                  but menial in her aspect . . . Bloomfield never gets beyond his own experience;
                  and that is somewhat confined” (145). But Bloomfield’s poetry has recently been
                  shown to disclose a complex engagement with contemporary political debate, drawing
                  eclectically on the wide variety of radical discourses to which he had been
                  exposed during his long association with urban artisan culture (Christmas 27-48;
                  White 10-25, 132-42). Even so, the distinction Bloomfield made between poetry and
                  politics deserves to be taken seriously, for his correspondence reveals this to be
                  more than just a marketing ploy, and it sheds much light on the difficulties faced
                  by plebeian autodidacts during this era of political agitation and reaction. While
                  for obvious reasons this particular laboring-class poet clearly felt more
                  comfortable commenting on political subjects in his private letters than in his
                  literary publications, it is of enormous interest, I think, that his letters
                  nevertheless communicate a general desire to find in poetry a space apart from
                  divisive political debate, even when it might have been safe to admit
                  otherwise.</p>
               <p>Before examining these issues, it is important to recall that the concept of
                  natural genius flourished in polite society at the same time as the political
                  horizons of plebeians were broadening, a development initiated by the Wilkes
                  affair and then massively escalated by the British response to the French
                     Revolution.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="author">For an unrivalled account of
                     this long view of the development of popular radicalism, see Clark
                     141-57.</note> The rehabilitation of Shakespeare and the cult of Ossian,
                  together with a new degree of emphasis on the primitivism of “peasant” poetry, all
                  occurred against a background of polite anxiety about the increasing political
                  activity of laboring people. In the 1770s, for example, the author of <title
                     level="m">The Minstrel</title> lamented that “All ranks are run mad with
                  politics”; and Elizabeth Montagu—patron of plebeian poetry and author of an
                  important essay on original genius—despaired that “Treason was talked in every
                  Alehouse, and sung in every street” (Forbes 1: 158; Blunt 2: 76). Unlike these
                  debating, ballad-singing plebeian patriots, the embodiment of original genius was
                  imagined as a quiet individual, whose strong sensibility and powerful imagination
                  ideally found succor in domestic and natural spaces, away from the tumult of
                  collective popular leisure or public political action. To quote one aesthetician,
                  such a person conceived poetry as a “sanctuary from which the noise and folly of
                  mankind are excluded,” a “refuge from the numerous perplexities of human life”
                  (Duff 363). In this context, given that every laboring-class poet had to identify
                  as a natural genius in order to satisfy polite taste, secure patronage, and
                  therefore get into print, this theory provided a potential vehicle for drawing
                  upwardly aspiring artisans away from the expanding sphere of popular radicalism.
                  The significance of this is reinforced by the fact that not only did many plebeian
                  reformers have literary aspirations, but, besides politics, poetry was the primary
                  means by which artisans could satisfy their intellectual ambitions.<note n="3"
                     place="foot" resp="author">Perhaps the most intriguing example of the literary
                     aspirations of plebeian political activists is the case of the London
                     Corresponding Society member Richard “Citizen” Lee, as described by Mee
                     151-66.</note> Well before the shoemaker Allen Davenport embarked on his career
                  as a Spencean and Chartist radical, for example, he was fantasizing about cutting
                  a figure in the world of literature, seeking to climb “Mount Parnassus” and
                  envisioning himself as a “little rustic bard” (5).</p>
               <p>To a large extent, Bloomfield genuinely embraced the idea of natural genius and
                  gained much confidence from its privileging of feeling, inspiration, and
                  simplicity over learning and artifice. Plebeian autodidacts characteristically
                  experienced great discouragement in their literary endeavors as they confronted
                  the aesthetic standards and other invisible boundaries that had formerly policed
                  access to polite culture. As Davenport wrote, reading the poetry of Pope operated
                  to all but “extinguish every spark of my poetic genius. I felt ashamed of my own,
                  as I now thought, wretched doggerel” (15-16). Likewise, in the year before
                  Bloomfield would be buoyed up by the overwhelmingly positive reception of his
                  first published poem, he remarked of the supreme arbiter of neoclassical taste
                  that “Dr. Johnson . . . is a ‘Thwackum’ amongst criticks; I allways look at him
                  and his abilities with a mixture of reverence and anger” (letter 16, 8 September -
                  6 October 1799). This anger was at least partly informed by Bloomfield’s rejection
                  of the assumption that the republic of letters was the exclusive preserve of
                  classically educated men of leisure, a notion evidenced by Johnson’s condescending
                  dismissal of an earlier shoemaker poet James Woodhouse: “better . . . furnish the
                  man with good implements for his trade, than raise subscriptions for his poems. He
                  may make an excellent shoemaker, but can never make a good poet” (Boswell
                  444).</p>
               <p>By contrast, while Wordsworth had in some measure simply placed the authority of
                  men of leisure on a different footing, Bloomfield was greatly encouraged by the
                  polite Romantic poet’s attempt “to come near,” if not actually speak, “the
                  language of Men” (letter 94, 2 September 1804). After reading <title level="m"
                     >Lyrical Ballads</title> in 1801, he wrote excitedly to his brother, George,
                  “if there is no poetry in them I will give up my pretension to feeling and Nature.
                  I can trust you I think to be struck with them, first with the extreem simplicity,
                  and then for what I before mentioned, NATURE” (letter 52, 19 April 1801). The
                  potentially leveling implications of this conception of poetry were not lost on
                  Bloomfield, and, in his first address to the public, his preface to <title
                     level="m">Rural Tales</title>, he declared “I feel peculiarly gratified in
                  finding that a poor man in England may assert the dignity of Virtue, and speak of
                  the imperishable beauties of Nature, and be heard, and heard, perhaps, with
                  greater attention for his being poor” (iv). In this sense, Bloomfield found the
                  theory of natural genius immensely attractive, for it popularized an aesthetic
                  which enabled him to circumvent at least some of the obstacles to polite literary
                  culture.</p>
               <p>But if the idea of natural genius permitted plebeian poets to enter the republic
                  of letters, it did so under terms that emphatically excluded their participation
                  in the public sphere of politics. In an early issue of the official journal of the
                  London Corresponding Society, a contributor argued that it was “once the
                  distinguished office of poetry to awaken and cherish [the] heroic virtues,” before
                  suggesting that, like liberty, such a function no longer prevailed in the present
                  “degenerate age” (<title level="j">Moral and Political Magazine</title> 1 [1796]:
                  26). And one of the aims of the journal was to reclaim for an artisan occupational
                  group the public purpose of poetry against what was perceived to be its
                  increasingly private range of concerns. For most commentators, however, the
                  qualities attributed to the natural genius—enthusiasm, imagination, simplicity,
                  sensibility, impetuosity, and wildness—remained a source of enormous value in the
                  context of poetic production. It was just that these qualities were conceived as
                  thoroughly incompatible with the more overtly rational skills thought necessary
                  for effective participation in political debate (Barrell 11-13). </p>
               <p>Most famously, in a critique of the sentimental language of Edmund Burke, Mary
                  Wollstonecraft asserted that the natural genius was a figure too impulsive and too
                  controlled by the imagination to qualify for citizenship. Although Wollstonecraft
                  admired the “genuine enthusiasm of genius,” she consigned it to the “infancy of
                  civilization” for, in modern Britain, liberty was possible precisely because
                  “reason” had clipped the “wing of fancy” and the “youth” had become a “man” (28).
                  Small wonder, then, that Thomas Paine decided to pursue a course of self-education
                  in natural and social philosophy, noting that “I had some turn . . . for poetry;
                  but this I rather repressed than encouraged, as leading too much into the field of
                  imagination” (49). Nor is it surprising that John Thelwall would justify his
                  literary endeavors to a reading public still largely hostile to his former career
                  as a radical orator on the grounds that his proven failure in politics would mean
                  probable success in poetry. With a heavy dose of irony, Thelwall announced that
                  “since he has proved so bad a politician as to plunge himself and his family in
                  ruin . . . it ought to be regarded as an argument <foreign>a priori</foreign> in
                  favour of his poetical talent: that species of imprudence . . . having always been
                  considered as a distinguishing characteristic of those whom Apollo and the Muse
                  inspire” (xliv). To put it simply, what were thought to be assets in poetry
                  acquired a largely pejorative connotation when carried over to the sphere of
                  politics. This was particularly true for the prototypical plebeian poet, who was
                  routinely represented as a child of nature, a figure unassisted by civilization,
                  and therefore implicitly deficient in such mature, masculine attributes as reason,
                  self-command, and foresight.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="author">For an
                     excellent analysis of the way in which the “Child of Nature” trope restricted
                     the autonomy and authority of laboring-class poets, see Richardson
                     247-59.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Accordingly, the <title level="j">British Critic</title> began its review of
                  Bloomfield’s second publication, <title level="m">Rural Tales</title>, with an
                  acknowledgement that the periodical’s focus had shifted from a serious to a
                  trivial, if still gratifying, subject. “We are pleasingly called away from our
                  abstruser studies, by these productions of a genuine Child of Nature”; and the
                  review concluded by praising this “original genius” as the “genuine inspiration of
                  a mind, whose thoughts and feelings turn naturally to poetry” (<title level="j"
                     >British Critic</title> 19 [1802]: 338). Similarly infantilizing was the
                  conclusion of another critic that “if we behold in Thomson an elegant scholar
                  adorning the simple beauties of nature from the stores of a cultivated mind, we
                  see in Robert Bloomfield, a simple farmer’s boy, painting such scenes as no poet
                  need be ashamed” (Anderson 3: 391). The implication is that a laborer could be a
                  poet but not a poet and a scholar, a distinction which ensured that laboring-class
                  poetry was regarded as a relatively superficial, even childish, pursuit, permitted
                  to please but not to please and instruct. As Charles Lamb very bluntly put it, “I
                  have had the felicity of hearing George Dyer read out one book of ‘The Farmer’s
                  Boy.’ I thought it rather childish. No doubt there is originality in it . . . but
                  no <emph>selection</emph>” (1: 162).</p>
               <p>Bloomfield was surprised at receiving such a positive response from the
                  conservative press, primarily because his patron, Capel Lofft, was a prominent
                  radical figure and a member of the polite reform association, the Society for
                  Constitutional Information. In fact, Lofft had used the preface to <title
                     level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> to express a number of political views, much
                  to the poet’s frustration. In a letter to his brother George, Bloomfield wrote of
                  the <title level="j">British Critic</title> and the <title level="j">Anti-Jacobin
                     Review</title> in the context of their admiration for <title level="m">Rural
                     Tales</title>, “they are <emph>avowd</emph> partizans on the side of existing
                  Systems, and existing abuses, and . . . I may think <emph>myself</emph> well off
                  to have escaped their lash” (letter 83, 3 May 1802). But the representation of the
                  plebeian poet as a natural genius found a congenial home in conservative culture,
                  undoubtedly because it enabled a talented and aspiring laborer to be celebrated
                  for possessing qualities which disqualified him from participating in the public
                  realm of politics. </p>
               <p>In its review of <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title>, for example, the
                     <title level="j">British Critic</title> drew from the preface of the poem to
                  emphasize the fact that Bloomfield had conscientiously avoided a “combination
                  among . . . journeymen shoemakers,” projecting an image of a sensitive individual,
                  opposed to collective artisan activity (15 [1800]: 602). Yet, like most shoemaker
                  poets, Bloomfield remained proud of his artisan heritage, and he greatly admired
                  the socialized forms of knowledge generated in the workshop, an environment which
                  played a formative role in nurturing his intellectual and poetic endeavors.<note
                     n="5" place="foot" resp="author">The public orientation of much shoemaker
                     poetry, along with its expression of craft pride, often defied the model of
                     natural genius, as revealed by Keegan 195-217.</note> “In our trade,” he wrote,
                  “when any one reads the newspapers or a book, by the neighbourly custom of sitting
                  all in one room . . . we have nothing to do, but to discuss the subject.
                     <emph>Community</emph>, is perhaps the point, to which those who say that
                  ‘shoemakers are politicians,’ might trace the solution of their wonder” (<title
                     level="m">Remains</title> 2: 91-92). Equally significant, he added, this custom
                  not only fostered the acquisition of political knowledge, but also intellectual
                  reflection of all sorts, again underscoring his belief in the dignity of the “talk
                  of the tap-room.” If the <title level="j">British Critic</title> sought to
                  distance Bloomfield from what was perceived as a vulgar and dangerous artisan
                  milieu, however, it simultaneously denied his ability to join the ranks of the
                  polite and to write poetry of a public or political character. “The writer’s
                  observations will not be found to have been very extensive . . . and he appears to
                  have attended to many minute circumstances, which would probably have escaped a
                  loftier mind” (<title level="j">British Critic</title> 15 [1800]: 602). Similarly,
                  the poem had “various errors and defects,” as if to confirm that Bloomfield
                  possessed genius, but not the authoritative rationality of the man of taste;
                  nevertheless, such blemishes, the review suggested, were outweighed by the
                  expression of “poetical feeling” and “warm and vigorous imagination,” with the
                  accompanying implication that <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> should be
                  read for its sentimental rather than its intellectual content (<title level="j"
                     >British Critic</title> 15 [1800]: 601). And this appeal to sensibility enabled
                  the <title level="j">British Critic</title> to subsequently disregard as an
                  irrelevance those “melancholy” “reflections” on the harvest home, which indicated
                  that the “author [had] received some impressions, probably at the
                  debating-society, of a questionable kind” (15 [1800]: 604).</p>
               <p>But the idea of natural genius could also serve a decidedly radical purpose, and
                  George Dyer, for one, claimed to delight in those very “questionable” reflections
                  on the harvest home, which did, indeed, highlight the injustice and degeneracy of
                  contemporary society.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="author">This is not
                     surprising, given that Dyer had recently written a pamphlet, frequently quoted
                     in the plebeian radical press, which listed many of the same developments that
                     Bloomfield identified in the harvest home passage as causes of the oppression
                     of the poor: “the reduction of small farms . . . the extravagant appearance and
                     profits of farmers” and “the extravagancies and luxuries of individuals”
                     (103).</note> A friend of Wordsworth, Dyer combined the identities of poet and
                  political activist during the 1790s, publishing several radical pamphlets and
                  actively participating in the democratic reform movement.<note n="7" place="foot"
                     resp="author">For an account of Dyer’s literary and political activities and
                     preoccupations during the 1790s, see Roe 19-42.</note> Through Capel Lofft, he
                  met and became friends with Bloomfield, whom he introduced into his polite
                  literary circles in the early 1800s. Of <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title>,
                  Dyer described in a letter to Lofft how “it recalled to my mind those ages and
                  those countries in which the Poet and the Shepherd were more naturally united . .
                  . . Your Shepherd’s Boy with the poetical character that he undoubtedly possesses,
                  requires indeed no other name; poetry is more immediately the language of nature .
                  . . I can truly say I have been charmed with his Seasons, and that my heart echoes
                  back every thing said by you in the preface” (letter 51, 19 April 1801). This
                  conception of poetry as a literary form that had been debased by the advance of
                  commercial refinement constituted a cultural version of the age-old condemnation
                  of luxury, which became a staple of radical argument in the post-revolutionary
                  period. To quote Thelwall, “let us . . . labour to abolish luxury. . . . Let us .
                  . . persuade mankind to discard those tinsel ornaments and ridiculous
                  superfluities, which enfeeble our minds, and entail voluptuous diseases on the
                  affluent, while diseases of a more calamitous description overwhelm the oppressed
                  orders of society from the scarcity resulting from this extravagance” (Claeys 67).
                  In the process of increasing social inequality, so the logic ran, luxury corrupted
                  the taste of the polite, leading to the predominance of a form of literature
                  governed by the shallow imperatives of fashion. But if the theory of natural
                  genius could be hitched to a radical political argument, Dyer implicitly imagined
                  its embodiment, Bloomfield, as a pre-political subject, a “Shepherd’s Boy,” as
                  deficient in the mature, masculine virtue of reason as he was free from the
                  modern, feminine vice of sensuality.</p>
               <p>And yet the image of the natural genius was also invoked in radical polemic as a
                  herald of revolutionary ardor, whose lack of exposure to polite learning and other
                  sorts of cultural refinement provided the basis for an authentic critique of the
                  subservience of the literary establishment to an aristocratic political system. In
                  an untitled poem he contributed to the <title level="j">Moral and Political
                     Magazine</title>, for example, Dyer proclaimed that the “poet’s untaught lays”
                  were essential to the extension of “Justice,” part of a “purer song” of “Freedom”
                  which served “Virtue’s cause” (1 [1796]: 95). The iconic figure in this respect,
                  of course, was Burns. Indeed, the “ploughboy poet” was celebrated in the same
                  magazine as an oppressed genius, whose neglect exemplified the prejudice of polite
                  culture and its associated refusal to encourage talent in and diffuse knowledge
                  among laboring people (<title level="j">Moral and Political Magazine</title> 2
                  [1797]: 48).<note n="8" place="foot" resp="author">For the contradictory image of
                     Burns in radical culture, see Janowitz 67-69.</note> But such an argument was
                  even more fraught with ambivalence. For it focused on the talent of the
                  “untaught,” “primitive” poet in order to justify an enlightenment belief in the
                  need to advance the improvement of laboring people, through the provision of
                  polite forms of knowledge no less than the support of plebeian varieties of
                  self-education, from reading groups to political associations.</p>
               <p>In the biography of Bloomfield, written by his brother, George, and included in
                  the preface to <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title>, it was noted that the
                  poet’s literary ambitions were fostered by a range of cultural institutions
                  available to artisan men in late eighteenth-century London, including newspapers,
                  periodicals, dissenting meeting houses, and debating societies.<note n="9"
                     place="foot" resp="author">For some reflections on the kind of ideas Bloomfield
                     encountered in these institutions, see Lucas 58-61.</note> But in a footnote,
                  Lofft glossed the present state of one of these institutions after the passing of
                  the Gagging Acts in the mid-1790s: “It is another of the Constitutional
                  Refinements of these times to have fettered, and as to every valuable purpose,
                  silenced, these Debating Societies. They were at least, to say the lowest of them,
                  far better amusements than drunkenness, gambling, or fighting. They were no
                  useless Schools to some of our very celebrated Speakers at the Bar and in
                  Parliament; and, what is of infinitely more importance, they contributed to the
                  diffusion of Political Knowledge and Public Sentiment” (Bloomfield, <title
                     level="m">Farmer’s Boy</title> vii). In this way, Bloomfield was held up by
                  Lofft to support the radical and liberal notion that the present climate of
                  surveillance and censorship threatened to stifle the moral and intellectual
                  improvement of laboring people, thereby leading to the growth of those brutish,
                  vulgar pastimes which had long been considered by individuals of all political
                  persuasions to be a lamentable hallmark of plebeian culture.</p>
               <p>On the issues of refinement, poetic liberty, and popular education, Bloomfield
                  clearly shared many of these radical views, though he maintained a far less
                  censorious attitude to the demotic culture of laboring people. He certainly
                  welcomed at least some of the effects of the French Revolution and subscribed to
                  the principle that the freedom of the press was a vital index of liberty,
                  presently under assault by the government. “I still think that the general system
                  of instruction, and the downfall of the feudal rights of families, with the
                  present religious toleration &amp;c are fruits of the revolution not to be
                  despised” he wrote to George, his most trusted correspondent during the early
                  stages of his career; and he then added “I should like to gossip with you face to
                  face . . . particularly on the subject of englands boast ‘the liberty of the
                  press’” (letter 133, 10 June 1804).<note n="10" place="foot" resp="author">Of
                     course, the notion of the freedom of the press as the “palladium of British
                     liberty” had a manifold range of political alignments and uses, as examined by
                     Keen 25-75.</note> But Bloomfield was a pragmatist rather than an ideologue,
                  neither embracing a utopian or party political program nor envisioning the reform
                  of parliament as the primary solution to social and economic injustice. </p>
               <p>Something of his general outlook may be indicated by his letter to the minor poet,
                  Samuel Jackson Pratt. In Pratt’s protest poem <title level="m">Bread</title>, the
                  poverty that became so controversial during the famine years of 1795-1796 and
                  1800-1801 was represented not simply as the result of a series of bad harvests,
                  but as the consequence of an array of unjust human developments, including
                  enclosure, monopolization, the deregulation of the grain trade, and the
                  introduction of the gentleman farmer, leaving the poor “robb’d of each right that
                  God bestows on man” (14). After receiving an adulatory letter and copy of the poem
                  from Pratt, Bloomfield replied: <quote>Your letter and your Poem on so great and
                     so interesting a subject as <title level="a">Bread,</title> came to hand last
                     week. Highly flattering as such marks of respect must be to me, and much as
                     they may demand my best acknowledgements, the pleasure of seeing the Cottager
                     vindicated is more grateful still. To see one class of the community grow
                     immensely rich at the expence of an other, to me allways argued an inefficiency
                     in the Laws of this or any country where it happens. If as Goldsmith says, we
                     are hastning to the rottenness of refinement, and if such things cannot be
                     avoided, I see no just reason for starving and contemning the Labourers of the
                     Vinyard, or for keeping from them such degrees of information as they may be
                     capable of receiving . . . . You, Sir, go much deeper into the subject than I
                     am able to follow you; I could never satisfy myself, that, increase of
                     population and increase of individual comforts are not enemys and strangers to
                     each other. (letter 87, 28 May 1802)</quote> Such a position did not fit
                  comfortably within the dividing lines of contemporary political debate. Most
                  obviously, it combined the Malthusian notion that a growing population inevitably
                  led to a rise in inequality with the rough agrarian egalitarianism of Goldsmith,
                  which was based on the contrary belief that a large, increasing rural population
                  was absolutely essential to the health of the nation. To some extent, this was
                  characteristic of the way Bloomfield, perhaps drawing on his artisan heritage,
                  felt confident to assert an independence of viewpoint on social and economic
                  questions, even to people of a superior class. As he wrote to his mother, “Don’t
                  be alarm’d for my safety I am no politician . . . I am my own master yet, and mean
                  to remain so” (letter 42, 3 November 1800).</p>
               <p>But the reference to Goldsmith is particularly revealing in light of Bloomfield’s
                  claim that the discussion of political issues was inappropriate in pastoral
                  poetry. For not only did <title level="m">The Deserted Village</title> directly
                  address such subjects, but Goldsmith’s poem became thoroughly politicized during
                  the 1790s and beyond, giving expression to the grievances of rural and urban
                  workers alike. Accordingly, it was extracted in a number of radical plebeian
                  periodicals, from <title level="j">Pig’s Meat</title> (1 [1795]: 33-36) to the
                     <title level="j">Moral and Political Magazine</title> (1 [1796]: 320), as well
                  as in later pamphlets on the condition of the rural laboring poor. In fact, in
                  1807, the author of one of these pamphlets argued, as Bloomfield everywhere
                  implied in his poetry, that a terrible decline in the condition of the rural
                  laboring poor had occurred “within the last half century,” and that, as a
                  consequence, rural leisure practices had to be respected and agricultural wages
                  had to be raised: “let the Peasant’s labour have its due” (Brewer 6, 14). On the
                  other hand, Bloomfield’s friend, the Devonshire poet, William Holloway, published
                  an anti-pastoral poem, <title level="m">The Peasants Fate</title>, in 1802, which
                  was lambasted in the conservative press, in part for borrowing its imagery and
                  subject matter from <title level="m">The Deserted Village</title>. To quote the
                     <title level="j">British Critic</title>, just as the author was “full of
                  particular discontent and <emph>universal benevolence</emph>,” so the poem lacked
                  feeling, failing to “raise it above flatness” (19 [1802]: 533-34). As evident in
                  an 1802 letter, Bloomfield followed the reviews of Holloway’s poetry, so he would
                  almost certainly have known that his friend was given short shrift for being one
                  of those writers who “profess to illuminate as well as to delight the public by
                  their poetical productions; and who think that questions of statistical and
                  political œconomy can be advantageously discussed in a series of descriptive
                  couplets” (<title level="j">Monthly Review</title> 40 [1803]: 98).<note n="11"
                     place="foot" resp="author">The reviewer ridiculed the basic premise of <title
                        level="m">The Peasants Fate</title>, as described in the poem’s preface:
                     “The drift of this little attempt is principally designed, (without adverting
                     to political argument,) to shadow forth the evils arising to the peasantry of
                     this country, from the system of engrossing small farms, and driving the
                     hereditary occupiers to the necessity of embracing a maritime or military life
                     for support, or being reduced to the most abject state of dependence, and
                     submitting to the galling hardship of becoming <emph>servants</emph> on the
                     spot where they once had been <emph>masters</emph>” (Holloway vi-vii). These
                     were also “evils” which Bloomfield criticized, directly or indirectly, in his
                     poetry and correspondence.</note> Paradoxically, therefore, while Bloomfield’s
                  political opinions were informed by his reading of the poetry of rural complaint,
                  he must have become acutely aware that he was writing at a time when pastoral
                  poetry had been reclassified as an index of personal feeling, even as it was being
                  increasingly politicized.</p>
               <p>Bloomfield was conscious of the fact that, particularly given his laboring-class
                  status, his poetry would be expected to have a purely private function. In his
                  first attempt to get <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> published, he wrote
                  to an unidentified bookseller that he intended the manuscript simply as an attempt
                  to put the “little events of my boyage into metre” and to present the result as a
                  gift to his mother (letter 6, before 21 June 1798). And this was reiterated by
                  Lofft in his preface to the first published version of the poem, to show that the
                  “Author, with a spirit amiable at all times,” was motivated by “duty and
                  affection” rather than “Fame or Advantage” (Bloomfield, <title level="m">Farmer’s
                     Boy</title> xvi). But Lofft seemed to ascribe to the older view of poetry as a
                  suitable arena for addressing public issues, though he may well have had
                  reservations about a laboring-class poet claiming to instruct, as well as to
                  please, people of higher social standing. After Bloomfield had repeatedly
                  requested his patron to remove or relocate some footnotes and other paratextual
                  comments from future publications, for example, Lofft resorted to the language of
                  class privilege, “renouncing . . . all future correspondence &amp; conversation
                  with a clown who would so forget himself to me” (letter 197, 16 November 1806). </p>
               <p>The quarrel began when Bloomfield, under pressure from acquaintances in the London
                  publishing scene, sought Lofft’s permission to omit from future editions some
                  radical remarks concerning the suppression of newspapers and debating societies.
                  “In his notes respecting Newspapers and Debating societies,” the poet later wrote
                  of his patron, “he had originally written and pertinaciously retained a downright
                  attack upon Government. . . . I still wish it was not there, for, I am not a
                  politician, nor never shall be” (letter 198, 19 November 1806).<note n="12"
                     place="foot" resp="author">Bloomfield had also included a political gloss on
                     the harvest home passage in <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> in the
                     form of a paratextual quotation from the work of the naturalist on Cook’s
                     second voyage to the Pacific, which comprised a denunciation of luxury, with
                     distinct leveling connotations. But this was before, he declared, “I had
                     considered the consequence of introducing even the appearance of politics into
                     a Rural production (let my own private notions be what they may)” (letter 62,
                     29 October 1801).</note> For Bloomfield, however, the key principle at stake
                  was that such political remarks would take away from his work’s poetical
                  character. As he first explained to Lofft, without apparently pretending “to
                  dictate,” there was “a very general, if not universal opinion, that political
                  thoughts and references (however just in themselves) ought not to be seen . . .
                  where rural poetry only should be found” (letter 63, before 31 October 1801). Of
                  course, Bloomfield did write about rural subjects such as cruelty to animals in
                  ways which carried quite specific political connotations, as several critics have
                  recently identified (Christmas 27-48; White 10-25). But whatever he actually
                  believed about the relationship between politics and rural poetry, he was clearly
                  conscious that polite taste was predicated on the incompatibility of these two
                  discourses. At the same time, Bloomfield was also troubled by the fact that, in
                  the present climate of political polarization, Lofft’s radical sentiments would
                  inevitably cause controversy, alienating a large section of his polite readership.
                  In addition, he could hardly have failed to be incensed by the way in which the
                  polite political reformer was using his poem to demonstrate his credentials as a
                  disinterested citizen, while silencing the demands of his plebeian protégé. And in
                  this context, Bloomfield was quite right to think that the best method for
                  maintaining his cherished sense of independence was to avoid the topic of politics
                  altogether.</p>
               <p>Indeed, Bloomfield’s worst fear was realized in dramatic fashion in 1802 when the
                  prominent conservative politician William Windham cited the preface of <title
                     level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> in parliament during a debate on the
                  Bull-Baiting Act. The speech was part of an attack on the movement to reform the
                  manners of the poor; and to this end, Windham recited the descriptions of
                  Bloomfield reading newspapers and attending debating societies, together with
                  Lofft’s radical remarks on these subjects, to illustrate the malign effects of
                  promoting the intellectual pursuits of laboring people. More specifically, he
                  maintained that giving the “lower orders a character of greater seriousness and
                  gravity” by restricting “what were termed idle sports and useless amusements”
                  fertilized the growth of Jacobinism and Methodism, political radicalism, and
                  religious enthusiasm (<title level="m">Parliamentary History</title> 36 [1820]:
                  833). Needless to say, after reading an account of the speech, Bloomfield was
                  angry at having been used as a pawn in a political conflict he had hoped to avoid,
                  which amply confirmed his prediction that “some publick notice would be taken of
                  Mr. Lofft’s reflections in the prefatory part of the Farmer’s Boy. The lot has
                  fallen to Mr. W” (letter 88, 30 May 1802).</p>
               <p>But Bloomfield was even more enraged by Windham’s denigration of the intellectual
                  capacity of the laboring poor. Of the former Secretary at War, he communicated to
                  his brother “I think the poor people of England have very little cause to thank
                  him for his compliment on the score of their capabilities and pursuits. We might
                  as well be totally without minds, for he seems to doubt the propriety of exerting
                  them, or of making an <emph>inward</emph> store of pleasure for ourselves. So much
                  of this speech is the most unadulterated aristocracy that I have ever heard”; and
                  with characteristic wit, he then inquired “where is the wisdom of saying that the
                  little sons of a little Taylor should amuse themselves with <emph>athletic
                     exercises</emph>? If we happen to think a moral page a better object to admire
                  than the frizzled forehead of a bull, and like the ascending of a lark in
                  preference to the mounting of a bull-dog, what has Mr. W to do with it?” (letter
                  88). This distinction between inward pleasure and collective leisure seems to
                  suggest that Bloomfield saw himself as a model of self-improvement, whose literary
                  talents and endeavors elevated him above his fellow artisans and laborers. Yet,
                  even though Bloomfield demonstrated an ambivalent attitude to popular
                     culture,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="author">See, for example, letter 199:
                     “I cannot help observing the great difference between an illdresst and a
                     well-dresst mob, and I must indeed be unfeeling and ungenerous to acknowledge
                     it. In our National Theatres I have often sided so far with the Patricians as
                     to wish the Plebeans at the Devel, not because they were such, (that I leave to
                     those who are weak enough, that is, proud enough,) but merely because they
                     would not be quiet.”</note> he did not generally hold a pejorative view of
                  plebeian habits and recreations or sanction the polite movement to reform or
                  abolish the customs of laboring people.</p>
               <p>In fact, Bloomfield conceived at least some of his poetry as an attempt to resist
                  this movement. Announcing his intention to avoid the “seriousness of a preacher,”
                  for example, he described his third publication, <title level="m">Wild
                     Flowers</title>, as a collection of “more . . . mirth . . . than many who know
                  me would expect, or than the severe will be inclined to approve” (x-xi). For
                  Windham, of course, the promotion of robust, manly pastimes and festivities was an
                  unabashed mode of social control, aimed at securing the contentment of the
                  laboring poor.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="author">To some extent, Windham’s
                     perception of laboring people as an army in reserve might well have added to
                     Bloomfield’s anger. For he expressed frequent opposition to war and, in 1803,
                     when an upsurge in chauvinism witnessed even radicals support the war with
                     France, he strongly criticized the mobilization of the militia: “The measures
                     persued by Government are such as to cause here the greatest consternation and
                     alarm. Great numbers are entering as Vollunteers without knowing I doubt, what
                     they have to trust to, or what will be their privilidges. . . . As to real
                     invasion we deem it less threatening than an appeal to the exercise of rights
                     by those of our own land. . . . I detest, I had allmost said scorn the
                     profession of Soldier” (letter 112, 31 July-[2 August] 1803).</note> In
                  response, Bloomfield wrote “the <emph>common people</emph> of his native country,
                  are a rough set no doubt, but I dislike the doctrine of keeping them in their
                  dirt. . . . how can we consistently praise the inestimable blessing of letters and
                  not wish to extend it? Or why should the great and the wealthy confine the
                  probable production of intellectual excellence to their own class, and exclude, by
                  withholding the polish, all that might amongst the poor by nature be intended to
                  be Newtons and Lockes?” (letter 88). And yet, as evident in his last poem, <title
                     level="m">May Day with the Muses</title>, this progressive commitment to
                  democratizing the republic of letters, to spreading the “<emph>Empire of the
                     Mind</emph>,” as he called it, could and did coexist with a belief in the
                  dignity of the culture of laboring people.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="author"
                     >For an illuminating analysis of <title level="m">May Day with the
                        Muses</title> in these terms, see White 121-46.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Given these views, it is perhaps surprising that William Cobbett, who also
                  respected the intellectual abilities and recreational customs of the laboring
                  poor, would later condemn Bloomfield for turning conservative and writing against
                  the interests of his class of origin. The accusation came in the course of an
                  attempt to show that the virtues and talents formerly used to justify the
                  political authority of the patrician class were now only manifest in the populace,
                  with the result being that laborers had both the right and capacity to govern
                  themselves. Cobbett began by asserting that he was “willing to trust to the
                  talent, the justice and loyalty of the great mass of the people, and especially
                  that part of them, who raise the food, the raiment and the buildings, and who
                  fight the battles”; but he then cautioned that the “cause of the people has been
                  betrayed by hundreds of men . . . whom a love of ease and of the indulgence of
                  empty vanity have seduced into the service of bribing usurpers”; and among those
                  men he listed Bloomfield, “the Farmer’s-Boy author” who, so it was claimed, had
                  been “taken <emph>in tow</emph>, and pensioned for fear he should write for the
                  people” (<title level="j">Political Register</title> 34 [1819]: 980-81). The
                  allegation was remarkable not only for being untrue, but because Bloomfield had
                  largely made good on his resolution to avoid taking an explicit political position
                  in any of his public writings. To add insult to injury, Cobbett again pilloried
                  Bloomfield in a later work, arguing that if the poet “had placed no reliance on
                  the faithless Muses, his unfortunate . . . family would . . . have not been in a
                  state to solicit relief from charity. I remember that this loyal shoemaker was
                  flattered to the skies, and (ominous sign, if he had understood it) feasted at the
                  tables of some of the great. Have, I beseech you, no hope of this sort; and, if
                  you find it creeping towards your heart, drive it instantly away as the mortal foe
                  of your independence and your peace” (43-44). The assumption here was that to
                  participate in any form of polite culture, particularly one such as poetry which
                  privileged imagination over fact, was inevitably to weaken the resolve, distort
                  the mind, and so endorse the progress of refinement, with all its attendant evils
                  of luxury, corruption, and social inequality.<note n="16" place="foot"
                     resp="author">For Cobbett’s privileging of fact over imagination, along with
                     his associated skepticism of polite culture, see Whale 141-47.</note> For
                  Cobbett, then, any decision Bloomfield might have made not to include politics in
                  his poetry was irrelevant, since poetic production was itself destructive of
                  political integrity, of industriousness, utility, and fairness. </p>
               <p>To some extent, poetry did offer an attractive alternative to politics for many
                  plebeian autodidacts. In particular, it provided opportunities for personal
                  expression which enabled the laboring-class poet to feel a sense of freedom,
                  however partially or briefly, from the restraints on individual thought and
                  conduct characteristic of many areas of collective plebeian life, including, of
                  course, political organization. Perhaps this was why John Clare, who, like
                  Bloomfield, had strong political views, distrusted Cobbett for being a
                  propagandist with “no principles” and argued against “party matters” and the
                  “reform of mobs,” while claiming “I am no politician” (<title level="m"
                     >Letters</title> 560). And though Clare, again like Bloomfield, revered rural
                  popular culture, his solitary ways and literary ambitions were derided by his
                  neighbors, leading him to contend that “Scandal and Fame are cheaply purchased in
                  a Village the first is a nimble tongud gossip and the latter a credoulous and
                  ready believer who . . . believd any thing” (<title level="m">By Himself</title>
                  78). Bloomfield similarly felt that his literary celebrity alienated him from the
                  community at Shefford, and, when T. J. Lloyd Baker forced the poet to declare his
                  political hand amidst rumors of his dangerous radicalism, he denounced the
                  “slander” that circulated in “this vile little town” (letter 352, 25 May
                  1821).</p>
               <p>But Bloomfield also had the disadvantage of writing in the three decades after the
                  French Revolution, when virtually every aspect of culture had become highly
                  politicized. Throughout his career, his work and public image were appropriated to
                  serve a political cause by people of a radical as well as a conservative
                  persuasion, and this must have reinforced the poet’s sense that politics was
                  utterly incompatible with the independence he so much wanted to preserve.
                  According to Bloomfield, even his fleeting encounters and birthplace were
                  scrutinized for their political implications. As he expressed to Lloyd Baker in a
                  brilliant attempt to highlight the unreasonableness, intrusiveness, and even
                  pettiness of his correspondent’s demands, not only had he kept company with
                  bastions of conservatism and radicalism alike, the Bishops Watson and Porteous no
                  less than the survivors of the treason trials, the polite reformer John Horne
                  Tooke and the plebeian dissident Thomas Hardy, but he had the “misfortune to be
                  born only six miles from the birthplace of Tom Paine!” (letter 354, 31 May-1 June
                  1821).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="citation">
               <head>Works Cited</head>
               <listBibl>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Anderson, James</author>
                        <title level="m">Recreations in Agriculture, Natural History, Arts, and
                           Miscellaneous Literature</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">5 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1800</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Barrell, John</author>
                        <title level="m">Imagining the King’s Death: Figurative Treason, Fantasies
                           of Regicide, 1793-1796</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
                           <date>2000</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1800</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">Rural Tales, Ballads, and Songs</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1802</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">Wild Flowers; or, Pastoral and Local Poetry</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1806</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">May Day with the Muses</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1822</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">The Remains of Robert Bloomfield</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Weston, Joseph</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Baldwin, Cradock and Joy</publisher>
                           <date>1824</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m"><ref
                              target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters/">The
                              Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</ref></title>
                        <editor role="editor">Fulford, Tim</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Pratt, Lynda</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>2009</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                     <series>
                        <title level="s">Romantic Circles Electronic Editions</title>
                     </series>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Blunt, Reginald</editor>
                        <title level="m">Mrs. Montagu, “Queen of the Blues”: Her Letters and
                           Friendships from 1762-1800</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Constable</publisher>
                           <date>1923</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Boswell, James</author>
                        <title level="m">Life of Johnson</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Chapman, R.W</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
                           <date>1980</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Brewer, J. N</author>
                        <title level="m">Some Thoughts on the Present State of the English
                           Peasantry</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1807</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic></analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">British Critic</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1793-1826</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Christmas, William J</author>
                        <title level="m">The Lab’ring Muses: Work, Writing and the Social Order in
                           English Plebeian Poetry, 1730-1830</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Newark</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>U of Delaware P</publisher>
                           <date>2001</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Christmas, William J</author>
                        <title level="a"><title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> and Contemporary
                           Politics</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Robert Bloomfield: Lyric, Class and the Romantic
                           Canon</title>
                        <editor role="editor">White, Simon J</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Goodridge, John</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Keegan, Bridget</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Lewisburg</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Bucknell UP</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Claeys, Gregory</editor>
                        <title level="m">The Politics of English Jacobinism: Writings of John
                           Thelwall</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>University Park</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Pennsylvania State UP</publisher>
                           <date>1995</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Clare, John</author>
                        <title level="m">The Letters of John Clare</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Storey, Mark</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                           <date>1985</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Clare, John</author>
                        <title level="m">By Himself</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Robinson, Eric</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Powell, David</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Ashington</pubPlace>
                           <pubPlace>Manchester</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Mid-Northumberland Arts Group</publisher>
                           <publisher>Carcanet Press</publisher>
                           <date>1996</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Clark, Anna</author>
                        <title level="m">The Struggle for the Breeches: Gender and the Making of the
                           British Working Class</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Berkeley</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>U of California P</publisher>
                           <date>1995</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Cobbett, William</author>
                        <title level="m">Advice to Young Men</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Spater, George</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
                           <date>1980</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Davenport, Allen</author>
                        <title level="m">The Life and Literary Pursuits of Allen Davenport</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Chase, Malcolm</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Aldershot</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Scolar</publisher>
                           <date>1994</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Duff, William</author>
                        <title level="m">Critical Observations on the Writings of the Most
                           Celebrated Original Geniuses in Poetry</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1770</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Dyer, George</author>
                        <title level="m">The Complaints of the Poor People of England</title>
                        <edition>2nd ed</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1793</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Forbes, William</author>
                        <title level="m">An Account of the Life and Writings of James
                           Beattie</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                           <date>1806</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Hazlitt, William</author>
                        <title level="m">Lectures on the English Poets</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
                           <date>1929</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Holloway, William</author>
                        <title level="m">The Peasants Fate</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1802</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Hurdis, James</author>
                        <title level="m">Equality: A Sermon</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1794</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Janowitz, Anne</author>
                        <title level="m">Lyric and Labour in the Romantic Tradition</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>1998</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Keegan, Bridget</author>
                        <title level="a">Cobbling Verse: Shoemaker Poets of the Long Eighteenth
                           Century</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">42</biblScope>
                           <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                           <date>2001</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">195-217</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Keen, Paul</author>
                        <title level="m">The Crisis of Literature in the 1790s: Print Culture and
                           the Public Sphere</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>1999</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Lamb, Charles</author>
                        <title level="m">The Letters of Charles Lamb</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Pocock, Guy</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Dent</publisher>
                           <date>1950</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Lucas, John</author>
                        <title level="a">Bloomfield and Clare</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">The Independent Spirit: John Clare and the Self-Taught
                           Tradition</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Goodridge, John</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Helpston</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>The John Clare Society</publisher>
                           <publisher>The Margaret Grainger Memorial Trust</publisher>
                           <date>1994</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Mee, Jon</author>
                        <title level="a">The Strange Career of Richard ‘Citizen’ Lee</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">British Literary Radicalism, 1650-1830: From Revolution to
                           Revolution</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Morton, Timothy</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Smith, Nigel</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>2002</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Monthly Review</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1749-1844</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Moral and Political Magazine of the London Corresponding
                           Society</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1796-97</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Paine, Thomas</author>
                        <title level="m">The Age of Reason</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Prometheus Books</publisher>
                           <date>1984</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Parliamentary History of England, from the Earliest Period
                           to the Year 1803</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">36 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1806-1820</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Pigs’ Meat; or, Lessons for the Swinish Multitude</title>
                        <edition>3rd ed</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1795</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Political Register</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1802-1836</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Pratt, Samuel Jackson</author>
                        <title level="m">Bread; or, The Poor</title>
                        <edition>2nd ed</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1802</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Richardson, Alan</author>
                        <title level="m">Literature, Education, and Romanticism: Reading as Social
                           Practice, 1780-1832</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>1994</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Roe, Nicholas</author>
                        <title level="m">The Politics of Nature: William Wordsworth and Some
                           Contemporaries</title>
                        <edition>2nd ed</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Basingstoke</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Palgrave</publisher>
                           <date>2002</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Sales, Roger</author>
                        <title level="m">English Literature in History, 1780-1830: Pastoral and
                           Politics</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Hutchinson</publisher>
                           <date>1983</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Spence, Joseph</author>
                        <title level="m">A Full and Authentick Account of Stephen Duck, the
                           Wiltshire Poet</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1731</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Thelwall, John</author>
                        <title level="m">Poems Chiefly Written in Retirement</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1801</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Whale, John</author>
                        <title level="m">Imagination Under Pressure, 1789-1832: Aesthetics, Politics
                           and Utility</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>2000</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>White, Simon J</author>
                        <title level="m">Robert Bloomfield, Romanticism and the Poetry of
                           Community</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Aldershot</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Wollstonecraft, Mary</author>
                        <title level="m">Political Writings</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Todd, Janet</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
                           <date>1994</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
