<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Robert Bloomfield: The Inestimable Blessing of Letters</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">Bloomfield in His Letters: The Social World of a London Shoemaker
               Turned Suffolk Poet</title>
            <author>
               <name>Tim Fulford</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">John Goodridge</editor>
            <editor role="editor">Bridget Keegan</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.fulford</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2010-11-01">March 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Introduction: The Inestimable Blessing of
                     letters</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Tim</forename>
                        <surname>Fulford</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Robert Bloomfield:</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-03-01">March 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#226;&#8364;&#339;,"
                  for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent11" scheme="css">margin-left: 6em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent12" scheme="css">margin-left: 6.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent13" scheme="css">margin-left: 7em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent14" scheme="css">margin-left: 7.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
            <keywords scheme="http://www.rc.umd.edu/#tags">
               <list>
                  <item>Robert Bloomfield's letters document one artist’s struggles (and sometimes
                     his victories) to share his unique voice and vision; the online publication of
                     his extant letters (a companion to this collection of essays) reveals new and
                     exciting insights into Bloomfield the artist and the man. The essays included
                     in this collection highlight and draw attention to aspects of Bloomfield's
                     literary production that would likely not be possible without the full access
                     to his letters that the edition provides, and make a strong case for why
                     Bloomfield continues to be worthy of study. They suggest how much more remains
                     to be said about this prolific poet. </item>
                  <item>Robert Bloomfield</item>
                  <item>labouring-class writing</item>
                  <item>landscape</item>
                  <item>correspondence</item>
                  <item>literary London</item>
                  <item>letters</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2010-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>
               <title level="a">Bloomfield in His Letters: The Social World of a London Shoemaker
                  Turned Suffolk Poet</title>
            </head>
            <byline>
               <docAuthor>Tim Fulford</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>Nottingham Trent University</affiliation>
            </byline>
            <p>The publication of Bloomfield’s collected letters gives us for the first time a
               chance to see him as a writer of intimate prose—prose in which he reveals his inner
               feelings and deepest desires, prose in which he comes to understand what he stands
               for, as a poet and as a man. Bloomfield’s letters, spanning the thirty and more years
               of his adult life, let us chart his progress from London shoemaker, living in an East
               End slum, through the best-selling poet of the early 1800s, to the impoverished
               villager living in obscure retirement. But they also show the development of a mind
               full of penetrating observation of himself, his acquaintances, and the world around
               him, and the emergence of a character endowed with generous humor, quiet
               determination, and exceptional sensitivity. These qualities made Bloomfield a
               wonderful correspondent: he never concealed himself from the person to whom he was
               writing, always offering them intimacy and thoughtfulness (resembling Keats in this)
               and always registering the nuances of events with a playful perceptiveness that
               escapes most. As a consequence, he was a fascinating social commentator (although
               social commentary is not the chief element of his letters), a perspicuous critic of
               other poets, and a forthright maintainer of his beliefs about writing against the
               interference of patrons, well-meaning or brow-beating. </p>
            <p> Many themes emerge from the letters: I shall concentrate in what follows on
               illustrating those which most sharply change our understanding of the writer, of his
               times, and of the business of being a laboring-class poet. </p>
            <p>First, then, the letters reveal with a new vividness what remains obscure in
               Bloomfield’s verse: that he was not a farmhand living in one of Britain’s thousands
               of villages. Despite his self-characterization in his poems as “Giles” the “farmer’s
               boy,” Bloomfield was, when he wrote, a Londoner working in one of the capital’s
               hundreds of cramped workshops. He was, in fact, a member of the wave after wave of
               immigrants that, in the late eighteenth century, flowed from the country to work in
               London’s burgeoning trades and industries, exchanging a boyhood spent herding animals
               and tending crops for an adolescence manufacturing items for the expanding consumer
                  market.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn1" place="end" n="1">On this immigration,
                  see Hitchcock. </note> The change in circumstances this move produced is revealed
               by his first surviving letter of 1788, in which he invites a Suffolk friend to visit
               him: <quote>[W]hen you are at my lodging you must expect such treatment as is in my
                  power to give, and when we are out you must have no objection to dine at a decent
                  Cook-shop, where there is good choice, and if you dont like porter we can get good
                  ale, in short, London is like other great places, allmost any thing may be had for
                  money and when we are out, whatever the expence may be for living or for seeing
                  the public buildings, &amp;c, my scheme is, that each bear his own charges, you
                  know how George and others of our trade live, but George have the honour of living
                  in a street, but I cannot Get into a street from my lodgings without going through
                  some such crook of a hole as between your near-barn and the hay-house, but take
                  notice you are not to lodge in such a place as this, you have boath had the
                  small-pox and I think I remember that your sister Judith have had it too, here is
                  a letter enclosed from my sister to Judith and I hope to see you all soon, I hope
                  it will not be thought disrespectful for me to mention only you and your brother,
                  the reason is, I could not procure a suitable accomodation for any woman whatever,
                  a single man have no chance to do it half so well as my sister have, if you all
                  come (as I hope you will) you and your brother must lodge near me, and the street
                  where your sister will live, lead into Berkley Square, just by where my sister
                  live, and we are about three miles apart, so you will have a good chance to see
                  the town in going backwards and forwards, I shall be allways with you and we must
                  be very particular and not be out late of night, nor frequent any low lived
                  places, and as long as we do so, there is no danger to be feard, if you consider
                  the whole expense I belive it will be found a cheap way of seeing London. (letter
                  1, 11 April 1788)</quote> Bloomfield’s description reminds us of Blake’s “London,”
               or Wordsworth’s <title level="m">Prelude</title> description of “Private courts, /
               Gloomy as coffins, and unsightly lanes / Thrilled by some female vendor’s scream,
               belike / The very shrillest of all London cries” (1805, 7: 196-9). East End poverty,
               cramped living conditions, endemic disease, “low lived places”: Bloomfield was
               writing from experience as one of the new class of “mechanics” about which Wordsworth
               spoke in his preface to <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title>, one of the nascent
               proletariat, in Marxist terms. It was this class that Wordsworth diagnosed as having
               acquired debased cravings for stimulation as a means of escape from their repetitive
               labor and that Marxists saw as being dosed with the opiates of popular religion and
               mass culture. Yet Bloomfield belies the Wordsworthian and the Marxist analysis: he
               suggests that, for first-generation migrants from country to city, it was not novel
               forms of urban entertainment, but the recollection and celebration of village
               community and customs, that was the goal. This is shown by a letter which he wrote in
               1806 about his first encounter with Italian opera: <quote><ab>The Scenery is truly
                     delightfull. The dancing wonderfull, and the whole, setting probability and
                     nature (allmost) out of the question, is a high treat, Yet I think more like
                     Mince-pie and made-dishes than substancial food. I am too great a novice in
                     Music to judge, I could only be surprize’d and astonished. I sat <del rend="strikethrough">alone</del>, in the
                     Pit, totally unknowing and unknown. Some Gentlemen behind me were extolling the
                     singular beauty of a Lady of easy Virtue who sat a few seats above us, and I
                     excercised my judgment too, (for when you <del rend="strikethrough">gave</del> sent me the ticket no
                     restriction was laid as to which way I should look,) and have to tell you that
                     of any <emph>essentials</emph> of beauty she had not a spark, not an atom! so
                     much for difference of opinion. I do not believe that men agree in this any
                     more than in their palates at Table, or their notions of what is beautifull in
                     a landscape.</ab><lb/>
                  <ab>I cannot help observing the great difference between an illdresst and a
                     well-dresst mob, and I must indeed be unfeeling and ungenerous not to
                     acknowledge it. In our National Theatres I have often sided so far with the
                     Patricians as to wish the Plebeans at the Devel, not because they were such,
                     (that I leave to those who are weak enough, that is, proud enough,) but merely
                     because they would not be quiet.</ab><lb/>
                  <ab>I observed, according to the best of my calculation, that the petticoats of
                     the women were about ten inches longer than those of the men, one of <del rend="strikethrough">them</del> the
                     former in particular I should have been glad to have accommodated with the loan
                     of a pair of pantaloons which I had left at home, and yet it is more than a
                     hundred to one if they had pleased her;—I do not wonder in the least that
                     Gentlemen, and ladies too, should frequent a place where they can hear the
                     finest Music, and see the most surprizing agility and grace, but I am now
                     convinced, <del rend="strikethrough">too</del> that the former have an additional incentive; the exhibition of
                     female beauty in a manner, and in a way which no other place in England will
                     warrant, and by my Soul, I think this is as <emph>natural</emph> a feeling as
                     any one there excited, “and further this deponent saith not.”</ab><lb/>
                  <ab>I have had the pleasure of witnessing the best Scenery and Dancing, and the
                     worst Lightning, in England. I saw Narcissus drown himself, (and, by the buy
                     that same Narcissus was worth going three miles to see,) I saw a very jolly and
                     delectable looking Venus, and a number of other young things whose motions
                     indicated that they felt the want of wings and were very angry indeed because
                     they had them not. They plagued poor little Cupid in a most barbarous manner,
                     because he fell asleep after whetting his arrows, on what?—on a
                     Grindstone!</ab><lb/>
                  <ab>Upon the whole I frankly own that I think I should have relish’d this show
                     much more if it had not happen’d that I had seen the preceeding, week the
                        <emph>English</emph> Opera of “Love in a Village”<note resp="editors"
                        xml:id="ftn2" place="end" n="2">
                        <title level="m">Love in a Village</title>: the comic opera in three acts
                        composed by Thomas Arne with libretto by Isaac Bickerstaff (1762). This
                        popular work sentimentalizing English rural life saw forty performances in
                        its first season and had many revivals. </note> and I am unfashionable
                     enough to declare, and my whole heart goes with it, that I would rather be the
                     Author of such a piece than proprietor of the Opera House and all the buildings
                     on his side of the Street. (letter 199, 24 December 1806)</ab><lb/></quote></p>
            <p>Bloomfield’s village—whether the village encountered in the opera-house or that of
               his own writing—is not the agricultural world seen by a laborer who works in it: it
               is, rather, a new country—the country seen from exile by an urbanite who has
               nostalgic desires to reconstitute, in memory and on paper, the rural community he
               associates with childhood. It is family and village togetherness, imagined as
               innocent by comparison with the experienced world of urban sophistication, that
               Bloomfield seeks—as Wordsworth himself did. This suggests that it was not, as
               Wordsworth thought, urban life and labor that destroyed respect for the values and
               taste of the older, rural world. Rather, urban exile from the country produced an
               intense idealization of the rural just as Wordsworth’s continental exile did. Exile,
               rather than city life per se, stimulated the major Romantic themes of idealization of
               the rural and fear for its loss. For Bloomfield, as for Wordsworth, it was the
               recollection of rural society and morality that he had, in practice, left behind that
               gave him a standard against which to judge the novel culture available in London’s
               metropolitan and cosmopolitan milieu. </p>
            <p>But he had not left it completely behind: in the early 1800s, the letters show, the
               urban and rural poor were not discrete, mutually unknowing populations. Bloomfield’s
               letters reveal the constant interchange between city and country-dwellers:
               Bloomfield’s family was typical in having some siblings who worked in the city while
               others remained in the home village—typical too in the frequent interchange between
               them. Letters carried news, invitations, and banknotes; parcels carried pheasants,
               leather-samples, and cheese. The foodstuffs traveled in both directions, Bloomfield
               taking advantage of his position in Europe’s largest commercial center to send to
               Suffolk better rural produce than could be found locally: “I send my Mother a piece
               of cheese such as she could not get at Honington if she had money” he wrote on 30
               November 1801 (letter 70), enclosing a Leicester cheese far superior to that of
               Suffolk (the best milk being sent out of Suffolk to supply London’s market).<note
                  resp="editors" xml:id="ftn3" place="end" n="3">See the passage in <title level="m"
                     >The Farmer’s Boy</title>, “Spring” 231-68.</note>
            </p>
            <p>People went back and forth too: Bloomfield returned to Suffolk to visit; his
               brothers, drawn to London’s commercial magnet, came to make their fortunes from music
               and from inventions, themselves returning. The laboring-classes, on the evidence of
               Bloomfield’s family, were simply not rigidly divided between shrinking rural and
               expanding urban populations: it was normal for families from the home counties to
               spend some of their lives in London, some back in the country, as did his brother
               George who grew up in Honington, worked as a shoemaker in London, and moved back to
               Suffolk, or his brother Nat, who moved from Suffolk to London, or Isaac, who lived in
               Suffolk but came to London to sell his musical settings of Robert’s poems, or Robert
               himself, who moved out of London to a Bedfordshire village in 1811. His sister Bet,
               meanwhile, emigrated to America. The Bloomfield family is revealed in Robert’s
               letters as being on the move to a degree that would have been extraordinary fifty
               years earlier, but nevertheless strenuously keeping in touch using the literacy with
               which their mother, a village schooldame, had endowed them. The causes of their
               peripatetic life illustrate the changes in rural society brought about by the
               combination of increased population, the development of “improved” capitalist
               agriculture, economic recessions, and a more centralized market economy. Brothers
               George and Isaac both had many children and found it impossible to provide for them
               from the proceeds of shoemaking. London, and the opportunity of selling poems and
               tunes there, offered the prospect of a way out of poverty.</p>
            <p>Bloomfield’s letters show<hi> </hi>his most abiding concern to have been the creation
               and preservation, in a more and more hostile social and political climate, of village
               and family rootedness. While he still enjoyed royalties from his poems, he used this
               income to try to recreate rural community from the distance of London. Thus he sent
               his London-reared daughter Hannah to Suffolk to give her experience of village life.
               Hannah was charged with retrieving the very rocks and stones Bloomfield remembered by
               their local names, so strong was his desire to have a bit of his boyhood about him:
                  <quote>I have several times intended to remind you that If your Cousins at
                  Honington or any other boys have any “Fairies Cakes,” curiously markd pebbles and
                  will part with them for halfpence, bring what you can, They will know what you
                  mean. Bring away some thunderbolts, and some “Devel’s Toe Nails”, which are found
                  in a field north of what was Mr Rolfs Rookery, but if these are not to be had,
                  dont stop for either. These strange names make it look like a queer errand to set
                  a young girl about, but I tell you they know what I mean—I feel proud of your
                  letters, but I would rather have your company. (Letter 243, 8 October
                  1809)</quote> Wanting his daughter to know him by reliving his own childhood,
               Bloomfield was excited when she witnessed the harvest-home festival that was
               customary in the area and which he had celebrated in his poem “The Horkey,” even
               preserving Suffolk dialect in an effort “to tell the rising race of mankind” of the
               customs “going fast out of use”<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn4" place="end" n="4"
                  >From the “Advertisement” to “The Horkey. A Provincial Ballad” in <title level="m"
                     >Wild Flowers</title> 31-32.</note> that, in his boyhood, ritualized the
               communal interdependence of farmers, reapers and womenfolk: <quote><lg type="stanza">
                  <l rendition="#indent14">XVI</l>
                     <l>And Farmer Cheerum went, good man,</l>
                     <l rendition="#indent2"> And broach’d the <emph>Horkey beer</emph>;</l>
                     <l>And <emph>sitch a mort </emph>of folks began</l>
                     <l rendition="#indent2"> To eat up our good cheer.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l rendition="#indent14">XVII</l>
                     <l>Says he, “Thank God for what’s before us;</l>
                     <l rendition="#indent2"> That thus we meet agen,”</l>
                     <l>The mingling voices, like a chorus,</l>
                     <l rendition="#indent2"> Joined cheerfully, “Amen”.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l rendition="#indent14">XVIII</l>
                     <l>Welcome and plenty, there they found ’em,</l>
                     <l rendition="#indent2"> The ribs of beef grew light;</l>
                     <l>And puddings—till the boys got round ’em,</l>
                     <l rendition="#indent2"> And then they vanish’d quite! (<title level="m">Wild
                           Flowers</title>, 61-72)</l>
                  </lg></quote> Bloomfield’s letter on the subject is full of quiet satisfaction at
               rural life experienced vicariously at the consequent reunion of his family: <quote>My
                  eldest Daughter has just return’d from an eight weeks residence in Suffolk at the
                  very Farm that employ’d me in my childhood. She has seen the Harvest, and was
                  present at the “Horkey” and with many of the persons who figured there thirty
                  years ago when I was 13 years old. There is a fund of gossip cut out for me during
                  the winter coming. She return’d on the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, the next day you
                  may recollect is sacred to our <emph>Leather Saint,</emph> and is besides her
                  birthday. It was a high holiday in London as a Jubilee, and to crown it all my
                  brother’s family postponed on her account the celebration of a Christning. Thus,
                  by having a family meeting we beat all the Doctors for we killd more than two
                  birds with one stone. (letter 245, 31 October 1809)</quote> Here rural, trade, and
               family celebrations coincide: in Honington Hannah participates in the horkey; in
               London Robert celebrates St. Crispin’s day with other cordwainers; also in London
               brother Nat’s family bring the Bloomfields together for a party. The reality behind
               such rural poems as “The Horkey,” is a family straddling city and country and
               occupying the social habitus of each.</p>
            <p> It was a brief moment. Dispersed across town and village, the Bloomfields were
               rarely able to, in his words, “kill more than two birds with one stone.” The letters
               show Bloomfield instead, like Wordsworth, attempting to repossess his rural childhood
               home. He did this by using the wealth poetry brought him to buy the cottage his
               mother had rented, letting his relatives live there. This scheme made little economic
               sense: what drove Bloomfield was the emotional pull of his home village and his need
               for a family togetherness he had lost when sent away to London as a youth. This need
               was not met: after his mother’s death Bloomfield found, predictably, that the house
               made him an absentee landlord, embroiled in legal disputes with once-friendly
               neighbors over rights to the garden and charged with ever-mounting repair bills while
               his resident relatives seemed ungrateful or begged for more financial help.
               Eventually, as relations soured under the pressure of the financial strain Bloomfield
               suffered after his booksellers’ bankruptcy, he felt reluctant to revisit the place:
               he could no longer sustain its image as a symbol of boyhood and familial community;
               it now spoke of his relatives’ expectation that he, having made money, would provide
               for them, of his own sadness that they were now his clients rather than his peers,
               and of his disappointment that he could no longer afford to maintain it.</p>
            <p> If Bloomfield could not return to Honington, he could get as near as was possible
               given the necessity of being in London to attend to his publications. Almost the
               first thing he did when the poetry began to sell was to quit the crowded East End,
               retire from shoemaking, and become one of a social class that mushroomed in this
               period—a suburbanite. The suburbs as we know them today were a phenomenon of the
               early nineteenth century, producing a tamed and domesticated simulacrum of the
               remembered countryside, leisure-time idylls of green in miniature garden-plots that
               were both retired and accessible from the city, where the suburbanites worked. The
               outlook of the growing class of people who lived like this—the clerks who, like
               Charles Lamb and Dickens’s Wemmick, worked in the increasing number of counting
               houses, offices, and chambers of the imperial and governmental city—found expression
               in a new kind of verse, ornamental and decorative, that eschewed the full-blown
               classicism of the epic and the large-scale loco-description of the georgic (both
               styles associated with the landowning gentry and aristocracy). The suburban was
               pretty, sentimental, bejeweled, representing the democratization of taste in a class
               that read magazines and novels rather than Latin and Greek poetry.</p>
            <p> Bloomfield was not Keats or Leigh Hunt, two poets whose early writing, Nicholas Roe
                  shows,<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn5" place="end" n="5">In his <title level="m"
                     >John Keats and the Culture of Dissent</title> 214-17.</note> was criticized as
               the suburban work of writers who had never known the real countryside. He avoided
               excessive ornamentation, garden settings, and tricked-out diction—all facets of Leigh
               Hunt’s verse that aroused the ire of traditionalist critics. Nevertheless, his
               letters reveal that he set out to choose a home that relocated the idealized virtues
               and pleasures of the country in miniature at the edge of the city. His cottage next
               to the Shepherd and Shepherdess Inn on the City Road, was situated at commercial
               London’s margin, where workhouses and almshouses ran out into smallholdings, gardens,
               and fields. Bloomfield cultivated the garden there, and ensured his family learnt to
               do so too, as a letter from his daughter Mary to her older sister reveals: “the first
               thing I have to tell you,” she wrote, “is of the garden, our lobernam will not blow
               so much as we thought it would, we have got two mugs full of butterflowers, and we
               have some beans coming up, this is holiday work and many people are crowding by our
               gate” (letter 163, 3 June 1805). She returned to the subject a week later, “You
               wanted to know about the garden. I first tell you the beans are growing very high, a
               good deal of your sweet Williams is dead, and your nut tree is very well, we are
               going to have a crop of scarlet beans over the grass plat, my father’s thistle will
               not thrive; Charlesis Cherry tree grows very well, shot<note resp="editors"
                  xml:id="ftn6" place="end" n="6">The family nickname for Bloomfield’s youngest
                  daughter Charlotte.</note> has got a nut tree and some butter flowers” (letter
               166, 10 June 1805).</p>
            <p> Bloomfield’s position on the margin gave him a double knowledge that neither East
               Enders nor Suffolk villagers possessed—a double knowledge that helped make his poetry
               unique. He used this double knowledge not just to drive his yearning to articulate a
               rural world he knew to be fragile, but also to demand realism about country and city.
               It allowed him to achieve a conscious recollection of country customs in plain,
               rustic language, before these customs were submerged by urban fashions and capitalist
               agriculture. In a letter of 2 September 1802, for instance, he criticized affected
               diction and uncolloquial word order in poetry (much like Wordsworth in the Preface to
                  <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title>), extending his argument to cover
               pictorial representations of the rustic: <quote>Something of this kind may be traced
                  in some pictures which I have occasionally seen, which indeed relates more to the
                  foregoing wrong adaptation of words, than to compound epithets—A scene extremely
                  rustic, the Death of the Fox in a Cottage-yard would you there expect to see up
                  against the wall what in London are called Bird-bottles for the sparrows to build
                  in? Country people know sparrows too well; the same picture has the error of
                  chimney pots to the cottage, which I never saw in reality; these are London and
                  Country ideas mixed. (letter 94, 2 September 1802)</quote> Had Bloomfield not, as
               a youth, read the magazines available in the shoemakers’ workshop (but unlikely to
               have come his way on a Suffolk farm) he would not have learnt to compose verse at
               all. He was, in fact, in the rare position of being able to benefit from both city
               and country: his rural tales benefited from his knowledge of contemporary taste as
               set out in town-based periodicals as well as from the authenticity that stemmed from
               his early upbringing on the land.</p>
            <p> Bloomfield’s suburban cottage was, nonetheless, a retreat from the city proper. In
               moving to London’s fringe, he was retiring from business—from the trade of shoemaking
               and from the incessant visitors who, keen to view the phenomenon of a laboring-class
               poet, had troubled him in his cheap lodgings. From the edge of London, he could
               supervise his works through the press and call on his literary acquaintances, without
               becoming a celebrity and having to appear on demand for any gentleman who wished to
               satisfy his curiosity and advise him what to read. The suburbs for Bloomfield—and
               here he was proleptic of the phenomenon Dickens fictionalized in Wemmick—were a daily
               retreat from an urban intercourse from which he could not altogether withdraw, an
               intercourse he found inimical not just for its crowdedness (although certainly for
               that) but also for the demeaning of human relationships by the pressures of
               market-driven work-discipline. Matters came to a head when the Duke of Grafton, his
               Suffolk patron, found him a job in the busy Seal Office, sealing legal contracts and
               charters (in a form of tax collection). Bloomfield’s letter on the subject (to his
               brother George, 29 February 1803)—a cry of desperation—reads as if written by the
               narrator of Blake’s “London” imprisoned by “each chartered street,” for it highlights
               the mental toll taken by the binding of self to bureaucratic and commercial
               institutions—the lack of privacy and self-command, the need to prepare a public face,
               the slavery to the new discipline of clock-time and office-hours, the reduction of
               human interaction to overworked clerk and demanding client: <quote>On Friday, the day
                  after the Holidays, I expected a busy day at the Seal Office; and so I found it
                  with a vengeance. I had eat no breakfast, and the Mob of Lawyers made me perfectly
                  savage: at One o’clock we shut the Office, but shut in between 40 and 50 people,
                  and did not get through the Work for 3 quarters of an hour after one. I then grew
                  faint, and knew if I walkd home to the City Road that my Wind and indigestion
                  would get the upper hand of my Stomach, and should eat no dinner; so I put into
                  the Cook’s in Salsbury Court and eat heartily. by this time there was no time to
                  go home and then to Temple Bar again by 4; so I sulkd away the time in St George’s
                  Fields, and then took another 3 hours’ Mobbing at the Office, having seald during
                  the day nearly 1100 Writs! by far the busiest day (if Mr A<note resp="editors"
                     xml:id="ftn7" place="end" n="7">Mr. Allen, Bloomfield’s boss at the Seal
                     Office.</note> is to be credited) that have occurrd for eight years past.
                  Returnd to my sick house, tired and insufferably disgusted. At home I found a
                  Letter from Troston,<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn8" place="end" n="8">Troston,
                     Suffolk, seat of Capel Lofft, Bloomfield’s disputatious patron.</note> not
                  quite the thing and your most melancholy tidings, and—to crown all, a young Man in
                  the neighbourhood fourced on me a M:S. book of poems for me to read and to give my
                  judgment of, which accorded with the feelings of the moment, being a doleful
                  string of Elegies as black as midnight—This I shall call Black Friday—Another
                  trifle had displeased me. I had found in the Morning Chronicle a bit of news put
                  there by some fool or other that “Bloomfield the poet has been recently appointed
                  to a <emph>handsome</emph> situation in the Seal Office in the Temple, thus he has
                  not courted the Muses unsuccessfully!”<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn9"
                     place="end" n="9">Bloomfield quotes verbatim the notice of his appointment to
                     the Seal Office printed in the <title level="j">Morning Chronicle</title> on 19
                     February 1803. </note> Your letter made it still worse by shewing me that Peter
                  had either <emph>originally</emph> printed this wonderfull piece of news,<note
                     resp="editors" xml:id="ftn10" place="end" n="10">The notice also appeared in
                     Peter Gedge’s <title level="j">Bury and Norwich Post</title> in early
                     1803.</note> or else had made it worse by adding to it what is as false as the
                  Chronicle’s “<emph>handsome</emph> appointment” is ridiculous. This story has
                  served the Herald <emph>two</emph> days, the first to say I was there, and the
                  next to say I had resignd it!!—tis useless to be angry, but if the Asses that
                  meddle with another mans business before they know it were buried three times as
                  deep as your poor Wife, I would not were [i.e. wear] black for them.—What G<note
                     resp="editors" xml:id="ftn11" place="end" n="11">I.e., George, Bloomfield’s
                     elder brother.</note> says in his paper is false, thus, because
                     <emph>confinement</emph> is not my objection, and I hope and trust that it is
                  well known to the Duke. Extreem publicity begins to be more and more disgusting to
                  my feelings, and these boobys make it worse.—The Good Man at Euston<note
                     resp="editors" xml:id="ftn12" place="end" n="12">I.e., the Duke of Grafton,
                     whose country house was at Euston, Suffolk.</note> will be here soon, and then
                  I shall know how I am to proceed. His last letter said that “<emph>he was sorry I
                     was going to leave it at all</emph>.” circumstances made it absolutely
                  necessary to reply that I would not leave it, at least untill I see him—thus we
                  stand now—Dr Jenner is in Town, and has written to me. Dr Perkins plagued me by
                  publishing my name with his Tractors, till I wrote to him to forbid it.<note
                     resp="editors" xml:id="ftn13" place="end" n="13">Edward Jenner, then a
                     little-known young doctor avidly promoting his cowpox remedy against smallpox;
                     Benjamin Perkins, an American bookseller and quack healer, resident in London,
                     who profited from his father Elisha’s “tractors,” metal rods supposed to cure
                     illnesses if the points were applied to the diseased area. Perkins advertised
                     the rods heavily and was satirized for his pains by Gillray, who depicted him
                     tractorizing a wart on John Bull’s nose.</note> my cough plagues me, and I have
                  no time to write down my Rhimes, I have enough on my mind to craze a saint, but I
                  feel my soul soar above it all—I know that I shall triumph—and “that Spring will
                  come and Nature smile again”.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn14" place="end"
                     n="14">Bloomfield quotes the last line of “Autumn” from his own <title
                        level="m">The Farmer’s Boy.</title>
                  </note> (letter 103)</quote> Charles Lamb wrote of his clerk’s work in Leadenhall
               Street as a form of slavery to the East India Company; for Bloomfield less than a
               mile away at Temple Bar, the situation was exacerbated by his dislike of being a
               celebrity and having his private feelings and actions tattled about in the London and
               Suffolk newspapers and his name used by quack doctors in their advertisements. </p>
            <p> Beyond the suburbs lay solace in the hills. When depressed by the city’s demands,
               Bloomfield took to making solitary walking tours, refreshing himself with a leisured
               consumption of nature in which he was, for a few days, his own master, his time and
               space his own. These tours were a reaction against his lack of a stable place in
               which independence, self-respect, and rural community could be sustained, when even
               the suburban retreat on the City Road became prey to the pressure of business and
               when his boyhood home in Honington seemed polluted by disputes with family and
               patron. So Bloomfield went to Dover and to Dorking, recording his trips in intimate
               and informal letters that bear comparison with Coleridge’s descriptions of his 1802
               walking tour in the Lakes and with Dorothy Wordsworth’s journals. They represent,
               that is to say, a new kind of tour-journalism reflecting a new social practice: the
               pedestrian tour was the creation of a class of writers (Romantics, as they were later
               called) who, dissociating themselves from gentleman and women tourists for reasons of
               poverty and politics, eschewed the horse and carriage and asserted their liberty and
               independence as solitary wanderers in nature.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn15"
                  place="end" n="15">On the pedestrian tour and its social and political valency,
                  see Jarvis.</note> Like Wordsworth, Bloomfield was an urbanite visiting
               countryside places he felt emotionally connected to by virtue of his rural upbringing
               but in which he had no present-day social or economic place. Like Coleridge, he was
               self-conscious of this anomalous status and was ready to record the funny side of
               being out of place wherever he visited. As such he was an unwitting pioneer of a
               practice of nature recreation and nature writing that became, and remains, one of the
               main pursuits of Britain’s suburban masses—a practice of countryside rambling that
               still has its dedicated organizations and magazines. The description he made of his
               Surrey tour in 1803, for instance, has the features we have come to see as familiar
               to the genre—unexpected adventures, hill country, romantic views, and assertions
               about nature’s restorative powers: <quote><ab>Having been harrassd by too much
                     thinking and too many trivial engagements, and an employment that I shall never
                     like, I determined that I would respire one mouthfull of real country air if
                     possible and I know at the same time that pollution of smoke reaches ten miles
                     round the Metropolis. I had heard much of Leithe Hills and of Box Hill in the
                     neighbourhood of Dorking. This was the time to see them. I started from the
                     Spread Eagle, GraceChurch Stt. At 3 in the afternoon of Monday and soon rode
                     away from the gay Bonnets and red faces that made a perfect current towards
                     Greenwich. The road is like all others within ten miles of town, much too
                     spruce and too full of inhabitants for my fancy. Epsom is a pretty little town
                     and the country round it open and flat; but 3 or four miles beyond it assumes a
                     quite different aspect, becoming more hilly than I had ever before seen.
                     Remember that I am no Welshman, therefore to me these Hills are Cader Idris’s
                     and Snowdens.—</ab><lb/>
                  <ab>Evening drew on as we approached the old town of Dorking, and the prospect to
                     me was delightful; but to prove that enjoyment is often dashd with a strange
                     and unexpected kind of naucia, we had behind us on the Coach two Lasses, the
                     one going to join the Thunderer<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn16" place="end"
                        n="16">
                        <emph>HMS Thunderer</emph>, a 74-gun ship of the line of the Royal Navy,
                        later took part in the Battle of Trafalgar.</note> on her arrival at
                     Portsmouth from Chatham, and the other to meet a party of Marines passing
                     through Dorking; they drank Brandy all the way, and then work’d off the fumes
                     by songs of a description which were new to me, so that you see that the school
                     of poetry has many stages. I supt and insured a lodging for two nights at the 3
                     Tons where the Coach put up, and on Tuesday morning set off with a
                     determination to reach Leith Hill; but though I had a good map of the County in
                     my pocket I took the wrong rout, and as the place of my destination was about 6
                     miles and my attention and inclination drawn to other and nearer objects I made
                     for the top of a Hill which is planted with about 8 or ten Fir Trees which are
                     very conspicuous at a great distance; this Hill the inhabitants denominate with
                     no small share of pride “Dorking’s Glory.” It affords certainly a most
                     delightfull view on every side; here I could discover that had I kept on nearly
                     in the direction in which I started that I might have passd over Boar Hills to
                     Leith Hills which here appear eminently conspicuous, having a square tower on
                     one summit and being much higher and of greater extant than any other in sight.
                     Being alone and in the pure unadulterated spirit of Idleness and Gratitude
                     mix’d, I cut on an oak bench</ab>
                  <lg>
                     <l rendition="#indent4"> “From the smoke of London free</l>
                     <l rendition="#indent4"> I bless thee, Rural Liberty.”</l>
                  </lg>
                  <ab>Box Hill which I had passd the foregoing evening in the way from town lay
                     southward from “Dorkings Glory” and made a noble appearance but it did not
                     appear to me to be higher than that on which I stood;— </ab><lb/>
                  <ab> Return’d into the town to dinner, which by the by was a poets dinner, Bread
                     and Cheese. (letter 106, 17 April 1803)</ab><lb/></quote> Bread and cheese was
               to be Bloomfield’s dinner increasingly in later years. After <title level="m">Wild
                  Flowers </title>(1806) his output declined and sales of his publications tailed
               off. In 1812 his booksellers went bankrupt, depriving him of his income. Much money
               went to supporting relatives and as donations made by his wife to the prophetess
               Joanna Southcott. In 1811 he moved from the City Road to the Bedfordshire village of
               Shefford, seeking to reduce his expenses and to rediscover the placedness in village
               life that he recalled in his Suffolk youth—a placedness impossible for him to
               reconstitute in Suffolk because that place had become vitiated by disputes. Some of
               his early letters from Shefford revel in finding it there instead. In July 1814, for
               instance, he sent his daughter Hannah (2-3 July 1814) a description of the village
               celebration of Napoleon’s defeat that is a comic masterpiece, Dickensian in its
               celebratory yet humorous portrait of village life as a teeming cavalcade in which all
               are united in sensual enjoyment. <quote><ab>In the procession rode Mr Williamson
                     &amp;c, Mr Walker, (two church parsons,) Mr Potier, the Catholick priest, and
                     Briggs the Methodest preacher, and all who could procure Horses, or wish’d to
                     join the Cavalcade, In the rear of which appeard an old black Horse decorated
                     with an enormous pair of Bullock’s horns place’d near his ears. On his back
                     rode the Devel with a monstrous Mask and horns to corispond, and drest in a
                     black cloak. Behind him rode (riding backwards both on a Horse) a lad with a
                     pale Mask, and in the utmost trembling and destress, to represent the fallen
                     Emperor. Both these perform’d their parts extreemly well, and cause’d the
                     utmost laughter, Inskip<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn17" place="end" n="17"
                        >Thomas Inskip (circa 1780-1849): watchmaker, Bloomfield’s Shefford neighbor
                        and friend. Inskip also befriended John Clare, whose poetry he printed in
                        the <title level="j">Bedfordshire Times</title> (1848).</note> was Devil,
                     and Jack sombody was Bounaparte. It was the best Devil I ever saw, and riding
                     thus like a whipper-in after the parsons, had a strange and ridiculous
                     appearance. A Bullock drest in Ribbons, followd likewise by music, had marchd
                     through the town two days before and was now on the Spit, and in the pot, as
                     dinner was to commence at 4. A long range of Tables were placed from
                        Westons<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn18" place="end" n="18">Joseph Weston:
                        Bloomfield’s friend in Shefford, a draper by trade, subject to depression.
                        He moved to Twickenham, where Hannah Bloomfield lived with him and his
                        family, acquiring experience in a trade. He edited <title level="j">The
                           Remains of Robert Bloomfield.</title>
                     </note> door to the George, capable of accommodating all the poor in the Town
                     that is, all who labour for bread, the whole was coverd with Canvass and form’d
                     a compleat tent, border’d throughout by garlands of flowers, and each table
                     having a flag inscribe’d, “Alexander”, “Blucher”, “Platoff” &amp;c.<note
                        resp="editors" xml:id="ftn19" place="end" n="19">Tsar Alexander I; Marshall
                        Gebhard von Blucher, leader of the Prussian forces against Napoleon; Count
                        Matvei Ivanovich Platoff, hetman of Cossacks, and Russian commander in the
                        Napoleonic wars.</note> At the end stood a kind of Maypole, bearing a gilded
                     Cock, surmounted by a flag—Across the center of the street was erected a stage
                     for the band, who had there a little bower of their own, above the passing
                     carriages.—At 4 about 250 people sat down to dinner in the greatest good order.
                     At the head of the Table sat Mr Williamson and the other conductors of the
                     feast took each of them a Table, as president and carver, Here you might have
                     seen two Doctors, two publican’s, a parson, and a Shopkeeper &amp;c &amp;c. in
                     White Aprons, slashing up the Beef and plumb pudding, and sharing out several
                     Baskets of potatoes.—The Town was crouded with spectators, and all was joy. At
                     6, (after grace in due order) dinner was removed, and the Gentlemen part of the
                     company had a boarded stage for their wine and refreshments, and here; while
                     men women and children were Huzzaing around, they did just what must be
                     expected, viz, got drunk by drinking Toasts. The musical performers at one time
                     did not know “God save the King,” from Jack’s-alive; but this fervor subsided
                     gradually so as to produce no mischief, and to leave the evening for a still
                     more singular exhibition, which is the beautiful effect of light under boughs,
                     which, as you have now seen Vauxhall, you can fully understand. I should here
                     tell you that in the evening Tea was serve’d on the platform to all the women
                     who choose it, and dancing commenced in the real country stile. Miss
                        Weston<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn20" place="end" n="20">Joseph Weston’s
                        sister.</note> made more tea than she ever did in one day in her life.
                     Amongsts the flags Inskip had two very large, inscribed “The Strength of Kings
                     is the Affections of the people” and, “Freedom to Slaves, and peace to the
                     World”. Mr Walker had a real fine transparency, and his house a croud of green
                     and blossoms,—Mr Gay several transparencies of his own painting, and his House
                     shaded by Oak-limbs planted in the street. Mr Radwell, Mr Betts &amp;c cut a
                     conspicuous figure; so that when I tell you that there was not a window in the
                     town without Candles, folliage, and flowers, you must try to guess at the
                     effect. It made my eyes water in spite of myself.—This first night’s frolick
                     was not all, though the Town was not quiet till two in the morning.—</ab><lb/>
                  <ab>On Thursday—A Ball had been announced to be held at the White Hart, to which
                     were invited all the Respectable people round the neighbourhood, and
                        Charles<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn21" place="end" n="21">Bloomfield’s
                        son (1798-1863).</note> had been busily employd with other scholars to write
                     Notes of invitation. This whole day was spent in mirth. Amongst the rest a
                     large party, (in fact any who pleased) danced to two fidlers on the platform,
                     Young Girls “threading the Needle along” the Street, Boys kicking a Bladder;
                     And more particularly a ridiculous scene, of a Rope suspended upon poles, to
                     which was tied by small twine two lumps of pudding drip’d in treacle, under
                     which stood on stools, two boys with their hands tied behind them, whose
                     business it was to catch the pudding in their mouths! I say nothing of their
                     faces! treacle betide us! what a mess. At Night about 40 Ladies and as many
                     Gentlemen danced at Barbers till morning, with fidlers from Bedford and
                     Nitshill &amp;c—Friday—Taylor the Sadler Chaird through the Town with the Band,
                     and the wife of our “Old Richard” riding on a great thundering black Horse
                     coverd with a white sheet and flowers. This old woman litterally danced all day
                     from Wednesday morning till Friday night. On the Ball night Mr Weston
                     ornamented his House with Hop-vines from his Garden, intersperse’d with Lamps;
                     with several transparencies of his own designing, Saturday—The Townsmen
                     presented a Flag to Sir George Osborn<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn22"
                        place="end" n="22">Sir George Osborne, of Chicksands Priory, near Shefford,
                        Bedfordshire: the 4th Baronet; served in the American War of Independence,
                        following which he became an MP.</note> in testimony of his bounty towards
                     this real and National holiday, which the good old man has promise’d to
                     presever and to leave to his grandchildren. &amp;c &amp;c</ab><lb/>
                  <ab>And now Father how did you get through this bustle,? what did our house look
                     like? did not you want to help?</ab><lb/>
                  <ab>I saw on Monday that I should “be drag”d” and directly began to regret that
                        Hannah<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn23" place="end" n="23">Hannah
                        Bloomfield (born 1791): Bloomfield’s eldest daughter and the child he
                        trusted to manage the household. After his death Hannah dealt with his
                        business affairs in conjunction with his friend Joseph Weston. </note> was
                     not at home to contrive and to help. “I wish Hannah was here” was repeated
                     oftener than I ever repeated it before, for Charles was busy at writing, and
                        Charlotte<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn24" place="end" n="24">Bloomfield’s
                        youngest daughter, born 1801.</note> my only housemaid,—However I naild up
                     lathes for the illuminatiion, sent for Candles, Cockades, &amp;c—Joe Saunders
                     procure’d a large bough of Oak, and Old Squires two tall branches of
                     Laurel;—Our three younkers went to Rowney and lug’d home as much Yellow Broom
                     and Cornflowers as they could carry, we set to work, made them with form, and
                     on Wednesday morning up at 6, I hung the outer circle of the parlour window
                     with a garland of flowers, naild a Rose-bush over the door, trimd up
                        Roberts<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn25" place="end" n="25">Robert Henry:
                        Bloomfield’s son, born 1807.</note> Hoop into a Garland and displayd it on a
                     pole from the Landing window.—In the evening lighted up about four score
                     Candle, and remove’d your old Richard and Kate<note resp="editors"
                        xml:id="ftn26" place="end" n="26">Presumably dolls named after the
                        characters in Bloomfield’s poem of that name in <title level="m">Rural
                           Tales</title>. </note> from the Mill, and with a White flag inscribed
                        <emph>peace</emph> mounted them on one of Barber’s Gin Kegs on a string
                     inside the parlour window, to the great amusement of the Boys. </ab><lb/>
                  <ab>Now my dear Girl you must absolutely come home <emph>this week</emph>, for
                     though Charlotte does all she can, we are in a <emph>muddle</emph> according to
                     your notions, thus far we have been starving upon bake’d Veal, Calve’s Liver,
                     Shoulder of Lamb and Goosbery pies. Charlotte has a Cold and sore throat.—
                     (letter 292, 4 July 1814)</ab><lb/></quote> Here Bloomfield’s evocation plays
               upon the shared knowledge he and Hannah, his daughter and correspondent, have of the
               people involved. If there is an occasional touch of sentimentality, this is because
               Bloomfield has a lot invested in his own and his family’s incorporation in the rural
               community. As the comparisons with London’s Vauxhall Gardens suggest, metropolitan
               entertainment remains a reference point: the country is engaged with and judged
               against the city. The country festival—the social expression of that community—and
               his description—its literary realization—dramatize the incorporation of incomers from
               London: they show the Bloomfields are at home, accepted in the village where the
               traditions of rural Englishness still flourish. Quietly in play in the letter is a
               self-consciousness about national identity: to be English, Bloomfield suggests, is to
               appreciate and participate in such bucolic communal pleasures. Hogarth’s “March of
               the Guards to Finchley,” Hone’s <title level="m">Every Day Book</title>, and
               Cobbett’s <title level="m">Rural Rides</title> present a similar comic vision of
               national character, in which ale-drinking figures loom large. As a small farmer, Cobbett
               would organize traditional rural sports on the village green, seeking to renew
               traditional English customs in which all rural classes participated, as a
               counterweight to the increasing class hostility between landlords and farmers on the
               one side and their laborers on the other.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn27"
                  place="end" n="27">On Cobbett and rural sports see Dyck, Thompson. On Hogarth and
                  Englishness see Uglow, Gatrell. On Hone and the <title level="m">Every Day
                     Book</title> see Hackwood. On ale-drinking and Englishness see Marchant.
               </note> Bloomfield is delighted to discover what Cobbett tried to revive, common
               customs both licensing and limiting the expression of appetite and eccentricity,
               ensuring the patriotic occasion remains jovial rather than riotous.</p>
            <p>Things changed after 1815. The depressions experienced nationwide by a newly
               centralized economy left Bloomfield and his family dependent on charity and poor
               relief, as they did so many others. Their era of mobility ended by poverty, Shefford
               became a place that Bloomfield often could not afford to leave: he stayed there
               isolated by ill-health and depression. Likewise his brother George became trapped in
               Suffolk, as is revealed in a late autobiographical letter sent by George some years
               after Robert died (to W. Weston, circa 1830). George’s response to his pauperdom is
               Uriah Heepish humility towards the gentlemen who gave him charity. His anger at the
               poverty he movingly describes is displaced instead onto other would-be laboring-class
               writers who come to visit him: <quote>I actualy became a corrispondant of Sir C
                  Bunbury Esq<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn28" place="end" n="28">Sir Thomas
                     Charles Bunbury, 6th Baronet, of Barton, Suffolk, MP for Suffolk 1790-1812.
                     Friend of George, Prince of Wales, keen patron of horseracing. Bunbury
                     recommended <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> to his friend the Duke of
                     York, who rewarded Bloomfield for his efforts with a “liberal sum.”</note> and
                  20 others, I do not mean that these persons wrote to me (they did not except Mr
                  Lofft) but were often sending queries by servants &amp;c which as I never would be
                  seen if I could help it caused me to lose much time and slur a great deal of
                  beautiful white paper, the private friendship and assistance I received from Bob
                  amply paid me for my loss of time &amp;c. and when they prevailed on me to be a
                     <emph>Master</emph> (in that which is now Mrs Armstrong the Hatters shop) my
                     <emph>Sheepishness</emph> increased so as to inspissate me, And besides it
                  pleased God to take from me my Excelant wife. The Gentlemen the Great friends of
                  my Brothers rais’d a subscription for me Mr Wright (once Recorder of this Borough)
                  set it of,) Mr Gedge, Sir C Bunbury, Capel Lofft Esq &amp;c joind raised upwards
                  of 30 pounds, still I was wretched, I had lost all my fireside comforts It was
                  soon discovered I was going to marry a young widow with 4 childrens!! And as I had
                  5 we had 9 to begin the world with, this imprudent step displeased some of my
                  great friends, But Mr Smith Sir C Bunbury, Mr gedge and many others continued to
                  be my Benefactors while they lived. In my second marriage I have had 3 children,
                  have (to late) been brought to my senses, In the 20 years that have past in my
                  present marriage I have seen most of my Brothers great friends removed by Death,
                  it is one of the great trials of those who live to be old, they outlive those they
                  love, and those who were able and wiling to help in Time of Need, were that
                  excelant man Mr Gedge or William Smith Esq Sir C Bunbury, Sir C Davers, Capel
                  Lofft &amp;c now alive old age would to me be disarmed of half its terrors here
                  are none to blame or to accuse, it is the lot of all the aged to out live their
                  friends and benefactors, I am truly grateful to kind providence, still Charles
                  Bloomfield Esq<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn29" place="end" n="29">Charles
                     Bloomfield (1762-1831) of Bury St. Edmunds, the grandson of Isaac Bloomfield
                     (died 1770—Bloomfield’s great-grandfather) by Isaac’s second wife, Susan Clift.
                  </note> lives, a man who did not know there were such a man as me in the world,
                  who on my Brothers account have been my sure protector and unwearied Benifactor
                  for 30 years, but for whome I must have been in a workhouse years ago; still how
                  precarious is my condition should providence remove him though Mr Hasted and other
                  Gentlemen have often befriended me yet I am at this instant, a poor feeble old man
                     <emph>allmost</emph> wholly dependant on Charity, I have Grand Children whom I
                  dearly love often nearly naked and bearfoot, and have not the power to help them,
                  And my Self in rags, for though I have clothes given me, my necessities send them
                  up the <emph>Spout</emph>, my natural Shyness makes me a recluse, for squallid
                  poverty soon pall the beholder, and seldom do I have a second visit from any one
                  unless it is Brassy faced pretenders to poesy, such as <emph>David Service</emph>
                  <emph>Ned Preston</emph>
                  <note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn30" place="end" n="30">David Service (?1776-?1828)
                     of Yarmouth, a shoemaker turned poet, who published several volumes of poetry.
                     Edward Bailey (Ned) Preston was a “Calligraphist” based in Barnwell, Cambridge,
                     whose work also took him to other places including Thetford. According to an
                     account of his life given to John Clare, following his time in the navy he had
                     lived “seven years” as a “planter” in the West Indies, before “losing all I
                     possesed [sic] in the tremendous hurricane of 1812.” A poet himself, Preston
                     wrote to and visited poets, including Bloomfield. Clare described him thus: “he
                     made me believe that he was a very great Poet and that he knew all the world
                     and that almost all the world knew him he had a vast quantity of M.S.S. he said
                     by him but had not published much at present . . .— he was for ever quoting
                     beautys from his own poetry and he knew all the living poets in England and
                     scotland as familiar as his own tongue—he was a living hoax—he had made two or
                     three visits to Bloomfield and talkd of him as familiar as if he had been his
                     neighbour half a life time he calld him ‘brother bob’” (123). </note> &amp;c
                  &amp;c who would willingly count up how many patches are on my old
                     <emph>Breeches</emph> (I beg pardon) I mean my <emph>Small Clothes</emph>,—now
                  had I been wise and prudent from 21 to 50 should I have been a poor Despicable
                  being, without the power of Doing any creature on Earth good!!! I had continued
                  health have not kep’d my bed for a single Day since I had the small pox in the
                  year 1765, was a good workman and found the greatest friendship from the wealthy
                  part of society, my present distresses arrise entirely from my too Eager persute
                  of information. (letter 423) </quote> Too poor to travel, reluctant to criticize
               the gentlemen landowners whom the Napoleonic wars had enriched, George Bloomfield
               found himself lonely and broken, regretting his literary ambitions but still
               compliant enough to write, at his patrons’ request, a poem condemning those of his
               class who, starving, were burning ricks to protest at the price of corn, kept high to
               profit landowners: <quote><lg>
                     <l>And, sons of Norfolk, proud in manhood’s boast,</l>
                     <l>Let not the honours of your name be lost;</l>
                     <l>But, cease, O cease, your sad misguided rage!</l>
                     <l>Blot not with guilt our fair historic page!</l>
                     <l>In <emph>manly fortitude</emph> sustain the blast— </l>
                     <l>The ills we suffer cannot will not last!</l>
                     <l>Since devastations evidently tend</l>
                     <l>To heighten woes they never can amend,</l>
                     <l>If want beset, if poverty enthral,</l>
                     <l>Consider those who had so <emph>far</emph> to fall;</l>
                     <l>Who, born to wealth, to every prospect fair,</l>
                     <l>Are sunk in gloom—in wretchedness—despair!</l>
                     <l>At death’s approach, would you at last be blest,</l>
                     <l>O, keep a living conscience in your breast!— </l>
                     <l>Soon, soon, will this terrific storm blow o’er;— </l>
                     <l>Believe my words, though I am old and poor! (“Friendly Hints”)<note
                           resp="editors" xml:id="ftn31" place="end" n="31">The text of the poem is
                           included in the Contextual Materials section of the Romantic Circles
                           edition <title level="m">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and his
                              Circle.</title>
                           &lt;http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/friendlyhints.html&gt;</note>
                     </l>
                  </lg></quote> George wrote these lines in 1831: they are a testament to the
               failure of the traditional rural community, its local paternalism shrunk to an empty
               gesture. They are also symptoms of changed times, as was Robert’s own correspondence
               with the husband of his friend and admirer, the gentlewoman Mary Lloyd Baker with
               whom he had toured the Wye valley in 1807. Mary having died in 1812, Lloyd Baker
               remarried and spent a fortune on building a new country seat for himself. He
               reentered Bloomfield’s life in 1821, sending a banknote to a poet now impoverished by
               his bookseller’s bankruptcy, but also in order to police him ideologically so as to
               ensure he did not agitate his fellow poor villagers: <quote><ab>I have heard lately
                     too with regret, that your health is not so good as we could wish it to be,
                     &amp; also that the failure of trade has been felt, &amp; I fear is still felt
                     by some parts of your family in common with many others. Allow me to request
                     your acceptance of the enclosed note for your use or theirs as you may think
                     right. . . . </ab><lb/>
                  <ab>Amongst other things which I have heard there is a report which nothing but a
                     sincere wish for your welfare should induce me to take the liberty of
                     mentioning to you. I have too high an opinion of you to give it credit, &amp;
                     therefore I have every hope that your answer will be full &amp; clear, &amp;
                     such as may enable me openly to contradict it. It has already occasioned you
                     the loss of some valuable friends; &amp; if not stopped, it will cause you to
                     lose the friendship of every man whose friendship is worth your
                     preserving.</ab><lb/>
                  <ab>We have long been aware of the unfortunate tendency of Mrs Bloomfield’s
                     religious opinions &amp; have lamented it, but it has been remarked that for
                     some time past <emph>neither yourself</emph> nor <emph>any of your
                        family</emph> have been in the habit of attending <emph>any place of worship
                        whatsoever</emph>. It has also been observed that you are in the habit of
                     reading some periodical works which are very hostile to the government of this
                     country. Perhaps from these two circumstances coupled together has originated
                     the idea that you have imbibed both Deistical &amp; Republican principles. The
                     latter tending to the subversion of that Government under which we have all
                     lived so long free from those calamities which have befallen almost every other
                     part of Europe—The former tending to the destruction of Christianity, &amp;
                     herein of <emph>every thing most valuable</emph> to us all (but most of all
                     endangering the eternal welfare of those who are unhappy enough to become its
                     Dupes) and both being so frequently united in the same persons—These
                     considerations have induced many of your friends &amp; patrons <emph>upon
                        principle</emph> to withhold from you their accustomed protection &amp;
                     assistance, thinking that by doing as they had done, &amp; as they still wish
                     to do, they should be giving countenance to a dangerous man. I cannot think
                     they are right. I cannot adopt such an opinion of you. In full hope that all
                     may be explained away, &amp; that you may again stand as high in the esteem of
                     your friends as the religious and moral tendency of your former life &amp;
                     works had placed you, I take advantage of being in your neighbourhood to give
                     you this information, &amp; to assure you that I shall have much pleasure in
                     making known to your former friends any answer to this letter which you may
                     think it right to favor me with for this purpose. (letter 351, 23 May
                     1821)</ab><lb/></quote> One-off aid comes with the threat of its withdrawal if
               Bloomfield does not agree to have his private life monitored to ensure its compliance
               with Tory and Evangelical, Church and State, conservatism. Bloomfield’s reply was
               dignified but firm: <quote><ab>I am glad to hear of my old friends at any time, but I
                     am sorry to hear of their coolling without sufficient information.—But
                        <emph>who</emph> are those who have coold? Who withheld their
                        <emph>accustom’d</emph> support &amp;c &amp;c—I have no
                        <emph>accustom’d</emph> support but the Duke of Grafton’s £15 per year, and
                     the ten pounds per ann for six years procured by Mrs Andrews Sharp. All the
                     rest has been casual as chance has directed it</ab><lb/>
                  <ab> When my subscription was going on many worthy hands assisted; the Earl of
                        Lonsdale,<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn32" place="end" n="32">The Earl of
                        Lonsdale: Lord Lowther, Wordsworth’s and Southey’s patron, a powerful Tory
                        landowner who controlled many MPs.</note> Mr Rogers,<note resp="editors"
                        xml:id="ftn33" place="end" n="33">Samuel Rogers, poet, wealthy banker, Whig.
                        He aided Bloomfield with advice, hospitality and by acting as banker for the
                        monies subscribed on Bloomfield’s behalf.</note> Lord Holland,<note
                        resp="editors" xml:id="ftn34" place="end" n="34">Henry Richard Fox, 3<hi
                           rend="sup">rd</hi> Baron Holland, Whig magnate and patron of the arts.
                        Fox was a nephew of Charles James Fox, the Whig leader and admirer of
                        Bloomfield’s verse.</note> and people of the most opposite opinions.</ab><lb/>
                  <ab> In the year 1800, (one and twenty years ago) I found that I must unavoidably
                     be brought before the public, raw and uncouth as I was, and I then made the
                     resolution—that I <emph>never would in public writing or intimate
                        correspondence enter into disputation or disquisition on the two grand
                        subjects which keep the world in agitation, Religion and politics. </emph>I
                     have kept my word or vow, and you will find that I can keep it. (letter 352, 25
                     May 1821)</ab><lb/></quote> Lloyd Baker was not satisfied. He wrote again,
               applying more pressure: if Bloomfield would declare he was “not hostile to the Church
               or Government of this country as each now exists, I am inclined to hope that
               something may yet be done for you” (letter 353, 29 May 1821). Bloomfield’s reply to
               this, a vindication of his private views, was, between the lines, furious:
                     <quote><ab>I say then there is not a man or woman living who would or could say
                     to <emph>my face</emph> that I have renounced the doctrines of Christ or his
                     Miracles.—There is not a soul upon earth to say “you are an enemy to the
                     government of your country” Fools, cannot they see that the <emph>form</emph>
                     of government of a country is rather different to the administration of it? . .
                     . </ab><lb/>
                  <ab> Cobbett and Hunt<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn35" place="end" n="35">Hunt:
                        Henry Hunt, radical campaigner for reform of parliament and of the
                        franchise. On 16 August 1819 Hunt had been arrested and many of the
                        supporters of reform whom he was addressing at a mass meeting in Manchester
                        killed. The Peterloo massacre, as it was called, caused popular protest
                        across the country. On 13 September Hunt returned to London, his trial
                        pending, to be met by huge cheering crowds, a procession and welcoming
                        committee. Bloomfield feared encountering “Hunts mob” in the streets.</note>
                     are men whom I would not trust with power; they are too eager to obtain
                     it.—Universal suffrage is an impracticable piece of nonscense;—Republicanism
                     will only do in <emph>new</emph> establishd countrys: not in those which have
                     been govern’d by Kings for a thousand years.— </ab><lb/>
                  <ab> It is the natural bent and practice of <emph>party</emph> to go to extreems.
                     Thus they could not let me rest even on the intermediate shelf of Scepticism
                     but made me a Deist at once!!—I have been in the presence of great and
                        <emph>good</emph> men, the Bishops Watson and Porteous,<note resp="editors"
                        xml:id="ftn36" place="end" n="36">Bishops Watson and Porteous: the Rt. Revd.
                        Richard Watson (1737-1816) was a clergyman and academic, who served as the
                        Bishop of Llandaff from 1782 to 1816. His 1796 <title level="m">An Apology
                           for the Bible</title>, a work written in response to the 1795 publication
                        of the second part of Thomas Paine’s <title level="m">Age of Reason</title>,
                        defended orthodox Christianity and the established church. In return,
                        Wordsworth wrote (but did not publish) his <title level="m">Letter to the
                           Bishop of Llandaff</title>, attacking Watson and supporting Paine. The
                        Rt. Revd. Beilby Porteous (d. 1809), Bishop of London, notable preacher,
                        supporter of the Evangelical movement and the Anti-Slavery campaign,
                        opponent of Paine and revolutionary radicalism.</note> but then it is
                     equally true that I have taken snuff with Horne Tooke, and have held
                     conversation with Hardy the Boot maker, who was tried for high treason!<note
                        resp="editors" xml:id="ftn37" place="end" n="37">John Horne Tooke
                        (1736-1812) was, by 1800, already a veteran campaigner for parliamentary
                        reform. Initially radicalized by the establishment efforts to exclude
                        newly-elected John Wilkes from parliament, Horne Tooke became an organizer
                        of societies dedicated to widening suffrage—including the Society for
                        Constitutional Information. He was arrested and charged with treason in 1794
                        when, in alliance with the London Corresponding Society, he attempted to
                        organize a radical convention. Acquitted, despite the bias of the judge, he
                        continued to argue for parliamentary reform, though in more moderate form.
                        Thomas Hardy (1752-1832), like Bloomfield a London shoemaker, was a
                        campaigner for parliamentary reform and the extension of the franchise. As
                        an organizer of the London Corresponding Society he, like Horne Tooke, was
                        tried for treason in 1794. Although acquitted, he lost his wife and unborn
                        child—both died in childbirth brought on prematurely by the stress of
                        fleeing from a pro-government mob. After his release from custody, Hardy
                        gave up politics and carried on his trade in Covent Garden.</note>—Yea, more
                     than all this, I had the misfortune to be born only six miles from the
                     birthplace of Tom Paine!! This, to some ears would be horrible!—I shall go to
                     worship again when I am well enough; and when my dear Daughter and Sons can
                     leave me in the company of a Woman whom you know little about, they will go
                     too. (letter 354, 31 May-1 June 1821)</ab><lb/></quote></p>
            <ab>(See also Peter Denney’s comments on these exchanges.)</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p> Letters of the Lloyd Baker kind are grim evidence of the ideological strife of
               post-war Britain: they place in stark illumination the repression by which the ruling
               classes maintained their grip on power, all the while fearing revolution. Bloomfield
               remembered the disinterested patronage of the old Duke of Grafton, Prime Minister in
               an earlier era, who had supported him as a fellow Suffolk man without ever expecting
               political or religious conformity to his views, or even public praise of his
               beneficence. He knew he was living through a reactionary era, in which the classes
               were polarized, and his public response was to create, in his final collection of
               poems <title level="m">May Day with the Muses</title> (1822), an ideal scenario in
               which, to celebrate the traditional May Day festivities, a squire invites the
               villagers to recite poems about village life. The squire thus renews old customs and
               patronizes, in the best sense, rustics who are able to voice their rural experience
               as verse. Clearly, this is wish-fulfillment on Bloomfield’s part: not only does he
               imagine that to be a rural poet is to be a cherished villager and vice versa, but
               also that poetry is a face-to-face oral activity of a united community. The
               benevolent squire, moreover, respects tradition and exacts no political toll for his
               benevolence, which he in fact regards as his duty. Meanwhile, the individual poems
               that the villagers recite also tell of a traditional community in which authority is
               vested in a single figure who can therefore be addressed, appealed to, and even,
               potentially, rebuked and chastised face to face. In the earlier verse-tale “The
               Broken Crutch,” Bloomfield had contemplated the possibility of just such a rebuke,
               should the squire turn out to be abusing the innocence of a village girl. In the
               event, the squire’s intentions are pure: he marries her, and her uncle does not need
               to beat him. The ideal village, for Bloomfield, is self-policing: the squire respects
               his tenants and they him. This was an old-fashioned and forlorn hope, perhaps, in
               face of the capitalization of farming, but it was one to which the conservative
               Wordsworth, Southey, and Gilpin, also subscribed as did the radical Cobbett—a
               Romantic rural paternalism.</p>
            <p>Bloomfield’s only public political discourse was his poetry. His claim to Lloyd Baker
               that he had kept a vow to make no declarations of opinion was true. Not a political
               thinker, he refused to become involved in radical writing and publishing, not
               necessarily through lack of sympathy but because radicals’ forthright and frank
               avowals seemed to him too exclusive of doubt, difference, and ambiguity, too easily
               certain and too egotistic. Like Clare in “To a Fallen Elm,” he resented radical
               campaigners’ assumption that because they were of his class they necessarily spoke
               for him, and he suspected their motives might include self-promotion. Despite,
               therefore, his private conversations with Horne Tooke and Hardy, men tried for
               treason for their radical campaigning, he was sharply critical of Thomas Paine when
               Paine’s disciple and bookseller, Thomas Clio Rickman, presumed, in an over-familiar
               way, that he would be keen to have him sell his poems: <quote>All your writings are
                  so confoundedly violent, that I who have four years past made a determination to
                  be nutral in Politicks and Religion, have much ado to convince myself that you
                  ought to expect much assistance from such a cowardly fellow. And it is because I
                  differ in both the above particulars from the Author you first put into my hands,
                  that I do not feel myself acting a consistant part in spreading his opinions. Mr
                  P[aine] in my estimation is the vainest of all authors. My circle of friends have
                  long ago regreted that his great mind should decend so as to disgust his readers
                  by boasting of himself. Perhaps when he laments the falling off of America from
                  her purity of principle he is only lamenting the utterly unavoidable effects of a
                  growing population there, or elsewhere, I believe that if perfect Republicanism be
                  not a dream, its durability is. I am thus commiting myself to you compleatly; but
                  it is to show you that I cannot propagate doctrines which I do not profess either
                  to believe or to understand. <emph>I must and will</emph> be as
                     <emph>private</emph> a Man as pastoral poetry will permit me to be, or subjects
                  that involve not creeds and systems of which all the world knows I have had small
                  means of judging. You are fond of frankness, of which you set an example both in
                  your writings and your manners. You will therefore not be offended or surprized
                  that I should follow it (letter 129, 29 May 1804)</quote></p>
            <p>The abiding theme of Bloomfield’s correspondence is the control of his own words—the
               very issue that most plagued his admirer John Clare. Writing freed him from wage
               labor for sixteen hours per day as a shoemaker. In terms of time, life habits, and
               money it gave him a precarious independence as an agent on a newly capitalized
               popular publishing market. It also subjected him to the pressures of the market while
               at the same time he was not free from the expectations of the patrons who had helped
               get <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> published. His most hands-on patron was
               the Suffolk gentleman Capel Lofft, who expected, as the price for the advice and
               literary connections he made available to Bloomfield, to have his own views published
               in the form of prefaces and notes to the poems. These views embarrassed Bloomfield:
               Lofft included irrelevant and vain justifications of his own political conduct in the
               Preface to <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> and added ridiculously fulsome
               and insipid commentary in footnotes to <title level="m">Rural Tales. </title>The
               booksellers responded to public demand and sought the removal of these notes in the
               second edition; Lofft, insulted, insisted they remain. Bloomfield, caught between
               patron and market, tried in letter after letter to negotiate with both, while
               maintaining his own dignity. Ultimately, to his own anguish, he failed: Lofft chose
               to sulk, regarding himself as betrayed, and Bloomfield lost his first supporter,
               despite a willingness to compromise to a degree. But he would neither simply
               acquiesce to Lofft’s will nor toady to him: he retained his independence but at a
               cost that showed him forcefully that his writing was the subject of competition by
               others. Bloomfield was, his letters reveal, caught in what we now know was a
               transitional stage from the eighteenth-century norm of publishing under patronage,
               with subscribers funding the work, to the nineteenth-century convention of selling
               via publishers to a mass market. Caught between patrons’ and booksellers’ demands, he
               struggled to retain possession of his own writerly self, to avoid becoming alienated
               from his own dearest words. Even well-meaning patrons pressured him, assuming it
               their prerogative to intervene on his behalf (as they thought) without first asking
               him. Thus the wealthy patron Lord Buchan, whose salon Bloomfield had visited in 1802,
               sent in 1806 to Bloomfield’s publishers, a private letter Bloomfield had written to
               him after the visit, in which Bloomfield confesses his shyness in polite company and
               apologizes for breaking down into tears. Buchan requested the publishers to include
               it in <title level="m">Wild Flowers</title> along with Buchan’s own description of
               the occasion, so as to promote the sale. The private letter reveals Bloomfield’s
               insecurity about appearing before his social superiors: <quote>It may look strange
                  that one, who has been repeatedly honoured with your lordship’s conversation,
                  should have anything left to express by writing: But the sudden transition from
                  shade to sunshine, from obscurity to publicity, which have fallen to my lot, has
                  sometimes proved almost painful, and often perplexing to a great degree.
                  Condescension from superiors ought at least to inspire confidence sufficient to
                  meet their approbation in all its shapes and modifications; and, when it does not,
                  I am apt to suspect, that it deserves no such plausible name as modesty. It is a
                  dastardly child, the offspring of ignorance and fear. I feel and know, that in my
                  composition there is not an atom of what is called wit. My replies are the slow
                  suggestions of contemplation, and my “good things” mostly come half an hour too
                  late. I find this to be true in conversation with my equals, where restraint can
                  have no force. There is however, another enemy (though in some cases my dearest
                  friend) whose power is resistless, and whose visits are perpetually made known by
                  a rising of the stomack, and a redundance of water in the eyes. Subjects of
                  interest to the feelings are frequent in parties, such as I have lately had the
                  honour to join; when, independent of the subject being often above my reach, I
                  find this weakness, (if it be a weakness) stand in my way, and absolutely obstruct
                  any remark or reply whatever. (letter 75, 19 January 1802)</quote> When Bloomfield
               heard from the publishers of Buchan’s request to publish their private
               correspondence, he politely insisted on retaining control of his own words and on
               succeeding on his own merits, without the cachet provided by publishing letters of
               recommendation from the socially powerful. He would not risk appearing to be a
               creature of a Lord who had solicited for favor—an honorable decision which it
               required considerable temerity, considering the disparity in rank between Buchan and
               himself, to make: <quote>To adopt your plan, great and honourable as it is, would
                  involve consequences that I cannot explain. One of the most difficult tasks that
                  arises from my extraordinary situation, for such perhaps with great truth I may
                  call it, is so to act as not to wound the feelings of my good and voluntary
                  friends, nor to violate my own. The Letter I long ago addrest to your Lordship is
                  such perhaps as I ought not to be ashamed of, and such that no person would
                  believe me did I pretend to it. But though I feel the intended honour, I feel too,
                  other sensations that many perhaps could suppress: I feel that it would be a
                  violation of my notions of delicacy to print it now. My object has been to abide
                  by the most simple methods of acquiring reputation, the standing alone, as far as
                  my abilities go, and as far as it can be done in justice to my friends. Thus it
                  has happened that of the many letters which I have had from his Grace the Duke of
                  Grafton, Sir C Bunbury &amp;c, one from the Duke of York, and one from that most
                  great, and most lamented man, Mr Fox,<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn38"
                     place="end" n="38">Charles James Fox (1749-1806), Whig leader and admirer of
                     pastoral verse, both in the classical languages and in English. Like
                     Bloomfield, Wordsworth sent a presentation copy of his rural poems <title
                        level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title> to Fox.</note> that none of them have been
                  made use of, though, as well as those from your Lordship of a nature highly to be
                  prized, they would have made a proud and conspicuous figure attach’d to any one of
                  my publications. I know not which most to admire, your Lordships candour in
                  stating your opinion of my poems, or your long remembrance of one so distant, and
                  so much longer silent than your kind letters formerly would fairly warrant.
                  (letter 191, 15 September 1806)</quote> Independence was indeed a delicate matter,
               almost impossible for the laboring-class writer to sustain. But Bloomfield was
               adamant, reserving his contempt for his elder brother George, on whom he had once
               depended, when George would not stand up for him but instead toadied to Capel Lofft:
                  <quote>that man would listen to Tom Cat if he could flatter him, so dont pretend
                  that you are too obscure and too humble to be able to do mischief. (whether
                  intended or not.) Were I to take it as a risible subject, there is abundance of
                  room for can anyone conceive a poor fellow more universally loaded with hangers
                  on! There is something in that same letter of yours respecting . . . which from
                     Nats<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn39" place="end" n="39">Nathaniel (Nat)
                     Bloomfield (1759-1831): Bloomfield’s brother, a tailor by trade and a poet who
                     published <title level="m">An Essay on War; Honington Green, a Ballad . . . and
                        Other Poems</title> (1803).</note> and my own sentiments differ so horribly
                  that I think I shall one day send it you with a few notes, that you may see if I
                  have understood it right or wrong’d you when I deem’d you a turntail and a
                  shufler. (letter 186, undated [after May 1806])</quote> After this, a once
               frequent and friendly correspondence between the brothers lapsed for seventeen years.
               Bloomfield wrote again only when he knew he was gravely ill. He had not been able to
               preserve his family intact in face of the social pressures that authorship produced. </p>
            <p>He found compensation—for some years—in the friendship of a gentle family of an
               unusual kind. The Sharp family was a philanthropic one, the best known of whom was
               Granville, the anti-slavery campaigner. It was, however, through the younger
               generation, a network of sisters and wives, that Bloomfield entered the extended
               circle. The married sister, Mary Lloyd Baker, wrote to him admiringly of his poetry
               and soon he was invited to the family’s houses in Hertfordshire, Gloucestershire, and
               Northamptonshire. There he was delighted to find admiring female company that made no
               demands upon him. The Sharp women<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn40" place="end"
                  n="40">Bloomfield’s principal friend was Mary Lloyd Baker, née Sharp (1778-1812),
                  whom he met in the company of her cousin Catherine Sharp (1770-1843) at her aunt’s
                  (Elizabeth Prowse, née Sharp) of Wicken Park, Northamptonshire. Daughter of the
                  surgeon William Sharp and niece of Granville Sharp the abolitionist, Mary
                  introduced Bloomfield to her extended family, allowing him to make visits to the
                  houses of family members at South Mimms, Northamptonshire and Fulham as well as
                  her own house at Uley in Gloucestershire.</note> neither sought to ride on the
               back of his writing nor to make him perform for them. In their company he relaxed,
               flirting and joking at their country houses. And since the women were not heads of
               the households they did not concern themselves with money and social authority as
               gentlemen did. Bloomfield was able to feel valued as part of sisterly and feminine
               world based on nature-love. The women appreciated poetry; they sketched; they toured
               the Wye valley, taking Bloomfield with them. In accessing the rural world through
               them, Bloomfield experienced it differently: it was not the countryside he met on his
               solitary pedestrian tours, nor the Suffolk village world of work and customs that he
               hoped to rediscover in Shefford, but a feminized world of beauty disinterestedly
               appreciated and shared at leisure. Bloomfield flourished in it, and was freed to
               exercise his talent for flirtatious humour, as a letter of 22 June 1804 reveals:
                     <quote><ab>The micrometer you will see is scratch’d into squares so minute that
                     each square form’d by the intersections is but the <emph>ten thousandth
                        part</emph> of an inch. I hope you will not feel any disappointment as to
                     its convenience or powers for I know that my manner of speaking of what pleases
                     me, is apt to make others feel a blank. Yet I think your own good sense and
                     your admirable perseverance will enable you to appreciate its merits, and thus
                     I have no doubt as to the pleasure you may derive from so pleasing an insight
                     into nature with so little trouble.—You have three ranges of objects as part of
                     your purchase, but if I might direct your attention I could point out others,
                     as for example—take your <emph>pride</emph> (which, by reason that you had no
                     microscope when I was with you I could never see at all) and place it
                     consciously in a good light:—but as such objects to the naked eye are so
                     disgusting I doubt this would give you but little pleasure if you should place
                     the glass so as to find it—secondly you may endeavour with the small spring
                     tweezers to place your <emph>affectation</emph> in the focus of the magnifier
                     by which means you will at once determine the power of the instrument, as you
                     will then have an object absolutely never seen before. It may be put to another
                     use still, whenever any man shall approach you with a view of sharing your
                     affection and your heart you may immediately put all the best of his virtues
                     into the insect-box and when you have magnified them to your liking give him
                     your hand.— </ab><lb/>
                  <ab>The kindness of yourself and your most affectionate Mother to me, has left on
                     my mind those impressions and feelings which virtue and goodness will and must
                     for ever inspire, I love you both. May your hearts never know sorrow and, and
                     &amp;c &amp;c I was going to flourish, but had better only beg that you will
                     both believe me to be your most sincere and humble servant. (letter
                  134)</ab><lb/></quote> The many letters to the Sharp sisters may prompt us to a
               new perspective on Bloomfield in particular and laboring-class poets in general—a
               perspective showing that he and they flourished in a feminized literary and social
               milieu that was itself growing rapidly, as female readers valued nature-writing and
               as more and more female poets popularized a kind of poetry that was not associated
               with the kind favored by ruling-class men—neither with classical genres, nor
               political satire, nor the representation of patrons’ country estates. Bloomfield, as
               revealed for the first time by his correspondence, was not simply a “peasant poet”
               chiefly valuable for his portrait of labor and for his symbolic position as the voice
               of the laboring classes. He was a varied—and often comic—writer of intimate prose and
               verse whose articulations of the struggles he faced are valuable not simply as
               symptoms of the dilemmas faced by laboring-class writers, or as illustrations of the
               social world he inhabited, but also—and principally—as sensitive, honest, innovative,
               and successful negotiations of the consequences, for one in his marginal position on
               the edge of both, of the changing relationship between country and city, and masters
               and markets.</p>
            <div type="citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>

               <listBibl>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Bloomfield, George</author>
                        <title level="a">Friendly Hints Affectionately Addressed, By An Old Man To
                           The Labouring Poor Of Suffolk And Norfolk: Occasioned by reading the
                           Accounts of the poor deluded Men who have suffered at Norwich and
                           Ipswich, for burning Corn Stacks, &amp;c</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Broadside</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Bury St. Edmunds</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy. A Rural Poem</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1800</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">Rural Tales, Ballads and Songs</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1802</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">Wild Flowers; or, Pastoral and Local Poetry</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1806</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">The Remains of Robert Bloomfield</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Joseph Weston</editor>
                        <edition>2 vols</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1824</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and his Circle</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Tim Fulford</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
                     </analytic>
                        <monogr><title level="m"><ref
                              target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters/">Romantic
                              Circles Electronic Editions</ref></title>
                        <imprint>
                           <publisher><ref target="http://www.rc.umd.edu">Romantic Circles</ref></publisher>
                           <date>2009</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Clare, John</author>
                        <title level="m">By Himself</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Eric Robinson</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">David Powell</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Ashington and Manchester</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Mid-Northumberland Arts Group and Carcanet Press</publisher>
                           <date>1996</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Dyck, Ian</author>
                        <title level="m">William Cobbett and Rural Popular Culture</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>1992</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Gatrell, Vic</author>
                        <title level="m">City of Laughter: Sex and Satire in Eighteenth-Century
                           London</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Atlantic</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Hackwood, Frederick William</author>
                        <title level="m">William Hone: His Life and Times</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>T. Fisher Unwin</publisher>
                           <date>1912</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Hitchcock, Tim</author>
                        <title level="m">Down and Out in Eighteenth-Century London</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Hambledon and London</publisher>
                           <date>2004</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Jarvis, Robin</author>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Writing and Pedestrian Travel</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Macmillan</publisher>
                           <date>1997</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Marchant, Ian</author>
                        <title level="m">The Longest Crawl: Being an Account of a Journey through an
                           Intoxicated Landscape, or a Child’s Treasury of Booze</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Bloomsbury</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Roe, Nicholas</author>
                        <title level="m">John Keats and the Culture of Dissent</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                           <date>1997</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Thompson, E. P</author>
                        <title level="m">Customs in Common</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Merlin</publisher>
                           <date>1991</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Uglow, Jenny</author>
                        <title level="m">Hogarth: A Life and a World</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Faber and Faber</publisher>
                           <date>1997</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Wordsworth, William</author>
                        <title level="m">The Prelude: The Four Texts (1798, 1799, 1805,
                           1850)</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Jonathan Wordsworth</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Penguin</publisher>
                           <date>1995</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
