<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Robert Bloomfield: The Inestimable Blessing of Letters</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">Introduction: The Inestimable Blessing of letters</title>
            <author>
               <name>John Goodridge</name>
               <name>Bridget Keegan</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">John Goodridge</editor>
            <editor role="editor">Bridget Keegan</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.goodridge-keegan</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2010-11-01">March 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                  <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                     prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                  <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                     their current ones.</item>
               </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Introduction: The Inestimable Blessing of letters</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Goodridge</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Bridget</forename>
                        <surname>Keegan</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Robert Bloomfield:</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-03-01">March 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#226;&#8364;&#339;,"
                  for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>                         
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>                         
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>                         
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>                         
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
            <keywords scheme="http://www.rc.umd.edu/#tags">
               <list>
                  <item>Robert Bloomfield's letters document one artist’s struggles (and sometimes
                     his victories) to share his unique voice and vision; the online publication of
                     his extant letters (a companion to this collection of essays) reveals new and
                     exciting insights into Bloomfield the artist and the man. The essays included
                     in this collection highlight and draw attention to aspects of Bloomfield's
                     literary production that would likely not be possible without the full access
                     to his letters that the edition provides, and make a strong case for why
                     Bloomfield continues to be worthy of study. They suggest how much more remains
                     to be said about this prolific poet. </item>
                  <item>Robert Bloomfield</item>
                  <item>labouring-class writing</item>
                  <item>landscape</item>
                  <item>letters</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2010-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay"><head>
            <title level="a">Editors’ Introduction: The Inestimable Blessing of letters</title>
         </head>
         
            <byline><docAuthor>John Goodridge and Bridget Keegan</docAuthor> <affiliation>Nottingham Trent University and Creighton University</affiliation></byline>
         
         <epigraph><quote><p rend="noCount">How can we consistently praise the inestimable blessing of letters and not wish to
            extend it?</p>
            <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent8"><bibl> - Robert to George Bloomfield, 30 May 1802</bibl></p></quote></epigraph>
            
         <p>This enthusiastic comment from the poet Robert Bloomfield to his older brother reflects
            one of the more varied and vigorous letter-writing sensibilities of the Romantic period,
            one that has hitherto been neglected, but is now gloriously showcased by the new online
            collection of the letters of Bloomfield and his circle, to which the present collection
            of essays forms a companion volume.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn1" place="foot" n="1">
               
                  <title level="m">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and his Circle</title>. Ed. Tim Fulford and
                  Lynda Pratt. <title level="s">Romantic Circles Electronic Editions,</title> 2009.
                  (http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters). These letters are cited
                  throughout the present collection of essays in short form, by their letter number
                  and, as appropriate, by their author, recipient and date.
            </note> Unlike many other eighteenth- and nineteenth-century laboring-class poets,
            Robert Bloomfield was able to sustain and develop his publishing career. While none of
            his subsequent publications received the acclaim of his debut poem, <title level="m">The Farmer’s
               Boy</title> (1800), after his initial success Bloomfield rightfully considered himself
            a professional author for the remainder of his life. His letters, made available to a
            modern audience for the first time with this online edition, document one artist’s
            struggles (and sometimes his victories) to share his unique voice and vision. Even
            though Bloomfield’s published legacy is rich and varied, the publication of his extant
            letters, as well as additional letters to and about him, reveals new and exciting
            insights into Bloomfield the artist and the man. Bloomfield in his letters demonstrates
            his active and thoughtful engagement with the London literary scene, with the broader
            literary culture of his day, and with his fellow laboring-class poets. The letters also
            provide a fascinating historical resource for those interested in the lives of the
            members of an extended laboring-class family, as they negotiated the new forms of
            mobility available to them in the early nineteenth-century, both geographic and
            intellectual.</p>
         <p>Although some of Bloomfield’s correspondence was made available in Joseph Weston’s 1824
               <title level="m">Remains</title>, and some in W. W. Hart's <title level="m">Selections of the Correspondence
               of Robert Bloomfield</title> (London, 1870; reprinted Redhill, Surrey, 1968), Tim
            Fulford and Lynda Pratt’s electronic edition offers a comprehensive and
            easily-searchable resource for anyone wishing to know more about Bloomfield and his
            personal and literary milieu. The letters and complementary texts offer insight into the
            poet’s larger literary concerns as well as his more quotidian activities. They include
            reflections on his creative process as well as detailed accounts of his personal
            finances. In short, the letters enable modern readers to better understand what made
            Bloomfield one of the best-selling poets of the early Romantic period, and they offer a
            compelling argument about the intellectual value of the recovery and study of
            laboring-class literary culture in general. The essays included in this collection
            highlight and draw attention to aspects of Bloomfield's literary production that would
            likely not be possible without the full access to his letters that this edition
            provides. As Tim Fulford notes in his introduction to the letters, Bloomfield's
            significance to the Romantic period has only recently begun to be reevaluated, and the
            following essays further the project of enriching our understanding of the poet's
            significance within a wide range of contexts. </p>
         <p>One particular epistolary exchange, highlighted in four of the essays, illustrates how
            the correspondence enables us to rethink Bloomfield’s consequence to literary history.
            This is the series of letters between Bloomfield and T. J. Lloyd Baker, one of the
            poet’s many “friends” throughout his career. Bloomfield had enjoyed a long relationship
            with Lloyd Baker, his wife Mary, and his wife’s family, the Sharps, including joining
            them on the trip along the Wye that formed the basis of Bloomfield’s ambitious long
            poem. (Among the more noteworthy members of the Sharp family was Mary's uncle, the
            celebrated abolitionist Granville Sharp, another interesting connection for the poet.)
            The exchange of 1821 is exemplary of the tensions between the public and the private,
            the personal and the professional that were particularly fraught for poets of
            laboring-class origins. Bloomfield had to negotiate these tensions throughout his
            career, and, as this series of letters reveal, his patience had begun to fray. </p>
         <p>While Bloomfield was burdened throughout his life with significant difficulties, he did
            not fit many of the stereotypes often associated with the cult of “natural genius” that
            affected the reception of so many other poets with plebeian origins, including early
            tragic death and chronic mental or physical illness, although as Peter Denney suggests,
            common ideas about original genius gave Bloomfield a potential justification for
            refusing to air any political opinions. But like other poets of his class (most notably
            John Clare), because Bloomfield’s first major poem was “semi”-autobiographical (as Ian
            Haywood discusses), much of the initial interest in the work was based as much upon
            curiosity about the author as appreciation for the work. And polite readers had certain
            expectations about what laboring-class poets should and should not say—both publicly and
            privately. These expectations are transparent in Lloyd Baker’s letter, which castigates
            Bloomfield for holding political and religious views that could be considered “radical.”
            Bloomfield’s rightfully indignant response helps to reveal some of the shifts in the
            poet’s understanding of what expectations could be legitimately imposed upon him. A
            similar transformation of patron-poet relations is evident in the study of earlier
            laboring-class poets, including Ann Yearsley and James Woodhouse. While Lloyd Baker’s
            letters demonstrate the late survival of the old patronage system well into the
            Romantic period, Bloomfield’s responses indicate just how far the poet’s sense of his
            professional identity—and his personal rights—had altered in the twenty years since his
            debut publication. These four letters touch on civil and creative liberties, family
            relations, the right to privacy in politics and religion. They challenge the more irenic
            presentation of the good-natured and well-behaved shoemaker poet that has perhaps made
            Bloomfield less enticing to modern critics who (like the poet’s contemporary audience)
            seem more drawn to writers whose lives embody more thrilling catastrophe or controversy. </p>
         <p>The essays in this companion collection elaborate upon the themes encapsulated in the
            letters discussed above<hi> </hi>and make a strong case for why Bloomfield continues to
            be worthy of study. They also suggest how much more remains to be said about this
            prolific poet. Tim Fulford’s essay, which opens the collection, demonstrates that
            contrary to most caricatures of the isolated Romantic genius, Bloomfield’s letters show
            his intense sociability. Fulford highlights some of the key themes and motifs from 426
            letters available in the edition. He challenges the view of Bloomfield as a strictly
            “rural” figure, elaborating upon his engagement in urban—and more
               significantly—<emph>suburban</emph> life. Nevertheless, the letters reveal too
            Bloomfield’s dedication to keeping alive village traditions important to himself and his
            family, and provide a degree of lively ethnographic detail of various popular customs,
            festivals, and pastimes. Bloomfield engages in nature-tourism like fellow early
            Romantics such as Coleridge, but his letters describing his clerical toils anticipate
            Victorian scenes such as those Dickens depicts in <title level="m">Great Expectations.</title> Regardless of the subject matter, as Fulford demonstrates, “[t]he abiding theme
            of Bloomfield’s correspondence is the control of his own words.” While Bloomfield was as
            besieged as any laboring-class poet by various patrons throughout his career, his
            letters show his skill in negotiating a variety of difficult social and financial
            transactions. His perspicacity, intelligence, and commitment to his art are continually
            underscored in his correspondence.</p>
         <p>Following Fulford, Ian Haywood offers what may be the riskiest and most iconoclastic—but
            also the most provocative and productive—reading of Bloomfield to date. While other
            critics have hinted at some of the potentially darker elements in Bloomfield’s work,
            Haywood uses a psycho-biographical approach to uncover the underside of the more
            congenial and complacent public image that Bloomfield (or at least his patrons) wanted
            to project. Focusing in particular upon the remarkable passage describing the slaughter
            of the lambs in <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title>, Haywood argues that this dramatic primal
            scene provides a key into a persistent pattern of mental anguish and psychic struggle
            that the pastoral façade of much of Bloomfield’s writing would seem to disguise. Like
            Fulford, Haywood asks us to look beyond a conventional reading of the rurality of
               <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> and to see in the georgic moments of violence
            evocations of contemporary events such as the 1798 Irish rebellion. Haywood integrates
            information from the letters into his reading of the poem to reveal degrees of
            ambivalence, anxiety, and guilt heretofore largely ignored in Bloomfield’s writing,
            offering insight into the possible shadow side of the seeming bucolic bliss ostensibly
            celebrated in the text.</p>
         <p>While Haywood looks to possible political allegories embedded in the scenes of animal
            slaughter, Peter Denney’s essay takes up the question of Bloomfield’s politics and
            explores this dimension explicitly. Bloomfield’s avowed refusal to discuss politics or
            religion in his poetry sets up an immediate roadblock for such an analysis, but by
            framing his discussion of any political dimension of Bloomfield’s writing within the
            parameters of cultural expectations surrounding “natural” or “original” genius, Denney
            is able to complicate productively our understanding of Bloomfield’s own nuanced sense
            of his relationship to the pressing social questions of his day. </p>
         <p>Finally, Bridget Keegan focuses on some of the literary texts made available along with
            the letters in the Fulford and Pratt online edition, namely Bloomfield’s writing for
            children. These seemingly “simple” works also embed a degree of social and political
            complexity that the other contributors have similarly highlighted in their essays. For
            example, while the moralistic plot of <title level="m">Little Davy’s New Hat</title> might seem yet
            another fairy tale of virtuous poverty rewarded, Bloomfield incorporates concrete
            details evoking the famines of the 1790s. And the charming letters of <title level="m">The Bird and
               Insects’ Post Office</title> evince the same ambivalence about violence toward animals
            that Haywood draws attention to in <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title>. Keegan aims to show
            that Bloomfield’s efforts in the genre of children’s literature are of a piece with his
            other writing—both published and personal. </p>
         <p>Far from providing the definitive reading of the letters and new materials made
            available in this edition, these essays attempt to further enrich the critical
            discussion of Bloomfield’s significance, modeling the variety of ways in which his work
            might be approached and the wealth of possible future readings that are possible through
            access to this larger body of his writing. Having, together with Simon White, edited and
            published the first modern collection of critical essays on Bloomfield in 2006, we are
            delighted to see how much these letters have added to current knowledge of this
            important poet, and fully anticipate that the letters and the critical conversation they
            have begun to inspire here will lead to future work and inspire other scholars of the
            period to investigate Bloomfield’s rich <emph>oeuvre</emph>, one that is becoming
            increasingly central to the discussion of the Romantic cultural and social
            environment.</p>
         <p rend="noCount">The editors would like to acknowledge the generous assistance of Jill Havlat and Krystal
            Kirwan who helped with the final preparation of these essays for publication. Bridget
            Keegan would also like to thank Gail Jensen, Dean of the Graduate School at Creighton
            University, for a small grant to help in the production of these essays. </p></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
