<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Robert Bloomfield: The Inestimable Blessing of Letters</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">Bloomfield’s Writing for Children</title>
            <author>
               <name>Bridget Keegan</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">John Goodridge</editor>
            <editor role="editor">Bridget Keegan</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.keegan</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2010-11-01">March 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Bloomfield’s Writing for Children</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Bridget</forename>
                        <surname>Keegan</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Robert Bloomfield:</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-03-01">March 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#226;&#8364;&#339;,"
                  for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
            <keywords scheme="http://www.rc.umd.edu/#tags">
               <list>
                  <item>Robert Bloomfield's letters document one artist’s struggles (and sometimes
                     his victories) to share his unique voice and vision; the online publication of
                     his extant letters (a companion to this collection of essays) reveals new and
                     exciting insights into Bloomfield the artist and the man. The essays included
                     in this collection highlight and draw attention to aspects of Bloomfield's
                     literary production that would likely not be possible without the full access
                     to his letters that the edition provides, and make a strong case for why
                     Bloomfield continues to be worthy of study. They suggest how much more remains
                     to be said about this prolific poet. </item>
                  <item>Robert Bloomfield</item>
                  <item>children's literature</item>
                  <item>laboring-class writing</item>
                  <item>The History Little Davy's New Hat</item>
                  <item>The Bird and Insects' Post Office</item>
                  <item>charity</item>
                  <item>representation of animals</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2010-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>Bloomfield’s Writing for Children</head>


            <byline><docAuthor>Bridget Keegan</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>Creighton University</affiliation></byline>

            <p>Robert Bloomfield twice wrote works explicitly for a juvenile audience. <title
                  level="m">The History of Little Davy’s New Hat</title> was first published in 1815
               and had gone through three separate editions by 1824. <title level="m">The Bird and
                  Insects’ Post-Office, </title>which he was writing with his son Charles at the
               time of his death, was published posthumously in Bloomfield’s <title level="m"
                  >Remains</title> (1824). To my knowledge, only Jonathan Lawson’s critical
               biography (1980) has given these works any attention and then only of the briefest
               sort. Tim Fulford and Lynda Pratt’s online edition of Bloomfield’s correspondence
               amply demonstrates the poet’s devotion to his family and especially his children, and
               a discussion of these neglected pieces might provide a useful critical complement to
               the picture the letters present of Bloomfield the father as much as Bloomfield the
               author. Bloomfield’s letters reveal the poet’s intense attachments to his family, and
               his concern for their wellbeing at every level—physical, moral, and intellectual.
               Remembering his own pursuit of knowledge under difficulties, Bloomfield consistently
               demonstrates his commitment to his children’s education, making it a recurrent theme
               in his personal and published writings. He mentions in the prefaces to each of his
               two works for children that his own mother was a schoolmistress, and his son and
               coauthor, Charles, became a teacher. Education was an important family legacy.</p>
            <p> A re-examination of the works for children thus contributes to the project of
               demonstrating how Bloomfield fully participates in his Romantic cultural moment.
               While differing in style and in audience, these two texts are also very much of a
               piece with Bloomfield’s other core moral and artistic concerns. Although celebrating
               Bloomfield’s children’s books could be seen as inviting the risk of once again
               relegating Bloomfield to the status of naïf—a writer capable only of simple works and
               observations because of his laboring-class background—if we understand them in
               relation to the rest of Bloomfield’s achievements they appear less anomalous and less
               simplistic. For instance, at a superficial level, the story of Little Davy might seem
               to express the same wishful charitable social circumstances represented in <title
                  level="m">May Day for the Muses</title>—where Sir Ambrose Higham decides to accept
               poems and songs instead of rent. However, for a children’s story the circumstances
               described in <title level="m">Little Davy</title> are socially complex and confront
               crucial contemporary political and economic crises. Bloomfield himself is alert to
               potential accusations of oversimplification. He writes in the preface to third
               edition of <title level="m">Little Davy</title>: “Perhaps the characters are too
               good—too perfect—for what we unfortunately see in real life; but that their poverty
               is not beyond truth, I am certain” (ix). </p>
            <p>As with much of Bloomfield’s writing for adults, what at first seems simple upon
               closer examination reveals the author’s larger awareness of broader cultural
               traditions and complicated social issues. Both of Bloomfield’s children’s works are
               unafraid to contend with life’s harsher realities even as they perform the typical
               moral function of children’s literature and extol the virtues of charity and kindness
               to the poor and to animals. More importantly, even in these works, Bloomfield is
               always an artist. Form and style matter as much as the content or lessons the stories
               contain. As he writes in the <title level="m">Remains</title>: “I never get hold of a
               child’s book but I feel an inclination to see how the story is told, be it ever so
               simple. If I can judge by my girls, the minds of children are much interested by such
               as are well written” (2: 120). Bloomfield knew that pure didacticism was unlikely to
               win readers, especially those readers he cared most about.</p>
            <p> But Bloomfield also knew that he was trying his hand at what was, in the early
               nineteenth century, a relatively new genre in England. While folktales and fairytales
               (genres which Bloomfield also engaged) are timeless, large-scale publishing
               specifically for children had only really begun in the mid-eighteenth century with
               John Newbery, whom Peter Hunt credits with beginning “the serious
                  <emph>business</emph> of publishing for children” (34). According to Hunt,
               “Newbery’s significance lay in developing the children’s side of his publishing
               business to such an extent that this class of book could be seen as worthy of the
               kind of artistic and financial investment reserved for adult books” (34-5). By the
               Romantic period, this business had developed into a very healthy market, with
               contributions from some of the most important authors of the age, such as Mary
               Wollstonecraft and William Godwin in the early part of the period and Charles Lamb in
               the later. Some of the most important publishers, such as Joseph Johnson, carried on
               Newbery’s legacy, bringing out children’s works by Wollstonecraft, Anna Barbauld,
               Sarah Trimmer, and Maria Edgeworth (Hunt 55).</p>
            <p> Writing these kinds of books was not something Bloomfield considered a frivolous
               endeavor, as he was well aware of the esteemed company he aspired to join. He did not
               see himself as another hack chapbook writer, but a professional children’s author. In
               finally signing his name to the third edition of <title level="m">Little Davy’s New
                  Hat</title>, Bloomfield writes: <quote>The longer I live, the more I am convinced
                  of the importance of children’s books. The feeling seems to be universal; and I
                  never talk with a man or woman of fifty years of age, without hearing, that what
                  they read in infancy, was very inferior to the juvenile publications of later
                  days. Reader, ask yourself if this is not the case; and remember the exalted names
                  of my betters, who have helped to turn, or, perhaps, have entirely turned the
                  scale in favour of your children and mine: and then, when you recollect the names
                  of Dr. Watts, M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> Barbauld, M<hi rend="sup">rs. </hi>Trimmer,
                     M<hi rend="sup">rs. </hi>Wakefield, Miss Edgeworth, and many others, allow me,
                  without any fear of shame, to sign myself, <ab rendition="#indent5"
                     >Respectfully,</ab>
                  <ab rendition="#indent5">Robert Bloomfield. (v-vi)</ab></quote> Bloomfield takes
               the pedagogic and artistic dimension of children’s literature seriously, seeing
               himself as part of a generation of authors improving the literary offerings available
               to young people. One can also speculate that he may have hoped to profit financially
               from his efforts in this genre, with its growing audience, especially at a time when
               the market for poetry was declining. In what follows, I will discuss the two works
               within the context of other children’s writing of the period as well as within
               Bloomfield’s broader literary concerns.</p>
            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>The History of Little Davy’s New Hat: Rural Social Relations and the Teaching
                  of Charity</head>

               <p> In the introduction to his first work for children, Bloomfield mentions that he
                  wrote the tale in 1801 to try to teach children moral lessons, primarily kindness
                  to the poor; he notes that he was inspired in this pursuit of using imaginative
                  literature to promote morality based on his own childhood experience. One of
                  Newbery’s most significant publications, <title level="m">Goody Two Shoes</title>,
                  taught Bloomfield to abominate the fantasies of other stories such as <title
                     level="m">The History of Jack the Giant Killer</title>. Bloomfield thus places
                  himself squarely in the camp of the more overtly moralistic “Goody” (an anonymous
                  story once widely suspected to have been the work of Oliver Goldsmith) despite the
                  fact that “Jack” was a tale approved of and enjoyed by such eighteenth-century
                  literary moralists as Samuel Johnson and Henry Fielding. </p>
               <p> Little Davy’s parallels to Goody Two Shoes are fairly direct. Like little Margery
                  Meanwell, who is so poor she only has one shoe, Davy also lacks a critical item of
                  apparel (though, to be fair, one can imagine Margery had slightly greater
                  hardship). Also, in both cases the child’s distress is alleviated by a generous
                  nobleman. One might say that the prospect of benevolent aristocrats returning to a
                  sense of their feudalistic charitable obligations is probably as much of a fantasy
                  as killing Cornish and Welsh giants, but <title level="m">Little Davy</title> does
                  not indulge in a social-climbing fantasy to the extent that <title level="m">Goody
                     Two Shoes</title> does. In the latter story, virtue is rewarded, Cinderella
                  style, as Margery’s goodness eventually brings her marriage to a wealthy widower.
                  While <title level="m">Little Davy</title> does include a marriage, it is that of
                  the benevolent Miss Wideland, the wealthy farmer’s daughter, who is matched with
                  the equally generous Mr. Stanmore. </p>
               <p> As noted above, the world of Little Davy is fairly complex. The Woodly family
                  includes Davy, his mother, ailing father, ailing grandfather, little sister Jane,
                  and absent older brother, Will, a soldier away at war in Jamaica. The wealthy
                  farmers, the Wideland family, are their most important neighbors, as is the
                  shopkeeper Mr. Soapgroat (to whom the family is indebted for their bread). Other
                  neighbors include Will’s fiancée Lydia, another wealthy neighbor, Mrs. Meadowly,
                  and her household staff as well as assorted neighborhood boys. Both Davy’s father
                  and grandfather attempt to earn a living making birch brooms. As both are ill (the
                  effects of malnutrition as one might guess from the pressing lack of food
                  highlighted in the story), they find it hard to keep up this trade, which was
                  probably not lucrative in the first place. Their house is falling down on one side
                  and Davy’s mother’s petticoats are tattered—sewn and re-sewn. Davy doesn’t go to
                  school but receives what education he can from his grandfather.</p>
               <p> Food is a central element in the plot of the story. All other expenditures,
                  including that of the hat of the title, are subordinated to its purchase. As the
                  text later reveals, the war in which Will is fighting has created the conditions
                  for famine, and starvation appears always at the door in this text. In the
                  narrative’s first episode Davy heads to the Wideland farm to get milk for his
                  family and in his boyish frolics on the route home, he twice almost loses the
                  precious contents of the pitcher. Davy’s guilt about his narrow escapes
                  underscores the critical need for nourishment that drives the story, even as the
                  tale seems to emphasize the moral lesson of not loitering. </p>
               <p> In the second episode, food again becomes a focus. Miss Wideland visits the
                  family and Davy’s three-year-old sister Jane accidentally breaks the family
                  teapot. Miss Wideland immediately sends Davy to the shop for a new one that she
                  will purchase for the family. The conversation then turns to the news of brother
                  Will in Jamaica, a “sad unhealthy place” (20) where Mr. Woodly had earlier lost a
                  brother due to the inhospitable climate. The war is not only responsible for
                  taking Will across the ocean, but in the conversation we learn that the war is
                  also responsible for the high cost of flour that forces the family to raid Davy’s
                  hat fund. Thus, the fairly recent memories of the historical reality of the famines
                  of the 1790s are written into what might seem a superficial story. Davy’s mother
                  notes in her conversation with Miss Wideland that with flour so dear, she cannot
                  even imagine eating meat. We learn too in this episode that because the father and
                  grandfather make brooms they are not eligible for as much parish support as they
                  might need to feed the family. Finally, we learn that old Mr. Woodly was once a
                  farmer himself, and that the house where the family resides belonged to another
                  farmer who is currently in the workhouse. In these details we see the limitations
                  of the poor laws and the hint of enclosure represented within this children’s
                  tale. The conversations among the adults place the tale squarely in its historical
                  and socio-economic moment. The family’s poverty is not mythic but has clear-cut
                  causes that Bloomfield explicitly includes and implicitly critiques.</p>
               <p> The initial reason for Miss Woodly’s visit is that she has come with the gift of
                  a puppy, which she had rescued from drowning and was going to offer to the Woodly
                  family. She begins to regret it upon hearing the family cannot afford meat for
                  themselves let alone for a pet. However, it is agreed that Davy will come to the
                  Wideland farm every morning for milk—for the dog and for the family—and the
                  situation is resolved. As will be discussed below, part of the charitable universe
                  that both texts celebrate involves kindness to animals as an essential barometer
                  of the moral code the stories try to instill. Teaching children kindness and care
                  for animals, creatures lesser than themselves, inspires in them that same empathy
                  and awareness for suffering humans. Although equating the poor with animals is
                  potentially problematic for modern readers, it is clear that Bloomfield believes
                  that greater sympathy and fellow feeling would go a long way to allay
                  socially-created distress. Although his is not the revolutionary social critique
                  we might hope for, we should recollect the target audience and imagine that the
                  adults reading the story to their children might be alert to the factual economic
                  and political details included. There is no naïveté in the author’s understanding
                  of the causes of the problems he depicts, as the discussion in these two chapters
                  demonstrates.</p>
               <p> During her visit, Miss Wideland invites Davy to go with her on a short journey
                  she must take in her chaise, asking him to assist her by opening the gates she
                  must pass through. Miss Wideland doesn’t simply give charity but tries to create
                  some opportunities for employment; thus, she is not only benevolent but also
                  enlightened. The only impediment is Davy’s going in public on this journey without
                  a hat, which is resolved when Miss Wideland digs up an old one, made of “cat-skin”
                  that used to belong to Abel the farmhand and which is so decrepit it must have the
                  earwigs knocked out of it before it is fit for use (more on earwigs below). </p>
               <p> Hatlessness addressed, Davy is off on a journey that takes him out of his
                  knowledge (to use John Clare’s phrase). On their drive, Miss Wideland quizzes Davy
                  as to how he became hatless and learns that his last hat was lost while he and a
                  friend were nutting the previous fall (no doubt as part of the effort to add some
                  much needed protein to his family’s diet). We learn that while his friend was
                  beaten, Davy escaped corporal punishment, which his parents do not practice
                  (another coded message to adult readers). On their journey Davy sees many new
                  things, such as a boat. But Miss Wideland rapidly becomes more interested in Mr.
                  Stanmore, who meets their chaise. He is the nephew of Mrs. Meadowly, whom Miss
                  Wideland is visiting.</p>
               <p> In the next chapter, Davy is handed over to the gossiping maid Betty who wishes
                  to learn all she can about Mr. Stanmore’s behavior. What is more likely to
                  interest today’s reader is the fact that Betty is also a lover of ballads and
                  sings one about war that she has recently purchased. She charges Davy to take it
                  back to his mother once Davy informs her that his mother also loves to sing. Davy
                  further receives sixpence from Mrs. Meadowly and Mr. Stanmore, as well as more
                  food to take home to his family from Betty. Returning to his family, Davy regales
                  them with tales of his adventure, and while everyone asks about his second-hand
                  cap, Davy holds on to the hope that he will soon have a new one. His father
                  believes that he will sell enough brooms at Brookside Fair in May. When Davy gives
                  the ballad that he has had from Betty to his mother, she begins to cry because it
                  is entitled “Soldier Will.” Fortunately, she does not stay to hear the ballad read
                  (it is quoted in full in the text) as it a tale of grave misfortune to the
                  eponymous hero. Grandfather Woodly is able to calm her by reading her chapters
                  from Job. Thus, Bloomfield offers us a vision of the variety of literary
                  influences present in a rural household, likely quite similar to what he might
                  have experienced growing up. While poor, the family is not without a sense of
                  traditional literary culture, both oral and written.</p>
               <p> The family’s engagement with the arts is described again in Chapter 8, when the
                  family goes to church and we learn of Davy’s father’s talent in singing the
                  Psalms. Furthermore, as we discover in Chapter 9, in Davy’s conversations while
                  sitting at his grandfather’s sickbed, his grandfather had aspired to be a poet and
                  had written some verses on the death of a horse killed by a hive of bees. Davy is
                  thus surrounded by poetry of all kinds—popular, biblical, and original. Despite
                  the family’s need for food, they are still rich in various forms of culture.</p>
               <p> In Chapter 9 we learn too of the broader social conditions and complexity of the
                  life of the Woodly family—again, with much historically significant information
                  woven into the details. As Davy’s father is preparing to go to the fair to sell his
                  wares, we are told that in the neighborhood there is only one “little farmer” left
                  in the area who has a cart that might be borrowed to transport the brooms. It may
                  be surmised that while the Wideland family might be generous, they have also been
                  involved in enclosure, although this possibility is only implied and not elaborated
                  upon. The story continues to follow the family from spring to summer, and as they
                  are successful at gleaning enough grain in the harvest to hold against the coming
                  winter, their prospects seem brighter. Miss Wideland and Mr. Stanmore marry, and
                  he takes over the Wideland family farm, offering to take Davy under his wing,
                  inviting him to live with him, and taking on the responsibility for clothing and
                  educating him.</p>
               <p> Lydia too receives a letter from Will in Jamaica, and soon after we are informed
                  that the peace has been signed and thus that Lydia and the Woodlys may expect Will
                  home. Mrs. Stanmore confirms the news that Will is coming home, and that, as a
                  result of the peace (presumably the Treaty of Amiens of 1802), the price of corn
                  will likely fall. To top off all the happiness and joy, Davy’s father is finally
                  able to buy him a new hat. The explicit lesson here is one of patience in poverty,
                  as the final lines repeat: “If, therefore, any good boy should read this story,
                  and should have been very poor, and often disappointed, I earnestly advise him to
                  have patience, and to remember <title level="m">Little Davy’s New Hat</title>”
                  (94-5). The fact that problems big and small, personal and international, coexist
                  in the space of this seemingly simple story show Bloomfield’s social commitments
                  even within the unadorned morality required for children’s stories in this period.
                  Davy’s need for a hat exists within a wider spectrum of needs, including that for
                  basic sustenance, which is threatened by enclosure as well as international
                  crises.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>The Bird and Insects’ Post-Office: Teaching Love for Nature</head>


               <p> Another of Bloomfield’s core social and ethical commitments emerges in his second
                  book for children: a love and respect for non-human creation. Richard Louv’s
                  recent book <title level="m">The Last Child in the Woods</title> makes an
                  impassioned (and scientifically supported) case for the developmental importance
                  of children encountering and experiencing nature. Louv’s study forms one of the
                  most popular recent works in the growing field of Environmental Education, also
                  known as Environmental Literacy, a burgeoning movement in the field of education,
                  complete with its own national organization in North America (the North American
                  Association of Environmental Education) designed to help teachers at all levels
                  instill awareness of and respect for the natural world in a generation of children
                  whose parents and grandparents will leave them with a destroyed planet. Such a
                  concern for educating children about nature and in nature is inherited from the
                  Romantics via Rousseau. “Let nature be your teacher,” expounds Wordsworth. But
                  such injunctions are not easy to carry out, especially if you are a child of the
                  early nineteenth century living in an urban or suburban area and perhaps compelled
                  to spend more of your time indoors working than outdoors roaming the Lake
                  District. This is the audience we can imagine that is implicitly being addressed
                  in Robert and Charles Bloomfield’s <title level="m">The Bird and Insects’
                     Post-Office</title>, one of the last works that the poet wrote.</p>
               <p> Elsewhere in the <title level="m">Remains</title>, Bloomfield explicitly
                  discusses the importance of children learning a love for nature: “What a wide
                  difference may be seen between the manner of bringing up children, as to the
                  chance of seeing in their youth, what we call the beauties of Nature” (2: 68).
                  Bloomfield notes how at least his earlier service as a farmer’s boy gave him ample
                  subject matter for poetry. He then recollects the situation of one of the other
                  boys who worked with him in the London shoemaker’s garret. Jem was an orphan who
                  lived his entire life in London and his encounter with “nature” was limited to
                  helping collect maggots to be used for fishbait for those angling in the New
                  River. Happily for us, Bloomfield’s exposure on the farm was a bit more wide
                  ranging. One cannot help but imagine that Bloomfield might have had his old friend
                  Jem as much as his own children in mind when he was writing this last work.</p>
               <p>
                  <title level="m">The Bird and Insects’ Post-Office</title> is certainly useful to
                  bookend with Bloomfield’s first work, <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title>.
                  Both texts concern themselves with how children can and should be educated about
                  nature and what nature will and should teach children. Both demonstrate an ethics
                  of stewardship toward nature, and both offer a portrayal of the beauties as much
                  as the realities of the natural world. As I have written elsewhere, in <title
                     level="m">The Farmer’s Boy </title>Bloomfield writes with exuberant pastoral
                  relish of the playful lambs, but he also provides grim georgic details of their
                  butchering as part of the cycle of life (and death) on a working farm. The young
                  Giles learns to sing along with the wild birds who serenade him as he trundles out
                  to the field to work, but some of that work involves killing the marauding crows
                  who steal the farmer’s grain and hanging up their corpses around the fields as a
                  warning to others (for more about this darker dimension of rural life, see Ian
                  Haywood’s essay in this collection). </p>
               <p> Similarly, the inherent charm of talking birds and bugs is offset in other
                  passages such as the lengthy description, offered by the poor mother earwig,
                  regarding the massacre of her children: <quote>I had my family all about me, all
                     white, clean, and promising children, when pounce came down that bird they call
                     a woodpecker; when, thrusting his huge beak under the bark where we lay, down
                     went our whole sheltering roof! and my children, poor things, running, as they
                     thought, from danger, were devoured as fast as the destroyer could open his
                     beak and shut it. (2: 140)</quote> The earwig writes this letter to her aunt as
                  she starves to death for fear of venturing out of hiding, as she is “surrounded by
                  woodpeckers, jackdaws, magpies and other devouring creatures” (2: 140-1). While
                  this situation might push the limits of a reader’s ability to suspend disbelief,
                  the earwig remains philosophical and her final thoughts remind us that the purpose
                  of such writing is not realism but morality. Even though she is trapped, starving
                  in her tree, with delicious ripening fruit in full view, she observes that
                  “perhaps, if I could know the situation of some larger creatures—I mean
                  particularly such as would tread me to death if I crossed their path—they may have
                  complaints to make, as well as I” (2: 141). She consoles herself with the thought
                  that perhaps the fruit would not be as tasty as it looked. The earwig’s
                  resignation is a lesson to children about putting one’s wants into perspective and
                  about the relative nature of suffering.</p>
               <p> In using the animals as a vehicle to convey human moral values, Bloomfield is
                  placing himself in direct relation to a classical tradition dating back to the
                  most celebrated writer of animal stories, Aesop, whose <title level="m"
                     >Fables</title> he explicitly mentions. In the Preface to <title level="m">Bird
                     and Insects’ Post-Office, </title>Bloomfield describes a controversy, fanned by
                  “some French author” about the advisability of using the fiction of a talking
                  animal as a vehicle to teach children, because this might delude children into
                  believing that animals could “in reality” talk—or in this case, even more
                  preposterously—write. Here Bloomfield responds as an experienced parent, observing
                  that most children are clever enough to understand the difference between reality
                  and make-believe. He describes how children, when playing with a pet, will often
                  imagine, by looking at the animal’s reaction and expression, what it might say if
                  it could speak, all the while knowing that it does not talk as humans do.</p>
               <p> This empathy is a critical characteristic that Bloomfield strives to develop in
                  the letters that follow, as he himself imagines in what style each of the birds
                  and insects he describes might write, based upon his observations of “their
                  well-known habits and pursuits” (2: 126). Bloomfield’s prefatory remarks are
                  comparable to those of many Romantic-period children’s writers, such as Sarah
                  Trimmer, who writes in the introduction to her <title level="m">The History of
                     Robins</title> (first published as <title level="m">Fabulous Histories</title>
                  in 1786) that “The book should be taken ‘not as containing the real conversation
                  of birds, (for that is impossible we should ever understand) but as a series of
                  fables intended to convey moral instructions applicable to themselves’” (quoted in
                  Hunt 72). As Hunt observes, Trimmer, like many others in the period, understood
                  that “children’s affinity and fascination with animals could be exploited to
                  deliver homilies on man’s duty toward them” (72). Hunt provides an inventory of
                  the proliferation of animal “biographies” that abounded during the late eighteenth
                  and early nineteenth century, including one of the most popular, the tale of Cock
                  Robin, which helped introduce children to the concept of death.</p>
               <p>
                  <title level="m">The Bird and Insects’ Post-Office </title>provides powerful
                  commentary on how we should treat the rest of creation. Perhaps the most dramatic
                  example of this comes in letter 12, written from the Pigeon to the Partridge,
                  vividly describing the “sport” of trap shooting. Explaining why he has not written
                  back, the Pigeon details how “we are subject to more than the random gun-shot in
                  the field, for we are sometimes taken out of our house a hundred at a time, and
                  put into a large basket to be placed in a meadow or a spare plat of ground suiting
                  the purpose, there to be murdered at leisure” (2: 158). The pigeon explains how
                  when the lid of the basket is lifted, they all fly out to escape and are then
                  fired upon. The pigeon is outraged that this is known as a sport, and Bloomfield
                  himself is compelled to add his own footnote descrying the wanton savagery of this
                  pastime, noting that he was so disgusted by what he saw, he wished that the hunter
                  could have suffered some of what he had inflicted while participating in this
                  “cowardly practice” (2: 158). The pigeon concludes his letter by telling his
                  friend the partridge that he would prefer to be torn apart by a hawk, who though
                  he “stands for no law, nor no season, but eats us when he is hungry. . . . He is the
                  perfect gentleman compared to these ‘Lords of Creation,’ as I am told they call
                  themselves” (2: 159).</p>
               <p> An earlier letter, letter 6, from the Wild Duck to the Tame Duck, also criticizes
                  hunting practices, here the use of decoys. While the Wild Duck extols the virtues
                  of his lifestyle to his tame cousin, he notes that “every station of our
                  duck-lives is subject to some disadvantages and some calamities. Thus, with all
                  our wildness, we are not secure: for we are taken sometimes by hundreds, in a kind
                  of trap, which is called a decoy” (2: 143). Bloomfield once again annotates this
                  passage to provide us with a brief history of the drained fenland known as Bedford
                  Level and to verify the astounding number of ducks taken from this area. While
                  this wild duck has narrowly escaped capture, he notes that he has a good sense of
                  what happened to his brother ducks who were less fortunate, and he condemns the
                  insatiable demand for ducks among that “very large assemblage of fellow creatures
                  to those, who catch us” (2: 145). As is evident in his writing as far back as
                     <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title>, Bloomfield does not object
                  unilaterally to killing animals. He objects to the excessiveness of the trap
                  shooting and duck hunting, which is not for animal husbandry or to meet human
                  nutritional needs. Rather, it is killing for the sake of killing. The letters
                  demonstrate that death is a part of nature as much as life, but that we should
                  recognize and condemn death when it is clearly <emph>un</emph>natural.</p>
               <p> The lessons that the book provides are not all grim. Humans are depicted not only
                  as violent and greedy creatures but as a bit stupid as well, as is evident in the
                  second letter, “From a Young Garden Spider to Her Mother,” which tells of how one
                  of the “striders” (as they call people) captured the newly born spiders in the
                  bottom of a glass bottle, little suspecting that they would use their web-building
                  powers to escape. She writes triumphantly: “I shall never forget how the great
                  booby stared when he saw us all climbing up our rope ladders” (2: 134). This
                  reflection leads the little spider to meditate upon whether humans ever try to
                  imprison one another and how, thus suggesting a more modest lesson about our need
                  to respect fellow creatures in their freedom.</p>
               <p> Another theme that runs through the collection is how each creature believes his
                  or her way of life to be the best. This argumentative device helps Bloomfield and
                  his son find a vehicle for describing the creature’s way of life in some detail.
                  For example, the first two letters provide the correspondence between a magpie and
                  a farmyard sparrow. The magpie, the only creature to appear more than once in the
                  letter series, officiously advises the sparrow to leave the farmyard and fly free.
                  He pompously extols his own powers as a singer. The sparrow, in response, is
                  rightfully offended, mocks the magpie’s “singing,” and warns the magpie away from
                  the farmyard and from stealing her eggs, thus teaching readers that the magpie has
                  a harsh voice and eats any food it can get its hands on. Magpies are one of the
                  few bird species that can recognize itself in a mirror, perhaps accounting for the
                  rather conceited tone Bloomfield gives “Mag” in his letter. The Tame Duck, in the
                  seventh letter, instead of sympathizing with the fate of the hunted Wild Duck,
                  devotes most of her message to belittling the hen’s ridiculous lifestyle. In
                  letter 9, the Dunghill Cock criticizes the chaffinches for stealing the barley
                  from the farmyard. Overall in the letters one bird’s habits are described by
                  another in largely negative terms. </p>
               <p> Charles Bloomfield’s contributions to the collection are all written in verse
                  (Robert’s are all in prose) but they treat similar topics. Letter 10, “The
                  Bluebottle Fly to the Grasshopper,” describes the fly as doubly threatened, first
                  by a human and then a spider, whereas letter 11, “The Glow-Worm to the Humble
                  Bee,” offers a warning to the bee about how humans are preparing to steal the
                  honey from the hive. The glowworm is compelled to turn to a written correspondence
                  because when it tried to tell the bee in person, the bee was too busy to listen.
                  The collection of letters, albeit unfinished, ends with a poem by Charles: “On
                  Hearing a Cuckoo at Midnight.”</p>
               <p> As we know from poems such as <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> and
                     <title level="m">The Banks of Wye</title>, Bloomfield was a powerful painter of
                  the natural world. Yet the natural world presented in these pieces is
                  circumscribed. Why, one might wonder, only birds and insects? Why not other
                  animals, such as sheep or cows or foxes or badgers? The answer may lie in the fact
                  that these are creatures that any child might encounter in a city, suburban area,
                  or the country. They are creatures that Bloomfield’s old colleague, Jem, might
                  have had a hope of encountering. These are not mythical or magical beasts that
                  would promote the kinds of superstitious beliefs that Bloomfield worked in other
                  poems to dispel (see, for example, another animal poem, “The Fakenham Ghost”), and
                  which he notes in the parental preface to <title level="m">Little Davy </title>is
                  reason for the book to be consigned to the fire. Bloomfield’s goal is to reach and
                  inspire as many children as he can, not just his own.</p>
               <p> Bloomfield’s works for children, while certainly not his masterpieces, are
                  important to understanding the author’s sense of his vocation. Bloomfield did not
                  conceive of himself only as an author who wrote a certain kind of rural poetry,
                  nor even as only a poet. He actively engaged with a variety of poetical and
                  non-poetical genres. And while conventions of Romantic-period children’s
                  literature demanded heavy didacticism, Bloomfield’s moralizing never strays from
                  the kinds of ethical and social commitments he expresses in other works. The need
                  to remember—and to live by—our responsibilities to others in our human and animal
                  communities is a thread that extends throughout Bloomfield’s career.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>

               <listBibl>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">The History of Little Davy’s New Hat</title>
                        <edition>3rd ed</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1824</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">The Remains of Robert Bloomfield</title>
                        <edition>2 vols</edition>
                        <editor role="ediotr">Joseph Weston</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <date>1824</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bloomfield, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m"><ref
                              target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters/">The
                              Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</ref></title>
                        <editor role="editor">Tim Fulford</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>2009</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                     <series>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Circles Electronic Editions</title>
                     </series>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Hunt, Peter</editor>
                        <title level="m">Children’s Literature. An Illustrated History</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
                           <date>1995</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Keegan, Bridget</author>
                        <title level="m">Labouring-Class Nature Poetry, 1730-1837</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Basingstoke</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Palgrave</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Lawson, Jonathan</author>
                        <title level="m">Robert Bloomfield</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Twayne</publisher>
                           <date>1980</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Louv, Richard</author>
                        <title level="m">The Last Child in the Woods. Saving Our Children from
                           Nature-Deficit Disorder</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chapel Hill</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Algonquin Books</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
