<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Staging Identity in Eighteenth-Century England: </title>
				<title type="subordinate">Restoration to Romantic Drama</title>
				<author>
					<name>Emily Anderson</name>
				</author>
				<editor role='editor'>
					<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Pedagogies Editor</resp>
					<name>Kate Singer</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>commons4.2011.anderson_syllabus</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
								Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="u" type="main">Staging Identity in Eighteenth-Century England: </title>
						<title level="u" type="subordinate">Restoration to Romantic Drama</title>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename>Emily</forename>
								<surname>Anderson</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Teaching Romantic Drama: </title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Pedagogies Commons Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
							<biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g18" scheme="#genre"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<date>2011-02-18</date>
				<list>
					<item>revised TEI</item>
					<item>XSLT</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Dave Rettenmaier</name>
				<date>2010-06-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				<date>2009-11-01T15:01:00</date>
				<list>
					<item>Proofed issue in Open Office Format</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>

			<div type="syllabus">
				<head>Staging Identity in Eighteenth-Century England: Restoration to Romantic Drama</head>
				<list>
					<item>Professor Anderson</item>
					<item>
						<name ref="mailto:ehanders@usc.edu"> ehanders@usc.edu </name>
					</item>
					<item>ENGL 530</item>
					<item>Fall 2006</item>
				</list>

				<epigraph>
					<quote>
						<lg>
							<l>All the world's a stage,</l>
							<l>And all the men and women merely players…</l>
						</lg>
					
						<ab rend="indent8"><bibl> —<name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>, <title level="m">As You Like It</title>,
						2.7.139-40</bibl></ab></quote>
				</epigraph>

			</div>

			<div type="section" n="1">
				<p rend="noCount">While the concept of <foreign>theatrum mundi</foreign>, or the metaphor of the world as a stage, is one
					of the most durable in intellectual history, in the eighteenth century the analogy had been carried so far that Henry Fielding
					would observe, "when transactions behind the curtain are mentioned, St. James's is more likely to occur to our thoughts than Drury
					Lane." Eighteenth-century life revolved around theater that existed outside the playhouse—and yet, it did so because it
					concurrently revolved around the theater that existed <emph>within</emph> it. The metaphor was so powerful because the model for
					it was so prevalent.</p>
				<p rend="noCount">This course asks us to consider these conscious links between the offstage and onstage regions of eighteenth-century
					life and to reflect on how these links affect eighteenth-century conceptions of identity. What does it mean that, in the
					eighteenth century, selfhood is depicted as both metaphorically and literally theatrical? What components of identity, in terms of
					race, class, and gender, are privileged or destabilized by the eighteenth-century stage? In what ways do evolutions in dramatic
					style (particularly the turn-of-the-century shift toward closet drama) reflect a changing concept of the self? </p>
				<p rend="noCount">To address these questions, we will read a range of plays that explore the intersections among theater, life, and
					self-fashioning, and we will situate our discussions in a framework that combines theater history with performance studies.
					Students will learn about eighteenth-century acting theory, stagecraft, and the economics and politics of theater management. We
					will explore important historical events, such as the Theater Licensing Act of 1737 and the eighteenth-century phenomenon of the
					masquerade. But we will also investigate how current theorists are using the terms "theatricality," "performance," and
					"performativity," and we will consider how terms that have migrated from their literal foundations can be productively brought to
					bear on them again. </p>
			</div>

			<div type="section" n="2">
				<head>Texts:</head>
				<list>
					<item><name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>, <emph>The Tempest </emph>(Pelican—may use alternate
						edition)</item>
					<item><name ref="BehnAphra">Behn</name>, <emph>Oroonoko</emph> (Norton—may use an alternate edition)</item>
					<item>Broadview Anthology of Restoration and Early Eighteenth-Century Drama, Concise Edition</item>
					<item> Contains: Southerne, <emph>Oroonoko</emph>
					</item>
					<item>
						<name ref="WycherleyWilliam">Wycherley</name>, <emph>The Country Wife</emph>
					</item>
					<item>
						<name ref="BehnAphra">Behn</name>, <emph>The Rover</emph>
					</item>
					<item> Congreve, <emph>The Way of the World</emph>
					</item>
					<item>Steele, <emph>The Conscious Lovers</emph>
					</item>
					<item>
						<name ref="GayJohn">Gay</name>, <emph>The Beggar's Opera</emph>
					</item>
					<item>
						<name ref="GoldsmithOliver">Goldsmith</name>, <emph>She Stoops to Conquer</emph>
					</item>
					<item> Sheridan, <emph>School for Scandal</emph>
					</item>
					<item>
						<name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name>, <emph>The Belle's Stratagem</emph>
					</item>
					<item>Eliza Haywood, <emph>Fantomina </emph>(Broadview—or may access on ECCO)</item>
					<item><name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>, <emph>Plays on the Passions</emph> (Broadview)</item>
					<item>Jane Austen, <emph>Mansfield Park</emph> (Broadview)</item>
				</list>
				<ab>An * indicates those texts contained in a course reader. The reader is available at the bookstore, and I will
					also place one copy on reserve at Leavey Library.</ab> <lb/>
				<ab>Some reading assignments will also require you to use the electronic database <emph>Eighteenth-Century
						Collections Online</emph>, or <emph>ECCO</emph>, which is available through the e-resources link on the USC library portal. To
						access this collection from off-campus, you must install the VPN-Client software.</ab>
				
				
			</div>



			<div type="section" n="3">
				<head>Assignments:</head>
				<list>
					<head>Keyword Analysis—Presentation and Write-up (30%):</head>
					<item>This assignment is modeled after Raymond Williams' book <emph>Keywords</emph>, his analysis of influential terms in culture
						and society. More than a dictionary, Williams' text is interested in the evolving or overlapping meanings of his chosen terms.
						These variations are often what indicate a term's importance—what identify them as "keywords"—and Williams' entries trace
						these variations to illuminate patterns in thought and culture.</item>
					<item>I've similarly paired our reading for each week with a specific "keyword" from theater / performance studies. These are
						terms that have resurfaced in contemporary theory, but that also have a particular bearing on our primary text for the week.
						Each of you will choose one of these words and write up your own <hi>4-6 page </hi>keyword analysis. Rather than giving an
						abstract, ahistorical definition, your entry should assess the evolving tensions or relationships among the uses of this
						term—of particular interest to me are relationships between theatrical and theoretical applications of the term and / or
						between eighteenth-century and contemporary usages. </item>
					<item>The results of your investigation will be shared collectively through an in-class presentation and in a more formal, written
						essay. Your write-up is due by <hi>10am</hi> on the Monday your word is assigned. To submit the assignment, you will email as
						an attachment your keyword entry, plus a bibliography of the sources you consulted, to the entire class (<hi>that includes
							me</hi>). Your essay then becomes part of our reading assignment for Monday afternoon. In class, the author of the essay
						will also come prepared to speak for about 15 minutes on the trajectory of the assignment: how he / she decided what sources
						to consult, what particular challenges this keyword presented, what was left in the entry, what was left out, and why. The
						presentation will end with two or three discussion questions meant to apply the author's research to our reading for the week.
						I would also like to encourage a discussion of the author's essay in light of its future applicability to seminar paper
						topics.</item>
					<item>We will discuss the assignment further in class, but I would encourage all students to peruse Williams' text as well as the
						2005 <emph>New Keywords</emph>, both of which are on reserve at Leavey Library. Students should also check with me in the
						weeks prior to their assignment for bibliography suggestions. </item>
				</list>
				<list>
					<head>Huntington Library Workshop (20%):</head>
					<item>People come from around the world to work at the Huntington Library, but the attractions and mechanics of a rare book
						library may be quite unfamiliar to you. Our mandatory session at the library should make this local resource more accessible. </item>
					<item>The Huntington's collection is especially strong in eighteenth-century drama, and Laura Stalker, Head of Reader Services,
						has agreed to run a daylong workshop for our class in which we will work with the eighteenth-century editions of our assigned
						plays. During the session, we will have the chance to trace a single play through multiple editions and adaptations; we will
						study playbills, contemporary reviews, and manuscript materials related to our texts; we will even view eighteenth-century
						prints and frontispieces inspired by our plays. Laura will also brief you on the mechanics of the Huntington Library: what it
						can offer you as a scholar, how you apply for a reader's card, and how you navigate its holdings once you are there. At the
						end of workshop, you will be asked to write-up a research plan for tracing the publication and performance history of another
						play on our syllabus.</item>
					<item>Logistics: We will discuss timing on the first day of class. I would like to try to schedule the workshop for a Friday or
						Saturday in October, or at the latest early November. <hi>The workshop will start at 10am and run until about 4pm, with a
							break for lunch.</hi> For those of you without cars, I am happy to provide transportation to and from campus.</item>
				</list>

				<list>
					<head>Performance Exercise (10%):</head>
					<item>Our class will culminate with a performed scene from one of the texts we have read. As a class, you must agree upon a scene
						(and here's to hoping you are a more compliant group than the Crawfords-Bertrams), cast the actors, decide on whatever props
						will be necessary, and rehearse to whatever extent you see fit. I'm perfectly willing to be cast, if you need the bodies. I
						would suggest that you appoint one classmate as the "director" who will act as the liaison among you all; this director should
						check in with the class about potential scenes periodically throughout the semester. (To aid in this process, and so that I
						can be privy to your discussions, I have set up a discussion forum on Blackboard. Go to <ptr target="https://totale.usc.edu/"
						/> and log in using your USC username and password.) Rehearsals should start no later than November 6<hi rendition="#sup"
							>th</hi>. Be prepared to discuss your choice of scene, your interpretative choices as actors, and how your experience of
						rehearsal and performance influenced your understanding of the text.</item>
				</list>
				<list>
					<head>Final Paper (40%):</head>
					<item>I would suggest, though I do not require, that your final paper incorporate elements from your keyword analysis. The papers
						are not required to be article length, but my comments will address areas for future expansion. Papers are due by noon on
						Friday, December 8<hi rendition="#sup">th</hi>. You may submit papers in my mailbox, THH 420. Alternately, you may email me
						your paper in MS Word as an attachment. If you submit your paper electronically, I will edit it using the comment function on
						Word and return it to you electronically. <hi>12-15 pages.</hi>
					</item>
				</list>
			</div>


			<div type="section" n="4">
				<head>Schedule of Assignments:</head>
				<table cols="2">
					<row>
						<cell width="100">Aug. 21:</cell>
						<cell>Introduction—Keyword: performance</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Aug. 28:</cell>
						<cell><name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>, <emph>The Tempest</emph>; Dryden and Davenant, <emph>The
								Tempest</emph>* </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>"Performance," in <emph>International Encyclopedia of Communications*</emph></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Joseph Roach, "Theatre Studies / Cultural Studies / Performance Studies: The Three Unities"*</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Diana Taylor, "Translating Performance"*</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Sept. 4:</cell>
						<cell>NO CLASS <lb/><hi>View <title level="m">Stage Beauty</title></hi></cell>
					</row>

					<row>
						<cell>Sept. 11:</cell>
						<cell><name ref="BehnAphra">Behn</name>, <emph>Oroonoko</emph>; Southerne, <emph>Oroonoko</emph>
							<hi>Keyword: ritual</hi></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Joseph Roach, "Betterton's Funeral"*</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Sept. 18:</cell>
						<cell><name ref="BehnAphra">Behn</name>, <emph>The Rover</emph>, <emph>The Lucky Chance</emph>* <hi>Keyword:</hi>
							<hi>mimesis</hi></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Katharine Eisaman Maus, "'Playhouse Flesh and Blood': Sexual Ideology and the Restoration Actress"*</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Elin Diamond, "<emph>Gestus</emph>, signature, body in the theater of <name ref="BehnAphra">Aphra
								Behn</name>," in <emph>Unmaking Mimesis*</emph></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Sept. 25:</cell>
						<cell><name ref="WycherleyWilliam">Wycherley</name>, <emph>The Country Wife</emph>; Congreve, <emph>The Way of
								the World</emph></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell><hi>ECCO assignment: </hi>Jeremy Collier, <emph>A Short View of the Immorality and Profaneness of the English
								Stage</emph> (1698; 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition online). Read the preface. Then use the search function to locate
							those sections that pertain to Congreve and <name ref="WycherleyWilliam">Wycherley</name>. Try searching by
							author's name, play title, character names, etc.--</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Oct. 2:</cell>
						<cell>Cibber, <emph>The Careless Husband</emph>* (or read on ECCO); </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Steele, <emph>The Conscious Lovers </emph>
							<hi>Keyword: character</hi></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Joseph Roach, "Nature Still, but Nature Mechanized"*; "Darwin's Passion: The Language of Expression on Nature's
							Stage"*</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Oct. 9:</cell>
						<cell>Haywood, <emph>Fantomina </emph>
							<hi>Keyword:</hi>
							<hi>masquerade</hi></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Joan Riviere "Womanliness as a Masquerade"*</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Oct. 16:</cell>
						<cell><name ref="GayJohn">Gay</name>, <emph>The Beggar's Opera</emph>
							<hi>Keyword: spectacle</hi></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>**modern adaptations of Beggar's Opera**<lb/> Choose and read one (on reserve at Leavey Library): <name
								ref="BrechtBertolt">Bertolt Brecht</name>, <emph>The Threepenny Opera</emph>; Wole Soyinka, <emph>Opera
								Wonyosi; </emph>Alan Ayckbourn, <emph>A Chorus of Disapproval</emph>; Václav Havel, <emph>The Beggar's Opera</emph>
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Oct. 23:</cell>
						<cell>Fielding, <emph>The Author's Farce</emph>* (or on ECCO); <hi>Keyword: satire</hi></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>"A Comparison between the World and the Stage," <emph>Tom Jones</emph> (Xerox)</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Matthew Kinservik, "The Establishment of the Licensing Act"*</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell><hi>EVENT: </hi>performance of <emph>The Threepenny Opera</emph> at Bing Theater, 10/26-29</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Oct. 30:</cell>
						<cell>Sheridan, <emph>The School for Scandal</emph>
							<hi>Keyword: sensibility</hi></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Diderot, <emph>The Paradox of Acting</emph>*</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell><hi>EVENT: </hi>performance of <emph>Mansfield Park</emph> at Scene Dock Theatre, 11/2-11/5</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell><hi>EVENT: </hi>Huntington Library Workshop, Friday, 11/3, 10am-4pm</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Nov. 6:</cell>
						<cell><name ref="GoldsmithOliver">Goldsmith</name>, <emph>She Stoops to Conquer</emph>;</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell><name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name>, <emph>The Belle's Stratagem</emph>
							<hi>Keyword:</hi>
							<hi>performativity</hi></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Judith Butler, "Performative Acts and Gender Constitution"*</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Nov. 13:</cell>
						<cell><name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>, <emph>Plays on the Passions</emph>
							<hi>Keyword:</hi>
							<hi>theatricality</hi></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Tracy Davis and Thomas Postlewait, "Theatricality: An Introduction"*</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Nov. 20:</cell>
						<cell><name ref="InchbaldMrs">Elizabeth Inchbald</name>, <emph>Lover's Vows,</emph>*<emph> </emph>"Preface" to
								<emph>Lover's Vows</emph> (Xerox); </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Austen, <emph>Mansfield Park</emph>, Vol. 1</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>W.B. Worthen, "Drama, Performativity, and Performance"*</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Stephen J. Bottoms, "The Efficacy / Effeminacy Braid: Unpicking the Performance Studies / Theatre Studies
							Dichotomy"*</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Nov. 27:</cell>
						<cell>Austen, <emph>Mansfield Park</emph> complete</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>DUE: CLASS PERFORMANCE EXERCISE</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>Final discussion</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell/>
						<cell>
							<hi>**Final seminar paper due on Friday, December 8th, by 12pm.** </hi>
						</cell>
					</row>
				</table>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
