<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">“La Belle Dame sans Merci”: </title>
				<title type="subordinate">a multimedia introduction to interpretive dynamics</title>
				<author>
					<name>Noah Comet</name>
				</author>
				<editor role='editor'>
					<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Pedagogies Editor</resp>
					<name>Kate Singer</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>commons4.2011.comet</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
								Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">“La Belle Dame sans Merci”: </title>
						<title level="a" type="subordinate">a multimedia introduction to interpretive dynamics</title>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename>Noah</forename>
								<surname>Comet</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Teaching Romantic Drama: </title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Pedagogies Commons Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
							<biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g18" scheme="#genre"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<date>2011-02-18</date>
				<list>
					<item>revised TEI</item>
					<item>XSLT</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Dave Rettenmaier</name>
				<date>2010-06-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				<date>2009-11-01T15:01:00</date>
				<list>
					<item>Proofed issue in Open Office Format</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">

				<head>
					<title level="a">'La Belle Dame sans Merci': a multimedia experiment in reading and seeing</title>
				</head>
				<byline>
					<docAuthor>Noah Comet</docAuthor>
					<affiliation>The Ohio State University</affiliation>
				</byline>


				<div type="section" n="1">
					<head>Overview</head>
					<p>This exercise consists of two parts: a take-home assignment (about 25 minutes), and an in-class movie screening, followed by
						classroom discussion (50 minutes or more). Students are to compare their own seemingly objective responses to <name
							ref="KeatsJohn">John Keats</name>’s “La Belle Dame sans Merci” with filmmaker Hidetoshi Oneda’s short adaptation of the
						poem (for more information, see <ptr target="http://www.celophaine.com/lbdsm/lbdsm_top.html"/>). The aim of the exercise is to
						challenge students’ notions of objectivity, and to make them self-aware readers, thus classroom discussion should emphasize
						the ambiguities of poetic language, and the role of the reader/viewer as co-creator of meaning. Additionally, you might ask
						the students to analyze their own reading practices in comparison with the process of adapting a text for a film.</p>
					<p>As I have presented it here, the exercise suits introductory major or non-major English courses. Since its primary purpose is
						to help students to appreciate the ostensibly passive act of reading as an active, creative process, it is most useful early
						in the term as a methodological primer. In addition, the exercise can be easily adapted to advanced courses specializing in
						Romanticism. To that end, below, I have suggested how an instructor might connect the themes at hand to other literary and
						generic contexts, with a particular emphasis on Romantic drama.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="1"><ab>For an
								upper-division course, <name ref="LambCharles">Charles Lamb</name>’s essay “On the Tragedies of <name
									ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>” would make for a fine companion-text to this exercise. <name
									ref="LambCharles">Lamb</name> states that, in seeing a <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name> tragedy
								performed, “we have given up that vantage-ground of abstraction which reading possesses over seeing” (I. 106). Given
								the task at hand, to compare reading and seeing, the generic distinction between our interest in dramatic poetry and
									<name ref="LambCharles">Lamb</name>’s interest in drama matters very little. This is not to argue that “La Belle
								Dame” confronts the reader with the range of complexities that <name ref="LambCharles">Lamb</name> notices in <title
									level="m">Hamlet</title>, but rather to point out similarities in practice as <emph>readers</emph> and
									<emph>seers</emph>, whether of poetry or drama.</ab><lb/>
							<ab> An advanced version of this exercise might consider the nature of filmic adaptation in <name ref="LambCharles"
									>Lamb</name>’s terms: “When the novelty is past, we find to our cost that, instead of realising an idea, we have
								only materialised and brought down a fine vision to the standard of flesh and blood. We have let go a dream, in quest
								of an unattainable substance” (I. 98). The students should not be led to a simplistic hierarchy of reading over
									performance—<name ref="LambCharles">Lamb</name> himself is careful to note that he is “not arguing that Hamlet
								should not be acted, but how much Hamlet is <emph>made another thing</emph> by being acted” (I. 101, my emphasis).
								Instead, they should develop a critique both for and against the idea of performance as transformative and
								simplifying, as detrimental to creative liberty and multidimensionality.</ab><lb/>
							<ab> Upper-division students might also explore such concerns about reading and seeing among the writings of other
								Romantic critics. <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name> considered the unsuitability of her own plays for
								stage performance in her note “To the Reader,” appended to <title level="m">A Series of Plays</title> (1812, also
								included as an appendix in <title level="m">The Broadview Anthology of Romantic Drama,</title> pp. 370-78). <name
									ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s argument complements <name ref="LambCharles">Lamb</name>’s in several
								respects, especially in her emphasis on the limitations of stage-mechanics and the difficulty of communicating emotion
								to an audience in one of <name ref="London">London</name>’s vast playhouses. <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel
									Taylor Coleridge</name>’s lectures on <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name> also provide numerous
								points of comparison, most importantly his agreement with <name ref="LambCharles">Lamb</name> that <name
									ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name> suffered in performance, thus the ineptitude of modern production
								companies “drove Shakespear[e] from the stage, to find his proper place, in the heart and in the closet” (<title
									level="m">Lectures</title> I, 563). <name ref="HazlittWilliam">William Hazlitt</name> went further than <name
									ref="LambCharles">Lamb</name> or <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>, declaring that “the reader of
								the plays of <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name> is almost always disappointed in seeing them acted;
								and, for our own parts, we should never go to see them acted if we could help it” (<title level="m">A View of the
									English Stage</title>, V, 222). (When introducing the subject of Romantic attitudes toward performance vis-à-vis
									<name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>, it might be useful to point students to <name
									ref="BurwickFrederick">Frederick Burwick</name>’s essay on the subject in the Blackwell <title level="m">Companion
									to Romanticism,</title> edited by Duncan Wu.)</ab><lb/>
							<ab>If we choose to point out these similarities underlying the dramatic criticism of <name ref="LambCharles">Lamb</name>,
									<name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>, <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>, and <name
									ref="HazlittWilliam">Hazlitt</name>, it makes good sense to spend some time talking about the history of English
								theater, including developments in licensing, bowdlerization (again, <name ref="LambCharles">Lamb</name> would figure
								prominently), celebrity culture, and leisure activities among the new middle class. The <name ref="KeatsJohn"
									>Keats</name> exercise could therefore take on a historical dimension it lacks in its present lower-division form.
								Furthermore, <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s own commentary on reading and seeing, his 1817 letter on Edmund Kean
								and “negative capability,” connects well with the themes at hand, and might be employed in tandem with or instead of
								the aforementioned prose writings.</ab></note></p>
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="2">
					<head>Directions</head>
					<list type="simple">
						<head>Required:</head>
						<item>Text of <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s “La Belle Dame sans Merci” (either version)</item>
						<item>Handout (see below)</item>
						<item>DVD of Hidetoshi Oneda’s short film, <emph>La Belle Dame sans Merci</emph></item>
						<item>Media-equipped classroom</item>
					</list>

					<p>For the first part of the exercise (here conceived as a take-home assignment, though it can be done in-class if time allows)
						students should read <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s “La Belle Dame sans Merci” and respond to questions on a handout.
						For the exercise to be most effective they should read the poem, put away their books, and then respond to the questions, thus
						referring back not to the text itself, but to their memories of it. Admittedly, this is a ruse: students relying on their
						memories are likely to conflate their own subjective contributions to the poem with textual details, and this conflation is
						the impetus for the second part of the exercise. This portion takes about 25 minutes.</p>
					<p>The second part of the exercise is based on an in-class screening of the short film (runtime approx. 15 min). Students should
						be attentive to Oneda’s creative liberties with <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s poem. After the screening the students
						should take a few minutes to review their own responses to the handout, comparing their answers with Oneda’s interpretation.
						Consider beginning the discussion by asking them how <title level="m">Oneda</title> would have responded to the handout
						questions.</p>
					<p>Ask the students if they thought that Oneda’s handling of <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s poem was “faithful” or “loose.”
						Have them identify both obvious and subtle variations between the poem and the film. Oneda’s directorial choices are in many
						instances quite startling, and the students will inevitably mention his liberties with the kinds of details they worked
						through in their handouts, particularly the age and appearance of the knight, and the identity of the first speaker. At this
						point, shift the discussion back to the text of the poem, perhaps even reading it aloud, and emphasize <name ref="KeatsJohn"
							>Keats</name>’s evasive use of descriptive detail. Have the students share their responses from the handout questions, and
						ask them to find strong textual support for them. In most cases, they will find sufficient ambiguity in <name ref="KeatsJohn"
							>Keats</name>’s poem to support Oneda’s choices with as much (or as little) stability as their own. This revelation should
						energize a discussion of reading as a creative act, even reading in its most apparently objective guise. If time permits, you
						might briefly discuss the semantic distinctions between an “adaptation” and an “interpretation.” Which term applies to Oneda’s
						film, and which term applies to the act of reading?</p>
					<p>Note: as laid out here, this exercise primarily addresses <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s poem <emph>vis-à-vis</emph> the
						practice and phenomenology of reading and dramatic interpretation, not as a Romantic text in all of its historical and textual
						glory. Below, I offer a few brief thoughts on what implications the exercise might have for our understanding of, and perhaps
						an extended classroom discussion about, <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s poem itself.<note place="foot" resp="editors"
							n="2"><ab>Much has been made of the fact that “La Belle Dame sans Merci” exists in two states, the 1820 <title level="j"
									>Indicator</title> text, beginning “Ah what can ail thee, wretched wight,” and the better known 1848 Charles Brown
								text, beginning “Oh what can ail thee, knight-at-arms.” Scholars will always debate over which version—if either—ought
								to be seen as definitive. While the nuances of publication history and textual variants might not enliven classroom
								discussion, the concerns about authority they raise can do so. The present exercise, with its emphasis on the
								collaborative nature of reading, calls into question the function of textual-authority and authorial-textuality, and
								enables, even at the undergraduate level, a discussion of the relative merits of Formalist and Historicist approaches.
								Are we reading <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s poem or a poem by <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>, belatedly
								inflected (perhaps first by a slightly older <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>, then) by Leigh Hunt or Charles Brown
								or Richard Milnes, then by ourselves or perhaps by Hidetoshi Oneda? This is fairly well-trodden theoretical ground,
								but it is especially apt with respect to the textual history of “La Belle Dame” and the potential of this exercise to
								problematize authorial and readerly intention and mediation.</ab><lb/>
							<ab>As <name ref="McGannJeromeJ">Jerome McGann</name>, <name ref="KelleyTheresa">Theresa Kelley</name>, and others have
								shown, “La Belle Dame” proposes a number of ambiguities—and its textual history only compounds these ambiguities—but
								this is not so much a problem as it is a provocation. Is it “merci” or “mercy,” “wild wild eyes” or “wild sad eyes”?
								It is, of course, all of the above, and therein lies not only the appeal of <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s
								poem(s) but also the immediacy of <name ref="McGannJeromeJ">McGann</name>’s early appeal for historical method.
								Moreover, the poem’s internal ambiguities, as outlined in the exercise (and present in either version of the poem),
								reinforce <name ref="KelleyTheresa">Kelley</name>’s persuasive argument that “‘La Belle Dame sans Merci’ explores the
								value of poetic figures whose meaning is not intuited but learned” (333). This is not to claim a unique status for “La
								Belle Dame,” but to suggest that, more insistently than many other works, it is a poem that invites and rewards
								analysis of its own processing (both of its production and its reception).</ab><lb/>
							<ab>All of this is to say that the exercise can and ideally does illustrate that “La Belle Dame” embraces narrative and
								linguistic indeterminacy, so that an ostensibly “loose” adaptation such as Oneda’s can be, all the same, just as
								“faithful” as any other interpretation. Having used the exercise to highlight this aspect of the poem, one seems
								well-situated to teach his or her students about how “La Belle Dame” connects with “negative capability,” Romantic
								irony, the ballad revival, Romantic subjectivity, and many other topics, themes and theories that usually inform our
								discussions of the period.</ab>
						</note></p>
				</div>



				<div type="section" n="3">
					<head>Handout Questions</head>
					<list type="ordered">
						<item>Draw and/or give a brief physical description of the Knight.</item>
						<item>Who is the speaker of the first three stanzas: what can we discern about him or her?</item>
						<item>How do you characterize the Lady? What motivates her behavior toward the knight?</item>
					</list>
				</div>

				<div type="section" n="4">
					<head>The Exercise in Practice: A Writeup</head>
					<ab>
						<hi rend="emph">Introduction:</hi>
					</ab>
					<p>Director Hidetoshi Oneda’s <title level="m">La Belle Dame sans Merci</title> evinces his keen familiarity not only with <name
							ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s poem, but with many other canonical works and conventions of Romantic literature. <name
							ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s ballad guides the storyline of the film: a lovelorn knight, abandoned on a hillside,
						recollects his encounter with an unforgiving, wild-eyed lady. But Oneda places the knight’s tale within a narrative frame akin
						to that of <title level="m">Frankenstein</title>, or <title level="m">The Rime of the Ancient Mariner</title>, and like <name
							ref="ShelleyMaryWollstonecraft">Mary Shelley</name> and <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</name>,
						Oneda employs this framing technique to gain moral perspective on his story. Whereas the speaker of the first three stanzas in
							<name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s poem is an ambiguous voice, all provocation with no discernible means of registering
						and responding to the story he or she provokes, in the film the speaker is embodied as the unwitting pupil—<name
							ref="ShelleyMaryWollstonecraft">Shelley</name>’s Walton, or <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>’s wedding
						guest—here re-imagined as a shipwrecked English navigator. The navigator, deposited on a desert island, finds the ancient and
						haggard knight, and is transfixed (and transformed) by his story. Oneda dramatizes the knight’s memories, presenting the belle
						dame as the archetypal Romantic <emph>femme fatale</emph>. Like Geraldine or Lamia, her seductive exterior belies a cold,
						reptilian nature. Still, her wickedness is avoided at a cost: in Oneda’s film, the lady represents the ideal for which each of
						us must make a great sacrifice upon faith, lest we end our lives like the knight, stranded, with only regret to sustain us. In
						fact, after the knight tells his tale of destiny unfulfilled, he dies and disintegrates before the navigator’s eyes, leaving
						the younger man sadder, wiser, and with a renewed commitment to his own dream: to be an artist. The <emph>kunstleroman</emph>
						concludes with a close-up shot of the navigator being rescued, a sparkle of creative determination in his eyes.</p>
					<p>This is, of course, the work of a director playing fast-and-loose with his literary source. However, <name ref="KeatsJohn"
							>Keats</name>’s “La Belle Dame sans Merci” is a sparsely detailed poem that relies upon a communal knowledge of medieval
						romantic tropes and ballad traditions, thus each reader must provide his or her own cultural capital as flesh for a skeletal
						story. If Oneda’s version is a bit fleshier than some, still there is little in <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s poem that
						undermines his interpretation. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="5">
					<head>Responses to the handout:</head>
					<p>[Note: I did not have access to the students' responses until after the in-class screening and discussion; my point in
						presenting the responses here, before recounting the classroom discussion, is to offer a summary of the exercise from the
						students’ perspective.] In responding to the first handout question, the students generally agreed that the knight was
						“dejected,” and “distraught.” They tended to portray his paleness and feverishness as that of a young man “prematurely
						aged”—according to one student “he resembles a dying flower, once young and vibrant, but now decaying [as if] nature has
						turned its back on him.” In their drawings the students tended to depict a small armor-clad figure dwarfed by his
						surroundings. In one way or another, nearly all of the students described a “physically strong man that has obviously been
						emotionally broken.” None of the students described the knight as aged or moribund (as does Oneda); instead they concentrated
						on the mental and emotional toll of his experience. One student likened the knight’s trauma to that of the survivors of 9/11:
						“like the extreme shock people experience after a terrorist attack.”</p>
					<p>The 9/11 example is a good indicator of the extent to which each student made the poem personal. But even conventional
						medievalist renderings of the knight were drawn from within: after all, <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s description of
						the knight is little more than a fragmentary <emph>blason</emph> on a tormented face. Bodily, the knight loiters alone, but
						his face is our only index of his physical and mental attributes: it is pale, haggard, woeful, clammy, feverish, blushing. He
						is a “knight at arms” (or a “wretched wight”), but to envision a handsome man in the prime of his life wearing a (perhaps
						disheveled) suit of armor is to provide a chivalric archetype in the place of a few vague details. Although my students were
						more familiar with Tolkien than with Spenser, from their descriptions and drawings it was clear that they had melded <name
							ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s language with their own preconceptions of medieval knights.</p>

								<figure n="1">
									<figDesc>Oneda envisions the knight as ancient and gaunt, with unkempt white hair, dark, deep-set eyes, and a
										haunting voice. After telling his story to the navigator, the old knight dies and rapidly decomposes into
										dust.</figDesc>
									<graphic url="../images/fig1.jpg"/>
								</figure>

					<p>The second question elicited mixed but intriguing responses. Of the eighteen students participating, only five suggested that the
						first speaker of <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s poem is unidentifiable—an “omniscient voice,” “perhaps <name
							ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name> himself.” Of that group, three went on to conjecture that this unidentifiable voice conveys a
						sense of sympathy in the act of questioning. In total, “sympathetic” “concerned” and “compassionate” turn up in eleven of the
						students' responses, whether describing an anonymous voice, a “stranger,” a “physician,” “another knight at arms,” or—the most
						popular response—the belle dame herself. Six students shared this idea, mostly without further justification, though one
						student ventured, “she [the belle dame] is a supernatural existence that is contacting him again after not taking him ‘beyond’
						[…] She allows him to ‘wake up’ and she is narrating to him to help him psychologically grasp what happened.” This tendency
						among the students to reach after ethical fact and reason deserves greater attention, but suffice to say it is another
						imposition of the reader on the text. </p>

								<figure n="2">
									<figDesc>Oneda not only grants the poem’s first speaker an identity (the shipwrecked navigator), but he also
										presents the poem’s conversation out of sequence: his knight <emph>begins</emph> the conversation, startling
										the navigator who is leaning down to drink from an inland lake, unaware that the ancient knight is sitting on
										a hillside just behind him. “Have you seen her?” the knight asks, referring to his long-lost belle dame. The
										navigator’s interest in hearing the knight’s tale (‘have I seen whom?’) stems not from sympathy, but from his
										instinct toward self-preservation, that is, his hope that someone else is on the island who might aid his
										return to safety (something the invalid knight cannot do).</figDesc>
									<graphic url="../images/fig2.jpg"/>
								</figure>

					<p>The third question divided the class. Roughly half of the students felt that the lady represented neither good nor evil; they
						resisted reading her as an allegorical figure or as a type, instead envisioning her as a human character with interiority and
						a personal history. “She might know the power she possesses, but it is not necessarily a bad thing,” one student suggested.
						Five students shared the idea that the lady had a distressing history of her own (a history that motivated her behavior in the
						poem), and one student even went so far as to compare the lady with Dickens’s Miss Havisham, “heartbroken, betrayed, and so
						grief-stricken by a man in her past that she spends all her time seeking revenge on every man she encounters.” This group
						tended to ignore the title of the poem, although one student did remark that “sans merci” was the knight’s judgment, and not a
						universal reproach. On the whole, they saw the lady as a “free spirit,” not as a <emph>femme fatale</emph>.</p>
					<p>The other half of the class endorsed the titular view of the lady “without mercy,” and dedicated no time to ascribing a motive
						for her “seduction” of the knight. In fact, this group tended to grant the lady no interiority at all, seeing her
						allegorically either as pure evil (“she eats these men’s hearts and spits them out”) or as emblematic of a concept such as the
						debased “passion of men,” or war (“Warriors, knights, and kings are her victims, after all”). While students on both sides of
						the question noted that the lady never speaks for herself—“she is only characterized through the knight’s words”—this fact did
						not seem to pose any problems for them in addressing the handout question (it became problematic when discussing the film; see
						below).</p>
					
								<figure>
									<figDesc>Oneda’s thoughtful treatment of the belle dame is paradoxical: she is malevolent (her face momentarily
										flickers into a skull-like visage) and representative of the seemingly impossible obstacles that we must
										overcome in order to fulfill our greatest desires. She is merciless, but only in the form of regret, and only
										to those who lack the courage to commit themselves to her.</figDesc>
									<graphic url="../images/fig3.jpg"/>
								</figure>
				</div>

				<div type="section" n="6">
					<head>Screening and discussion:</head>
					<p>When we screened the film in class, the students were quick to note Oneda’s contributions to <name ref="KeatsJohn"
						>Keats</name>’s story, especially his addition of a fourth character (the navigator survives the shipwreck with an ailing,
						alcoholic ship’s physician who dies within the first few minutes; this character is likely a conjecture as to what the
						apothecary <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name> might have amounted to, had he not become a poet and a consumptive). The
						enthusiasm with which they noted and critiqued these differences between the poem and the film, even while the screening was
						underway, boded well for the more nuanced discussion to follow. After the screening, I gave the class five minutes to reflect
						on their own responses to the handout questions, and to consider Oneda’s implied responses to the same questions, given his
						handling of the poem.</p>
					<p>We opened the discussion by reviewing the first issue from the handout, the description of the knight. The students were
						unanimous in voicing their surprise (both approving and disapproving) at Oneda’s decision to cast the knight as an old man—and
						within seconds, a student noted the similarity to <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>’s <title level="m"
							>Ancient Mariner</title>, which we had read earlier. By depicting the knight as elderly, one student contended, Oneda gave
						the character an air of wisdom and experience, a superior position from which to impart a moral lesson to the young navigator:
						“do as I say, not as I have done.” Another student suggested that the casting choice made the knight seem feeble or senile,
						and that his story was somehow less convincing and reliable because of the amount of time elapsed since the events related.
						(Not surprisingly, both of these arguments had also informed our discussion of <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor"
							>Coleridge</name>.)</p>
					<p>I asked the class if they thought this directorial choice was unfaithful to <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s poem or merely
						an interpretation made possible by the poem’s ambiguities. A number of students quickly answered that Oneda had strayed from
							<name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s text; no one disagreed, though I noticed many thoughtful stares. We opened our books
						and I read through the stanzas in which <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name> offers descriptive details of the knight:
							<quote>“palely,” “haggard,” “woe-begone,” “a lily on thy brow,” “with anguish moist and fever dew”; “on thy cheeks a
							fading rose / withereth,”</quote> We agreed that none of these details explicitly tells us the knight’s age, or anything
						substantial about him beyond the expressiveness and sickliness of his face. I suggested that, for all <name ref="KeatsJohn"
							>Keats</name> tells us, the knight could be three feet tall with one eye and no teeth, wearing a ball gown and army boots.
						Within the vast realm of <emph>possibility</emph> (ignoring, for the moment, the smaller realm of <emph>probability</emph>)
						Oneda’s version of the knight actually seemed approximate to their own envisioning; but where did the students’ and Oneda’s
						ideas about the knight come from? Not from the text of “La Belle Dame” itself, I assured them.</p>
					<p>This appeared to be a disturbing proposition for many of them, and the room fell silent for a minute. I decided to move through
						the other two handout questions in short order, to leave more time at the end of class for a discussion of the implications of
						the exercise. The next handout question, involving the first speaker of the poem, drew mixed responses (I did not yet know the
						variety of explanations the question had elicited). It was generally agreed that Oneda’s invention of the navigator (or
						rather, his distillation of the poem’s narrator into the navigator), and his employment of a frame narrative, distorted the
						content and form of <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s poem. This agreement took a few minutes to materialize among a group
						of students now wary of my evidently deceptive questions. But even looking at the text, it seemed difficult to find anything
						defensible in Oneda’s handling of the poem’s first speaker.</p>
					<p>I asked the students to tell me how <emph>they</emph> had responded to the question—if not a stranded ship’s navigator, who
							<emph>was</emph> the first speaker? Reluctantly, a few students shared their ideas: one said she thought the speaker was
						the belle dame, and I saw a few nods of affirmation to this. Another student replied that the first speaker was anonymous and
						indistinguishable, and she said that Oneda could just as easily have done away with such a character altogether, since he/she
						makes no difference to the plot of the poem (after instigating it). At this, a number of students voiced disagreement, and
						shared more ideas about who the first speaker was. But with each additional suggestion came the renewed assertion from all
						corners of the room, that we simply cannot identify the speaker. To identify the speaker, one student said, was a temptation
						for the reader—and for someone making a film from the poem, it is a temptation that must be indulged. In other words, Oneda
						was compelled by the exigencies of filmmaking to “over-interpret” the poem in order to make it a comprehensible story. The
						student argued that as readers we do the same thing, but we can leave the identities of characters less resolved in our minds,
						remaining comfortable with ambiguity. Such ambiguity is difficult to convey in a film. (It seems that, after seeing the movie,
						at least a few of the students became more negatively capable.)</p>
					<p>While I was thrilled to see an emerging correlation between active reading and filmmaking, I decided to lead the discussion to
						the third and final handout question, the characterization of the lady. Again, as I would learn when I collected their
						responses, this question split the class down the middle, some characterizing the lady as a “free spirit,” others as an “evil
						temptress.” Though I had chosen the first two “objective” questions in order to emphasize the amount of
							<emph>subjective</emph> judgment needed to answer them, with this more obviously interpretive question, I had a different
						goal. Since the knight characterizes the lady and her actions, she is, in a sense, a text-within-a-text, and one that comes to
						us pre-interpreted, refracted through the knight’s own convictions and (perhaps) misjudgments. Nevertheless, in my experience
						teaching this poem, students rarely consider the possibility of the knight as an unreliable narrator. Even when they notice
						that the lady never speaks for herself, they do not usually propose that the knight is a dubious—even downright
						bad—interpreter or relater of his own experience. These issues of fallible narration (often familiar to the students as a
						convention of the dramatic monologue, from Chaucer’s <title level="m">Canterbury Tales</title> or Browning’s “My Last Duchess”
						at least) greatly enrich a reading of “La Belle Dame,” and I was interested to see how Oneda’s film might or might not
						influence the students’ awareness of such narrative complications.</p>
					<p>Usually, when I teach this poem, I note lines 19 and 27-28 as instances at which the knight’s judgment must be scrutinized.
						“She look’d at me <emph>as</emph> she did love,” can mean either that she looked at the knight <emph>while</emph> she loved
						him, or that she looked at the knight <emph>as if</emph> she loved him, in which case the knight has made a questionable
						observation, and one that the lady’s actions later in the poem seem to undermine. Similarly, the phrase “sure in language
						strange she said— / I love thee true,” hinges on our understanding of the word <emph>sure</emph>: it might imply that the lady
						said “I love thee true” <emph>surely</emph>, with confidence. Alternatively, the word might stand in for equivocal phrasing
						like <emph>I am sure that</emph> or <emph>to be sure</emph>, in which case the knight is casting doubt on his ability to
						translate the lady’s “language strange,” even as he claims self-assurance. </p>
					<p>Oneda does a fine job with these ambiguities. As the ancient knight tells his tale to the navigator in voiceover, the
						flashback-story comes to life on the screen. For the most part, during this voiceover, the young knight and the lady
						communicate through meaningful glances, without spoken language. But at the exact moment when the ancient knight recounts the
						cryptic declaration of love (“I could not understand her words, but I am sure she said, ‘I love thee true’”), the lady in the
						flashback actually speaks a few words of unintelligible non-language, suggesting the fallibility of the knight’s translation.
						I wanted to see how the students reacted to this dramatization of one of the poem’s subtler elements. Would it change the way
						they interpreted the poem?</p>
					<p>As we reviewed the handout question, the students who shared their responses were those who believed the lady was motivated by
						neither good nor evil, the “free spirit” group (as I would later label them). None of the <emph>femme fatale</emph> group
						volunteered their thoughts. Indeed, when I asked if anyone in the class felt that the lady was motivated by revenge or hatred,
						a student raised his hand and said that he had thought so after reading the poem, but not after seeing the film. A number of
						his classmates nodded consensually. I asked them why. Two students replied that Oneda’s film made them think that the lady
						represented a positive concept (“ambition” and “creativity”), and that the fault lies not in the lady, but in the knight’s
						inability to commit to her. “Does the knight really understand her?” I asked.</p>
					<p>A number of hands went up immediately. The students had appreciated Oneda’s use of voiceover narration to convey ambiguity,
						and—to my delight—they noted the same ambiguity in lines 27-28 of the poem without my prompting. One of them suggested that
						the knight in the film was an unreliable narrator. I asked if the same might be said of the knight in <name ref="KeatsJohn"
							>Keats</name>’s poem, and the overwhelming response was “yes.” “It was way more obvious in the movie, though,” one student
						added. I told her to hang onto that thought.</p>
					<p>With the three handout questions laid out before us, we now had two big issues to consider: from the first question, the issue
						of <emph>where our visual ideas of the knight came from</emph>; from the second and third questions, the issue of <emph>the
							differences between reading a text and adapting it for a film</emph>. Fifteen minutes remained in the class period.</p>
					<p>I introduced the first issue in a broad context. If our conception of the knight in the poem is not drawn from the poem itself,
						then it is coming from some other source or sources—what does this suggest about reading? Is it an individual or communal (and
						cumulative) process? Is it an active or passive engagement with a text? I established these questions as the basis for our
						discussion, then I asked a more finite question: “when you addressed the first prompt on the handout (before seeing the film)
						did you think it was an objective or subjective question?” The response, predictably, was that they had thought of the
						question as “more on the objective side,” though they now realized the problems with this conclusion. “<name ref="KeatsJohn"
							>Keats</name> doesn’t tell us what the knight looks like, or the lady. It’s like we have to picture them in our heads as
						we read.” After some more discussion, another student added, “even the most basic details in this poem—we have to create
						them.” I suggested, then, that reading—especially reading a poem like this one—is an active process in which the reader fills
						in a lot of gaps, often without realizing that he or she has done so. </p>
					<p>A student admitted that when he reads novels he “casts” certain Hollywood actors in the characters’ roles. In some way, I said,
						we all do this. Didn’t we cast the knight, if not with a specific actor, at least with our idea of what knights are
							<emph>supposed</emph> to look like? On both a conscious and subconscious level, we are constantly integrating the
						information we get from the text we are reading (whether a sparsely detailed poem like this, or a richly detailed realist
						novel) with information we already have. Being aware of, and analyzing this synthetic process, I argued, makes us sharper,
						more sophisticated readers and critics.</p>
					<p>We talked about this a little more, in reference to other texts we had read (and again, <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor"
							>Coleridge</name> loomed large in the discussion). By way of analogy, someone mentioned the great difference between
						reading a play and seeing it performed. I explained that this was not a distinction lost on the Romantics (a few of the
						students had, in fact, read <name ref="LambCharles">Lamb</name>’s essay on the topic in a <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam"
							>Shakespeare</name> course). In the remaining time, I turned to the comparison of reading and filmic adaptation.</p>
					<p>I began, “Someone mentioned that the possibility of seeing the knight as an unreliable narrator was ‘more obvious in the
						movie.’ Why?” A few students replied that “seeing it [the poem] visualized made it more obvious.” Again I asked why, and was
						met with silence. I offered more: “In the film, you tended to notice the moment when the knight interprets—probably
							<emph>misinterprets</emph>—the lady’s words, ‘I love you.’ But this moment is there in the text too. Specifically, what
						made this moment stand out in the film, more so than in the poem?” I suggested that the answer might be somehow related to the
						just-mentioned differences between reading and watching <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>. A student answered
						that Oneda had decided to make this issue important in his film, and that was why he used the voiceover technique. “Good,” I
						said, “as with his use of the navigator as the first speaker in the poem, Oneda makes a series of interpretive choices in his
						film. We’ve mentioned that we like to ‘cast’ actors in the mental performances of our readings—so let me ask you this: is what
						Oneda does in adapting <name ref="KeatsJohn">Keats</name>’s poem for a movie different from or similar to what we do in
						reading the poem on our own? Indeed, is there a big difference between reading—what we might call interpretation—and adapting?
						Or is all reading adaptation?”</p>
					<p>With time running out, I left them with this question. This had been a lively discussion, and the questions it raised
						(especially this last one) were recurrent throughout the quarter. After this exercise I found it much easier to move beyond
						plot-level discussions of texts to meta-commentaries on the practice of reading and the dynamics of interpretation. The
						knight’s superimposition of his own desires upon the lady’s “language strange” became a cautionary example for us as critical
						readers. I worried that I would need to explain further: the point was <emph>not</emph> that no right or wrong way to read a
						text existed and that reading was an entirely subjective experience. But the students understood: they were generally prepared
						to critique their assumptions, and to consider elisions and lacunae in literary texts as rhetorical strategies. They were more
						aware of the dimensions of their personal involvement in the act of reading—that is, aware that reading is by definition a
						co-creative endeavor. I believe that I also succeeded in helping the students to appreciate filmic adaptation as a means of
						literary criticism, in which a director makes an argument about a text through a series of interpretive choices.</p>
				</div>

			</div>
			<div type="citations">
				<head>Works Cited</head>
				<listBibl>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor</author>
							<title level="m">Lectures 1809-1819 On Literature</title>

							<editor role='editor'>Foakes, R.A.</editor>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="vol">2 vols</biblScope>
								<pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Princeton UP</publisher>
								<date>1987</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<editor role='editor'>Cox, Jeffrey</editor>
							<editor role='editor'>Gamer, Michael</editor>
							<title level="m">The Broadview Anthology of Romantic Drama</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Broadview Press</publisher>
								<date>2003</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Hazlitt, William</author>
							<title level="m">The Complete Works of William Hazlitt</title>

							<editor role='editor'>Howe, P.P.</editor>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="vol">21 vols</biblScope>
								<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
								<date>1956-71</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Keats, John</author>
							<title level="m">Complete Poems</title>
							<editor role='editor'>Stillinger, Jack</editor>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Harvard UP</publisher>
								<date>1978</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Kelley, Theresa</author>
							<title level="a">Poetics and the Politics of Reception: Keats's 'La Belle Dame sans Merci'</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<title level="j">ELH</title>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="vol">54</biblScope>
								<biblScope type="no">2</biblScope>
								<date>Summer 1987</date>
								<biblScope type="pp">333-62</biblScope>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>McGann, Jerome</author>
							<title level="m">The Beauty of Inflections</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
								<date>1985</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<title level="m">La Belle Dame Sans Merci</title>
							<editor role='editor'>Oneda, Dir. Hidetoshi</editor>
							<edition>DVD</edition>
							<imprint>
								<publisher>Prod. Celophaine Films</publisher>
								<date>2005</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Lamb, Charles</author>
							<author>Mary</author>
							<title level="m">The Works of Charles and Mary Lamb</title>

							<editor role='editor'>Lucas, E.V.</editor>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="vol">7 vols</biblScope>
								<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Methuen &amp; Co.</publisher>
								<date>1903-05</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
