<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="RCs.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Lifting the Painted Veil: </title>
				<title type="subordinate">Romantic Drama as Holy Theatre</title>
				<author>
					<name>Amy Muse</name>
				</author>
				<editor role='editor'>
					<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Pedagogies Editor</resp>
					<name>Kate Singer</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>commons4.2011.muse_holy_theatre</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
					Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
						or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
						purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
						use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
						are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
						with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
						permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
						requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
						forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
						conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
						them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
						have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
						Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
						continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
						a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
						use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Lifting the Painted Veil: </title>
						<title level="a" type="subordinate">Romantic Drama as Holy Theatre</title>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename>Amy</forename>
								<surname>Muse</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Teaching Romantic Drama: </title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Pedagogies Commons Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
								Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
							<biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for
						‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
						keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
						such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
						been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
					10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
						on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g18" scheme="#genre"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<date>2011-02-18</date>
				<list>
					<item>revised TEI</item>
					<item>XSLT</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Dave Rettenmaier</name>
				<date>2010-06-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				<date>2009-11-01T15:01:00</date>
				<list>
					<item>Proofed issue in Open Office Format</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">

				<head>
					<title level="a">Lifting the Painted Veil: Romantic Drama as Holy
						Theatre</title>
				</head>
				<byline>
					<docAuthor>Amy Muse</docAuthor>
					<affiliation>University of St. Thomas</affiliation>
				</byline>

				<p n="1">“Holy Theatre” is a term known to drama students and theatre practitioners
					primarily from <name ref="BrookPeter">Peter Brook</name>’s treatment of it in
					his 1968 classic, <title level="m">The Empty Space</title>. It is, <name
						ref="BrookPeter">Brook</name> says, “the Theatre of the Invisible – Made –
					Visible” (42); it is the kind of theatre that arises from a deeply felt urge to
					“capture in our arts the invisible currents that rule our lives” (45). <name
						ref="InnesChristopher">Christopher Innes</name>, in his study <title
						level="m">Holy Theatre</title>, observes that its “hallmark” is an
					“aspiration to transcendence, to the spiritual in its widest sense” (3) and that
					it attempts to “transcribe subjective experience directly into stage terms”
					(29). The effect is meant to be communal: a theatre “that brings its spectators
					into emotional harmony with one another by celebrating their common identity as
					human beings” (Auslander 13).<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="1">Innes’s and
						Auslander’s descriptions may strike readers as very Romantic and therefore
						familiar, but some further clarification may be in order since the term
						“holy theatre” can be misleading and, for some, off-putting. It does not
						mean, for instance, a “religious” drama; indeed, much of <name
							ref="ArtaudAntonin">Artaud</name>’s and <name ref="GrotowskiJerzy"
							>Grotowski</name>’s work in the twentieth century (and <name
							ref="IbsenHenrik">Ibsen</name>’s and <name ref="StrindbergAugust"
							>Strindberg</name>’s, for that matter) was considered sacrilegious, even
						blasphemous. Most theatre that meets the criteria I discuss in this essay is
						no longer given the label of “holy,” and a look at the scholarship of <name
							ref="InnesChristopher">Christopher Innes</name> is instructive for
						understanding why. His book <title level="m">Holy Theatre: Ritual and the
							Avant Garde</title> (1981) was revised and updated in 1992 under the
						title <title level="m">Avant Garde Theatre 1892-1992</title>. While the
						content and organization of the book remain much the same in the course of a
						little over a decade, he felt it necessary to change his title: the term
						“holy theatre” had apparently run its course. Did it seem hopelessly dated,
						a hangover from the 1960s, like “groovy” and “far out”? The clue is found in
							<name ref="InnesChristopher">Innes</name>’s initial definition of his
						book’s subject. In the 1981 <title level="m">Holy Theatre</title> his
						introduction describes a number of qualities (e.g., exploration of dream
						states, interest in ritual) that the works of this master current of theatre
						share, and observes that “it is in light of these qualities that the term
						coined by <name ref="ArtaudAntonin">Antonin Artaud</name> is so apt: ‘the
						Holy Theatre’” (3). However, in 1993’s <title level="m">Avant Garde Theatre
							1892-1992</title>, following the same description of qualities, <name
							ref="InnesChristopher">Innes</name> remarks that “<name
							ref="ArtaudAntonin">Antonin Artaud</name>’s pretentious claim to a ‘Holy
						Theatre’—picked up by various avant garde artists . . . is revealing” (3).
						Perhaps there’s little talk of a holy theatre, then, because the idea (and
						the ideal?) of a holy theatre has become pretentious. It is considered
						affected, showy, claims more than it can actually demonstrate. This course
						is hoping to revive the term for its evocative power—or at least to revive
						an interest in this theoretical approach to theatre and its plays.</note>
					<name ref="BrookPeter">Brook</name> took the term “holy” from Antonin <name
						ref="ArtaudAntonin">Artaud</name>’s vision of theatre as “a metaphysical
					force,” “holy rite and quasi-religious practice” (<name ref="EsslinMartin"
						>Esslin</name>, <title level="m"><name ref="ArtaudAntonin">Antonin
							Artaud</name></title> 101). <name ref="ArtaudAntonin">Artaud</name>’s
					work was in part a return to and a nostalgia for the prehistory of theatre, the
					ancient cult rituals and goat-songs that developed into Greek drama, and that
					were celebrated as the “Dionysian” split from “Apollonian” harmony, rationalism,
					and sculpture in Nietzsche’s highly influential <title level="m">The Birth of
						Tragedy</title> (1872). This metaphysical or “holy” impulse in theatre has a
					long history, and can be seen as one of the “master currents” of dramatic
					literature and theatre theory. </p>
				<p n="2">As is well known, the study of European drama has greatly favored the
					master current that flows toward realism and naturalism, a narrative of progress
					that celebrates the late nineteenth century arrival of the “well-made play” and
					the “problem play” (ushered in by the reigning triumvirate of <name
						ref="IbsenHenrik">Ibsen</name>, <name ref="StrindbergAugust"
						>Strindberg</name>, and <name ref="ChekhovAnton">Chekhov</name>, with the
					frequent addition of Shaw), dramas that work from the “bottom up,” grounded in
					the material world and social issues. Plays that endeavor something else, namely
					to stage subjective states, have been dropped into the valley of the unstageable
					and unstageworthy. These are the plays of the master current of the holy
					theatre. They tend to get labeled “closet dramas,” “symbolist,” “impressionist”
					or “expressionist,” “experimental” or “avant garde.” Philosophical plays
					concerned with revealing states of mind, consciousness, dreams, ghosts, magic,
					they work from the “top down” and begin in abstraction, “sojourning through
					consciousness and affecting the ‘reality’ of the material world beneath it,” as
						<name ref="DemastesWilliam">William Demastes</name> explains in <title
						level="m">Staging Consciousness: Theater and the Materialization of
						Mind</title> (15). The plays are an exploration of the human condition, but
					from the “inside out” rather than the social realism approach of “outside in.”
					(However, plays with the greatest lasting impact tend to be a combination of
					both these traditions, from <title level="m">Hamlet</title> to <title level="m"
						>Death of a Salesman</title> to <title level="m">Angels in
						America</title>.)<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="2"><name
							ref="DemastesWilliam">William Demastes</name> argues in <title level="m"
							>Staging Consciousness: Theater and the Materialization of Mind</title>
						(Ann Arbor: U of Michigan P, 2002) that “<emph>either</emph> consciousness
							<emph>or</emph> materiality is not really a choice. Inevitably, theater
						uses a both/and proposition of confronting consciousness integrally through
						materialism rather than discretely through mystical or spiritual channels”
						(41). I have borrowed the useful terms “bottom up” and “top down” from his
						work. </note>
				</p>
				<p n="3">The dramatists of this lineage (loosely defined) were also deeply invested
					as theorists of the theatre (or, put differently, this way of seeing theatre
					attracted theorists who became dramatists to test their theories). We see this
					pattern very clearly in the emergent Romantic theatre of the eighteenth century
					in Germany (e.g., in the work of Lessing, Schiller, Tieck, and Kleist) and in
					early nineteenth-century England in the staged theories of <name
						ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name> and <name
						ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor"> Samuel Taylor Coleridge</name>.<note
						place="foot" resp="editors" n="3">Theatre and consciousness studies have
						only grown more popular in recent years, alongside and as a result of the
						rise of cognitive sciences in humanities research. In addition to Demastes’s
							<title level="m">Staging Consciousness</title>, see Ralph Yarrow, <title
							level="m">Sacred Theatre</title> (2007) and Yarrow and Peter Malekin’s
							<title level="m">Consciousness, Literature, and Theatre</title> (1997)
						as well as Daniel Meyer-Dinkgräfe’s <title level="m">Theatre and
							Consciousness</title> (2005), <title level="m">Performing
							Consciousness</title> (2010), edited with Per Brask, and his edited
						issue, “Drama and Consciousness,” for <title level="j">Studies in the
							Literary Imagination</title> (34.2: Fall 2001). Within Romantic studies,
						Alan Richardson’s work is essential reading, from his 1988 <title level="m"
							>A Mental Theater: Poetic Drama and Consciousness in the Romantic
							Age</title> to his more recent <title level="m">British Romanticism and
							the Science of the Mind</title> (2005) and <title level="m">The Neural
							Sublime: Cognitive Theories and Romantic Texts</title> (2010).</note>
				</p>
				<p n="4">In this drama course we examine some of the major dramatic texts that could
					be said to make up a holy theatre tradition, with <name
						ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>’s <title level="m"
						>Remorse</title> (1813) and <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s
						<title level="m">Orra</title> (1812) representing Romantic drama.<note
						place="foot" resp="editors" n="4">My argument is to incorporate Romantic
						drama into courses on drama (where it has long been neglected), but the
						approach I outline in this essay could certainly be used for an entire
						course on Romantic drama. Plays such as <title level="m">Manfred</title> and
							<title level="m">Prometheus Unbound</title> obviously fit the paradigm
						of exploring consciousness. For this course I have chosen to include <title
							level="m">Orra</title> and <title level="m">Remorse</title> because of
						their intriguing relationship to Shakespeare, the Gothic, and the avant
						garde, and for the opportunities they present for examining notions of
						“high” and “low,” “avant garde” and “popular.” They are also both included,
						most conveniently, in Jeffrey N. Cox and Michael Gamer’s <title level="m"
							>Broadview Anthology of Romantic Drama</title> (2003).</note> Alongside
					these plays we read theatre theory and study developments in stagecraft that
					allowed dramatists to explore subjective states onstage. In this context
					students are encouraged to see Romantic drama as inspired by the vision and
					techniques learned from <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>’s
					plays (rather than weak imitations of <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam"
						>Shakespeare</name>), as a reworking and transformation of the Gothic, and
					as the birthplace of the modern avant garde. To many Romanticists this is going
					to look (suspiciously, perhaps) like the “old” approach to Romantic drama—that
					is, Romantic drama as “mental theatre,” a label under which it has not tended to
					fare well in criticism. However, when studied within the lineage of holy
					theatre, Romantic drama can stand out as a peak—rather than a valley—in the
					history of dramatic literature and theatre theory.<note place="foot" n="5"
						resp="editors">
						<p rend="noCount">I am not interested in establishing a new hierarchy. But,
							for illustrative purposes only, let's say we charted a theatre history
							using as our standard the criteria of holy theatre (rather than the
							criteria of realism): plays in which the invisible is made visible, in
							which states of mind are explored onstage, and what is most prized is
							not verisimilitude, mimesis, the staging and working out of a dramatic
							conflict, psychological characterization, and dialogue on social issues,
							but instead the unveiling of the hidden, the representation of internal
							states of mind and feeling, and symbolic presentation of psychological
							issues. Furthermore, in these plays, language is used at its height not
							for witty stichomythia, political speechifying, or ironic distancing,
							but for the revelation of internal states, the representation of being,
							and startling the audience into communal feeling. A charting of “peaks”
							and “valleys” might show <title level="m">Remorse</title>, <title
								level="m">Orra</title>, <title level="m">Manfred</title>, <title
								level="m">Prometheus Unbound</title>, and <title level="m">A Dream
								Play</title> as peaks, and <title level="m">The Way of the
								World</title>, <title level="m">A Doll’s House</title>, and <title
								level="m">The Iceman Cometh</title> as valleys.</p>
						<p rend="noCount">My idea here is not to denigrate the plays in the new
							“valley”; I’ve deliberately selected excellent, “classic” plays to point
							out the absurdity of doing so. It is instead to question the idea of
							constructing a historical narrative of peaks and valleys, “golden ages”
							and “dark ages.” Categorizing dramas by their affinities with parallel
							“master currents,” grouping them by their primary concerns and the
							approaches to staging those concerns (the “top down” and “inside out”
							versus “bottom up” or “outside in” methods mentioned above) may prove a
							more effective method. </p>
						<p rend="noCount"> One key reason Romantic drama has been seen as odd is
							because of the way theatre history was produced and, later, reproduced
							in teaching. As <name ref="BrattonJacky">Jacky Bratton</name> has
							written, “the continuing strength of the received way of reading theatre
							history can be gauged from the difficulties critics, performers and
							historians still have when they attempt to recuperate anything from the
							early nineteenth-century stage” (<title level="m">New Readings in
								Theatre History </title>12). My long-range goal is to re-see
							dramatic history and encourage the reorganization of courses in theatre
							history and dramatic literature. For instance, instead of the standard
							two-semester survey that moves chronologically from the ancient Greeks
							to the present, we could teach a course in two master currents of world
							drama, the “holy” and the “rough,” to use Peter <name ref="BrookPeter"
								>Brook</name>’s terms, or the “top down” and “inside out” interest
							in consciousness, versus the “bottom up” and “outside in” interest in
							social realism. While the typical historical timeline reveals the
							dialectical development of theatre and drama between “outside in” and
							“inside out” approaches, the “master currents” approach avoids the
							conception of peaks and valleys, and may allow students to see more
							clearly patterns of influence between particular playwrights and other
							theatre artists, and of approaches to playwriting and theatre. Core
							differences on the <emph>function</emph> of drama and theatre come into
							focus, and this master current challenges some fundamental assumptions
							of drama and theatre, such as whether there is even a natural
							relationship between drama and the theatre—that a dramatic text is
							indeed intended expressly for and only completed upon performance. </p>
						<p rend="noCount">For an argument similar to my own, see Jeffrey N. Cox’s
							discussion of Romanticism’s “counter-theatre of ‘virtuality’” (177) in
							“The Death of Tragedy; or, The Birth of Melodrama,” <title level="m">The Performing
								Century: Nineteenth-Century Theatre’s History</title>, ed. Tracy C. Davis and
							Peter Holland (Hampshire and New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2007),
							161-81.</p>
					</note>
				</p>
				<p n="5">There are several tributaries of the master current of holy theatre: one
					focuses on pure form (we see this in the modernist avant garde in particular,
					e.g., in the theatrical experiments of Gertrude Stein and Wassily Kandinsky),
					another on myth and ritual (which points up the ancient origins of holy theatre,
					running from Euripides’s <title level="m">The Bacchae</title> to Peter Shaffer’s
						<title level="m">Equus</title>). In order to highlight the stream of holy
					theatre attempting the revelation of consciousness, this version of the course
					begins with <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>’s “strategic
					opacity” and <title level="m">Hamlet</title>, the Ur-text of the dramatic
					representation of consciousness.</p>
				<p n="6">To Romantics and their followers, the conditions of the Elizabethan theatre
					(and the thereby conditioned Elizabethan audiences) were ideal because they drew
					upon the imagination, truly created a “theatre of the mind.” Those early modern
					audiences viewed a virtually bare stage with no external lighting (at the
					outdoor theatres such as the Globe, anyway); the language of the plays
					frequently remind them to imagine the scene that is being played out before
					them. <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>’s eighteenth-century
					admirers developed a new form of literary criticism—“character criticism”—in
					response to the complexity and seeming humanness of his characters, and gave us
					the now-familiar figure of the natural genius <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam"
						>Shakespeare</name> who had discovered the secret to how to reveal
					interiority on the stage. <name ref="SchlegelAugustWilhelmvon">A. W.
						Schlegel</name>’s image from his 1808 lectures is a familiar one: <name
						ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>’s characters are like “watches
					with crystalline plates and cases, which, while they point out the hours as
					correctly as other watches, enable us at the same time to perceive the inward
					springs whereby all this is accomplished” (“A Course of Lectures on Dramatic Art
					and Literature” 362). More recently, <name ref="GreenblattStephen">Stephen
						Greenblatt</name> has echoed this language in <title level="m">Will in the
						World</title> when he argues that <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam"
						>Shakespeare</name> “perfected the means to represent inwardness” (299)
					through the innovation of the soliloquy, in particular what <name
						ref="GreenblattStephen">Greenblatt</name> refers to as “strategic opacity,”
					or a new technique of “radical excision” in which <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam"
						>Shakespeare</name> took out a “key explanatory element, thereby occluding
					the rationale, motivation, or ethical principle that accounted for the action
					that was to unfold” (323-24). Relying on “inner logic” rather than causal
					events, <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name> “fashioned an inner
					structure through the resonant echoing of key terms, the subtle development of
					images, the brilliant orchestration of scenes, the complex unfolding of ideas,
					the intertwining of parallel plots, the uncovering of psychological obsession”
					(324). <name ref="GreenblattStephen">Greenblatt</name>’s <name
						ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name> is remarkably Romantic, and
					effectively introduces holy theatre dramaturgy; strategic opacity was “not only
					a new aesthetic strategy,” but “expressed <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam"
						>Shakespeare</name>’s root perception of existence, his understanding of
					what could be said and what should remain unspoken, his preference for things
					untidy, damaged, and unresolved over things neatly arranged, well made, and
					settled” (324). </p>
				<p n="7">Both <title level="m">Hamlet</title> (1600-01) and <title level="m">The
						Tempest</title> (1610-11) exhibit the Renaissance view of the world as a
					stage and faith in theatre as a means of revealing truth. Thanks in large part
					to Romantic writers and critics—Goethe, Lamb, Hazlitt, Coleridge—<title
						level="m">Hamlet</title> has come to be considered a play about
					consciousness, and Hamlet the “prince of the inward insurrection” (<name
						ref="GreenblattStephen">Greenblatt</name> 303). When read as a foundational
					text of holy theatre, what comes into focus are Hamlet's conversation with the
					Ghost and the unfolding of Hamlet’s consciousness through the soliloquies,
					tracing the fluctuations of his mind from his first appearance to Act V. The
					course then moves to <title level="m">The Tempest</title>, which, among its
					dominant interpretations, can be seen as a play about the magical power of
					theatre to bring about reconciliation and forgiveness. It also provides an
					excellent entrance into <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>’s
						<title level="m">Remorse</title>, as both plays use an act of magic, of
					dramatic illusion, to prick the conscience of and draw remorse from a wayward
						brother.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="6"><name
								ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s <title level="m">Orra</title>
							(1812) is chronologically prior to <title level="m">Remorse</title>
							(1813), but teaching it afterward allows the course to move immediately
							into <name ref="StrindbergAugust">Strindberg</name>’s <title level="m"
								>The Ghost Sonata</title>, which is similarly “hauntological” and
							includes an apparition as well as “living ghosts,” characters who are,
							like Orra in the final scene of the play, psychologically haunted and
							poised between death and life. Moreover, <name ref="StrindbergAugust"
								>Strindberg</name>’s desire for an intimate performance space that
							could capture the nuances of his plays—which resulted in the founding of
							the Intimate Theater in Stockholm in 1907—carries startling echoes of
								<name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s “Introductory
							Discourse.”
						</note>
				</p>

				<div type="section" n="2">
					<head>Teaching Samuel Taylor <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor"
						>Coleridge</name>’s <title level="m">Remorse</title></head>

					<p n="8">The main plotline of <title level="m">Remorse</title> echoes themes in
							<title level="m">The Tempest</title>; in both, an ambitious and
						rebellious younger brother (Antonio in <title level="m">The Tempest</title>,
						Ordonio in <title level="m">Remorse</title>) plots to kill a virtuous older
						brother (Prospero, Alvar) and sends that virtuous brother into exile. (The
						differences can be illuminating to discuss. Prospero can set up
						circumstances to awaken Antonio to his wrongdoing, but cannot ultimately
						transform Antonio’s inner self; while Prospero expresses forgiveness in the
						end, Antonio does not appear to express remorse.) In <title level="m"
							>Remorse</title>, while Alvar is gone (Ordonio had arranged to have him
						killed, and assumes him dead), Ordonio tries to win over Alvar’s beloved,
						Teresa. She wants nothing to do with Ordonio, and, anyway, is waiting with
						hope for Alvar’s eventual return, since his body has never turned up.
						Ordonio designs a spectacular illusion to convince Teresa of Alvar’s death:
						a glowing altar which will summon the image of the dead Alvar. Unbeknownst
						to all (except the audience), Alvar is not dead; he had escaped the assassin
						and has returned with a plot to awaken Ordonio to his evil deeds. Notably,
						this plan is <emph>not</emph> to seek revenge on Ordonio, but to bring him
						to remorse. Alvar manipulates the altar trick, making it boomerang on
						Ordonio: the altar bursts into flames to reveal a picture of the
						assassination attempt on Alvar, masterminded by Ordonio. Thus Ordonio
						realizes (1) Alvar is still alive, and (2) he knows about the plot to kill
						him. </p>
					<p n="9">
						<title level="m">Remorse</title> (1813) is a reworking of an earlier
						revolution-oriented play entitled <title level="m">Osorio</title> (1797)
						into a deeper, more psychological study of consciousness: the revision of
						title alone gives us a clue. In <title level="m">Remorse</title>
						<name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name> is staging a shift in
						consciousness, which brings about a change in conscience.<note place="foot"
							resp="editors" n="7">The psychological state of remorse was a familiar
							theme in Gothic plays, although <name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Jeffrey
								Cox</name> points out that <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor"
								>Coleridge</name>'s work, as one in the second wave of Gothic
							popularity, reassesses the theme and can be read as a “culminating work
							in the Gothic tradition” (30). <name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> charts
							two major surges of Gothic drama, the first in the 1790s, which <name
								ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name> catches onto with
								<title level="m">Osorio</title> (1797), the second hitting its peak
							in 1815, which <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>
							anticipates with <title level="m">Remorse</title> (1813). <name
								ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> links these two surges to political
							issues surrounding the French Revolution and Napoleonic Wars,
							particularly the fall of the Bastille and the fall of Napoleon. See
								<name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name>, ed. and intro., <title level="m"
								>Seven Gothic Dramas 1789-1825</title> (Athens: Ohio UP, 1992),
							30-32.</note> In the <title level="m">Table Talk</title> jottings,
						Coleridge expressed a special fondness for <title level="m">Remorse</title>:
						“the ‘Remorse’ is certainly a great favourite of mine,” he stated, “the more
						so as certain pet abstract notions of mine are therein expounded” (II: 360).
						Exactly what those pet abstract notions were was never explicitly stated,
						but reading <title level="m">Remorse</title> within the communality that is
						characteristic of holy theatre illuminates the play as a tragedy intended to
						wake not just the character Ordonio but the audience from their dogmatic
						slumbers or wrongdoings and force them to confront the Otherness that exists
						inside as well as outside themselves. As has been discussed in a number of
							studies,<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="8">As well as <name
								ref="ThomasSophie">Sophie Thomas</name>’s “Seeing Things (‘As They
							Are’)” from <title level="j">Studies in Romanticism</title> (included on
							the Reading List), see <name ref="MooreJohnDavid">John David
								Moore</name>, “<name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>
							and the ‘modern Jacobinical Drama’: <title level="m">Osorio</title>,
								<title level="m">Remorse</title>, and the Development of <name
								ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>’s Critique of the
							Stage, 1797-1816” <title level="j">Bulletin of Research in the
								Humanities</title> 85.4 (Winter 1982): 443-64; and <name
								ref="MortensenPeter">Peter Mortensen</name>, “The Robbers and the
							Police: British Romantic Drama and the Gothic Treacheries of <name
								ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>’s <title level="m"
								>Remorse</title>” in <title level="m">European Gothic: A Spirited
								Exchange 1760 – 1960</title>, ed. Avril Horner (Manchester UP,
							2002): 128–46.</note> in order to present this concept effectively,
							<name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name> drew upon the
						spectacular stagecraft of the popular Gothic drama, which contradicts his
						theoretical writing, where he finds the Gothic weak and even dangerous.</p>
					<p n="10">As a companion text, students can read “Letter II” of “Satyrane’s
						Letters”—included in Chapter XXII of the 1816 <title level="m">Biographia
							Literaria</title> but written in 1798—where <name
							ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name> as much as accuses the
						Gothic theatre of inciting terror. He found the self-reflection of Gothic
						drama dangerous on at least two counts. The Gothic drama had a tendency
						merely to reflect, rather than to challenge, the selves of the audience; the
						values often reflected an easy morality that kept the audiences complacent
						and inert. Also a dangerous aspect of facile self-reflection, and a more
						tempting one for <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name> and
						others, was, as <name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Jeffrey Cox</name> notes in his
						discussion of North's <title level="m">The Kentish Barons</title>, that the
						emotions can be “more deeply rooted by reflection,” a feature much
						glamourized in Gothic hero/villains. One ideally wants neither passive
						reflection nor the dangerous inward turn to self-consciousness, both of
						which can result in fixation and a resistance to change, but instead a
						self-consciousness which has its ultimate origin in a moral relation to
						others and which develops dialectically in continual relation to others. One
						way to break out of a potentially solipsistic cycle is to engage with
						others, and for a writer, the stage is therefore an ideal medium. <name
							ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name> was frustrated with the
						limitations of the commercial stage of his day, but he knew that that was
						the means through which to present such ideas visibly and publicly, and to
						reach the widest audience for his ideas. As <name ref="GalperinWilliam"
							>William Galperin</name> points out in <title level="m">The Return of
							the Visible in British Romanticism</title>, issues of the visible
						continually verge upon issues involving <emph>community</emph> (164) and,
						though <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name> in his criticism
						may have occasionally demonstrated an anti-theatrical bias, he reached for
						the visible to present the transformation of a consciousness to and for a
						community. In <title level="m">Remorse</title> he adapted the Gothic formula
						to his own purpose, and used the Gothic spectacle to affect his audiences,
						as he advises in “Satyrane’s Letters,” “in union with the activity both of
						[their] understanding and imagination” (XXII:437).</p>
					<p n="11">The Drury Lane playbill for <title level="m">Remorse</title>
						advertises all new sets, which, according to the dictates of the stage
						directions, included “wild and mountainous” country scenery and a desolate
						cavern dripping with water; the setting is the Spanish Inquisition, a remote
						and terror-ridden time. <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>
						commissioned a score from Michael Kelly, who had composed the music for the
						most successful of all Gothic dramas, Matthew Lewis’s <title level="m">The
							Castle Spectre</title> (1797). As Paula Backscheider has noted, “Gothic
						drama used music in sophisticated ways to engage the senses while
						subliminally both exercising and containing anxieties” (173); it was as
						crucial to the play as scores are to film and, increasingly, theatre today.
						The dramatic structure of the play, however, is focused on Ordonio's
						consciousness. <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name> wastes no
						time getting to his purpose; very little exposition is given before Alvar
						declares that he has returned to confront his brother and “rouse within him
						/ REMORSE!” in order to “save him from himself” (I.i.18-19). Preparations
						begin at once for the visible spectacle which will force upon Ordonio a
						cathartic experience, described by Alvar as “the punishment that cleanses
						hearts” (I.ii.319)—remorse, rather than revenge. This experience is designed
						to raise Ordonio's self-consciousness which will in turn prick his
						conscience and force him to face his transgressions. The visual elements are
						crucial: Alvar queries his servant Zulimez concerning what they need, “Above
						all, the picture / Of the assassination—.” “—Be assured / That it remains
						uninjured, Zulimez answers him (I.i.92-4). The spectacle will work in such a
						way, Alvar discloses when alone, that “That worst bad man shall find / A
						picture, which will wake the hell within him, / And rouse a fiery whirlwind
						in his conscience” (II.ii.172-74).</p>
					<p n="12">In order to understand how Gothic techniques can work to present
						onstage the awakening of a consciousness—and, perhaps, to model a
						transformation of consciousness in the audience—try staging the key scene of
						the play in your classroom. This is the moment of the climactic trick that
						boomerangs on Ordonio, the overwhelming spectacle that results in the first
						awakening of his conscience.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="9">It
							should be noted that the scene enacted, III.i, is <emph>not</emph> the
							scene in which Ordonio feels remorse. It works much like “The Mouse
							Trap” in <title level="m">Hamlet</title> in that the consequence is that
							Ordonio (like Claudius) has been aroused to the point where he is
							conscious that someone is working on him, and so he becomes watchful. He
							feels guilty, yes, but only to the extent that, again, like Claudius, he
							is anxious to rid himself of the external causes of his pain; in other
							words, he seeks to kill the “traitors” (Isidore, and the “sorcerer” [the
							disguised Alvar]) rather than experience fully the internal pain and
							attempt to alleviate it through conversion and reformation. However,
							others notice the experience he underwent, and become players in the
							process of forcing his essential confrontation with what he tried to do
							to Alvar, which finally occurs in V.i. Unfortunately, Ordonio has hardly
							begun to experience the pangs of true remorse when Alhadra and a band of
							Morescos enter and demand Ordonio's life in exchange for his murder of
							Isidore, a conclusion that comes far too quickly for many spectators
							(and readers) to feel the full impact of the remorse, and undercuts
								<name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>’s apparent
							design.</note> This spectacle is the showpiece of the evening. It was
						well-advertised, and no theatrical elements were spared. Thomas Barnes’s
						review of the play (included in the <title level="m">Broadview Anthology of
							Romantic Drama</title>) provides an eyewitness description: “the altar
						flaming in the distance, the solemn invocation, the pealing music of the
						mystic song, altogether produced a combination so awful, as nearly to
						overpower reality, and make one half believe the enchantment which delighted
						our senses” (392). Barnes’s choice of words—“mystic,” “awful,” “overpower
						reality,” and “half believe the enchantment”—are all central to the desired
						effect of the holy theatre.</p>
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="3">
					<head>EXERCISE 1: STAGING THE AWAKENING OF CONSCIOUSNESS</head>
					<p>In this exercise students will perform Act III, scene I of <title level="m"
							>Remorse</title>, recreating the Gothic setting for the “altar scene” in
						order to understand how the stagecraft works to convey an experience of an
						awakening of consciousness. You will need at least six actors to play Alvar,
						Ordonio, Teresa, Valdez, Monviedro, and a few “familiars of the Inquisition”
						who act but don’t have speaking parts. Others can create music “expressive
						of the movements and images” of the scene, play it according to the stage
						directions, and sing the Chorus parts. A third crew can construct the altar
						spectacle.</p>
					<list type="ordered">
						<item n="1">From the text, gather information about the stage setting and
							recreate this in your classroom. For instance, <name
								ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>'s stage directions call
							for <emph>“a Hall of Armory, with an Altar at the back of the
								Stage”</emph> and <emph>“soft music from an instrument of Glass or
								Steel.”</emph>
						</item>
						<item n="2">Onstage enter Alvar (dressed in a Sorcerer’s robe; the others
							don’t recognize him), Ordonio, Teresa, and Valdez (father of the
							brothers Ordonio and Alvar). </item>
						<item n="3">The music should score their dialogue and action. Beginning at
							about III.i.62, a “voice behind the scenes sings ‘Hear, sweet spirit’”
							during (the disguised) Alvar’s incantation to raise up the soul of
							Alvar.</item>
						<item n="4">The goal of the altar spectacle is to awaken Ordonio’s
							consciousness, so the actor playing Ordonio needs to convey a change
							over the course of the scene. In the early stages of Alvar’s
							presentation, for instance, Ordonio still thinks that <emph>he</emph> is
							controlling the action, and comments that it would be a joy to see Alvar
							again. Alvar then begins to unleash upon him a verbal barrage and
							throughout the scene addresses his lines “still to Ordonio,” heedless of
							Valdez's interruptions, protesting this assault, which culminates with
							the stinging “it gives fierce merriment to the damned, / To see these
							proud men, that loath mankind, / At every stir and buzz of coward
							conscience, / Trick, cant, and lie, most whining hypocrites!” Alvar then
							turns away, shooing him “Away, away!” Then, like a director perfectly
							timing his dramatic effects, he orders, “Now let me hear more music"
							(III.i.110-14). </item>
						<item n="5">Music cue: the stage directions read “The whole Music clashes
							into a Chorus.” The Chorus chants “Wandering Demons! Hear the spell! /
							Lest a Blacker charm compel—”</item>
						<item n="6">Recreate the spectacle of the portrait: the stage directions
							indicate that “the incense on the altar takes fire suddenly, and an
							illuminated picture of Alvar's assassination is discovered, and having
							remained a few seconds is then hidden by ascending flames.”</item>
						<item n="7">Ordonio “<emph>start[s] in great agitation</emph>” and tries to
							blame the situation on “the traitor Isidore.”</item>
						<item n="8">Monviedro and the familiars of the Inquisition enter and seize
							Alvar.</item>
						<item n="9">Ordonio “<emph>recovers himself as from stupor</emph>” and
							orders that they take Alvar to the dungeon.</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="4">
					<head>CLASS DISCUSSION</head>
					<p>Reflect on how the class’s performance affected you as an actor, designer,
						and/or spectator. How did the Gothic elements, particularly the music and
						the altar spectacle, highlight the emotional relationships between the
						characters and the theme of awakening remorse?</p>
					<p>It is likely that the Gothic elements felt awkwardly phony, even laughable,
						to you. Imagine the <emph>original</emph> performance circumstances: you are
						watching <title level="m">Remorse</title> in the 3,000-plus seat theatre at
						Drury Lane. You go to the theatre eager for spectacle, delighted with and
						amazed by the technological developments in theatre and the effects they
						have on you as they lure you into a belief in their reality. (To imagine
						this, fast forward to the spectacular theatre of today, such as <title
							level="m">The Lion King</title>, <title level="m">Phantom of the
							Opera</title>, or <title level="m">Miss Saigon</title>.) How do you
						think you would have reacted in those circumstances?</p>
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="5">
					<head>Teaching <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>’s <title
							level="m">Orra</title></head>
					<p n="13"><name ref="ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</name>’s sonnet “Lift not the
						painted veil” (1818) provides an effective lead-in to this reading of <title
							level="m">Orra</title> because holy theatre, like Orra herself, seeks to
						lift the painted veil, with often (and necessarily) painful—or, as <name
							ref="ArtaudAntonin">Artaud</name> later famously phrased it,
							<emph>cruel</emph>—results. <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s
						tragedy on <emph>fear</emph> in the <title level="m">Plays on the
							Passions</title>, <title level="m">Orra</title>’s dramaturgical concept
						is to show the progression of fear in Orra, which starts in a somewhat
						playful fashion with the enjoyment of ghost stories, and ends in a terrible
						madness; this aspect of the play takes precedence over the plotline about
						Orra’s resistance to a forced courtship. <title level="m">Orra</title> shows
						Orra’s internal state; the audience doesn’t physically see any ghosts, but
						instead watches the actor playing Orra unveil her hauntedness, or, in other
						words, react to fear. </p>
					<p n="14"><name ref="CarlsonJulieAnn">Julie Carlson</name>’s essay “<name
							ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s <title level="m">Orra</title>:
						Shrinking in Fear” (included in the recent collection <title level="m"><name
								ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>, Romantic
							Dramatist</title>) works well as a contemporary supplement to the play.
							<name ref="CarlsonJulieAnn">Carlson</name> proposes the idea that
						“hauntology” rather than ontology describes our current being and time, and
						writes that <title level="m">Orra</title> is a haunted and haunting play; it
						is the exception rather than the rule in the <title level="m">Plays on the
							Passions</title> and undermines <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
						>Baillie</name>’s usual emphasis on rational morality. Orra herself is a
						“spectral subject” in the play (216), a position between the “twos” of
						binaries (much like <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s own unusual
						situation in Romanticism and theatre history—not yet acknowledged as a truly
						“major” figure, yet too major to be “minor”).<note place="foot"
							resp="editors" n="10">This conundrum is discussed in <name
								ref="CrochunisThomas">Thomas Crochunis</name>’s introductory essay
							to <title level="m"><name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>,
								Romantic Dramatist</title>, ed. <name ref="CrochunisThomasC"
								>Crochunis</name> (New York and London: Routledge, 2004), 3.</note>
						Like <title level="m">Remorse</title>, <title level="m">Orra</title> draws
						upon the conventions of the Gothic and of Romantic medievalism, and
						similarly, the spectacle is utilized, <name ref="CarlsonJulieAnn"
							>Carlson</name> argues, as a way of transporting us to a psychic space
						of sensory perceptions—a “before-human” state that precedes meaning-making
						(217)—a technique used in <name ref="ArtaudAntonin">Artaud</name>’s
						twentieth-century performance events that gave audiences a “sensory
						overload” to break down their habitual rational responses. Gothic spectacle
						provided “a way of exploring the psychological even before twentieth-century
						constructions of it,” and “becomes linked to the internal state of the
						characters’ minds as authors explore how individuals react in times of great
						stress,” Christine Colón explains (xxiii). Furthermore, since the Gothic
						“compels an audience to derive pleasure from fear,” it “clearly allies
						itself with the idea of the sublime”; and “for a playwright like <name
							ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name> who desperately wishes to stir her
						audience members’ imaginations and compel them to transform their lives, the
						spectacle of the Gothic sublime would have been appealing. It had the
						potential to awaken audiences and cause them to act” (Colón xxii-xxiii). </p>
					<p n="15">In addition, <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s “Introductory
						Discourse” and note “To the Reader” to the <title level="m">Plays on the
							Passions</title> should be taught alongside <title level="m"
							>Orra</title>.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="11"><name
								ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name> is slowly becoming recognized as
							a significant theorist of theatre; each year a larger number of
							articles, it seems, appears on <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>,
							and <name ref="BurroughsCatherine">Catherine Burroughs</name>’s <title
								level="m">Closet Spaces</title> (1997), Judith Bailey Slagle’s
							critical biography <title level="m"><name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna
									Baillie</name>: A Literary Life</title> (2002), and Thomas C.
								<name ref="CrochunisThomas">Crochunis</name>’s edited collection of
							essays, <title level="m"><name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>,
								Romantic Dramatist</title> (2004) have all been major contributions.
							Excerpts or complete versions of her “Introductory Discourse” have been
							anthologized for some time in collections of Romantic-era writing,
							particularly of women’s writing, e.g., <title level="m">The (Other)
								Eighteenth Century</title> (1991) and <title level="m">Women Critics
								1660-1820</title> (1995), and in Peter Duthie’s edition of the 1798
								<title level="m">Plays on the Passions</title> (2001). However, she
							is not yet included in the major, much-used critical studies or
							anthologies of theatre theory or dramatic criticism such as Marvin
							Carlson’s <title level="m">Theories of the Theatre</title>; Daniel
							Gerould’s <title level="m">Theatre/Theory/Theatre</title> or Bernard
							Dukore’s <title level="m">Dramatic Theory and Criticism</title>. She has
							been given a paragraph in the latest (tenth) edition of the standard
							textbook <title level="m">History of the Theatre</title>, by Oscar
							Brockett and Franklin Hildy, but as a playwright, not a theatre
							theorist. Furthermore, while scholarship on <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
								>Baillie</name> has been impressive, it hasn’t yet penetrated drama
							scholarship deeply to show <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s
							influence on the modern avant garde. For instance, one description of
							expressionist drama is not just that it is a highly subjective art form
							in which “internal acts become externalized,” but, more specifically,
							that the “drama becomes concentrated to a point of ‘pure’ emotion”
								(<name ref="InnesChristopher">Innes</name>, <title level="m">Holy
								Theatre</title> 44, 45), an innovation of <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
								>Baillie</name>’s. </note> (Both are excerpted in <title level="m"
							>The Broadview Anthology of </title>
						<title level="m">Romantic Drama</title>.) As do the other
						dramatist-theorists in the holy theatre tradition, <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
							>Baillie</name> is writing a manifesto: creating drama for a theatre
						that could be—that is, the theatre she wants rather than the theatre she
						has. It is in the “Introductory Discourse” that <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
							>Baillie</name> develops the idea for which she’s become best known,
						that of “sympathetic curiosity.” She does not just make the point that we
						are curious about other humans, especially when they are experiencing
						emotional trauma, but that we want to fix our eyes on the manifestation of
						such trauma on their bodies and faces—to observe their
						<emph>symptoms</emph>, as it were. To take just one example that works well
						with teaching <title level="m">Orra</title>, <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
							>Baillie</name> writes that one of the things humans are most curious
						about, yet most scared of, are ghosts. “No man wishes to see the Ghost
						himself, which would certainly procure him the best information on the
						subject, but every man wishes to see one who believes that he sees it, in
						all the agitation and wildness of that species of terror” (359). In other
						words, we are more interested in reactions to ghosts, in witnessing the
						experience of having seen a ghost, than in the ghosts themselves. We are
						aware that it is rude to stare at people, yet we have an overwhelming urge
						to watch people in distress: “how sensible are we of this strong propensity
						within us, when we behold any person under the pressure of great and
						uncommon calamity!” Out of courtesy we will turn our eyes away, yet “the
						first glance we direct to him will involuntarily be one of the keenest
						observation, how hastily soever it may be checked; and often will a
						returning look of enquiry mix itself by stealth with our sympathy and
						reserve” (359). In short, we enjoy staring at others who are experiencing
						emotional turmoil; while we restrain ourselves, and offer merely expressions
						of sympathy, we covertly observe in minute detail the features and
						physicality that indicate the person’s suffering. Such gazes are
						inappropriate in polite society; however, our sympathetic curiosity is
						satisfactorily aroused and exercised by attending the theatre. It gives
						spectators the opportunity to vicariously steal into the closet—and into the
						mind—of another. For, as <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name> writes,
						“there is, perhaps, no employment which the human mind will with so much
						avidity pursue, as the discovery of concealed passion, as the tracing the
						varieties and progress of a perturbed soul” (360). </p>
					<p n="16">The success of <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s designs to
						allow audiences to trace the varieties and progress of Orra’s perturbed soul
						depend heavily on the skill and style of the actors, and thus it is no
						surprise that her script is filled with detailed prescriptions for gesture
						and movement to convey the internal state of the character. Here, too, she
						is advocating for a transformed, intimate theatre in opposition to the
						conventional performance spaces of her day, which were growing ever larger;
						in “To the Reader” she writes that the “department of acting that will
						suffer most under these circumstances, is that which particularly regards
						the gradual unfolding of the passions, and has, perhaps, hitherto been less
						understood than any other part of the art—I mean Soliloquy” (375). The plays
						she is creating need actors who can exhibit “the solitary musings of a
						perturbed mind” with “muttered, imperfect articulation which grows by
						degrees into words” or “that rapid burst of sounds which often succeeds the
						slow languid tones of distress” (375). These precisely observed descriptions
						remind us of what may be most remarked upon about <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
							>Baillie</name>’s playwriting, in her own day as well as ours: her
						diagnostically observant eye and analytic, “anatomical” dramaturgy. The
						reviewer from <title level="j">Edinburgh Magazine</title> writes in 1818
						(excerpted in the <title level="m">Broadview Anthology of Romantic
							Drama</title>) that “no one” except <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
							>Baillie</name> ever thought of giving, in dramatic form, “an anatomical
						analysis, a philosophical dissection of a passion” (381). Her plays work as
						a kind of “microscope, by means of which she seems to think that she has
						brought within the sphere of our vision things too minute for the naked
						intellectual eye” (381-2). The reviewer thinks this is the “radical defect”
						of her plays, but today it is considered perhaps her most brilliant
						endeavor, an innovative theatrical experiment. </p>
					<p n="17">The names of <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name> and <name
							ref="StanislavskiConstantin">Constantin Stanislavski</name> are rarely,
						if ever, linked, but he too taught a form of anatomical observation, telling
						his students that, when creating a role, they should first read the text
						carefully for the “physical truths” about the character. The fame of
						American Method acting’s “inside out” approach has obscured other ways of
						building characters and distorted part of <name ref="StanislavskiConstantin"
							>Stanislavski</name>’s original teachings; he instructs his actors not
						to “truncate” the “inner line” of a role and replace it with their own
						“personal line,” but to begin with the “physical life” of the character,
						which is tangible. “The spirit cannot but respond to the actions of the
						body, provided of course that these are genuine, have a purpose, and are
						productive,” he explains (<title level="m">Creating a Role</title> 149). Put
						differently, instead of the later Method acting technique of drawing on the
						actor’s own emotional and sense memory, the actor was to take on the
						physical stance, gestures, posture that signaled the emotional feeling of
						the character. By putting oneself into the physical position, the emotion
						would follow. </p>
					<p n="18">In the eighteenth century, the use of ritualized gestures and poses to
						convey specific states of emotion had been made popular, codified in acting
						manuals that illustrated the proper appearance of the gesture or pose and
						explained what each indicated. (This often seems oddly nonrealistic to us.
						Similarly, in late nineteenth- and early twentieth-century avant garde
						theatre, actors would strike archetypal poses, rather than move and pause in
						the realistic manner that’s familiar to us now; these poses were meant to
						convey certain emotional effects, indeed to heighten the emotional effect
							altogether.)<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="12">It is not unusual
							for playwrights to prescribe the acting style that fits the view of how
							consciousness is presented in the play, particularly in this holy
							theatre tradition in which realistic causal explanations for behavior
							are eschewed or excised. For instance, Sam Shepard told the cast of
								<title level="m">Angel City</title>, one of his earliest
							experimental plays (written right before <title level="m">Suicide in B
								Flat</title> and predating his turn to more naturalistic family
							dramas with <title level="m">Curse of the Starving Class</title> and
								<title level="m">Buried Child</title>): “Instead of the idea of a
							‘whole character’ with logical motives behind his behavior which the
							actor submerges himself into, he should consider instead a fractured
							whole with bits and pieces of character flying off the central theme . .
							. . In other words, more in terms of collage construction or jazz
							improvisation” (105). See <name ref="SheweyDon">Don Shewey</name>,
								<title level="m">Sam Shepard</title> (New York: Da Capo Press,
							1997).</note> The unveiling or revelation of a character’s internal
						state was a primary feature of late eighteenth-century and Romantic acting
						theories; the matter of expressing a character’s “passion” is considerably
						more complicated than having the actors constantly emoting onstage, which
						would eventually result in a flattened-out performance and not move the
						audience. To express internal states convincingly, performers developed a
						number of techniques that included drawing upon their own memories,
						thoughts, and emotions and transferring them to the character; focusing on
						communicating explicitly the specific <emph>shifts</emph> of feeling of
						thought that a character experiences from one moment to the next; and
						cultivating an attitude of sympathy among the triangle of character,
						performer, and viewer by finding the vulnerability of the character and
						inviting the audience to experience it. As we see featured in <title
							level="m">Orra</title>, one way an actor would reveal the interiority of
						a character was by focusing on the way the character <emph>reacted</emph> to
						the dramatic situation. As <name ref="BateJonathan">Jonathan Bate</name> has
						written, the popular view among Romantic theatre artists was that “the
						essence of human nature is to be found in reaction, not action, and so it
						was that their performances were most intense at certain moments of
						reflection” (“The Romantic Stage” 97). </p>
					<p n="19"><name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s detailed descriptions of
						Orra’s physical actions and gestures, particularly in her mad scene,
						instruct the actor on how to accurately depict the progression of her fear.
						To see how <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s stage directions
						“direct” the play and help her actors create their roles through anatomical
						analysis, and to experience how physical gestures can work to help
						performers feel for themselves and reveal to spectators the characters'
						emotions, try the following exercise.</p>
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="6">
					<head>EXERCISE 2: PHYSICALLY CREATING THE INTERIOR STATE OF MADNESS</head>
					<p>In this exercise students can test <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s
						instructions to the actor playing Orra in the key scene where she finally
						goes mad from fear (IV.iii). To play the entire scene you will need actors
						for Orra, Rudigere, Cathrina, Theobald, and Franko. You could also choose to
						play just Orra’s soliloquies (IV.iii.27-52 and IV.iii.147-165), as these are
						the moments for which <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name> provides most
						specific direction. </p>
					<list type="ordered">
						<item n="1">Make a list of all the stage directions that describe Orra’s
							actions (or reactions) in the scene. (For instance, “<emph>pacing to and
								fro,” “stands fixed with her arms crossed on her breast,” “striking
								the floor with her hands,”</emph> etc.) </item>
						<item n="2">To experience the physical life of the character and the “arc”
							or progression of Orra’s madness, practice enacting all of the stage
							directions, the gestures and postures, <emph>without</emph> saying the
							lines of the scene. You might treat this as a kind of dance, repeating
							the series of gestures and movements until you begin to feel the
							emotional life of the character.</item>
						<item n="3">Then go back and play the scene in its entirety, following the
							directions as you deliver the lines. </item>
						<item n="4">Everyone should have a chance both to enact Orra’s gestures and
							to watch others doing so. </item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="7">
					<head>CLASS DISCUSSION</head>
					<p>What did performing the gestures and actions feel like? Did you ever feel
						fear rising in yourself simply from doing the physical gestures associated
						with a person feeling fear? If so, when in particular did you feel it? Of
							<name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s descriptions of a person
						becoming overwhelmed with fear, in what ways were they <emph>accurate</emph>
						and in what ways merely <emph>literary</emph>?</p>
					<p>How did others look when they played Orra? Which gestures or postures most
						effectively conveyed fear? Which looked most outdated or stagy?</p>
					<p>The final scene of <title level="m">Orra</title> makes a nice pairing with
						Strindberg's <title level="m">The Ghost Sonata</title> (1907). Orra returns
						to the stage, completely mad, and tells her guardian Hughobert, upon hearing
						the news that his son died, that “the damn’d and holy / The living and the
						dead, together are / In horrid neighbourship. – ‘Tis but thin vapour, /
						Floating around thee, makes the wav’ring bound” (V.ii.208-12). <title
							level="m">The Ghost Sonata</title> also takes up the notion that the
						living and dead are in “horrid neighbourship” together, with only the finest
						boundary between them, although it does so to more psychological ends. In
						the second act’s famous “ghost supper,” the characters “look like ghosts”
						and have been drinking tea together for twenty years, “always the same
						people, saying the same things, or else too ashamed to say anything” (279).
						“God, if only we could die! If <emph>only</emph> we could die!” the
						character named the Mummy cries (283). <title level="m">Remorse</title> can
						be reintroduced at this point because it also pairs well with <title
							level="m">The Ghost Sonata</title> when the characters seek to make
						Jacob Hummel (“Old Man” in the <emph>dramatis personae</emph>) awaken to his
						past evil actions and feel remorse for them. Like <title level="m"
							>Remorse</title> and <title level="m">Orra</title>, <title level="m">The
							Ghost Sonata</title> is rather Gothic and could profitably be brought
						into a discussion of distinctions between “Gothic,” “Romantic,” “symbolist,”
						and “expressionist,” for the same elements of stagecraft are alternately
						labeled “Gothic” when describing <title level="m">Remorse</title>, <title
							level="m">Orra</title>, and many other Romantic dramas and are thus
						often considered “low,” pandering to the masses’ love of being surprised
						with special effects; or they are labeled “Romantic,” “experimental,” or
						“avant garde,” and then considered “high art.”</p>
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="8">
					<head>Romantic drama as the birthplace of the modern avant garde</head>
					<p n="20">When works of the modern avant garde are studied immediately after
							<title level="m">Remorse</title> and <title level="m">Orra</title>, the
						kinship with Romantic drama becomes clear in both the shared vision of
						theatre and the stagecraft employed to realize it. As <name ref="BrookPeter"
							>Peter Brook</name> explains, the holy theatre does not only
							<emph>present</emph> the invisible in drama, it “also offers
							<emph>conditions that make its perception possible</emph>” (56), such as
						theatrical spectacle, lighting, a use of ritualistic devices, dance and
						movement, musical scores and other kinds of sound, and even, in some cases,
							smell.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="13">Amiri Baraka’s use of
							smell in <title level="m">Slave Ship</title> to convey a sense of
							“atmosfeeling” is a good example.</note> Far from being “mere” spectacle
						or surface—an entertaining painted veil—these elements, whether labeled
						Gothic, Romantic, or Holy, are employed to lift or transcend reality. <name
							ref="BackscheiderPaula">Paula Backscheider</name> writes in <title
							level="m">Spectacular Politics</title>, in a discussion of <title
							level="m">The Castle Spectre</title>, that Gothic playwrights who added
						the word “romance” to their titles “signaled their freedom from the
						referential, veridical world of realist texts and allied themselves with a
						highly symbolic art, often reaching for a higher reality or a deeper
						psychology” (156). Theorists of the Gothic, <name ref="BackscheiderPaula"
							>Backscheider</name> continues, have argued that the form “is best
						distinguished by the experience its readers or spectators have, and it is
						now widely accepted as an expression of dissatisfaction with the
						possibilities of conventional literary realism” (156). This dissatisfaction
						leads to the modern avant garde tendency to elevate mood over plot, or
						internal over external states, presaged by <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
							>Baillie</name>’s work in particular. </p>
					<p n="21">The twentieth century part of the course looks at <name
							ref="StrindbergAugust">Strindberg</name>’s <title level="m">A Dream
							Play</title> (1901); one-act experiments <title level="m"
							>Interior</title> (1891) by Maurice Maeterlinck, <title level="m">The
							Wayfarer</title> (1910) by Valery Briusov, and Wassily Kandinsky’s
							<title level="m">The Yellow Sound</title> (1909); Beckett’s <title
							level="m">Waiting for Godot</title> (1953), the text seen by <name
							ref="BrookPeter">Peter Brook</name> as the apotheosis of holy theatre;
						Sam Shepard’s <title level="m">Suicide in B Flat</title> (1976) and the
						off-off Broadway movement; Amiri Baraka’s Artaudian “historical pageant”
							<title level="m">Slave Ship</title> (1967) and Ntozake Shange’s
						“choreopoem” <emph>for colored girls who have considered suicide/when the
							rainbow is enuf</emph> (1975); and ends with consideration of the career
						of Sarah Kane, particularly her plays <title level="m">Blasted</title>
						(1995) and <title level="m">4:48 Psychosis</title> (2000). We also discuss
						the influence of director-theorists <name ref="ArtaudAntonin">Antonin
							Artaud</name> (<title level="m">The Theatre and Its Double</title>
							[1938])<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="14">It might be interesting
							for students to note that <name ref="ArtaudAntonin">Artaud</name>’s
							Théâtre Alfred Jarry planned seasons that included <name
								ref="StrindbergAugust">Strindberg</name>’s <title level="m">A Dream
								Play</title> (a favorite, intended for his first season, 1926/27,
							but produced in 1928), Büchner’s <title level="m">Woyzeck</title> and
								<name ref="ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</name>’s <title level="m">The
								Cenci</title> (perhaps <name ref="ArtaudAntonin">Artaud</name>’s
							best-known production—as well as the best-known version of <title
								level="m">The Cenci</title>), as well as an archival reconstruction
							of the story of Blue-Beard and the Jacobean drama <title level="m">The
								Revenger’s Tragedy</title>) (<name ref="EsslinMartin">Esslin</name>,
								<title level="m"><name ref="ArtaudAntonin">Antonin
								Artaud</name></title> 96; <name ref="ArtaudAntonin">Artaud</name>,
								<title level="m">The Theatre and Its Double</title> 99-100).</note>
						and Jerzy Grotowski (<title level="m">Towards a Poor Theatre</title>
						[1968]—probably best known to people outside the theatre from Andre
						Gregory’s descriptions of his participation in Grotowski’s life-changing
						rituals in the film <title level="m">My Dinner with Andre</title> [1981]),
						whose methods and experiments are probably what first come to mind when one
						learns about holy theatre. What often strikes twenty-first-century students
						about this current of theatre is how raw it seems, how earnest or even naïve
						in its search for authenticity; there’s an openness and vulnerability that
						can make contemporary audiences conditioned to irony uncomfortable.
						Contemporary traces of holy theatre are difficult to find; we see them more
						in rave music, light shows, art installations, and communal performance
						events such as Burning Man than in staged drama. Postmodernism so changed
						the tenor of much of the aesthetic that when consciousness is examined in
						contemporary performance, the tendency has been toward a deconstruction
						rather than a search for universals and communality. An important response
						comes in the form of Jill Dolan’s argument for “reanimating humanism (after
						we’ve deconstructed the blind, transcendent universalisms it once espoused)”
						(163) and her conceptualization of “utopian performatives” in <title
							level="m">Utopia in Performance: Finding Hope at the Theater</title>
						(2005). </p>
					<p n="22">Film is probably the most engaging and accessible contemporary
						porthole for entering the realms of the holy theatre tradition. As <name
							ref="CardulloBert">Bert Cardullo</name> notes of modernist avant-garde
						plays, Romantic dramas would perhaps have been “better suited to the screen
						than to the stage, assaulting as they did the theater’s traditional
						objectivity or exteriority and its bondage to continuous time and space”
						(3). Film is a medium that has been friendly to experiments with the
						concerns of holy theatre—consciousness, dream states, alternative realities,
						magic—as can be seen in the popularity of films about consciousness, such as
						Richard Linklater’s <title level="m">Waking Life</title> (2001) and the
						documentary <title level="m">What the Bleep Do We Know?</title> (2004),
						critical acclaim for Julian Schnabel’s evocation of human consciousness in
							<title level="m">The Diving Bell and the Butterfly</title> (2007), the
						work of Michel Gondry (<title level="m">Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless
							Mind</title> [2004], <title level="m">The Science of Sleep</title>
						[2006]), and Christopher Nolan’s <title level="m">Inception</title> (2010),
						to name just a few recent examples. A work like <title level="m">Prometheus
							Unbound</title> (1820), for example, seems to call out for a film
						adaptation (although the first known staging, by the Rude Mechanicals
						theatre company in Austin, Texas, in 1998 would challenge that statement. It
						was excellent.) While film lacks the communality in liveness called for in
						holy theatre, it can conjure the images and experience of transcendence that
						were desired onstage. Students probably bring a curiosity about the
						philosophical, scientific, and psychological matters explored in these
						films, which may raise interest in seeing how Romantic drama attempts to
						explore them, too, with the result that Romantic drama is seen as relevant,
						even prescient, to our artistic concerns, and as a fertile ground for
						theatrical experimentation.</p>
				</div>

			</div>

			<div type="citations">
				<head>Works Cited and Referenced</head>
				<listBibl>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Artaud, Antonin</author>
							<title level="m">The Theatre and Its Double</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Grove Press</publisher>
								<date>1958</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Auslander, Philip</author>
							<title level="m">From Acting to Performance: Essays in Modernism and
								Postmodernism</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
								<date>1997</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Backscheider, Paula R.</author>
							<title level="m">Spectacular Politics: Theatrical Power and Mass Culture
								in Early Modern England</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Baltimore and London</pubPlace>
								<publisher>The Johns Hopkins UP</publisher>
								<date>1992</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Baillie, Joanna</author>
							<title level="a">'Introductory Discourse' to the <emph>Plays on the
									Passions</emph></title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<ref target="#CG"/>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="pp">357-370</biblScope>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Baillie, Joanna</author>
							<title level="a">Orra</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<ref target="#CG"/>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="pp">133-164</biblScope>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Bate, Jonathan</author>
							<title level="a">The Romantic Stage</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<title level="m">The Oxford Illustrated History of on Stage</title>
							<editor role='editor'>Bate, Jonathan</editor>
							<editor role='editor'>Jackson, Russell</editor>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
								<date>1991</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<editor role='editor'>Brask, Per</editor>
							<editor role='editor'>Meyer-Dinkgräfe, Daniel</editor>
							<title level="m">Performing Consciousness</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Newcastle upon Tyne</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Cambridge Scholars Publishing</publisher>
								<date>2010</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>

					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Bratton, Jacky</author>
							<title level="m">New Readings in Theatre History</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Cambridge and New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
								<date>2003</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Brook, Peter</author>
							<title level="m">The Empty Space</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Atheneum</publisher>
								<date>1968</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Burroughs, Catherine B</author>
							<title level="m">Closet Stages: Joanna Baillie and the Theater Theory of
								British Romantic Women Writers</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
								<publisher>The University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
								<date>1997</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Burwick, Frederick</author>
							<title level="m">Illusion and the Drama: Critical Theory of the
								Enlightenment and Romantic Era</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>University Park, PA</pubPlace>
								<publisher>The Pennsylvania State UP</publisher>
								<date>1991</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<editor role='editor'>Cardullo, Bert</editor>
							<editor role='editor'>Knopf, Robert</editor>
							<title level="m">Theater of the Avant-Garde, 1890-1950: A Critical
								Anthology</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New Haven and London</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Yale UP</publisher>
								<date>2001</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Carlson, Julie</author>
							<title level="a">Baillie’s <emph>Orra</emph>: Shrinking in Fear</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<ref target="#TCC"/>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="pp">pp. 206-20</biblScope>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor</author>
							<title level="a">Biographia Literaria</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<title level="m">Samuel Taylor Coleridge: A Critical Edition of the
								Major Works</title>
							<editor role='editor'>Jackson, H. J.</editor>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Oxford and New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
								<date>1985</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor</author>
							<title level="a">Remorse</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<ref target="#CG"/>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="pp">165-204</biblScope>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<editor role='editor'>Cox, Jeffrey N.</editor>
							<title level="m">Seven Gothic Dramas 1789-1825</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Athens</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Ohio UP</publisher>
								<date>1992</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct xml:id="CG">
						<monogr>
							<editor role='editor'>Cox, Jeffrey N.</editor>
							<editor role='editor'>Gamer, Michael</editor>
							<title level="m">The Broadview Anthology of Romantic Drama</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Peterborough, Ontario</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Broadview Press</publisher>
								<date>2003</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct xml:id="TCC">
						<monogr>
							<editor role='editor'>Crochunis, Thomas C.</editor>
							<title level="m">Joanna Baillie, Romantic Dramatist</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
								<date>2004</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Demastes, William</author>
							<title level="m">Staging Consciousness: Theater and the Materialization
								of Mind</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Ann Arbor</pubPlace>
								<publisher>University of Michigan P</publisher>
								<date>2002</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Esslin, Martin</author>
							<title level="m">Antonin Artaud</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Penguin</publisher>
								<date>1976</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Galperin, William</author>
							<title level="m">The Return of the Visible in British
								Romanticism</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Baltimore and London</pubPlace>
								<publisher>The Johns Hopkins UP</publisher>
								<date>1993</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Greenblatt, Stephen</author>
							<title level="m">Will in the World: How Shakespeare Became
								"Shakespeare"</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>W. W. Norton</publisher>
								<date>2004</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Haney, David P.</author>
							<title level="m">The Challenge of Coleridge: Ethics and Interpretation
								in Romanticism and Modern Philosophy</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>University Park, PA</pubPlace>
								<publisher>The Pennsylvania State UP</publisher>
								<date>2001</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>

					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Innes, Christopher</author>
							<title level="m">Avant Garde Theatre 1892-1991</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
								<date>1992</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Innes, Christopher</author>
							<title level="m">Holy Theatre: Ritual and the Avant Garde</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
								<date>1981</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Kushner, Tony</author>
							<title level="m">Angels in America: Part One: Millennium
								Approaches</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Theatre Communications Group</publisher>
								<date>1992</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Malekin, Peter</author>
							<author>Yarrow, Ralph </author>
							<title level="m">Consciousness, Literature, and Theatre</title>

							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York and London</pubPlace>
								<publisher>St. Martin’s</publisher>
								<date>1997</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Meyer-Dinkgräfe, Daniel</author>
							<title level="m"> Theatre and Consciousness: Explanatory Scope and
								Future Potential</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Bristol, UK and Portland, OR</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Intellect Books</publisher>
								<date>2005</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>

					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Moore, John David</author>
							<title level="a">Coleridge and the 'modern Jacobinical Drama':
									<emph>Osorio</emph>, <emph>Remorse</emph>, and the Development
								of Coleridge’s Critique of the Stage, 1797-1816</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<title level="j">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</title>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="vol">85</biblScope>
								<biblScope type="no">4</biblScope>
								<date>Winter 1982</date>
								<biblScope>443-464</biblScope>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Mortensen, Peter</author>
							<title level="a">The Robbers and the Police: British Romantic Drama and
								the Gothic Treacheries of Coleridge's <emph>Remorse</emph></title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<title level="m">European Gothic: A Spirited Exchange 1760–1960</title>
							<editor role='editor'>Horner, Avril</editor>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Manchester and New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Manchester UP</publisher>
								<date>2002</date>
								<biblScope>128–146</biblScope>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Richardson, Alan</author>
							<title level="m">British Romanticism and the Science of the Mind</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
								<date>2005</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Richardson, Alan</author>
							<title level="m">A Mental Theater: Poetic Drama and Consciousness in the
								Romantic Age</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>University Park, PA</pubPlace>
								<publisher>The Pennsylvania State UP</publisher>
								<date>1988</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Richardson, Alan</author>
							<title level="m">The Neural Sublime: Cognitive Theories and Romantic
								Texts</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Baltimore and London</pubPlace>
								<publisher>The Johns Hopkins UP</publisher>
								<date>2010</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Schlegel, August Wilhelm</author>
							<title level="m">A Course of Lectures on Dramatic Art and
								Literature</title>
							<editor role="translator">Black, John</editor>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>AMS Press</publisher>
								<date>1973</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Shewey, Don</author>
							<title level="m">Sam Shepard</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Da Capo Press</publisher>
								<date>1997</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Stanislavski, Constantin</author>
							<title level="m">Creating a Role</title>
							<editor role="translator">Hapgood, Elizabeth Reynolds</editor>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Theatre Arts Books</publisher>
								<date>1961</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Strindberg, August</author>
							<title level="a">The Ghost Sonata</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<title level="m">Strindberg: Five Plays</title>
							<editor role="translator">Carlson, Harry G.</editor>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Berkeley</pubPlace>
								<publisher>U of California P</publisher>
								<date>1983</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Strindberg, August</author>
							<title level="m">Open Letters to the Intimate Theater</title>
							<editor role="translator">Johnson, and Intro. Walter</editor>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Seattle and London</pubPlace>
								<publisher>U of Washington P</publisher>
								<date>1967</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Thomas, Sophie</author>
							<title level="a">Seeing Things ('As They Are'): Coleridge, Schiller, and
								the Play of Semblance</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<title level="j">Studies in Romanticism</title>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="vol">43</biblScope>
								<biblScope type="no">4</biblScope>
								<date>2004</date>
								<biblScope type="pp">537-55</biblScope>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Yarrow, Ralph</author>
							<title level="m">Sacred Theatre</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Bristol, UK and Portland, OR</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Intellect Books</publisher>
								<date>2008</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
