<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Holy Theatre; </title>
				<title type="subordinate">or, Theatre of the Invisible-Made-Visible</title>
				<author>
					<name>Amy Muse</name>
				</author>
				<editor role='editor'>
					<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Pedagogies Editor</resp>
					<name>Kate Singer</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>commons4.2011.muse</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
					Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
						or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
						purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
						use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
						are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
						with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
						permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
						requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
						forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
						conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
						them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
						have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
						Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
						continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
						a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
						use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Holy Theatre; </title>
						<title level="a" type="subordinate">or, Theatre of the
							Invisible-Made-Visible</title>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename>Amy</forename>
								<surname>Muse</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Teaching Romantic Drama: </title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Pedagogies Commons Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
								Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
							<biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for
						‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
						keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
						such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
						been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
					12pt;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
						on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g18" scheme="#genre"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<date>2011-02-18</date>
				<list>
					<item>revised TEI</item>
					<item>XSLT</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Dave Rettenmaier</name>
				<date>2010-06-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				<date>2009-11-01T15:01:00</date>
				<list>
					<item>Proofed issue in Open Office Format</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="syllabus">

				<head>Holy Theatre; or, Theatre of the Invisible-Made-Visible</head>

				<byline>
					<docAuthor>Amy Muse</docAuthor>
					<affiliation>University of St. Thomas</affiliation>
				</byline>
				<div type="section" n="1">
					<head>
						<emph>Course Description:</emph>
					</head>

					<p rend="noCount">This is a course in the theory and dramatic literature of what
						can be called “Holy Theatre.” The course might also be titled “Staging
						Consciousness,” “Ontological Theatre,” “The Evolution of Modern Avant Garde
						Drama,” or, as some of you will find, “Weird Plays by Cool Theatre
						Theorists.” </p>
					<p rend="noCount">“Holy Theatre” makes up one “master current” in the history of
						drama and theatre. Director Peter Brook defines it as “the Theatre of the
						Invisible – Made – Visible.” That is, this kind of drama is generally
						concerned with making things that are invisible to us (e.g., human
						consciousness, states of being, dreams, ghosts) visible through the language
						and technologies of the theatre. It can be contrasted with the “master
						current” of realism or naturalism, plays that are concerned with staging
						social issues. (Both tend to provide explorations of the human condition,
						but holy theatre moves from the “inside out” while social realism goes from
						the “outside in.” The very best plays, of course, generally have attributes
						of both currents.)</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Although the “hallmark” of this tradition of theatre is an
						“aspiration to transcendence, to the spiritual in its widest sense”
						(Christopher Innes, <title level="m">Holy Theatre</title> 3), the word
						“holy” can be a misnomer, for this course is not studying religious drama.
						Instead, “holy” should be imagined as a way of seeing theatre: creating and
						attending theatre as if it were a holy rite, a communal passage into the
						mysteries of life, rather than a venue for entertainment or for political
						debate.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Working together, we will strive to define and perhaps even
						experience holy theatre and to make meaningful connections between the
						artists, which may include questioning the grouping together of these
						particular dramatists and theorists under one categorical umbrella. Our
						learning will involve reading closely a number of plays and works of theatre
						theory; writing responses to the reading; viewing and reviewing a
						performance event; creating a manifesto; and thoroughly researching and
						envisioning one of the plays as if you were the dramaturg or director for a
						production of it. In addition, we will be learning through performing and
						producing scenes from the plays, experimenting with acting methods and forms
						of stagecraft.</p>
				</div>

				<div type="section" n="2">
					<head>
						<emph>Course Texts:</emph>
					</head>
					<list type="bulleted">
						<item>Peter Brook, <title level="m">The Empty Space</title>
						</item>
						<item><name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> and <name ref="GamerMichael"
								>Gamer</name>, eds. <title level="m">The Broadview Anthology of
								Romantic Drama</title>
						</item>
						<item>Cardullo and Knopf, eds. <title level="m">Theater of the Avant-Garde,
								1890-1950</title>
						</item></list>
						
							
						
						<list>
							<head>Individual Plays:</head><item><name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>, <title level="m"
								>Hamlet</title> and <title level="m">The Tempest</title>
						</item>
						<item><name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">S. T. Coleridge</name>, <title
								level="m">Remorse</title> (found in <title level="m">The Broadview
								Anthology of Romantic Drama</title>)</item>
						<item><name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>, <title level="m"
								>Orra</title> (found in <title level="m">The Broadview Anthology of
								Romantic Drama</title>)</item>
						<item>August Strindberg, <title level="m">The Ghost Sonata</title> (found in
								<title level="m">Theater of the Avant-Garde, 1890-1950</title>)
							&amp; <title level="m">A Dream Play</title>
						</item>
						<item>Maurice Maeterlinck, <title level="m">Interior</title> (found in
								<title level="m">Theater of the Avant-Garde,
							1890-1950</title>)</item>
						<item>Valery Briusov, <title level="m">The Wayfarer</title> (found in <title
								level="m">Theater of the Avant-Garde, 1890-1950</title>)</item>
						<item>Wassily Kandinsky, <title level="m">The Yellow Sound</title> (found in
								<title level="m">Theater of the Avant-Garde,
							1890-1950</title>)</item>
						<item>Samuel Beckett, <title level="m">Waiting for Godot</title>
						</item>
						<item>Sam Shepard, <title level="m">Suicide in B Flat</title>
						</item>
						<item>Amiri Baraka, <title level="m">Slave Ship</title>
						</item>
						<item>Ntozake Shange, <title level="m">for colored girls who have considered
								suicide / when the rainbow is enuf</title>
						</item>
						<item>Sarah Kane, <title level="m">4:48 Psychosis</title> and <title
								level="m">Blasted</title>
						</item></list>
					
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="3">
					<head>
						<emph>Course Requirements:</emph>
					</head>
					<list type="ordered">

						<item n="1">A manifesto for a holy theatre (about 5 pages)</item>
						<item n="2">A performance review seen through the lens of holy theatre
							theories (3-4 pages)</item>
						<item n="3">A director’s or dramaturg’s portfolio on one of the plays (12-15
							page seminar paper)</item>
						<item n="4">Weekly reading responses (2-3 pages each)</item>
						<item n="5">Active contribution to seminar discussion</item>
					</list>

					<lb/>
				
					<ab>
						<emph>Essay 1: Manifesto for a Holy Theatre</emph>
					</ab>
					

					<p rend="noCount">This project will allow you to create a manifesto that sets
						forth a vision of holy theatre and how it could be manifested today, drawing
						upon the theory and drama we read this semester. This essay is a work of
						theory, but it should acknowledge its influences (and perhaps its
						opposition) and be well-grounded in examples rather than be purely
						abstract.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Please address the following in your manifesto, considering
						both the aesthetics and the politics or ethics of the various elements:
							<list type="bulleted">
							<item>What is the function and purpose of your theatre?</item>
							<item>What is the role of text, of drama? And, more generally, what is
								the role of language in your theatre?</item>
							<item>Describe your ideal performance space.</item>
							<item>What is the role of design and spectacle (including all aspects of
								the use of stage space, setting, lighting, costumes, special
								effects, music, dance/movement, etc.) in your theatre?</item>
							<item>How should your actors perform, and what will be important in
								their training?</item>
							<item>What is the relationship between actor and spectator? What is the
								ideal effect your theatre will have on the spectator?</item>
						</list>Note: you do not have to imagine this as a professional theatre. You
						can certainly work in the context of educational theatre, community-based
						theatre, or any other context. </p><lb/><lb/>

					<ab>
						<emph>Essay 2: Performance Review</emph>
					</ab>
					<p rend="noCount">Attend a live performance event (not necessarily a traditional
						play) and write a 2-3 page review of it. While you are there, take note of
						all of the elements that create a theatrical experience: text, acting,
						directing, design, the use of space in general (the theatre building and/or
						performance space itself), and the actor-audience dynamic. Depending upon
						the specific event, some of these elements will be more noteworthy than
						others. Give all of them consideration in your initial analysis (something
						may be more important than you first realize), but don’t worry about
						covering all of them in your paper.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">Then, reflect upon how your response to the performance is
						being shaped by the theoretical work on holy theatre we’re doing in class.
						View this performance through that lens, making connections to plays and
						theory we’ve been reading and discussing. What do you notice now that you
						would not necessarily have noticed before? Give special attention to
						questions of <emph>affect</emph>. How does the performance make you feel?
						What does the audience’s response in general seem to be? Does the
						performance work to build communality among its spectators?</p>

					<p rend="noCount">Although you may also evaluate its merit and advise us whether
						or not to attend it ourselves, your review should concentrate on
							<emph>analysis</emph> (think about 90% analysis to 10% evaluation). </p><lb/>
					<ab>
						<emph>Essay 3: Dramaturg’s or Director’s Portfolio</emph>
					</ab>
					<p rend="noCount">This final project will allow you to demonstrate your
						understanding of a play dramatically, theatrically, theoretically, and
						culturally. The center of this portfolio project is a <hi>12-15 page seminar
							paper</hi> in which you will develop an interpretation of one of the
						plays we read this semester as if you are either the dramaturg or the
						director for a production of it. </p>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi><emph>Dramaturg’s Portfolio</emph></hi>: Take the role of
						the dramaturg, the member of the production team who is responsible for
						researching the play and its context and helping the director, actors, and
						designers understand it. For instance, the dramaturg can explain the origins
						of the play and its dramaturgy—i.e., its dramatic structure, how it
							<emph>works</emph>; can put the play into intellectual and aesthetic as
						well as cultural and political contexts; and trace its influence or
						significance.</p>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi>The paper</hi>: Closely examine the text of your play in
						the contexts that most matter to it—whether theoretical, psychological,
						cultural, political, or biographical. This might include: <list>
							<item>performance and reception history</item>
							<item>intellectual and/or cultural influences on the playwright</item>
							<item>the playwright’s aesthetic, ethical, and/or political motivation
								or agenda</item>
							<item>a history and/or analysis of the cultural moment the play
								addresses</item>
							<item>dramaturgical elements: style of the play, innovative aspects,
								staging</item>
						</list>
						<emph>Throughout, use specific scenes and lines from the play to support
							your arguments.</emph> In addition, as illustration in the essay,
						analyze closely at least one key scene we should be familiar with to
						understand the play. Examine it according to your thesis about the play, and
						place the scene in the context of the whole play and its milieu.</p>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi>The portfolio</hi>: The rest of the portfolio should
						resemble a theatre program, filled with your notes, pictures, explanations,
						and the like. Place carefully considered, digested bits in the portfolio
						that we could read rather quickly to understand the play (as opposed to lots
						of printouts from websites, or photocopied entire articles). For instance,
						you might include: <list>
							<item>a biographical timeline of the author</item>
							<item>quotations from the author, those involved in a production,
								etc.</item>
							<item>quotations from scholarship on the play</item>
							<item>excerpts from other works—theory, other plays—that relate to the
								play and help us understand it</item>
							<item>photographs or artwork related to the play, its aesthetics, or its
								cultural context</item>
							<item>pictures or excerpts from reviews of performances of the
								play</item>
						</list> You can actually design and bind this as a program, if you wish. My
						basic expectation, though, is that you will turn in a pocket folder or ring
						binder with the essay and contextual material filed in it.</p>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi><emph>Director’s Portfolio</emph></hi>: Take the role of
						director, the member of the production team whose vision guides the
						performance of the play. Provide your overall vision and show how you’d
						achieve it by giving specific details of dramatic (textual) and theatrical
						(performance) interpretation.</p>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi>The paper</hi>: Develop the interpretation of your play.
							<emph>Throughout, use specific scenes and lines from the play to support
							your choices</emph>. Answer questions such as: <list>
							<item>Why would you direct this play today?</item>
							<item>What is your interpretation or vision of the play? Do you think
								you are fulfilling the playwright’s own vision of the play, or that
								you are extending or even challenging it in some way?</item>
							<item>What is the key scene of the play and how would you stage it to
								convey your interpretation?</item>
							<item>Where would you stage the play? How would you use the space,
								design the look and feel of the theatrical experience?</item>
							<item>Whom would you cast?</item>
							<item>Whom would you target as your audience? What kind of relationship
								with your audience would you strive for?</item>
						</list>
					</p>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi>The portfolio</hi>: Submit a portfolio of images and
						ideas. All portfolios must include the first two items below, and all must
						include at least one design scheme, as relevant to your interpretation. <list>
							<item>Casting choices, with sketches or photographs of actors (or
								non-actors)</item>
							<item>A sketch of your performance space showing what kind of stage
								space you will use (you don’t have to use a professional theatre
								space), and where the audience is located in relation to the
								actors</item>
							<item>Set design with sketches of the set and/or photographs of
								settings, locales, artwork, etc.</item>
							<item>Lighting design ideas with sketches, photos, artwork, etc.</item>
							<item>Costume design ideas with sketches, photos, artwork, swatches,
								etc.</item>
							<item>Sound design ideas with a cd or digital file of songs, music,
								sound effects, etc.</item>
							<item>Smell design ideas with swatches, vials, scratch-and-sniff
								patches, etc.</item>
						</list></p><lb/>
					<ab>
						<emph>Weekly Seminar Work: Reading Responses</emph>
					</ab>
					<p rend="noCount">Each week, in response to the theory and play(s) scheduled,
						you are to write a response that raises critical questions and concerns for
						seminar discussion. If we’re reading more than one text, <emph>respond to
							both or all, and make connections between them</emph>. In content the
						responses should be <emph>thoughtful</emph>: focus on depth rather than
						breadth, and work closely and specifically with the texts themselves. In
						form the responses should be 2-3 pages, typed and double-spaced. You’ll be
						asked to read from them in class. </p>
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="5">
					<head>Reading Schedule</head>
					<ab>(Week 1) - <emph>Course introductions</emph>: <emph>defining holy theatre
						</emph></ab>
					<list type="simple">
						<item>Brook, “Holy Theatre” from <title level="m">The Empty Space</title>
						</item>

						<item>Demastes, Chapter One, “Toward a Materialization of Consciousness in
							Theater and the Sciences” in <title level="m">Staging Consciousness</title>
						</item>
						<item>Innes, “Themes and definitions” in Chapter One of <title level="m"
								>Holy Theatre: Ritual and the Avant Garde</title>
						</item>
						<item>Nietzsche, on the Apollonian and Dionysian, in <title level="m">The
								Birth of Tragedy</title>
						</item>
						<item>Auslander, “Holy Theatre and Catharsis” in <title level="m">From
								Acting to Performance</title>
						</item>
						<item>Film clips: <title level="m">Waking Life</title>, <title level="m"
								>What the Bleep Do We Know?</title></item>
					</list>
					<ab>(Week 2) - <emph>Renaissance “theatre of the imagination” and <name
								ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>’s development of
							techniques to reveal interiority; ”strategic opacity” and innovations in
							the soliloquy</emph></ab>
					<list type="bulleted">
						<item><title level="m">Hamlet</title></item>
						<item>Greenblatt, <title level="m">Will in the World</title>, pp. 298-324 </item>
						<item>Film clip: <title level="m">The Diving Bell and The Butterfly</title>
						</item>
					</list>
					<ab>(Week 3) - <emph>“Rough magic” and the conjuring of remorse</emph></ab>
					<list type="bulleted">
						<item><title level="m">The Tempest</title></item>
						<item>Burwick, from <title level="m">Illusion and the Drama</title> (pp.
							63-71; plus Chapter Five, “Illusion and the Poetic Imagination: <name
								ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>”)</item>
						<item>Film clip: <title level="m">Inception</title></item>
					</list>
					<ab>(Week 4) - <emph>Theatre of Romanticism: Gothic spectacle and Romantic
							illusion</emph></ab>
					<list>
						<item><name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>, <title level="m"
								>Remorse</title> and Letter II from “Satyrane’s Letters” in <title
								level="m">Biographia Literaria</title></item>
						<item><name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> and <name ref="GamerMichael"
								>Gamer</name>, Introduction to <title level="m">The Broadview
								Anthology of Romantic Drama</title>
						</item>
						<item>Reviews of <title level="m">Remorse</title> from the <title level="j"
								>Morning Chronicle</title> and <title level="j">The Examiner</title>
							(pp. 389-392 of the <title level="m">Broadview Anthology</title>)</item>
						<item>Thomas, “Seeing Things (‘As They Are’)”</item>
						<item>Haney, from <title level="m">The Challenge of Coleridge</title>, pp.
							146-49 and 196-99</item>
					</list>
					<ab>(Week 5) – <emph>Staging passions: “hauntology” and ontology</emph></ab>

					<list>
						<item>P. B. Shelley, “Lift Not the Painted Veil”</item>
						<item>Baillie, <title level="m">Orra</title></item>
						<item>Review of <title>A Series of Plays</title> and “Remarks on the Plays
							on the Passions” (pp. 378-83 of the <title level="m">Broadview
								Anthology</title>)</item>
						<item>Carlson, “Baillie’s <title level="m">Orra</title>: Shrinking in
							Fear”</item>
					</list>
					<ab>(Week 6) – <emph>Sympathetic curiosity and the need for an intimate
							theatre</emph>
					</ab>
					<list type="bulleted">
						<item>excerpts from “Introductory Discourse” and “To the Reader” of <title
								level="m">A Series of Plays</title> (pp. 357-378 of the <title
								level="m">Broadview Anthology</title>) </item>
						<item><name ref="BurroughsCatherineB">Burroughs</name>, from <title
								level="m">Closet Stages</title>, pp. 86-109.</item>
						<item>Forbes, “‘Sympathetic Curiosity’ in Joanna Baillie’s Theater of the
							Passions”</item>
						<item>Film clip: <title level="m">A Single Man</title></item>
					</list>

					<ab>(Week 7) – <emph>Staging the unconscious, dreams, liminal states</emph>
					</ab>
					<list type="bulleted">
						<item> Strindberg, “Open Letter to the Intimate Theater” </item>
						<item>
							<title level="m"> The Ghost Sonata</title> and <title level="m">A Dream
								Play</title>
						</item>
						<item>Film clips: <title level="m">The Science of Sleep</title>, <title
								level="m">What Dreams May Come</title>
						</item>
					</list>
					<ab>(Week 8) - <emph>Symbolist drama and “total theatre”</emph>
					</ab>
					<list type="bulleted">
						<item>Maeterlinck, <title level="m">Interior</title> and “The Modern
							Drama”</item>
						<item>Kleist, “On the Marionette Theater”</item>
						<item>Briusov, <title level="m">The Wayfarer</title> and “Against Naturalism
							in the Theater”</item>
						<item>Kandinsky, <title level="m">The Yellow Sound</title> and “On Stage
							Composition”</item>
					</list>
					<ab>(Week 9) – <emph>Theatre stripped of theatricality: staging existence</emph>
					</ab>
					<list type="bulleted">
						<item>Beckett, <title level="m">Waiting for Godot</title>
						</item>
						<item>Esslin, from <title level="m">Theatre of the Absurd</title></item>
						<item>Essif, from <title level="m">Empty Figure on an Empty
							Stage</title></item>
					</list>
					<ab>(Week 10) – <emph>Holy performers, theatre as holy rite and
						sacrifice</emph></ab>

					<list>
						<item>Overview of 1960s-70s Off-off-Broadway movement, Happenings, the
							Living Theatre, the Open Theatre, the Performance Group’s <title
								level="m">Dionysus in 69</title></item>
						<item>Artaud, “No More Masterpieces,” “Theater of Cruelty” from <title
								level="m">The Theatre and Its Double</title></item>
						<item>Chaikin, from <title level="m">The Presence of the
							Actor</title></item>
						<item>Shepard, <title level="m">Suicide in B Flat</title></item>
						<item>Grotowski, “The Theatre’s New Testament” from <title level="m">Towards
								a Poor Theatre</title></item>
						<item>Film clip: <title level="m">My Dinner with Andre</title></item>
					</list>

					<ab>(Week 11) – <emph>Catharsis and communion: holy theatre and the Black Arts
							Movement</emph></ab>

					<list>
						<item>Baraka, <title level="m">Slave Ship</title></item>
						<item>Baraka, “The Revolutionary Theatre”</item>
						<item>Shange, <title level="m">for colored girls…</title></item>
					</list>

					<ab>(Week 12) – <emph>Presentation of your own theatre manifestos</emph></ab><lb/>

					<ab>(Week 13) – <emph>Where can we find contemporary holy theatre?</emph></ab>

					<list>
						<item>Sarah Kane, <title level="m">4:48 Psychosis</title> and <title
								level="m">Blasted</title></item>
					</list>

					<ab>(Week 14) – <emph>Dramaturg’s/Director’s portfolio due</emph></ab>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
