<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ENDNOTES</p>


<div>
    <br clear="all"/>
    <hr class="c6" size="1" width="33%"/>
    
    <div id="edn1">
        <p><a href="#_ednref1" name="_edn1" title="">[i]</a> Regarding British Romantic
            drama and international politics, see monographs by Matthew S. Buckley, <ref
                target="people.html#CarlsonJulieAnn">Julie Carlson</ref>, Jeffrey Cox,
            Daniel O&#39;Quinn, <ref target="people.html#MoodyJane">Jane Moody</ref>,
            Gillian Russell, and George Taylor.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn2">
        <p><a href="#_ednref2" name="_edn2" title="">[ii]</a> Paul Friedland,
            Marie-H&eacute;l&egrave;ne Huet, Mona Ozouf, and Susan Maslan all dissect
            theater in order to explicate the Revolution.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn3">
        <p><a href="#_ednref3" name="_edn3" title="">[iii]</a> On Revolutionary
            festivals, see Ozouf and Nielsen (&quot;Staging Rousseau&#39;s
            Republic&quot;).</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn4">
        <p><a href="#_ednref4" name="_edn4" title="">[iv]</a> On productions of
            Marat&#39;s assassination onstage in France, see Marie-H&eacute;l&egrave;ne
            Huet&#39;s book.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn5">
        <p><a href="#_ednref5" name="_edn5" title="">[v]</a>
            <i>L&#39;Ami des loix</i> premiered 2 Jan. 1793 and played through 15
            January before being suspended against the will of the public. See Susan
            Maslan, esp. 61-4.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn6">
        <p><a href="#_ednref6" name="_edn6" title="">[vi]</a> Some reflections on
            <i>Reflections</i> include those written by Steven Blakemore, Paul
            Hindson and Tim Gray, Jacqueline M. Labbe, Ronald Paulson, Elizabeth D.
            Samet, and Linda M. G. Zerilli.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn7">
        <p><a href="#_ednref7" name="_edn7" title="">[vii]</a> Dorinda Outram has
            brought this type of iconography to light.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn8">
        <p><a href="#_ednref8" name="_edn8" title="">[viii]</a> Lynn Hunt documents the
            Republicans&#39; attack on the morality of the Queen.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn9">
        <p><a href="#_ednref9" name="_edn9" title="">[ix]</a> An example of <ref
            target="people.html#BurkeEdmund">Burke</ref>&#39;s use of extended
            metaphors is the following: &quot;When the old feudal and chivalrous spirit
            of <i>fealty</i>, which, by freeing kings from fear, freed both kings and
            subjects from the precautions of tyranny, shall be extinct in the minds of
            men, plots and assassinations will be anticipated by preventive murder and
            preventive confiscation, and that long roll of grim and bloody maxims, which
            form the political code of all power, not standing on its own honour, and
            the honour of those who are to obey it. Kings will be tyrants from policy,
            when subjects are rebels from principle&quot; (<ref
                target="people.html#BurkeEdmund">Burke</ref> 74).</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn10">
        <p><a href="#_ednref10" name="_edn10" title="">[x]</a> On composition and
            creative writing, see Starkey&#39;s collection. On ethos, see
            Gon&ccedil;alves.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn11">
        <p><a href="#_ednref11" name="_edn11" title="">[xi]</a> An example of this
            arbitrary censorship is Edmund John Eyre&#39;s <i>The Maid of Normandy; or,
                the Death of the Queen of France</i> (1793), which sympathizes with the
            royal family (see Nielsen, &quot;Edmund Eyre&#39;s <i>The Maid of
                Normandy</i>&quot; and L. W. Conolly, esp. p. 93). George Taylor and
            <ref target="people.html#MoodyJane">Jane Moody</ref> also provide
            excellent references on censorship.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn12">
        <p><a href="#_ednref12" name="_edn12" title="">[xii]</a> I discuss the French
            roots of <i>The Massacre</i> elsewhere (Nielsen, &quot;A Tragic
            Farce&quot;).</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn13">
        <p><a href="#_ednref13" name="_edn13" title="">[xiii]</a> Marie-Pierre Le Hir
            provides strong evidence for the influence of colonists on the reception of
            <i>Black Slavery</i> (see esp. p. 81-2).</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn14">
        <p><a href="#_ednref14" name="_edn14" title="">[xiv]</a>
            <i>The Rights of Woman and Citizen</i> is available in English online as
            well. See Day 4 of my syllabus under &quot;External Links:&quot;
            &lt;romanticsyllabus.html#4&gt;</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn15">
        <p><a href="#_ednref15" name="_edn15" title="">[xv]</a> See <ref
            target="people.html#CoxJeffreyN">Jeffrey Cox</ref> and volume five of
            <i>Slavery, Abolition, and Emancipation</i>.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn16">
        <p><a href="#_ednref16" name="_edn16" title="">[xvi]</a> It is also worth
            considering Romantic drama as a genre after 1830. After all, the Danish
            Romantic writer Adam Oehlenschl&auml;ger (1779-1850) influenced Henrik
            Ibsen&#39;s early historical plays. <i>The Warrior&#39;s Barrow</i> (prem.
            Sept. 1850 in Christiania, now called Oslo) resembles Romantic drama more
            than Ibsen&#39;s later Naturalist plays.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn17">
        <p><a href="#_ednref17" name="_edn17" title="">[xvii]</a> G. G. and J. J.
            Robinson Keppel published a translation of <i>The Robbers</i> in 1795.
            Richard Craven&#39;s translation of <i>The Robbers</i> (<i>Die
                R&auml;uber</i>, 1781) was performed at Brandenburgh House Theatre in
            1798 and published in 1799. Perhaps that is the same translation that
            appeared at the Haymarket on 21 August 1799. For Schiller&#39;s connections
            to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, see <ref
                target="people.html#CarlsonJulieAnn">Carlson</ref>.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn18">
        <p><a href="#_ednref18" name="_edn18" title="">[xviii]</a> The work of <ref
            target="people.html#BurroughsCatherineB">Catherine Burroughs</ref>, <ref
                target="people.html#CrochunisThomasC">Thomas C. Crochunis</ref>, <ref
                    target="people.html#DonkinEllen">Ellen Donkin</ref>, Michael
            Eberle-Sinatra, Judith Pascoe, and <ref
                target="people.html#PurintonMarjeanD">Marjean Purinton</ref> reminds us
            of some of the important scholarship on female dramatists.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn19">
        <p><a href="#_ednref19" name="_edn19" title="">[xix]</a> Susanna Kord wrote a
            compendium that traces the multiple pseudonyms of over 200 eighteenth- and
            nineteenth-century female dramatists. On censorship of women dramatists in
            Germany, see Becker-Cantarino and Kaiser.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn20">
        <p><a href="#_ednref20" name="_edn20" title="">[xx]</a> English translations of
            German women writers are available, although these feature more prose and
            fiction than drama. See Blackwell&#39;s and Zantop&#39;s collection
            <i>Bitter Healing</i> and the online database, <i>Sophie: a Digital
                Database of Works by German-speaking Women</i>.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn21">
        <p><a href="#_ednref21" name="_edn21" title="">[xxi]</a> Charlotte von Stein
            (1742-1827) knew Goethe because she grew up in the court of Weimar. Stein
            also wrote a tragedy, <i>Dido</i> (1794), translated partially by Goodman,
            p. 86-8.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn22">
        <p><a href="#_ednref22" name="_edn22" title="">[xxii]</a> See Cyrus Hamlin&#39;s
            review of Peter Stein&#39;s three-day-long production of <i>Faust</i>, Parts
            1 and 2, in Berlin in 2001. In New York City, the Classic Stage Company
            produced a six-hour-long version of both parts (May 2006, trans. Douglas
            Langworthy and dir. David Herskovits).</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn23">
        <p><a href="#_ednref23" name="_edn23" title="">[xxiii]</a> See David Marshall
            for a comparison of Shelley and Rousseau.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn24">
        <p><a href="#_ednref24" name="_edn24" title="">[xxiv]</a> G&eacute;raud de
            Lavedan, Martin Nadeau, Anastassia Sakhnovskaia, and Jean-Philippe van
            Aelbrouck edit <i>C&eacute;sar: Electronic Calendar of Plays during the Old
                Regime and during the Revolution</i> (<i>calendrier &eacute;lectronique
                    des spectacles sous l&#39;ancien r&eacute;gime et sous la
                    r&eacute;volution</i>), a collaborative research project begun in
            2001.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div id="edn25">
        <p><a href="#_ednref25" name="_edn25" title="">[xxv]</a> For comparative studies
            of Romanticism, see Frederick Burwick, Angela Esterhammer, Michael Ferber,
            Lillian Furst, Gerald Gillespie, Gregory Maertz, Martin Meisel, and Virgil
            Nemoianu.</p>
    </div>