<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Circulations: Romanticism and the Black Atlantic</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
				<title level="a">Abstracts</title>
				<editor>Eric Eisner</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
					<name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>abstracts</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p rend="noCount">Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
					<p rend="noCount">By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
						<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
							Circles.</item>
						<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
					</list></p>
					<p rend="noCount">Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Abstracts</title></analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Romantic Fandom:</title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p rend="noCount">All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for "," for ", ' for ', and ' for '.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p rend="noCount">Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p rend="noCount">Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p rend="noCount">&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
					<p rend="noCount">All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Mike Quilligan</name>
				<date>2010-06-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="paratext">
				<head>Abstracts</head>
				<p rend="noCount"><quote rend="center"><ref target="#YoungquistAbstract">Paul Youngquist and Frances Botkin</ref> | <ref target="#TwaAbstract">Lindsay J. Twa</ref> | <ref target=
					"#SzwydkyAbstract">Lissette Lopez Szwydky</ref> | <ref target="#AlmeidaAbstract">Joselyn Almeida</ref> | <ref target="#KennedyAbstract">Dustin Kennedy</ref> | <ref target="#SpeitzAbstract">Michele Speitz</ref></quote></p>
				
			<!-- Authors, titles, and abstracts here -->
				<div><head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="YoungquistAbstract"></anchor>Paul Youngquist and Frances Botkin</hi>, <title level="a">Introduction: Black Romanticism: Romantic Circulations</title></head>
				
					<p rend="noCount">The whiteness of Romantic studies is a symptom of amnesia. It bespeaks a massive act of forgetting on the part of contemporary scholarship, an institutional disavowal of the economic conditions that help make cultural production during the Romantic Era possible: the maritime economy of the Atlantic. Black Romanticism deterritorializes British national identity and the culture of the Romantic era, reimagining them as the effect of myriad economic and cultural exchanges circulating throughout the Atlantic. It remembers the forgotten ancestry of British culture, recovering the vital role Africans and other diasporic commoners play in the cultural production called Romanticism, and practices counter-literacy, reading the works of nation, empire, and colony against themselves to liberate the common cultures they occlude. This volume focuses on Jean-Jacque Dessalines, Jack Mansong, Juan Manzano, John Gabriel Stedman, and Mary Prince, Caribbean figures whose biographies have over the past two centuries become part of a constellation of stories about slavery and colonialism, following a circuitous route that began in Africa and traveled from Haiti, Jamaica, Cuba, Suriname, Bermuda, and Antigua to corresponding points in England, America, and the continent. Each narrative has endured transformations that render the “original” story less significant than the ways they have changed, been changed, or changed the stories connected with them. Each of these figures has acquired multiple and contradictory reputations in part due to changing audiences and media.</p>
				
				<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.youngquist.html">go to
					essay</ref>]<lb/></p></div>
				
				<div><head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="TwaAbstract"></anchor>Lindsay J. Twa</hi>, <title level="a">Jean-Jacques Dessalines: Demon, Demigod, and Everything in Between</title></head>
				
					<p rend="noCount">This essay examines how popular representations of Jean-Jacques Dessalines, a Haitian Revolutionary general and Haiti’s first head of state, have shaped his legacy for various political, creative, and ritualistic purposes.  After an overview of Dessalines’s biography, the essay examines negative representations of Dessalines, from nineteenth-century pro-slavery tracts, to twentieth-century publications during the U.S. Occupation of Haiti.  These representations are then compared against those created by African American writers who, in particular, represent Dessalines as a dramatic and powerful black hero, but omit from their accounts his more brutal actions.  The essay concludes with an examination of the Haitian folk religion, Vodou, and how it is one of the few arenas that actually recognizes and celebrates the contradictory nature of this mercurial historic figure.</p>
				
				<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.twa.html">go to
					essay</ref>]<lb/></p></div>
				
				<div><head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="SzwydkyAbstract"></anchor>Lissette Lopez Szwydky</hi>, <title level="a">Rewriting the History of Black Resistance: The Haitian Revolution, Jamaican Maroons and the 'History' of Three-Fingered Jack in English Popular Culture, 1799-1830</title></head>
				
					<p rend="noCount">The story of Three-Fingered Jack (the escaped slave who terrorized the British colonists in Jamaica from 1780 to 1781) appeared in England in at least five major versions between 1799 and 1830.  These adaptations included Benjamin Moseley’s <title level="m">Treatise on Sugar</title> (1799), William Earle’s novella <title level="m">Obi; or, The History of Three-Fingered Jack</title> (1800), a pantomime by John Fawcett titled <title level="m">Obi; or, Three-Finger’d Jack</title> (1800), a sixty-page pamphlet by William Burdett titled <title level="m">Life and Exploits of Mansong, Commonly Called Three-Finger’d Jack, the Terror of Jamaica</title> (1800), and finally <title level="m">Obi; or , Three-Fingered Jack</title>, a melodrama by William Murray (1830). Although different in their respective politics and approaches, these five nineteenth-century version of the story deemphasized the collective threat that underlies Three-Fingered Jack’s exploits in 1780-81, during an time of several slave uprisings in the Caribbean, including the Haitian Revolution.  The English adaptations misrepresented the history of collective resistance in Jamaica in two major ways. First, Three-Fingered Jack, the leader of a gang of sixty rebels, became a lone rebel. Stripping Jack of his followers made the story appear to be an isolated incident, as opposed to a collective effort.  The second way that Three-Fingered Jack’s popular history in England ignored the actual history of black resistance and independence in Jamaica was by changing the identity of Jack’s captor from a Maroon to a slave. All of the nineteenth-century adaptations of the story of Three-Fingered Jack misrepresent the identity of Jack’s killer. Whether intentional or not, this change completely distorted the story of Three-Fingered Jack by ignoring the role that free blacks played in restoring order to the island.</p>
				
					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.szwydky.html">go to
					essay</ref>]<lb/></p></div>
				
				<div><head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="AlmeidaAbstract"></anchor>Joselyn Almeida</hi>, <title level="a">Translating a Slave’s Life: Richard Robert Madden and the Post-Abolition Trafficking of Juan Manzano’s <title level="m">Poems by a Slave in the Island of Cuba</title></title></head>
				
					<p rend="noCount">Almeida examines the translations of Juan Manzano’s <title level="m">Poems</title>, a manuscript that followed a labyrinthine route before its eventual publication. Almeida suggests that the translation provided British abolitionists with the cultural capital necessary to “ensure a future beyond 1840 given the realignment of geopolitical and economic power in the Atlantic” (11). Madden’s translation functions, she argues, “as a sign of appropriated cultural labor, and performs an ideological accommodation of slavery within the free market/free labor system” (3). </p>			
					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.almeida.html">go to
					essay</ref>]<lb/></p></div>
				
				<div><head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="KennedyAbstract"></anchor>Dustin Kennedy</hi>, <title level="a">Going Viral: Stedman's <title level="m">Narrative</title>, Textual Variation, and Life in Atlantic Studies</title></head>
					
					<p rend="noCount">The current multiplex configuration of Stedman's <title level="m">Narrative</title> emerged in 1988, the result of Richard and Sally Price's new scholarly edition. The Prices' text transcribed Stedman's 1790 manuscript version aiming to restore his original authorial intent and exposing the extent to which the text had been altered by Stedman's first editor, Joseph Johnson. Both versions of the <title level="m">Narrative</title> are troubled by what they cannot contain, whether it be the sexual exploitation made possible by plantation-slavery, or the inter-racial desire that would eventually mark Stedman's <title level="m">Narrative</title> as a singular example of resistance to the exploitations inherent in the eighteenth-century Atlantic world. Stedman was more than a traveler in Surinam, and he was also more than a colonial agent and oppressor. The <title level="m">Narrative</title> can be read as the outgrowth of social subjectivity categories that typify the operation of the larger plantation slavery system in the West Indies and South America, but it must also be recognized in its particularity. In the following sections, I will consider what happens when Stedman's authorship becomes displaced in the larger archive – how critics rewrite what they read, how an author becomes a character, and above all else, how textual changes challenge criticism's reduction of Stedman to imperialist. </p>				
					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.kennedy.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p></div>
				
				
				<div><head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="SpeitzAbstract"></anchor>Michele Speitz</hi>, <title level="a">Blood Sugar and Salt Licks: Corroding Bodies and Preserving Nations in <title level="m">The History of Mary Prince, a West Indian Slave, Related by Herself</title></title></head>
				
					<p rend="noCount">Speitz demonstrates how Prince’s narrative attests to the importance of salt, a central product of slave labor in the British-held West Indies. Although its overall value is largely ignored in literary scholarship, Speitz demonstrates how harvesting salt proved harmful enough to inspire Prince’s rendition of a horrific contortion of being. Her repeated detrimental exposure to salt transforms Prince’s body, consciousness, and ultimately, of course, her narrative--making it tantamount to a material history and psychological case study of a forced merger of landscape, labor, body, and mind. Prince’s text records how lethal amounts of salt seep through the skin, forging a visceral, literal, and grotesque union between salt, the commodified substance, and the slave, the commodified worker. Further, buttressing the vast amount of scholarship on the historical significance of luxury consumables which could easily impede international or regional revenue streams if boycotted, Speitz brings to light the unacknowledged history of Caribbean salt raking relative to not only British colonial economies and politics, but also to the revolutionary history of the United States, in which it plays a pivotal role.</p>
				
					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.speitz.html">go to
					essay</ref>]<lb/></p></div>
				
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
