<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Circulations: Romanticism and the Black Atlantic</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">Rewriting the History of Black Resistance: The Haitian Revolution,
               Jamaican Maroons and the “History” of Three-Fingered Jack in English Popular Culture, 1799-1830</title>
            <author>
               <name>Lissette Lopez Szwydky</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">Paul Youngquist</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <editor role="editor">Frances Botkin</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.szwydky</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Rewriting the History of Black Resistance: The
                     Haitian Revolution, Jamaican Maroons and the “History” of Three-Fingered Jack
                     in English Popular Culture, 1799-1830</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Lissette Lopez</forename>
                        <surname>Szwydky</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Circulations:</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#226;&#8364;&#339;,"
                  for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
            <keywords scheme="http://www.rc.umd.edu/#tags">
               <list>
                  <item>The story of Three-Fingered Jack (the escaped slave who terrorized the British colonists in Jamaica from 1780 to 1781) appeared in England in at least five major versions between 1799 and 1830.  Although different in their respective politics and approaches, these five nineteenth-century version of the story deemphasized the collective threat that underlies Three-Fingered Jack’s exploits in 1780-81, during an time of several slave uprisings in the Caribbean, including the Haitian Revolution.</item>
                  <item>Benjamin Moseley</item>
                  <item>Treatise on Sugar (1799)</item>
                  <item>William Earle</item>
                  <item>William Burdett</item>
                  <item>Life and Exploits of Mansong, Commonly Called Three-Finger’d Jack, the Terror of Jamaica (1800)</item>
                  <item>William Murray</item>
                  <item>Obi; or , Three-Fingered Jack, a Melodrama (1830)</item>
                  <item>Three-Fingered Jack</item>
                  <item>culture</item>
                  <item>popular reception</item>
                  <item>history</item>
                  <item>Obi; or, The History of Three-Fingered Jack (1800)</item>
                  <item>John Fawcett</item>
                  <item>Obi; or, Three-Finger’d Jack (1800)</item>
                  </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2011-03-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head><title level="a">Rewriting the History of Black Resistance: The Haitian
                  Revolution, Jamaican Maroons and the “History” of Three-Fingered Jack in English
                  Popular Culture, 1799-1830</title></head>
            <byline><docAuthor>Lissette Lopez Szwydky</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>The Pennsylvania State University</affiliation></byline>


            <div>
               <head> </head>
               <p> Michel-Rolph Trouillot begins his essay, “From Planters’ Journals to Academia:
                  The Haitian Revolution as Unthinkable History,” with an anecdote. In 1790, a
                  planter in Saint Domingue writes a series of letters to his wife in France
                  reassuring her that the Revolution has not spread to the Caribbean. He writes,
                  “There is no movement among our Negroes . . . . They don’t even think of it. They
                  are very tranquil and obedient. A revolt among them is impossible” (Trouillot 81).
                  Apparently, all was quiet on the (French) Western front. There was no sign of an
                  organized slave revolt. The thought of an uprising was “impossible.” </p>
               <p>In August of the following year, the Haitian Revolution began. The irony of this
                  story is not lost on Trouillot, who explains: <quote>The Haitian Revolution thus
                     entered history with the peculiar characteristic of being unthinkable even as
                     it happened. Publications of the times, including the long list of pamphlets on
                     Saint Domingue published in France from 1790 to 1804, reveal the incapacity of
                     most contemporaries to understand the ongoing Revolution on its own terms. They
                     could read the news only with their ready-made categories, and these categories
                     were incompatible with the idea of a slave revolution. (82) </quote> Trouillot
                  chalks up the planter’s ignorance to a larger world view shaped and shared by
                  slave owners about enslaved peoples. He argues, “When reality does not coincide
                  with deeply-held beliefs, human beings . . . phras[e] interpretations that force
                  reality within the scope of these beliefs. They devise formulas to repress the
                  unthinkable and to bring it back within the realm of accepted discourse”
                     (Trouillot 81). In short, the planters were in denial. To
                  believe that the principles of the French Revolution could be adopted by slaves in
                  Saint Domingue required that planters not only acknowledge the humanity of slaves,
                  but also admit that stereotypes and misinformation spread about their intellectual
                  abilities were untrue. Identifying with revolutionary principles and, more
                  importantly, rising in arms <foreign>en masse</foreign> in order to defend those
                  principles required both intellectual and military prowess—two things that French
                  colonists living in Saint Domingue during the French Revolution preferred to deny.
                  As one may easily guess, the idea of a mass slave revolt would have been a
                  frightening image for slave owners in Saint Domingue (where slaves outnumbered
                  the free population by ten to one) after the revolution broke out in France 1789.
                  Nevertheless, it was the image they were met with in 1791. A well-organized slave
                  revolt turned into a full-scale revolution that lasted until 1804 and led to the
                  formation of the Republic of Haiti. </p>
               <p> Although the Haitian Revolution is the most successful slave revolt in the
                  Western hemisphere, it was preceded by many smaller uprisings, not only in Saint
                  Domingue, but also throughout the Caribbean and the Americas.<note place="foot"
                     resp="editors" n="1">For a recent comprehensive history, see Alvin O. Thompson,
                        <title level="m">Flight to Freedom: African Runaways and Maroons in the
                        Americas</title> (Kingston: U of the West Indies P, 2006).</note> Jamaica,
                  in fact, was home to the second most successful slave revolt in the Americas just
                  a few decades later, with the Christmas Rebellion of 1831. Jamaica was also home
                  to several uprisings throughout the late-seventeenth and eighteenth centuries,
                  with resistance coming from both slaves and free blacks. There were at least five
                  organized slave insurrections in the central region of the island between 1673 and
                     1725.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="2">According to Thompson, there were
                     outbreaks of violence in the following years 1673, 1678, 1685, 1690, and 1725.
                     See also Werner Zips, <title level="m">Black Rebels: African-Caribbean Freedom
                        Fighters in Jamaica </title>(Kingston: Ian Randle, 1999).</note> The most
                  famous slave revolt in eighteenth-century Jamaica, Tacky’s Rebellion, occurred in
                  the spring of 1760 in St. Mary Parish and took several weeks to quell. An existing
                  copy of the record book of slave trials in St. Andrew Parish (located just south
                  of St. Mary) lists 56 individual cases of “rebellious” activities prosecuted
                  between 1746 and 1782, including not only violent offences, but also the harboring
                  of runaway slaves and possession of obeah materials.<note place="foot"
                     resp="editors" n="3">See Diana Paton, “Punishment, Crime, and the Bodies of
                     Slaves in Eighteenth-Century Jamaica,” <title level="j">Journal of Social
                        History</title> 34 (2001): 923-54. The record shows a total of 202 cases
                     tried during the period.</note>
               </p>
               <p>English colonists in Jamaica also fought multiple wars against free blacks in the
                  eighteenth century. The First Maroon War lasted four decades and ended with two
                  treaties signed in 1739 and 1740; the Second Maroon War occurred in 1795-96. Both
                  conflicts posed serious threats to the European colonists with regard to both the
                  cost of troops and the financial burdens of war. In the four decades leading up to
                  the culmination of the First Maroon War, the Jamaican Assembly passed 44 acts and
                  spent £240,000 before signing treaties with the Maroons (Robinson 38). The
                  eight-month long conflict with the Trelawny Town Maroons in 1796 is estimated to
                  have cost between £350,000 and £500,000. “All this,” Mavis Campbell points out,
                  “to quell just over 150 arms-bearing Maroons” (244). Yet, despite their relatively
                  small numbers, the Trelawny Town Maroons were not to be underestimated. An early
                  nineteenth-century history by R. C. Dallas details the feared outcome of not
                  taking every expense necessary to end the Second Maroon War. He writes as follows:
                     <quote>[The Trelawny Town Maroons] threatened the entire destruction of the
                     island; for had this body of Maroons evinced that their rebellion was not a
                     temporary struggle, but a permanent and successful opposition to the
                     Government, it is highly probable that the example might in time have united
                     all the turbulent spirits among the slaves in a similar experiment . . . such a
                     decided triumph might have tempted numbers of the plantation negroes, unwilling
                     before to change a state of peace for warfare, to join the Maroons: at all
                     events they would have been a rallying point for every discontented slave . . .
                     . The lives of the colonists must have been spent in continual terror; massacre
                     and depredation would have spread throughout the country . . . . (2-3)</quote>
                  According to Dallas, any expense taken to remove the Maroon threat in 1796 was
                  worth it. The above passage explicitly expresses a fear of mass revolt on the part
                  of both Maroons and slaves that is much larger in scale than actually occurred in
                  Trelawny Town. </p>
               <p> So, why was Dallas convinced that the expense was worth it? Because the threat
                  posed by the Saint Domingue Revolution was very real. News of the rebellion in
                  Saint Domingue spread quickly to Jamaica. “Within a month after the August
                  uprising in St. Domingue,” writes David Geggus, “slaves in Jamaica were singing
                  songs about it” (276). British planters on the island took note. Using a wide
                  range of primary material, including the governor’s correspondence, Geggus
                  describes the subsequent months as follows: <quote>By November, whites were
                     complaining of “insolent” behavior and that the slaves had become “so different
                     a people from what they were.” “I am convinced,” wrote one master, “that the
                     Ideas of Liberty have sunk so deep in the minds of <emph>all</emph> Negroes,
                     that whenever the greatest precautions are not taken they will rise. “Head
                     negroes” were overheard talking of killing whites and dividing up their lands.
                     “Negroes in the French country,” they said, “were men.” (Geggus 277)</quote>
                  According to the picture painted here, Jamaican planters and French planters were
                  obviously on opposite sides of the spectrum with regard to acknowledging the
                  potential threat of being vastly outnumbered by slaves. Yet, the Jamaican
                  planters’ fears were never fully realized. After 1792, rebellious activity on the
                  island decreased over the next decade when compared to the previous three decades.
                  After 1792, the initial cause for alarm greatly subsided and all but vanished from
                  existing documents.</p>
               <p> For Geggus, the answer to the paradox as to why Jamaica remained stable during
                  the Haitian Revolution is quite simple. British military presence was key. Slave
                  resistance in the British Caribbean was low during the Age of Revolution for the
                  following reason: <quote>It was precisely during the years 1776-1815 that
                     Britain’s military presence in the region was at its peak. . . . . The British
                     colonial garrisons were boosted during the American War of Independence, and
                     they were not cut back to prewar levels in 1783. . . . . A succession of
                     international crises ensured that, when the St. Domingue slave revolt broke
                     out, there were already more soldiers in Jamaica than ever before in peacetime.
                     (Geggus 293)</quote> The worrisome tone that underscored the earlier examples
                  provided by Geggus vanished quickly because British military presence kept
                  rebellious activity at a minimum after 1792. Within months the tone had completely
                  shifted, and the island’s planters were calm.<lb></lb> 
                  <quote>The impact of the St.
                     Domingue Revolution on Jamaica’s slaves appears to have been slight . . . . The
                     slaves did not revolt . . . . Yet the initial reaction to the 1791 uprising had
                     been one of excitement and admiration accompanied in some quarters by a desire
                     to emulate it. Quite possibly planters covered up minor incidents on their own
                     estates, and there can be no doubt that they wished to avoid giving an
                     impression of public alarm that might damage their all-important commercial
                     credit. (Geggus 288)</quote> The English had their assurances that the island
                  was tranquil. Public documents gave no indication of unrest among the slaves.</p>
               <p>The history laid out above demonstrates that the opinions of planters in Saint
                  Domingue in 1791 lay in stark contrast to the ideas of planters in Jamaica shortly
                  thereafter. Similarly, the French colony and British colony would take very
                  different trajectories over the next decade. However, there is one trend that
                  French and British literature about black resistance in the Caribbean shared
                  during the same period. Despite the fact that all of the colonies in the Caribbean
                  had their share of revolts both small and large, many historical and literary
                  sources written by European colonists misrepresented mass revolts (even denied
                  them) by focusing on isolated incidents involving one or two individuals, as
                  opposed to well-organized, collective rebellions. Trouillot again gives us a
                  useful summary of the reports from Saint Domingue immediately preceding the
                  Haitian Revolution: <quote>Close as some were to the real world, planters and
                     managers could not fully deny resistance, but they tried to provide reassuring
                     certitude by trivializing all its manifestations. Resistance did not exist as a
                     global phenomenon. Rather, each case of unmistakable defiance, each possible
                     instance of resistance, was treated separately and drained of its political
                     content. Slave A ran away because he was particularly mistreated by his master.
                     Slave B was missing because he was not properly fed. Slave X killed herself in
                     a fatal tantrum. Slave Y poisoned her mistress because she was jealous. The
                     runaway or the rebellious slave emerges from this literature . . . as an animal
                     driven by biological constraints . . . . This is not “a man in revolt” . . .
                     but a maladjusted Negro . . . . (Trouillot 86)</quote> Although he is referring
                  to reports written by French colonists in Saint Domingue, Trouillot’s “unthinkable
                  history” of organized black resistance also applies to English representations of
                  Jamaica at the turn of the nineteenth century that appeared both in print and on
                  stage just as the French lost control of their own Caribbean colony. </p>
               <p>The misrepresentation of collective rebellion just outlined also characterizes the
                  history of Three-Fingered Jack in English popular culture.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>“The Terror of Jamaica” in England</head>
               <p>The story of Three-Fingered Jack (the escaped slave who terrorized the British
                  colonists in Jamaica from 1780 to 1781) appeared in England in at least five major
                  versions between 1799 and 1830. These adaptations included Benjamin Moseley’s
                     <title level="m">Treatise on Sugar </title>(1799), William Earle’s novella
                     <title level="m">Obi; or, The History of Three-Fingered Jack </title>(1800), a
                  pantomime by John Fawcett titled <title level="m">Obi; or, Three-Finger’d Jack
                  </title>(1800), a sixty-page pamphlet by William Burdett titled <title level="m"
                     >Life and Exploits of Mansong, Commonly Called Three-Finger’d Jack, the Terror
                     of Jamaica</title> (1800), and finally <title level="m">Obi; or ,
                     Three-Fingered Jack</title>, a melodrama by William Murray (1830). Although
                  different in their respective politics and approaches, these five
                  nineteenth-century version of the story deemphasized the collective threat posed
                  by Three-Fingered Jack’s exploits in 1780-81. </p>
               <p> Although he was notoriously dubbed the “Terror of Jamaica,” Three-Fingered Jack
                  is loosely tied to the Haitian Revolution in contemporary scholarship. In the
                  article that introduced Three-Fingered Jack to twentieth-century readers, Alan
                  Richardson shows that the popularity of this story in the first decade of the
                  nineteenth century fits into a larger trend in English literature and popular
                  culture much like the one outlined by Trouillot. Richardson’s piece demonstrates
                  how English representations of obeah generally played up the most sensational
                  aspects of the African tradition in an attempt to cover up the more unsettling
                  reality of black uprisings in the West Indies. Voodoo priests were partly
                  responsible for several organized revolts in Saint Domingue including the 1791
                  rebellion that began the Haitian Revolution.<note place="foot" resp="editors"
                     n="4">See Richardson for a more detailed account, as well as C. L. R. James,
                        <title level="m">The Black Jacobins: Toussaint L'Ouverture and the San
                        Domingo Revolution </title>(New York: Vintage, 1989).</note> Similarly,
                  obeah men were responsible for several uprisings in Jamaica throughout the
                  eighteenth century, the most famous being Tacky’s Rebellion in 1760, which led to
                  the outlawing of the practice on the island.<note place="foot" resp="editors"
                     n="5">See Srinivas Aravamudan’s introduction to his edition of William Earle’s
                        <title level="m">Obi; or, The History of Three-Fingered Jack
                     </title>(Peterborough, Ontario: Broadview, 2005), 7-51.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Although there is no hard evidence proving that Three-Fingered Jack was involved
                  in obeah rituals, obeah made its way into the story of Three-Fingered Jack
                  beginning with Moseley’s 1799 account. The following year, his name became
                  synonymous with the practice with the appearance of three popular adaptations
                  including Earle’s novella, Fawcett’s pantomime, and Burdett’s account. The
                  popularity of the story of Three-Fingered Jack at the height of the Haitian
                  Revolution makes sense. Richardson explains, “In the defeat of Jack and of obi
                  with him, the ‘Terror of Jamaica’ and the ‘Horror’ of Saint Domingue could be
                  symbolically exorcised” (Richardson 19). Richardson sees the obvious subtext of
                  the Haitian Revolution written into Fawcett’s pantomime. However, unlike the
                  revolution in Saint Domingue, the story of “The Terror of Jamaica” ends with the
                  colonial government’s authority restored, partly through the containment of rogue
                  religious and rebellious practices. The addition of the obeah storyline into the
                  popular English history of Three-Fingered Jack certainly invites such
                  conclusions.</p>
               <p>However, the defeat of obeah in the English adaptations of Three-Fingered Jack was
                  not the only way that the popular history was rewritten at the turn of the
                  nineteenth century in order to shape popular understanding of black resistance in
                  the West Indies. The English adaptations misrepresented the history of collective
                  resistance in Jamaica in two major ways. First, Three-Fingered Jack, the leader of
                  a gang of sixty rebels, became a lone rebel. Stripping Jack of his followers made
                  the story appear to be an isolated incident, as opposed to a collective effort.
                  Moseley and Murray erase Jack’s gang in their versions of the story. Earle and
                  Fawcett give Jack a few rag-tag followers, but neither acknowledges the actual
                  size and loyalty of Jack’s gang. Only Burdett makes Jack the leader of a large
                  group of slave rebels; however, his account quickly dispatches of the gang that
                  eluded government officials for more than one year.</p>
               <p>The second way that Three-Fingered Jack’s popular history in England ignored the
                  actual history of black resistance and independence in Jamaica was by changing the
                  identity of Jack’s captor from a Maroon to a slave. All of the nineteenth-century
                  adaptations of the story of Three-Fingered Jack misrepresent the identity of
                  Jack’s killer. Whether intentional or not, this change completely distorted the
                  story of Three-Fingered Jack by ignoring the role that free blacks played in
                  restoring order to the island. Most of the adaptations contain no free black
                  characters in the story. The two major changes to the story rewrote the history of
                  Three-Fingered Jack so that it (like other stories of slave insurrections in the
                  West Indies) was depicted as an isolated incident as opposed to a link in a chain
                  of organized rebellions that occurred in the European colonies in the Caribbean in
                  general, and Jamaica in particular, during the decades leading up to the Slave
                  Trade Act of 1807, and later full emancipation through the Slavery Abolition Act
                  of 1833.</p>
               <p>According to Diana Paton, the popularity of Three-Fingered Jack during the first
                  three decades of the nineteenth century is undeniably tied to English abolition
                  debates. The story of Three-Fingered Jack was particularly appealing for
                  nineteenth-century writers because it could be used to argue both for and against
                  slavery. Paton explains as follows: <quote>The cumulative impact of the cultural
                     figure of Three-Finger Jack was not to a produce a coherent argument regarding
                     the slave trade or slaver. Rather, representations of Jack could be adapted and
                     adopted by those on all sides of the slavery debates. Nevertheless, the easiest
                     fit was with a gradualist and ameliorationist viewpoint; potentially hostile to
                     the slave trade, but not emancipationist. Criticisms made by the prose and
                     stage versions of Three-Fingered Jack could be reconciled with the continuation
                     of slavery. (59) </quote> Paton argues that the shift in British public opinion
                  that led to full emancipation less than three decades after Three-Fingered Jack
                  became a household name in London motivated Murray to give a more sympathetic
                  portrayal of Jack in the 1830 melodrama. This may be true to some extent; however,
                  the massive overhaul made to the story by its earliest English adapters forever
                  changed the popular history of Three-Fingered Jack’s rebellion.</p>
               <p> There is some disagreement among scholars as how best to approach the various
                  adaptations of the story given the diverse range of political sympathies expressed
                  in each. For example, Earle’s novella is fervently abolitionist in its
                  presentation of Jack’s story. The pantomime by Fawcett, on the other hand, is
                  hardly radical in tone. Instead, the Fawcett pantomime, as Robert Hoskins
                  explains, <quote>. . . is woven into the imperial age. The site of the plantation
                     is assumed ripe for commercial exploitation and political control. The moral
                     and civic imperative is to impose the unquestioned superiority of Western
                     civilization on new lands and peoples. This mind-set in itself assumes
                     juxtaposition and conflict of opposites—civilization versus savagery and a
                     tamed, pastoral nature versus an untamed wilderness. Thus Afro-Caribbean
                     society and Jack as black insubordinate by definition became that dangerous or
                     unpleasant Other. (Hoskins par. 6)</quote> Jeffrey Cox agrees that an
                  overarching conservative ideology dominates Fawcett’s pantomime; however, he sees
                  moments where “aspects of Jack's story and of his culture break free from the
                  play's ideology,” and suggests that these moments of subversion were possible in
                  performances (depending on the cast, venue, and audience), if not explicitly
                  expressed in its printed songs and scene descriptions (Cox par. 7). </p>
               <p>James O’Rourke’s recent article on Murray’s 1830 melodrama argues that the play is
                  full of Jacobin sympathies, specifically because Jack’s character undergoes major
                  development from the 1800 pantomime. He writes, “the 1830 <title level="m"
                     >Obi</title> is . . . in fact a Jacobin play, both in its legitimation of the
                  violence of the oppressed and underclass and in the repudiation of its inherited
                  romantic plot” (O’Rourke 286).<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="6">While in
                     some ways the melodrama might be seen as a more radical version than its
                     earlier dramatic predecessor because it humanizes Jack within a similar
                     domestic framework, the production as a whole depoliticizes the history of
                     Three-Fingered Jack. Murray’s melodrama primarily sympathizes with Jack’s
                     desire to avenge his murdered wife and deemphasizes revolutionary rhetoric. For
                     example, in Act I, Scene 3, Jack expresses a desire to avenge “the wrongs of my
                     poor country,” but only after listing his wife and children and spending most
                     of his lines discussing personal motives. Murray’s melodramatic anti-hero is
                     significantly humanized through this domestic storyline when compared to the
                     earlier pantomime, but he is in no way presented as a rebel who posed an actual
                     threat to the colonial government protecting England’s strongest asset in the
                     West Indies.</note> This observation is accurate insofar as the two popular
                  dramas are concerned. Cox and Paton also agree that Three-Fingered Jack was cast
                  in a more sympathetic light on the 1830 stage when compared to the 1800 pantomime.
                  Most notably, Murray’s addition of spoken lines delivered by Ira Aldridge (the
                  first black actor to portray the Jamaican folk hero) introduced radical
                  possibilities in the performance of the melodrama that were absent from the 1800
                  pantomime. However, the 1830 melodrama hardly sounds radical when compared to
                  Earle’s abolitionist novella, which actually introduces Three-Fingered Jack as “a
                  bold Defender of the Rights of Man.”<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="7">The
                     quote is from the Advertisement to Earle’s novella.</note> (You really can’t
                  get more “Jacobin” than that.) O’Rourke’s reading is a convincing comparative
                  reading of the two plays, but is less convincing when one considers all of the
                  nineteenth-century adaptations in unison, and then compares them to the historical
                     record.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="8">One recent work that puts forth
                     a very different interpretation of Fawcett’s pantomime is Peter P. Reed,
                     “Conquer or Die: Staging Circum-Atlantic Revolt in <title level="m"
                        >Polly</title> and <title level="m">Three-Finger’d Jack,”</title>
                     <title level="j">Theatre Journal </title>59 (2007): 241–258. Reed reads
                     Fawcett’s pantomime as a radical play, a conclusion that, I believe, is
                     sustainable only if the pantomime is read independent of the other popular
                     adaptations of the story.</note>
               </p>
               <p> There is validity in all of the readings outlined above, especially since there
                  is no way to gauge how different readers and theatergoers may have interpreted any
                  of the adaptations produced in the nineteenth century. However, what is very clear
                  is how the nineteenth-century versions of the story simplified the events leading
                  up to Three-Fingered Jack’s demise either by erasing an entire population of free
                  blacks from the narrative or at least drastically downplaying their role in the
                  defeat of Three-Fingered Jack. My reading does not discredit existing scholarship
                  on the subject. However, my argument questions to what extent any of the
                  adaptations can be read as radical given that by erasing or downplaying the
                  involvement of Maroons and by making Three-Fingered Jack a one-man show,
                  nineteenth-century adapters failed to portray a long history of black resistance
                  in colonial Jamaica during a period of major unrest in Saint Domingue and
                  Jamaica.</p>
            </div>


            <div type="section" n="3">
               <head>Three Fingered Jack in Fact and Fiction</head>

               <p>According to eighteenth-century sources including Moseley, Three-Fingered Jack was
                  killed by a Maroon named Reeder, a free man. However, all of the
                  nineteenth-century adaptations of the story recast Reeder as a slave named Quashee
                  who (along with another slave named Sam) agrees to fight Three-Fingered Jack in
                  return for his freedom (and sometimes money). Moseley, Earle, and Burdett explain
                  the name change (contemporaneous news reports only use the name Reeder) by telling
                  the reader that Quashee took the name Reeder after being christened in order to
                  help him fight Jack. In the two theatrical pieces, Reeder is simply replaced by
                  Quashee, with no name change ever taking place during the course of the play
                  (although the christening still takes place in the pantomime). </p>
               <p>There are two important things to note with regard to this change in the English
                  versions. First, there is no historical evidence to support the name change to
                  Reeder through christening. Geggus explains that by the late eighteenth century,
                  three-quarters of Maroons had British names (284). Therefore, the only explanation
                  for the addition of a Christian storyline is to depict the superiority of British
                  culture and values and propagandize British imperialism through the devaluation of
                  an African religion. (The adaptations all sensationalize obeah while discrediting
                  it as mere superstition.) The second point to note is that the five English
                  versions push the Maroons to the margins of the story of Three-Fingered Jack, or
                  erase them entirely. Erasing the Maroons from the story’s afterlife in English
                  popular culture also made it easy to depict Jamaica as a stable British colony
                  during the time of the greatest unrest in the West Indies. </p>
               <p>By 1780, the year of Three-Fingered Jack’s activity in Jamaica, the Maroons had a
                  long history on the island. Maroon populations in Jamaica date back to the
                  sixteenth century, when the island was under Spanish control. When the British
                  gained control of the island in 1655, the Maroons refused to give up their
                  independence. They violently resisted the British colonists, and they were very
                  successful. Decades of confrontations ultimately resulted in the First Maroon War,
                  which officially lasted from 1731 until 1740. Unable to defeat the Maroons, the
                  British colonists instead entered into a series of official treaties that granted
                  the Maroons autonomy and approximately 2500 acres (concentrated in the five towns
                  of Trelawny Town, Scots Hall, Nanny Town, Accompong, and Moore Town). Independence
                  and land were “granted” in exchange for assistance in quelling slave riots and
                  capturing escaped slaves. Maroons were expected to participate in the capture of
                  Three-Fingered Jack, and eighteenth-century Jamaican newspapers and government
                  documents confirm that a Maroon named Reeder was in fact responsible for killing
                  him (Aravamudan, 11-13). </p>
               <p> The consensus in the eighteenth-century primary sources of information makes the
                  change from Maroon to slave all the more pronounced in the nineteenth-century
                  adaptations. The source of the confusion seems to be Moseley’s 1799 treatise,
                  where the story of Three-Fingered Jack is included in an appendix as a subsection
                  of an essay on obeah. The reader gets a significantly changed version of the story
                  in Moseley’s text, which begins “I saw the Obi of the famous negro robber,
                     <emph>Three fingered</emph> Jack, the terror of Jamaica in 1780 and 1781. The
                  Maroons who slew him brought it to me” (rpt. in Aravamudan, 164). He refers to the
                  man as Quashee, not Reeder as named in the reports. Why the name change? Moseley
                  offers a simple explanation. “Quashee, before he set out on the expedition, got
                  himself christianed, and changed his name to James Reeder” (rpt. in Aravamudan
                  166). Moseley’s account marks the first mention of religious conversion in the
                  story of Three-Fingered Jack. There is no mention in any contemporary newspapers
                  or other documentation. The absence of this information in any previous source
                  does not necessarily mean that Moseley’s explanation is false; however, there is
                  no primary source material to confirm Moseley’s claim. </p>
               <p>Although Moseley never explicitly calls Quashee a slave (in fact, he calls him a
                  Maroon), his description of Quashee is vague and likely the source of confusion
                  among most of the later adapters. Moseley tells his readers that Jack was finally
                  apprehended after the colonial government offered a substantial reward for his
                  capture, as well as the promise of freedom to any slave who managed to dispatch of
                  the menace. These rewards were in fact offered, but only the bounty was claimed
                  since Jack was killed by a Maroon. This fact is erased in all of the adaptations
                  that follow. From 1800 on, Quashee was always a slave. In the adaptations that
                  follow Moseley, Quashee’s characterization ranges from an industrious slave
                  primarily motivated by the colonial government’s financial reward and promise of
                  freedom, to a loyal slave who earns his freedom after risking his life to defend
                  his benevolent (and grateful) master. </p>
               <p>Earle’s 1800 novella (without a doubt the most explicitly abolitionist adaptation
                  of the story) also casts Quashee as a slave; however, Earle’s narrator focuses
                  more on the bounty offered by the colonial government, rather than the promise of
                  freedom. Disgusted by the financial reward offered for Jack’s capture, Earle’s
                  narrator offers the following take on Three-Fingered Jack’s demise: “Thus died as
                  great a man as ever graced the annals of history, basely murdered by the hirelings
                  of Government” (Earle 157). Earle’s description is the most accurate of the
                  nineteenth-century English adaptations because money did in fact play a major role
                  in Three-Fingered Jack’s capture; Reeder collected a reward of at least £300.
                  However, Earle’s Quashee is described as a slave working on behalf of the same
                  government that enslaves him. This historical inaccuracy—in the most radical
                  adaptation of the five versions produced in England, no less—not only
                  misrepresents Reeder’s identity, but does so at the expense of recognizing the
                  Maroons, the most significant example of free blacks living in Jamaica at the
                  time.</p>
               <p>Because of Earle’s abolitionist sympathies, Quashee’s actions are ultimately
                  un-heroic in the novella; however, Earle’s characterization is a far cry from the
                  other nineteenth-century versions of the story by Fawcett, Burdett, and Murray.
                  Burdett’s version (also published in 1800) makes Quashee a hero, a well-deserving
                  recipient of his dual reward. Despite its claims to historical accuracy, Burdett’s
                  account presents Quashee as a slave fighting primarily for his freedom—the money
                  is just an added bonus. The final lines of his pamphlet are “Reeder and Sam,
                  gifted with freedom and the rewards, annually celebrate the fall of the once
                  terror of the whole island of Jamaica” (Burdett 56). The order of words “freedom
                  and rewards” is significant. Fawcett, Burdett, and Murray all focus on the reward
                  of freedom; in fact, the two stage adaptations mention <emph>only</emph> this
                  reward. By 1800, this became the standard storyline for Quashee. In other words,
                  Earle’s characterization of Quashee as a government mercenary faded as soon as it
                  was introduced because it was overshadowed by less radical adaptations with a
                  wider popular reach.</p>
               <p>Unlike the textual accounts, which give Quashee/Reeder more agency in his decision
                  to pursue Three-Fingered Jack, the theatrical adaptations characterize him as a
                  loyal slave whose duty to his master is rivaled only by his dedication to his own
                  family. Fawcett’s pantomime presents Quashee and Sam as loyal fathers fighting for
                  freedom. Their duty to their wives and children is presented alongside
                  subservience to the owner of the plantation. This sentimental characterization
                  would certainly raise the eyebrows of today’s readers, but was a typical
                  characterization of slaves in literary and theatrical productions that argued for
                  abolition of the slave trade, if not for full emancipation.<note place="foot"
                     resp="editors" n="9">For more on this popular, sentimental representation of
                     slaves see George Boulukos, <title level="m">The Grateful Slave: The Emergence
                        of Race in Eighteenth-Century British and American Culture
                     </title>(Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 2008).</note> This characterization is taken
                  to a greater extreme in the 1830 melodrama where Quashee’s motivation for fighting
                  Jack is presented as a humble slave’s loyalty to a benevolent owner, which is made
                  explicit at the end of the melodrama’s first act: <quote>QUASHEE. (<emph>with
                        great feeling</emph>) Massa! you have been kind massa to me; and Missee Rosa
                     been kind missee to wife and pickaninny here, and I now show you black man's
                     heart beat warm as white. I will go; and if I meet this Jack, Quashee will kill
                     him, or him kill Quashee, only if poor nigger die, you take care of wife and
                     little Massa Quashee. (Act I, Scene vii)</quote> Quashee puts his life on the
                  line in order to defend his master’s family. All that he asks in return is that
                  his “Massa” will look over his wife and child should he be killed in the conflict.
                  Quashee’s loyalty is rewarded with freedom at the close of the melodrama, giving
                  this final popular adaptation of the legend of Three-Fingered Jack an exaggerated
                  sentimental tone that completely contradicts the historical record as far as
                  scholars have been able to piece it together.</p>
               <p> The stories presented in both the 1800 pantomime and the 1830 melodrama are
                  ridiculous when compared to the reality of Three-Fingered Jack’s defeat at the
                  hands of a Maroon. Although the Maroons in Jamaica were required to work with the
                  colonial government as a condition of their autonomy, this group was in not
                  subservient to government officials or planters in the way that is suggested by
                  the nineteenth-century adaptations of the story. As mentioned earlier, fifteen
                  years after Three-Fingered Jack was killed in Jamaica and five years before he was
                  resurrected through adaptations in England, the Trelawny Town Maroons were
                  involved in a violent eight-month-long insurrection against the colonial
                  government. In 1796, the government, once again unable to control the Maroons,
                  shipped the Trelawny Town Maroons to Nova Scotia. Most of the Maroons involved in
                  this transportation eventually resettled in Sierra Leone in 1800, the same year
                  that a Maroon named Reeder was transformed into a slave named Quashee for the
                  entertainment of English audiences.</p>
               <p>The historical inaccuracies in presentations of the Quashee/Reeder character may
                  be attributed to innocent errors on the part of Earle, Fawcett, and Murray who, as
                  far as we know, did not spend time in Jamaica prior to authoring their
                  adaptations. However, the versions written by Moseley and Burdett are a different
                  case. For example, Moseley’s explanation that Quashee and Sam were “allured by the
                  rewards offered by Governor Dalling . . . and by a resolution which followed it,
                  of the House of Assembly,” implies that the promise of freedom played a part in
                  motivating these men to confront Three-Fingered Jack. This statement contradicts
                  Moseley’s earlier claim that he once met the Maroon who defeated Jack, as well as
                  his explanation that both Quashee and Sam were both of Scots Hall, Maroon Town.
                  Moseley, who spent time in Jamaica prior to publishing his 1799 treatise, would
                  know the difference between a Maroon and a slave. His vague version of the story
                  comes across as rather disingenuous given his otherwise meticulous descriptions of
                  the cultural practices, geography, and economy of Jamaica.</p>
               <p>The same error also seriously undermines the credibility of Burdett’s account.
                  Like Moseley, Burdett explains that Quashee and Sam are from Scots Hall, Maroon
                  Town. Nevertheless, he describes Quashee as “the Slave who, some time before, in a
                  battle, had cut off Jack’s two fingers,” and that Quashee was once an “intimate of
                  Jack’s in his days of slavery” (Burdett 46, 35). These claims are blatantly false.
                  Similar discrepancies can be found in his characterization of Mr. Chapman, who
                  Burdett describes as “an eminent Planter in <emph>Maroon’s Town</emph>,” despite
                  the fact that there were no white planters in any area belonging to the Maroons
                  (Burdett 37). Chapman’s character is likely based on white superintendents,
                  appointed by the Governor, who lived in Maroon settlements according to the terms
                  of the treaties signed between Maroons and the colonial government. Carey Robinson
                  describes the duties of superintendents as chiefly maintaining friendly relations
                  between the government and the Maroons. Superintendents also resolved disputes
                  among Maroons, held court alongside four other Maroons, and reported to the
                  Governor every three months regarding the population, crime, and the condition of
                  the roads of the town where they resided (Robinson, 64-65). Although
                  superintendents were granted significant authority in the officially-sanctioned
                  Maroon communities, they were not slaveholders. There is no basis for Burdett’s
                  Chapman, at least not the way that he is presented to readers. It is hard to
                  believe that a “many years overseer of a Jamaican plantation,” as Burdett claims
                  to be, would make such a critical error, especially in 1800, less than five years
                  after the Second Maroon War, which was widely reported in English
                     publications.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="10">A Royal Proclamation
                     dated August 13, 1795 regarding the Trelawny Town insurrection was reprinted on
                     the front pages of the <title level="j">St. James's Chronicle or the British
                        Evening Post</title> on Tuesday, November 3, 1795 and the <title level="j"
                        >Star</title> on Wednesday, November 4, 1795. Between April 30 and May 2,
                     1798, the Trelawny Town maroons found their way into London newspapers such as
                        <title level="j">Lloyd’s Evening Post</title>, the <title level="j"
                        >Whitehall Evening Post</title>, the <title level="j">Sun</title>, and the
                        <title level="j">True Briton</title> General Walpole (the chief architect of
                     the treaty that ended the conflict) publicly decried the deportation of the
                     Trelawny Town maroons to Nova Scotia. Other contemporaneous accounts include
                     Bryan Edwards, <title level="m">Observations on the disposition, character,
                        manners, and habits of life, of the Maroon negroes of the island of Jamaica;
                        and a detail of the origin, progress, and termination of the late war
                        between those people and the white inhabitants</title> (London: J.
                     Stockdale, 1796), reprinted in the author’s <title level="m">Historical Survey
                        of the Island of Saint Domingo</title> (J. Stockdale, London, 1801),
                     303-360; and R.C. Dallas, <title level="m">The History of the Maroons, from
                        Their Origin to the Establishment of Their Chief Tribe at Sierra
                        Leone</title>, 2 vols., (London: Longman, 1803).</note>
               </p>
               <p>The factual errors in Burdett’s version are particularly disturbing because the
                  author presents his account as a history written to provide contextual information
                  for Fawcett’s popular pantomime. From the onset, the publication is put forth as
                  an educational tool meant to be read as a history. Burdett’s version of the story
                  is billed as a “Narrative of Facts” on which “the Public may depend” (iv).
                  However, as anyone acquainted with the history of Three-Fingered Jack would note,
                  Burdett’s history is largely a fiction, and Paton even describes it as a
                     novel.<note resp="editors" place="foot" n="11">“History” is a loaded term.
                     While it is possible that Burdett was using the term loosely, he also plays up
                     his historical sources and includes references to many actual events as if he
                     is partly depending on his account to be taken as truth. First, the publication
                     is presented as a history, and although many novels (Earle’s included) made
                     similar claims about their narratives’ authenticity, the publication’s lengthy
                     title and its overall presentation suggest that the text is a history, not a
                     fiction. Second, Burdett repeatedly stops the action to cite sources and
                     provide other first-hand accounts that will corroborate his “history.” Finally,
                     several publications published throughout the nineteenth century cited
                     Burdett’s account as a history. For a list of works derived from Burdett’s
                     version see Diana Paton’s “Histories of Three-Fingered Jack: A Bibliography,
                     William Burdett, <title level="m">Life and Exploits of Mansong</title>, and
                     pamphlet accounts deriving from Burdett,” an electronic bibliography available
                     online at www.brycchancarey.com/slavery/tfj/burdett.htm.</note> Burdett draws
                  explicitly upon Bryan Edwards’s <title level="m">History of the West
                     Indies</title> and Moseley’s works; however, these sources are used to paint a
                  detailed picture of obeah as a practice, not Three-Fingered Jack the person. </p>
               <p>The historical inaccuracies in the portions of the text that deal specifically
                  with Three-Fingered Jack are apparent from the onset. The first ten pages of
                  Burdett’s history cover Jack’s life in Africa among warring tribes, his capture by
                  his enemies, his sale to a slave merchant headed for Jamaica. This is a
                  fascinating story; however, to date there is no proof that Three-Fingered Jack was
                  born in Africa. The liberty that Burdett takes with the tale of Jack’s origins is
                  similar to Earle’s novella. However, Earle’s novella is clearly a work of fiction,
                  whereas Burdett’s version of the story floats back and forth between fact and
                  fiction.</p>
               <p>For example, about a third of the way through Burdett’s adaptation of the story,
                  he includes a lengthy digression about obeah and the role that it played in the
                  “formidable insurrection” that occurred in St. Mary Parish in 1760. Here Burdett
                  is drawing on actual events. The insurrection is Tacky’s Rebellion, and Burdett is
                  correct in explaining that the insurrection led to the outlawing of obeah. The
                  historical digression lends Burdett’s account historical credibility. When Burdett
                  returns to Three-Fingered Jack, the author brings up another actual uprising—the
                  attack on Crawford Town on February 10, 1780, which burned the community to the
                  ground. Burdett claims that Three-Fingered Jack was the leader of this organized
                  attack. However, as L. Alan Eyre has explained, “The burning of Crawford Town
                  certainly did take place, but there is no other evidence [aside from
                  nineteenth-century accounts] that Jack took part in it” (12). </p>
               <p>The conflation of these two separate events—the burning of Crawford Town and
                  Three-Fingered Jack’s year-long run—is significant. Making Jack responsible for
                  the attack on Crawford Town is one way that Burdett’s self-described history by a
                  former planter resembles the planter’s journals from Saint Domingue discussed
                  earlier. In this example we see two independent, organized rebellions portrayed as
                  a single event. The result is the appearance that these were orchestrated by a
                  single man and, therefore, not widespread. The two incidents did in fact around
                  the same time and in the same general vicinity; however, conflating the burning of
                  Crawford Town with Three-Fingered Jack’s activities ignores the range of
                  rebellious activity from the island’s dispersed and diverse black populations.</p>
               <p>Despite acknowledging that Crawford Town was completely destroyed by this
                  uprising, the author wraps up the anecdote with a decisive victory for the
                  colonial government. According to Burdett: <quote>The Governor sent five hundred
                     choice Maroons in pursuit of those rebels. They met—they fought; the negroes,
                     as before, rushed upon their guns, but the Maroons firing as they retreated,
                     kept them at bay, and made a great slaughter. –Jack encouraged his men, but
                     could not rouze them to the combat, and they fled in every direction. The next
                     day, the Governor published a pardon to such of the insurgents as would return
                     to their duty; this had the desired effect; for they all returned, except Jack,
                     who was still determined to harass the European settlers. (Burdett 33)</quote>
                  This account is yet another example of the gross discrepancies found in Burdett’s
                  version. Contemporaneous news reports date the disbanding of Jack’s gang in
                  December 1780, ten months after Crawford Town was set ablaze. While it may be true
                  that Governor Dalling issued a pardon for slaves involved in that incident, he did
                  no such thing for Jack’s band of rebels. In fact, by the end of 1780, a reward of
                  £5 was issued for the capture of any of Three-Fingered Jack’s accomplices.
                  Admittedly, this bounty was nowhere near the £300 reward offered for their
                  captain, but the situation was not resolved as easily as Burdett claims in his
                  version of the story.</p>
               <p> Burdett’s account of the Crawford Town incident is also interesting because it is
                  the only appearance of Maroons in the text. Burdett uses the word “Maroon” exactly
                  four times in his account, but this is the only time that he uses the word to
                  describe a group of residents on the island.<note place="foot" resp="editors"
                     n="12">The second use in this edition is a quote from Moseley referring to the
                     “Maroon who killed” Three-Fingered Jack. Burdett insists that Quashee is a
                     slave despite quoting Moseley to the contrary. The other two references are
                     geographic, referring to Scots Hall, Maroon Town.</note> The term is never
                  defined. The Maroons’ cameo is misleading to say the least. They are depicted as
                  foot soldiers in the service of the colonial government when, in truth, their
                  relationship to the plantocracy (as well as with slaves) was much more complicated
                  than Burdett would have his readers assume.<note place="foot" resp="editors"
                     n="13">For example, Paton explains that slaves were often angry with the
                     Maroons for working with the plantocracy to keep them enslaved. However,
                     several sources report that many Maroon settlements often welcomed escaped
                     slaves, completely disregarding their official orders to turn in any slave
                     found. The treaty that ended the Second Maroon War required the Trelawny Town
                     maroons to surrender all runaway slaves that had joined their numbers.</note>
               </p>
               <p>What could have led Burdett to make such an obvious mistake? Paton offers a few
                  suggestions. She explains that “the British understanding of the place of black
                  people in the Caribbean located them firmly as slaves,” and the adaptations
                  produced in England did nothing to challenge those assumptions, presumably because
                  it was deemed unnecessary (or undesirable). “Maroons, as autonomous black
                  characters, even if tied to the plantocratic state through treaties, would have
                  disrupted such a vision” (Paton 52). This argument holds up for all of the English
                  adaptations. Although Paton defends Earle and Burdett for at least acknowledging
                  the presence of the Maroons, the passage cited above clearly shows that Burdett’s
                  account only brings in the Maroon soldiers to move the action along. He never
                  gives a definition, nor explains to his readers that Maroons were free blacks
                  living in independent areas gained through treaties with the colonial government.
                  There is no mention that their military skill was perhaps stronger than the
                  British soldiers on the island, and that the treaties signed were the only way
                  that the colonists could “control” the island. Granted, most English newspapers
                  also omitted these facts, and other sources also misrepresented Maroons (Moseley,
                  for example). However, his inclusion of the Maroons is ultimately so misleading
                  that he may as well have omitted them entirely from the story as the stage
                  adapters did. </p>
               <p>I agree with Paton’s explanation of the misrepresentation or omission of the
                  Maroons in the English adaptations because they challenged conventional categories
                  that many would have been interested in upholding. However, Paton is less
                  convincing in her final explanation for Quashee’s change from Maroon to slave in
                  the nineteenth-century adaptations. “Forgetting the maroon status of Jack’s
                  killers also made sense because the tension it raises was less relevant to British
                  audiences than to Jamaican” (Paton 52). Her reasoning is that Jamaican audiences
                  would have understood the strained relationship between Maroons, slaves, and the
                  colonial government directly caused by the conditions laid out in the treaties
                  signed between the free blacks and the white colonists. These nuances are lost in
                  the English adaptations. <quote>In becoming a British story told about Jamaica,
                     rather than a Jamaican story, Three-Fingered Jack lost sight of the complex
                     relationships and strategic difficulties among different segments of those
                     struggling and negotiating with plantocractic power, substituting a more
                     straightforward vision of social relations in which there were only two sides
                     to choose from: with Jack, or with the social order of slavery and the
                     plantation. (Paton 53) </quote> The English adaptations certainly simplify the
                  story into a black-and-white narrative with no shades of gray; however, the
                  consistent erasure of the Maroons from the English adaptations suggest that there
                  was more to the revisions made to the story than merely a question of its
                  “relevance” to British audiences. The Maroons were certainly relevant to both
                  Jamaicans and Britons, especially only four years after the Second Maroon War.
                  Perhaps it is more accurate to say that affording the Maroons their proper place
                  in the popular history of Three-Fingered Jack would have required Britons to face
                  the reality of black resistance in Jamaica, just as the greatest slave revolution
                  in history was taking place on a neighboring island, and only a few short years
                  after the Maroons were able to sustain an eight-month long conflict against
                  British authorities. </p>
               <p>If Burdett actually spent time in Jamaica as the overseer of a plantation as he
                  claims, then his failure to provide an accurate representation of the Maroons and
                  their continued resistance against the plantocracy is similar to the “objective”
                  accounts of life in the West Indies by French planters outlined by Trouillot at
                  the beginning of this article. If Burdett only claimed to be an authoritative
                  source that his readers could rely on for accurate information, then his version
                  of the history of Three-Fingered Jack was a fiction that followed the same
                  strategies used by actual planters in order to promote a particular agenda. In the
                  case of Burdett’s adaptation of the story, the politics of the piece are clearly
                  laid out in his description of Mr. Chapman, the supposed eminent planter from
                  Maroon Town: <quote>Mr. Chapman was a good man, and very generally beloved; his
                     slaves appeared all happy; and his plantation was esteemed the most thriving in
                     the island. This may very readily be imputed to the willingness with which the
                     negroes laboured for so good a master; and we can assert, from experience, that
                     if every planter in Jamaica were to follow his humane example, it would not
                     only tend to increase their own private wealth, but the good of the country at
                     large; and it is indisputably as easy for a master to gain the love of his
                     slaves as their hatred. (42)</quote> Whether or not Burdett actually spent time
                  as a planter in Jamaica is uncertain; however, his sympathies obviously lie with
                  the “benevolent planter” characterization widely circulated during the decades
                  leading up to abolition.</p>
               <p>Obviously, the story of Three-Fingered Jack was well known and could not be
                  denied. The story had also proved to be quite popular and profitable in England,
                  and Burdett even includes a scene-by-scene description of Fawcett’s pantomime as
                  an appendix to his own publication in order to capitalize on its success.<note
                     place="foot" resp="editors" n="14">A description of Fawcett’s pantomime was
                     included in at least the first five editions of Burdett’s text.</note> However,
                  although it did not make any sense to deny the story of Three-Fingered Jack from a
                  financial perspective, it also did not make much sense to give an accurate history
                  of the rebel slave and his death at the hands of Maroons. To accurately depict the
                  Maroons in the English adaptations of the story of Three-Fingered Jack would have
                  been to admit that the colonial government did not have complete control over
                  black populations in Jamaica. Pushing the Maroons to the margins of this
                  historical event effectively erased a history of black resistance in Jamaica from
                  this popular story at precisely the time that the most successful slave revolution
                  in the Western Hemisphere was at its peak.</p>
               <p>The Haitian Revolution that produced “unthinkable” moments in prose coincided with
                  both the Second Maroon War in Jamaica and the appearance of four of the five
                  English adaptations of the story of Three-Fingered Jack. The fact that the
                  adaptations by Moseley, Earle, Fawcett, and Burdett significantly downplay the
                  real possibility of revolution and resistance from Jamaica’s black populations
                  demonstrates that Trouillot’s analysis of documents produced about the revolution
                  in Saint Domingue may be easily applied to English representations of Jamaica.
                  However, the extent to which they reveal British anxieties about the spread of
                  revolution to their own colonies is unclear, mostly because of the military’s
                  strong presence in the region. The end of Fawcett’s 1800 pantomime—where all
                  characters including the chorus of slaves sing “God Save the King”—certainly
                  presented English audiences with a confident image of the island’s stability.</p>
               <p>All of the nineteenth-century adaptations of the story of Three-Fingered Jack fail
                  to acknowledge the possibility of a massive slave rebellion inherent in both the
                  historical event they were adapting and the more immediate examples of resistance
                  and revolution taking place in the West Indies at the turn of the nineteenth
                  century. The adaptations of the story of Three-Fingered Jack are especially useful
                  in showing how nineteenth-century English accounts changed the politics behind the
                  events that transpired in Jamaica in the late eighteenth century. Collectively,
                  the adaptations demonstrate how an instance of collective rebellion could be
                  sensationalized to the point of being rendered politically insignificant. As such,
                  the popular history of Three-Fingered Jack should be read as part of a broader
                  history of misrepresenting black resistance and independence in the Caribbean. The
                  nineteenth-century adaptations of the story show that even though the history of
                  black resistance and independence was not wholly “unthinkable,” it was
                  nevertheless an unfolding history that these writers preferred not to think about.
                  More importantly, ignoring the possible tensions in Jamaica was a luxury only
                  afforded by a strong British military presence on the island. The end result was
                  that the story of Three-Fingered Jack, just like many stories of the West Indies,
                  allowed English audiences to imagine Jamaica as a colony in close proximity to
                  Saint Domingue, but closed from its revolutionary influence.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>
               <listBibl>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Aravamudan, Srinivas</author>
                        <title level="a">Introduction</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Obi; or, The History of Three-Fingered Jack</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Srinivas Aravamudan</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Peterborough, Ontario</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Broadview</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">7-52</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Burdett, William</author>
                        <title level="m">Life and Exploits of Mansong, Commonly Called
                           Three-Finger’d Jack, the Terror of Jamaica in the Years 1780 &amp; 1781:
                           With a Particular Account of the Obi</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Sommers Town</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>A. Neil</publisher>
                           <date>1800</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Campbell, Mavis C</author>
                        <title level="m">The Maroons of Jamaica, 1655-1796: A History of Resistance,
                           Collaboration &amp; Betrayal</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Granby, Mass</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Bergin &amp; Garvey</publisher>
                           <date>1988</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Cox, Jeffrey N</author>
                        <title level="a"><ref target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/praxis/obi/cox/cox.html"
                              >Theatrical Forms, Ideological Conflicts, and the Staging of <title
                                 level="m">Obi</title></ref></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Romantic Circles Praxis Series</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Charles Rzepka</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <date type="access">August 10, 2009</date>
                           <biblScope type="issue"><title level="m">Obi</title></biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Dallas, R.C</author>
                        <title level="m">The History of the Maroons, from Their Origin to the
                           Establishment of Their Chief Tribe at Sierra Leone</title>
                        <edition>Vol. 2</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Longman</publisher>
                           <date>1803</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Earle, William, Jr</author>
                        <title level="m">Obi: Or, the History of Three-Fingered Jack</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Srinivas Aravamudan</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Peterborough, Ontario</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Broadview</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>L. Alan Eyre</author>
                        <title>Jack Mansong: Bloodshed or Brotherhood</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Jamaica Journal </title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">7.2</biblScope>
                           <date>(1973)</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">9-14</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Geggus, David</author>
                        <title level="a">The Enigma of Jamaica in the 1790s: New Light on the Causes
                           of Slave Rebellions</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The William and Mary Quarterly</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">44.2</biblScope>
                           <date>(April 1987)</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">274-299</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Hoskins, Robert</author>
                        <title level="a"><ref
                              target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/praxis/obi/hoskins/hoskins.html">Savage
                              Boundaries: Reading Samuel Arnold's Score</ref></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Romantic Circles Praxis Series</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Charles Rzepka</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <date type="access">August 11, 2009</date>
                           <biblScope type="issue"><title level="m">Obi</title></biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>O’Rourke, James</author>
                        <title level="a">The Revision of <title level="m">Obi</title>;
                              <emph>or</emph>, <title level="m">Three-Fingered Jack</title> and the
                           Jacobin Repudiation of Sentimentality</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Nineteenth-Century Contexts</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">28.4</biblScope>
                           <date>(2006)</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">285-303</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Paton, Diana</author>
                        <title level="a">The Afterlives of Three-Fingered Jack</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Slavery and the Cultures of Abolition: Essays Marking the
                           Bicentennial of the British Abolition Act of 1807</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Brycchan Carey</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Peter Kitson</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Woodbridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Boydell and Brewer</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Richardson, Alan</author>
                        <title level="a">Romantic Voodoo: Obeah and British Culture,
                           1797-1807</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Studies in Romanticism</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">32</biblScope>
                           <date>(1993)</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">3-28</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Robinson, Carey</author>
                        <title level="m">The Fighting Maroons of Jamaica</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Kingston</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>William Collins and Sangster</publisher>
                           <date>1969</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Trouillot, Michel-Rolph</author>
                        <title level="a">From Planter's Journals to Academia: The Haitian Revolution
                           as Unthinkable History</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Journal of Caribbean History</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">25</biblScope>
                           <date>(1991)</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">81-99</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
