<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Circulations: Romanticism and the Black Atlantic</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">Jean-Jacques Dessalines: Demon, Demigod, and Everything in
               Between</title>
            <author>
               <name>Lindsay J. Twa</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">Paul Youngquist</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <editor role="editor">Frances Botkin</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.twa</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Jean-Jacques Dessalines: Demon, Demigod, and
                     Everything in Between</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Linday J.</forename>
                        <surname>Twa</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Circulations:</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#226;&#8364;&#339;,"
                  for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
            <keywords scheme="http://www.rc.umd.edu/#tags">
               <list>
                  <item>Popular representations of Jean-Jacques Dessalines, a Haitian Revolutionary general and Haiti’s first head of state, have shaped his legacy for various political, creative, and ritualistic purposes.  While most factions have presented Dessalines as either completely demonic or virtuously heroic, only Haiti’s religion of Vodou recognizes and actually celebrates his many contradictions.
                  </item>
                  <item>Dessalines</item>
                  <item>Haiti</item>
                  <item>Vodou</item>
                  <item>representation</item>
                  <item>art</item>
                  <item>revolution</item>
                  <item>Brown</item>
                  <item>St. John</item>
                  <item>Easton</item>
                  <item>Matheus</item>
                  <item>Hughes</item>
                  <item>Still</item>
                  <item>Barthe</item>
                  <item>Troubled Island</item>
                  <item>Ogou</item>
                  <item>Desalin</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2011-03-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head><title level="a">Jean-Jacques Dessalines: Demon, Demigod, and Everything in
                  Between</title></head>
            <byline><docAuthor>Lindsay J. Twa</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>Augustana College, Sioux Falls, SD</affiliation></byline>

            <p>On October 17, Haiti commemorates the assassination of its revolutionary hero and
               first head of state, Jean-Jacques Dessalines (ca. 1758-1806). Haiti dignifies no
               other individual with an official national holiday. Haiti’s <foreign>Père de la
                  Patrie</foreign> was born a slave in what was at that time France’s most valuable
               colony, Saint-Domingue. There are few extant details of his personal life and
               thoughts. In his early life, he seems to have been most noted for his ugliness and
               the extent of his scars. And most accounts agree that within the strictly stratified
               society of Saint-Domingue, Dessalines began life at the absolute bottom: he had the
               infinite misfortune of being the black slave of a black master who brutalized him
               with frequent floggings (Harvey, 21; Heinl, 88). All this would change for
               Dessalines, however, when the enslaved laborers organized and rebelled. </p>
            <p>The complexities and amazing extremes of this slave-to-emperor’s biography cannot be
               separated from the extraordinary times and place in which he lived. It would not be
               hyperbole to proclaim that the Haitian Revolution (1791-1804) was the most signal and
               transformative event in the Age of Revolution. Saint-Domingue’s astounding journey
               from a French sugar colony of nearly a half million enslaved to an independent black
               nation is a convoluted tale. With the slave uprising, the colony erupted into battles
               that fell along economic and racial fault lines. At one point there were as many as
               six factions warring at once, with alliances formed and dissolved in rapid succession
               between the various groups: rich white planters, poorer white laborers, French troops
               trying to restore order in the colony, the opportunistic armies of England and Spain,
               free persons of color (most of mixed-race ancestry, “mulattos”), and the enslaved
               majority with its own internal divisions between African and Creole born. During the
               long years of fighting, most sides at one point courted the rebel blacks with offers
               to arm and then to emancipate. A “born soldier,” Dessalines became known as a
               courageous fighter and a fear- and fealty-inspiring commander in his own right. He
               ascended rapidly through the ranks, becoming a key and indefatigable general under
               the famous Toussaint L’Ouverture, fighting for the royalist Spanish army, then for
               the French republican army fighting against the Spanish and British. In 1799,
               Toussaint entrusted Dessalines with putting down a civil war, which has been
               typically understood as a conflict between mulattos in the south against the blacks,
               who were aided by a U.S. Navy blockade. With the revolts crushed, Toussaint needed to
               stabilize the black armies and eliminate officers and soldiers loyal to his rival,
               the defeated southern leader Andre Rigaud. Dessalines’s reprisals led to many
               executions, to which Toussaint is said to have chastised, “I said to prune the tree,
               not to uproot it.” Some scholars have suggested, however, that Toussaint had ordered
               these killings but had his generals take responsibility in order to keep his hands
               and reputation (relatively) clean (James 236; Dubois 236). Regardless of the veracity
               of the claims of such political underworkings, the war’s events have allowed most
               histories to treat Dessalines as Toussaint’s brutal foil.</p>
            <p>Nonetheless, Dessalines was the soldier that the battlefield and times necessitated,
               a general willing to see plainly what was needed and not hesitating to respond
               accordingly if bluntly. Military expediency, not diplomacy, distinguished Dessalines.
               After Toussaint’s capture and deportation in 1802, Dessalines deemed that the war was
               now a revolution for total independence rather than colonial autonomy with
               emancipation. And he succeeded in completing history’s most successful slave revolt,
               leading the colony to national independence, though Haiti’s subsequent instabilities
               have and continue to call into question how well this dream was achieved. Historian
               Laurent Dubois’s cogent assessment of Toussaint just as easily applies to Dessalines:
               “Though his ultimate inability to construct a multiracial, egalitarian, and
               democratic society in Saint-Domingue might strike us as particularly tragic, given
               his origins, this was a failure he shared with the leaders of every other
               postemancipation society in the Atlantic world” (174).</p>
            <p>History and legend link Dessalines with several signal acts in the birth of this
               first modern independent black nation. In May 1803, he tore the white band from the
               French <foreign>tricolour</foreign>, uniting the blue and red in a new flag. This became
               the symbol of racial unity between blacks and people of color in the face of France’s
               final attempts to retake the colony through a desperate war of extermination (Dubois,
               292-3). The symbol of the flag would later be made concrete in the nation’s 1805
               inaugural constitution, which proclaimed that all citizens would henceforth be
               designated “black.”<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="1">Haiti’s constitution
                  pronounced all Haitians “black,” even the Polish and German mercenaries who had
                  remained on the island after defecting from the French and British armies.
                  Dessalines and his advisors were well aware that Haiti’s precarious independence
                  and the freedom of the self-liberated slaves depended on not allowing the tensions
                  of skin color, with its underlying meaning of caste, to weaken the fledgling
                  nation. David Nicholls has suggested that this may be one of the earliest, if not
                  the first, time that the term “black” was employed ideologically (36). </note>
               Dessalines’s “indigenous army” and a growing coalition of guerilla fighters, aided by
               a yellow fever epidemic, decimated the remaining French forces, who ultimately
               surrendered in December, 1803. On January 1, 1804, Dessalines proclaimed national
               independence and severed colonial ties by replacing the name Saint Domingue with the
               Amer-Indian word Haiti (<foreign>ayti</foreign>). As Dubois has noted, the re-christening
               of the nation with its original Taino name attempted to symbolically disrupt
               centuries of European empire and brutality (299). More ominously, the declaration
               also chided the new black citizens for not fully avenging their dead by allowing some
               French planters to remain on the island. Later that spring, rhetoric moved to action.
               Convinced that the French who had remained in the colony in the hopes of reclaiming
               some of their land and property were already plotting to destabilize the young
               nation, Dessalines ordered their execution. Ignoring the hideous atrocities of
               France’s campaign of extermination at the close of the revolution, popular accounts
               describe Dessalines’s orders as a barbarous aberration. By ordering the remaining
               colonists’ doom, Dessalines sealed for Haiti a lasting reputation as a nightmare
               republic in the eyes of the greater white world. </p>
            <p>Dessalines’s meteoric rise from abject slave to iron-fisted emperor willing to
               preserve his fledgling nation’s freedom by any means necessary seems only fit to
               engender an even more dramatic downfall. Dessalines’s despotism, draconian labor
               policies, and enforced land reform plans soon disillusioned the peasants,
               fair-skinned elite landowners, and military alike. On October 17, 1806, Dessalines’s
               soldiers ambushed their leader and rendered his body to pieces. Legends state that
               the madwoman Défilée, possibly Dessalines’s spurned lover and a sutler to his troops,
               gathered, buried, and guarded the emperor’s remains in a final act of restorative
               devotion. </p>
            <p>At his death, Dessalines was both torn asunder and repaired. His complex legacy
               suffered a similar fate. Over two centuries of Haitian, European and U.S. American
               popular representations of Dessalines reconstruct this leader, though often by
               eliminating his contradictions, thus rendering his complex legacy piecemeal. Haiti’s
               revolutionary heroes, especially the black triumvirate of Toussaint L'Ouverture,
               Henri Christophe and Jean-Jacques Dessalines, are important not only in political
               histories but also cultural storytelling. And not surprisingly, their biographical
               narratives are often conflicting and depend greatly on who is enacting the telling.
               In this essay, I will examine some of the many ways that popular representations of
               Dessalines have shaped his legacy—politically, creatively and ritualistically. I will
               begin with an overview of representations of the demonic Dessalines, which continued
               into the twentieth century, particularly during the U.S. Occupation of Haiti. Next, I
               will outline how African-American writers in particular have recovered Dessalines as
               a dramatic and powerful black hero, though one unburdened from his more extreme
               actions. I will conclude my discussion with the Haitian folk religion of Vodou, which
               is one of the few spaces that recognizes and celebrates the contradictory nature of
               this mercurial figure. </p>
            <p>Early Haitian histories with accounts of Dessalines largely do not appear until
               around the mid-nineteenth century, during the waning years of the Revolutionary
               generation and a growing economic divide that tended to fall along color
               distinctions. These written accounts were largely put forward by the economically and
               politically powerful educated mulatto elite who, perhaps not surprisingly, privileged
               mulatto revolutionary leaders like André Rigaud over black leaders like Dessalines
               and Christophe. Historian David Nicholls gives one of the most comprehensive
               meditations on the divide between racial and color identities within Haitian culture
               and its importance in the construction of its history for political purposes. He
               notes, “Mulatto historians developed a whole legend of the past, according to which
               the real heroes of Haitian independence were the mulatto leaders…. The black leaders
               were portrayed as either wicked or ignorant, and the legend was clearly designed to
               reinforce the subjugation of the masses and the hegemony of the mulatto elite” (11;
               see also 85-101). </p>
            <p>These early Haitian historians who chose to demonize Dessalines found good company
               with an already established and ever increasing body of European and U.S. accounts
               that established the vocabulary and interpretive lens through which this founding
               father and all of Haiti would be judged: African savage, diabolical, inhuman,
               ferocious, base and sanguinary, cruel and brutal, vain and capricious, lustful and
               insatiable (Barskett; Chazotte; Dubroca, Franklin; Harvey). In his literary analysis
               of narratives of the Haitian Revolution, Matt Clavin argues that the ubiquitous
               published histories and biographies that circulated throughout the nineteenth-century
               trans-Atlantic world commodified the Haitian Revolution and its principal actors.
               This flood of writing captured the attention of and titillated a growing boom of
               readers in a competitive literary market. Clavin argues that this was accomplished
               through the use of standard literary techniques, especially the conventions of Gothic
               literature, such as crumbling and exotic scenery, characters seemingly outside the
               bounds of Enlightenment rationality, and, above all, descriptions of “indescribable”
               violent and brutal acts (14-29). Dessalines provided the most direct and titillating
               example of exotic barbarity, the Enlightenment turned on its head but corrected with
               the equally brutal downfall of the black emperor, an example of horrific history that
               far outpaced Gothic fiction and found an eager audience. </p>
            <p>Not surprisingly, these numerous accounts of the Haitian Revolution can also be
               sorted based on the ideologies of their authors: abolitionist or pro-slavery.
               Abolitionist accounts tended to diminish the role of Dessalines in lieu of Toussaint
               L’Ouverture, who in turn was presented as gentle, educated, Christian and
               compromising. Captured and deported before the extremely brutal final revolutionary
               period, where both sides waged a desperate war of extermination, Toussaint as martyr
               could become a positive symbol of black potential and enlightened character. What the
               Abolitionists downplayed, the pro-slavery side sought to exploit: Dessalines’s
               killings, portrayed as the sanguinary finale of blacks’ mercurial treachery, served
               as the shining example of the disasters that awaited sudden and complete
               emancipation. Pierre Etienne [Peter Stephen] Chazotte, who claimed to be one of the
               few eyewitnesses to survive Dessalines’s ordered massacre of French whites in 1804,
               published an English translation of his experiences in 1840, based, as he claimed, on
               notes he had written during the events. His work was meant to discredit what he saw
               as the abolitionist lies particularly propagated by the English. For Chazotte,
               Dessalines was a mindless executioner, a puppet of the English Wilberforce Society
               (41, 48, 69). Over several detailed pages, Chazotte regaled his readers with his
               direct observations of the executions (46-51), adding voyeuristic passages of pathos
               for the killings in the night that he overheard but did not see from his guarded
               residence: “Cries of murder, defiance, despair, rage, and vociferations, intermixed
               with the groans and lamentations of the wounded and the dying, resounded through the
               whole place” (50). Chazotte used his narrative to produce a damning account of the
               English as the main force who spurred the barbaric yet simplistic blacks towards
               violence, while also concluding that this merely shows the imitative nature of all
               persons of African descent and that a modern self-rule was well beyond Haitians’
               capabilities. </p>
            <p>Building upon earlier descriptions like Chazotte’s, the British Minister Resident to
               Haiti Sir Spenser St. John wrote the most popular and widely circulated of
               nineteenth-century descriptions of Haiti’s history and religion, <title level="m"
                  >Haiti or the Black Republic </title>(1884), a work <emph>intended</emph> to prove
               the inferiority of blacks, especially regarding self-government. According to St.
               John, although Dessalines had been a revolutionary hero, what truly “endears his
               memory to the Haytians” was his inaugural act of white massacre (77). St. John notes
               that Dessalines suspected that some of his generals, out of “interest or humanity,”
               may not have carried out his orders fully and took it upon himself to tour the
               country and “pitilessly massacred every French man, woman, or child that fell in his
               way.” St. John continued, “One can imagine the saturnalia of these liberated slaves
               enjoying the luxury of shedding the blood of those in whose presence they had
               formerly trembled; and this without danger; for what resistance could those helpless
               men, women, and children offer to their savage executioners?” (77) (St. John,
               however, did allow that more properly enlightened and educated Haitians were at least
               “in truth utterly ashamed of the conduct and civil administration of their national
               hero” (79).) St. John’s work remained highly influential into the twentieth century,
               becoming one of the most frequently cited sources behind early accounts justifying
               and supporting the U.S. military invasion and occupation of Haiti. Two days after the
               initial U.S. Marine invasion of what would become a nineteen-year occupation
               (1915-1934), the <title level="j">New York Times</title> outlined the Black
               Republic’s “customs” of corruption, despotism, revolution, and assassination, noting
               that this has held true since Haiti’s founding father had ordered the massacre of the
               country’s remaining whites (“Latest Revolution” 8). By invoking the terrifying events
               of 1804, the <title level="j">New York Times</title> assured its readers of the vital
               importance of a strong U.S. military presence in 1915. </p>
            <p>Five years later and in direct response to damning revelations of the U.S.
               Occupation’s financial and military abuses, the December 1920 <title level="j"
                  >National Geographic Magazine </title>defensively presented the benefits of
               occupation in a lavishly illustrated, three-article suite which cited St. John’s
               1880s work frequently. British explorer and photographer Sir Harry Johnston
               contributed one of the articles, presenting a picturesque Haiti greatly improved
               under U.S. guidance. Johnston, however, takes issue with a few lingering details. In
               Port-au-Prince, Johnston describes the great expanse of the Champ de Mars: “In the
               middle of this open space is a preposterously vulgar statue of Dessalines, who is
               regarded as the national hero of Haiti, the people having, with typical ingratitude,
               put on one side the real great man of their history, the remarkable and noble-hearted
               Toussaint L'Ouverture” (“Haiti” 496). The monumental honoring of a monster, rather
               than the more beneficent and accommodating Toussaint, underscored the <title
                  level="j">National Geographic</title>’s presentation of Haitians, particularly the
               peasants who dared to resist their U.S. occupiers, as petulant children who neither
               appreciated what was good for them, nor showed proper gratitude or respect. </p>
            <p>Importantly, the information within this article was gathered during Johnston’s
               six-month trip through the Caribbean and United States in 1908-9, <emph>before</emph>
               the U.S. occupied Haiti. The <title level="j">National Geographic</title>, therefore,
               has shifted the meaning and context of Johnston’s text to coincide with a vision of
               Haiti as newly cleaned-up and “regenerated” by the United States. Originally
               publishing his findings in <title level="j">The Negro in the New World</title>
               (1910), Johnston did note at that time the ugly nature of the statue of Dessalines on
               the Champ de Mars and called for its removal (177). Johnston described the massacring
               Dessalines to be an “abominable monster of cruelty” and an example of “the Negro at
               his very worst” (159). Additionally, he argued, “It is a <emph>disgrace</emph> to
               Haiti that amidst all her monuments, good, bad, and indifferent, none has been raised
               to commemorate the character and the achievements of Toussaint Louverture, whose
               record is one of the greatest hopes for the Negro race” (158-9, italics in original).
               Johnston’s pronouncement mirrors Englishman Hesketh Prichard’s lament of 1900 that
               Haitians have consciously selected the barbarous Dessalines over the noble (and
               probably not “full-blooded negro”) Toussaint for their national hero (279-80). For
               both authors, Toussaint is the exception that proves Dessalines’s bloody rule.
               Moreover, outside observers continued to be incredulous of contemporary Haitians’
               choice of Dessalines as the country’s highest honored national hero, a sure
               indication of the faulty and incompetent progress of the black nation. </p>
            <p>What these outside observers failed to acknowledge, however, was that the honoring of
               Dessalines had and continued to be rigorously deliberated by the Haitian elite. The
               beginnings of the official recovery of Dessalines began in the 1840s. As the
               revolutionary generation passed away, Dessalines’s legacy was rehabilitated enough to
               allow for a modest grave marker, and an even more modest pension for his aging widow.
               In 1861, Haitian newspapers heatedly debated a proposal for the creation of a
               monument to Dessalines. As historian David Nicholls has pointed out, Haitians chose
               sides in this “acute controversy” based on political and racial allegiances; blacks
               and those espousing a <foreign>noiriste</foreign> ideology supported the creation of the
               monument, while most mulattoes opposed it. The few supportive mulattoes carefully
               advocated honoring Dessalines the “liberator,” not Dessalines the “despot” (86). Not
               surprisingly, French diplomats in Haiti actively campaigned against a monument in
               honor of one who had killed so many French citizens. No major monument resulted from
               this debate. Perhaps more fitting, Haiti had a gunboat named after Dessalines long
               before any memorial.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="2">In the fall of 1883,
                  President Salomon acquired the gunboat <emph>Dessalines</emph>. Its namesake would
                  have approved that its first major expedition was to run down the ship of the
                  president’s rebelling opponent. Dessalines, however, surely would have disapproved
                  of the fact that an American commanded the boat (Heinl 270).</note> Full and
               official state-sponsored recovery of Dessalines as the liberator of the Haitian
               people waited until the 1890s with President Florvil Hyppolite (1889-96), who had a
                  <emph>French</emph>-made marble mausoleum erected, and more importantly,
               rhetorically linked himself to the revolutionary hero to strengthen his own political
               agendas (Brutus 246-65). Nord Alexis, president during the 1904 centennial, completed
               the recovery of Dessalines’s patriotic legacy by unveiling the national anthem, “La
               Dessalinienne,” and commissioning the leading Haitian sculptor of the day, Normil
               Charles, to create the Champ de Mars monument. </p>
            <p>Dessalines’s statue and rehabilitated legacy continued to prove malleable. Posed high
               on a pedestal, Johnston’s photograph (c. 1908-9) shows Dessalines stepping stiffly
               forward and holding aloft a saber in his right hand, and a scabbard in the left,
               which Johnston identified as an excessive second sword (“Haiti” 496) [fig. 1].
               Dessalines braces a painted metal national flag permanently unfurled with the
               national motto, “Liberty or Death!” and “To die rather than be under the domination
               of Power.”<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="3">Dessalines, here, does not present
                  the flag that flew under his reign. While he is credited with first creating the
                  blue and red national flag, with its vertical bands from the removal of the white
                  from the French flag at a ceremony at Arcahaie on 14 May 1803, Dessalines changed
                  the blue to black soon after independence. These early flags also included Haiti’s
                  national emblem, the palm tree surmounted by a Phrygian cap, with flags and
                  cannons at its base. Alexandre Pétion, Haiti’s first mulatto leader, returned the
                  black band to blue, though switched the bands to a horizontal orientation, which
                  is what is used for this 1904 statue. Extreme <foreign>noiriste</foreign> François
                  Duvalier changed the blue back to black in 1966, with the blue returning after the
                  fall of the Duvalier regime in 1986 (Heinl 109; Nicholls, 234-5). </note> Later
               1920s photographs, taken at the height of the U.S. occupation, show the isolated
               Dessalines still dominating the great public space, but now with his painted flag
               removed. Perhaps the call to liberty at all cost did not sit comfortably
               with a foreign occupier and accommodating administration working to put down
               insurgency and dissent. Charles’s statue would soon succumb to a similar fate.
               Criticized for its “cold mask” which did not resemble the likeness more popularly
               accepted by this time as the emperor’s, the Haitian government later removed the 1904
               Dessalines to the town hall of Gonaives (Brutus, II, 261). </p>
            <p>While nearly every history outlines Dessalines’s fierce and brutal character, there
               are very few contemporary descriptions of what he physically looked like. ‘A short,
               stout Black,’ seems to be the most thorough description left and no likenesses taken
               from life have been authenticated (Heinl 126). Rather, a range of likenesses from
               nineteenth-century engravings abound, with a few becoming privileged, and one
               accepted as a correct representation by state-sponsored commissions in the twentieth
               century: the portrait of Dessalines from the series of paintings displayed in the
               national palace, <title level="s">Heros de l’independence d’Haiti</title> (1804-1806)
               (fig. 2). Several Haitian administrations promoted this particular likeness of
               Dessalines and had it copied into medallions, engravings, and even a 1949
               commemorative postage stamp by famed Haitian designer Louis Vergniaud Pierre-Noël. A
               new Dessalines monument now dominates Port-au-Prince’s Champ de Mars, this one
               created by famed African-American sculptor Richmond Barthé and installed in 1953. In
               this commission, Barthé worked directly from a photograph of the national palace
                  painting.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="4">Richmond Barthé’s personal papers
                  held at Amistad Research Center, Tulane University, New Orleans, still include the
                  photograph of the Dessalines portrait painting, and his preliminary sketches from
                  this copy. The Haitian government may have provided Barthé with a copy of the
                  painting from which to work. During this period, the national Haitian tourist
                  bureau circulated copies of this series of paintings as part of their advertising
                  brochures, with the entire series printed in a special issue on Haitian culture
                  and history: “Tricinquantenaire de l’Indépendance d’Haïti,” <title level="j"
                     >Formes et Couleurs </title>12.1 (1954).</note> All of these elite- and
               state-sanctioned images present a heroic black figure arrested in his grandeur, and
               not as a mercurial fighter and contested leader.</p>
            <p>Perceptions of Dessalines’s character proved even more malleable than his image.
               Dessalines expected and embraced the fact that the greater world would find him
               horrific and blood thirsty. The January 1, 1804 declaration of independence was
               proclaimed before a crowd at Gonaïves. It is clear, however, that Dessalines and his
               secretary, an educated officer of color named Louis Félix Boisrond-Tonnerre who
               authored and read the proclamation on Dessalines’s behalf, understood the
               proclamation’s audience to include not only the new citizens of Haiti, but also the
               greater international community. The declaration rebukes Haiti’s new black citizens
               for failing to avenge their dead by allowing some French to still remain in the
               country. The elimination of these French would serve not only as the final step in
               completing the war of emancipation, it would also ensure that no remaining foreigner
               would continue to plot “to trouble and divide us” (Dubois and Garrigus 189). More
               importantly, Dessalines/Boisrond-Tonnerre prods that a final act of massacre would
               send the most dramatic message possible to dissuade France and any other power that
               this fledgling nation could ever be reclaimed for slavery: <quote>…know that you have
                  done nothing if you do not give the nations a terrible, but just example of the
                  vengeance that must be wrought by a people proud to have recovered its liberty and
                  jealous to maintain it. Let us frighten all those who would dare try to take it
                  from us again; let us begin with the French. Let them tremble when they approach
                  our coast, if not from the memory of those cruelties they perpetrated here, then
                  from the terrible resolution that we will have made to put to death anyone born
                  French whose profane foot soils the land of liberty (Dubois and Garrigus
                     189).<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="5">Dessalines’s declaration, however,
                     quickly follows this provocation of France and greater transatlantic powers
                     with ameliorating lines for the nations within Haiti’s immediate region: “Let
                     us ensure, however, that a missionary spirit does not destroy our work; let us
                     allow our neighbors to breathe in peace; may they live quietly under the laws
                     that they have made for themselves, and let us not, as revolutionary
                     firebrands, declare ourselves the lawgivers of the Caribbean, nor let our glory
                     consist in troubling the peace of the neighboring islands. Unlike that which we
                     inhabit, theirs has not been drenched in the innocent blood of its inhabitants;
                     they have no vengeance to claim from the authority that protects them” (Dubois
                     and Garrigus 190).</note>
               </quote> Importantly, in the declaration’s closing lines, Dessalines also claimed his
               own legacy: “Recall that my name horrifies all those who are slavers, and that
               tyrants and despots can only bring themselves to utter it when they curse the day I
               was born…” (Arthur and Dash 44). In April 1804, following the actual killings of the
               remaining French planters, Dessalines proclaimed: <quote>‘We have rendered to these
                  true cannibals, war for war, crime for crime, outrage for outrage. Yes, I have
                  saved my country; I have avenged America. The avowal I make in the face of earth
                  and heaven, constitutes my pride and my glory. Of what consequence to me is the
                  opinion which contemporary and future generations will pronounce upon my conduct?
                  I have performed my duty; I enjoy my own approbation: for me that is sufficient’
                  (Barskett 183). </quote> Dessalines carefully posited his acts against a history
               of the French slave system notorious for its excessive cruelties, tortures and rapes,
               and he orchestrated the executions to be a signal to the greater world of an
               unrepentant blackness that grounded the newly created Haitian identity. </p>
            <p>Amazingly, despite his extreme rhetoric and actions, Dessalines’s character lent
               itself not only to disparaging accounts, but also dramatic and even morally uplifting
               representations. Since there are few records of Dessalines’s own accounting of his
               thoughts and actions, his life has been used as a blank canvas for more romantic
               inscriptions. Indeed, given how he proclaimed his own legacy, Dessalines probably
               would have been shocked by the numerous representations that attempt to sanitize his
               legacy, especially those examples put forth by fellow blacks. Several prominent
               African-American writers have attempted to recover a revolutionary hero without the
               accrued weight of his harsher actions. In 1863, former slave William Wells Brown
               published <title level="m">The Black Man</title>, a collection of biographical
               sketches designed to refute stereotypes of black inferiority. For Brown, the
               courageous Dessalines “was a bold and turbulent spirit, whose barbarous eloquence lay
               in expressive signs rather than in words” (111). Brown, however, does not describe
               Dessalines’s “expressive signs,” stating that enough historians have noted them, but
               without rightly considering the circumstances under which he lived and led. </p>
            <p>Three decades later, African-American publisher and activist William Edgar Easton
               out-distanced Brown’s positive portrayal in his play <title level="m"
                  >Dessalines</title> (1893). In the play, Dessalines awakens from his excessive
               brutality when he rescues his mulatto enemy’s sister, Clarisse, from a voodoo witch
               and then falls in love with her. The fair Clarisse converts Dessalines to
               Christianity and the play ends without even a hint of massacres or political
               despotism. In the play’s preface, Easton openly admits to taking factual liberties in
               creating a play that would highlight the rich possibilities of uplifting racial
               drama. Yet his preface also laments the lack of African Americans writing and staging
               black history, implying the importance of historical fact. Easton believes drama to
               be the perfect medium for teaching both history and moral virtue. He prefers
               ultimately, however, to skew history and reconstitute a sanitized Dessalines in order
               to fulfill the higher purposes of serious moral drama and race pride: “Let the critic
               with a charitable hand separate its [the play’s] history from romance and give the
               author the credit, at least, of seeking, in the way he knows best, to teach the
               truth, that ‘minds are not made captive by slavery’s chains, nor were men’s souls
               made for barter and trade’” (vii). </p>
            <p>Indeed, the debut staging of Easton’s interpretation of Haiti’s history was actually
               about the visibility and control of African-American self-presentation. <title
                  level="m">Dessalines</title>’s debut has been called the “most note worthy
               African-American event” during the 1893 Chicago World’s Columbian Exposition, even
               though it did not actually occur on the fairgrounds or with Exposition sanctioning.
               Rather, it was produced privately at the Chicago Freiberg’s Opera House as a part of
               the African-American protest against the Exposition’s exclusion of African Americans
               in its planning and the rejection of many proposals for exhibits to display the
               accomplishments of African Americans (Hill and Hatch 88-9, 138-9). Dessalines,
               therefore, needed first and foremost to represent black heroic accomplishment, and
               not the gray zone of a complex and violent historical reality. </p>
            <p>Prominent twentieth-century African-American writers continued Easton’s belief in
               racial uplift through black historical drama, with Haiti frequently providing
               exciting material and inspiring heroic figures. And like Easton before them, those
               who staged their work around Dessalines as their lead character did so by ignoring
               the more contradictory and violent aspects of his actions. For example, writer and
               linguist John Matheus wrote the libretto to the opera <title level="m">Ouanga: a
                  Haitian Opera in Three Acts</title> (c.1929; copyrighted 1938) centered on
               Dessalines’s 1804-1806 rule, but omitted his ordered killings. Rather, <title
                  level="m">Ouanga</title> portrays the emperor’s greatest crimes as forsaking his
               true love Défilée and attempting to outlaw voodoo, with both directly causing his
               assassination. Matheus preferred to have his romantic protagonist in dramatic
               confrontation with voodoo, rather than admit the terrorizing and tyrannical aspects
               of his hero. </p>
            <p>Famed writer Langston Hughes also had an abiding fascination with Haiti, its
               revolutionary history, and the character of Dessalines. In February 1928, Hughes
               began work on an opera on the Haitian Revolution, first sketched as a “singing play”
               entitled <title level="m">Emperor of Haiti</title>. His plot traces the rise and fall
               of a fierce Jean-Jacques Dessalines, whom he envisions as a key leader of the initial
               uprising. He revised his text into a play entitled <title level="m">Drums of
                  Haiti</title>, which was first performed in 1934; he continued to revise (and
               rename) the work, premiering <title level="m">Troubled Island</title> in 1936. It was
               this later version that would be finally turned into an opera with music by William
               Grant Still, debuting in 1949 (Hughes Papers, boxes 536, 539; see also Rampersad
               165-6, 175-9). Like <title level="m">Ouanga</title>, Hughes’s play and opera
               dramatize the life and downfall of Jean-Jacques Dessalines, and provide another
               example of a sanitized Dessalines as main character. <title level="m">Troubled
                  Island</title> begins on the eve of the revolutionary uprising in 1791. Act II
               then jumps forward over two decades to the end of Emperor Dessalines’s reign, thus
               omitting both the bloody fight for independence and Dessalines’s ordered massacres.
               While alluding to Dessalines’s military exploits, the heart of the later acts present
               Dessalines’s failures as a statesman, his rejection of the country’s African roots in
               voodoo, and his assassination as a betrayal by his treacherous mulatto assistants and
               consort. </p>
            <p>In one final example of Dessalines’s extreme sanitization at the hands of
               African-American writers, Helen Webb Harris composed <title level="m">Genifrede: The
                  Daughter of L’Ouverture, a Play in One Act</title> (1923) as part of a drama class
               at Howard University. In her example, Harris centers the play around the iron-will of
               Toussaint L'Ouverture, but presents Dessalines as a moderator to Toussaint’s extreme
               sense of justice, which included executing his daughter’s fiancé. All of these
               productions present the Haitian revolutionary as a figure of heroic black
               masculinity, reflecting an African-American focus on representational figures to
               instill race pride. </p>
            <p>These African-American writers portrayed Dessalines as a simplified and somewhat
               thuggish saint. Interestingly, within the Haitian folk religion of Vodou, Dessalines
               actually has become a saint. Vodou is a highly syncretic, African-derived, complex
               New World religion that has vibrantly adapted (and continues to adapt) to the needs
               and struggles of Haitians. Like Dessalines, this much maligned religion has been
               distilled in the popular imagination outside of Haiti in the form of a highly
               circumscribed stereotype. The religion is known more popularly by the moniker
               “voodoo”; histories, sensationalized travelogues, and, especially, horror films
               present “voodoo” as a demonic, brutal, and blood- and zombie-driven cult of death and
               debauchery. While many Haitians believe in a single supreme God, they also believe in
               a pantheon of intermediary spirit-saints, or <foreign>lwas</foreign>, who actually
               intercede within their lives through personal encounter. Vodou’s dominant spirit and
               warrior is Ogou. Within the Vodou pantheon, Ogou splits into multiple manifestations,
               creating a family of spirits tied to war and, since the army is never far removed
               from government in Haiti, politics and social power. Vodou’s adaptability means that
               new historical events and leaders can be incorporated into this divine army. The
               historic Jean-Jacques Dessalines, like most elite blacks and mulattos of his era,
               probably opposed and even worked to suppress Vodou (Nicholls 170). In death, however,
               Haitian adherents incorporated him into the Vodou pantheon as Ogou Desalin. Like his
               historical counterpart, Ogou Desalin is a powerful guardian and fierce conqueror. He
               is also vainglorious with a notorious sexual appetite, a penchant for blind rage, and
               an equivocal nature (Dayan 139; Largey 328). </p>
            <p>Vodou rituals involve what religious scholar Karen McCarthy Brown has termed
               “performance-possession”: the dramatic moment when a Vodou spirit possesses (or
               mounts) an adherent (<title level="m">Mama Lola </title>6). Through the possessed
               individual, the <foreign>lwa</foreign> bodily displays his personality, and interacts with
               those present at the ceremony. His physical likeness shifts, therefore, with each
               person possessed, transcending the visual representations of Dessalines codified by
               the state’s various commemorative and political projects. In Haiti’s highly visual
               and oral culture, such ritual performances become bodily manifestations where past
               histories meet present problems, helping to create meaning and solutions. </p>
            <p>All manifestations of Ogou poignantly model the constructive and destructive uses of
               power. Brown has described the ritual dance performed by those possessed by Ogou.
               First, Ogou takes a ritual sword and wields it against an invisible enemy. Before
               long, however, his aggressive swipes and jabs become directed towards people present
               at the ceremony. Finally, Ogou turns the sword upon himself. Ogou performs the paradox
               at the center of Haitian military and political history, where leaders heralded as
               heroes have time and again turned upon their own people while also instigating their
               own destruction (<title level="m">Mama Lola</title> 95-6). Dessalines proclaimed
               himself the avenger of the former slaves, yet he considered his people ungrateful and
               unruly, and used his standing army to enforce draconian labor policies. In
               establishing a national identity centered on blackness and land ownership, Dessalines
               also threatened the fairer-skinned elite, contributing to his assassination. </p>
            <p>Historian Joan Dayan has provided one of the most extensive analyses of Dessalines’s
               leap from revolutionary leader to <foreign>lwa</foreign>. Kreyol folk and ritualistic
               songs, which may be as old as the revolutionary era, focus on the liberty that
               Dessalines brings, yet through a body that is both powerful and dismembered, heroic
               and corrupt, living and dead. The songs’ Kreyol words embody multiple meanings and
               necessarily duplicitous, interpretations. Likewise, in Vodou ritual, when Ogou
               possesses an adherent and makes himself manifest to worshippers, his ritualistic
               actions and pronouncements are also duplicitous, revealing both his multiple nature
               and the contradictions inherent within power structures: ritualistic actions show
               both devotion and vengeance, efficacy and blind rage railing against insurmountable
               odds (Dayan 31). As we have seen, and much to the chagrin of nineteenth- and
               twentieth-century outside observers, many Haitians claim Dessalines as their most
               revered national hero despite his dramatic faults. Perhaps this is because Dessalines
               goes beyond his fighting for and founding of independence; now as Ogou Desalin, he
               both resists oppression and displays how power can corrupt. This is a prescient model
               for understanding the personal and political injustices found within the adherent’s
               contemporary world. </p>
            <p>Within Vodou, remembered histories possess the power to shape and interact with
               contemporary problems. The worship of Ogou Desalin performs an important
               revolutionary history and embodies contemporary relationships with power structures. Ogou
               Desalin shows that liberation is never complete, while teaching that the most
               powerful can be the most vulnerable and vice versa. Ogou Desalin also shows that
               power in general is always corruptible, and that the dispossessed must always be wary
               of whom they call hero. Rendered to pieces at his death, Dessalines’s spirit and
               legacy has only grown more powerful as representations continuously reconstitute,
               rework and repair this mercurial hero. Most popular representations circumscribe him
               to the space of either demon or saint. Vodou, however, provides a model that accepts
               and even finds necessary Dessalines’s equivocal nature. </p>
            <p>*Acknowledgments: Initial research that led to this article was made possible through
               the support of the Henry Luce Foundation/American Council of Learned Societies’
               Doctoral Dissertation Fellowship in American Art, 2004-2005 and was presented at the
               College Art Association Annual Conference in 2006. Research for its completion was
               enabled by support from the Augustana Research and Artist Fund of Augustana College,
               Sioux Falls, SD, and an A. Bartlett Giamatti Fellowship from the Beinecke Rare Books
               and Manuscript Library at Yale University.</p>
          
         <div type="citations">
            <head>Works cited</head>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <editor role="editor">Arthur, Charles</editor>
                     <editor role="editor">Michael Dash</editor>
                     <title level="m">A Haiti Anthology: Libète</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Latin American Bureau</publisher>
                        <date>1999</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Barskett, James</author>
                     <title level="m">History of the Island of St. Domingo: from Its First Discovery
                        by Columbus to the Present Period</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Frank Cass</publisher>
                        <date>1818</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Brown, Karen McCarthy</author>
                     <title level="m">Mama Lola: A Vodou Priestess in Brooklyn</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>University of California</publisher>
                        <date>1991</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author>---</author>
                     <title level="a">Systematic Remembering, Systematic Forgetting: Ogou in
                        Haiti</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="m">Africa's Ogun: Old World and New</title>
                     <editor role="editor">Sandra Barnes</editor>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Bloomington</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Indiana University Press</publisher>
                        <date>1989</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">75</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">78</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Brown, William Wells</author>
                     <title level="m">The Black Man: His Antecedents, His Genius, and His
                        Achievements</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>James Redpath</publisher>
                        <date>1863</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
                  <relatedItem type="otherEdition">
                     <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                           <imprint>
                              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                              <publisher>Kraus Reprint Co.</publisher>
                              <date>1969</date>
                           </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                     </biblStruct>
                  </relatedItem>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Brutus, Timoleon</author>
                     <title level="m">L’Homme D’Airain: etude monographique sur Jean-Jacques
                        Dessalines fondateur de la nation haitienne; histoire de la vie d’un esclave
                        devenu empereur jusqu’a sa mort, le 17 Octobre 1806</title>
                     <edition>2 Vols</edition>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Port-au-Prince</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Imprimerie de l’Etat</publisher>
                        <date>1947</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Chazotte, Peter Stephen [Pierre Etienne]</author>
                     <title level="m">Historical Sketches of the Revolutions, and the foreign and
                        Civil Wars in the Island of St. Domingo, with a Narrative of the Entire
                        Massacre of the White Population of the Island</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>WM. Applegate, 1840</publisher>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author>Clavin, Matt</author>
                     <title level="a">Race, Rebellion, and the Gothic: Inventing the Haitian
                        Revolution</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">Early American Studies</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope type="date">(Spring 2007)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">1-29</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Franklin, James</author>
                     <title level="m">The Present State of Hayti</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>John Murray</publisher>
                        <date>1828</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
                  <relatedItem type="otherEdition">
                     <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                           <imprint>
                              <pubPlace>Westport</pubPlace>
                              <publisher>Negro Universities Press</publisher>
                              <date>1970</date>
                           </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                     </biblStruct>
                  </relatedItem>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Dayan, Joan</author>
                     <title level="m">Haiti, History and the Gods</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>University of California Press</publisher>
                        <date>1995</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Dubois, Laurent</author>
                     <title level="m">Avengers of the New World: The Story of the Haitian Revolution </title>
                     <imprint>
                        <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>2005</pubPlace>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Dubois, Laurent</author>
                     <author>John Garrigus</author>
                     <title level="m">Slave Revolution in the Caribbean 1789-1804: A Brief History
                        with Documents</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Bedford/St. Martin’s</publisher>
                        <date>2006</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Dubroca, Louis</author>
                     <title level="m">Vida de J. J. Dessalines, gefe de los negros de Santo Domingo. </title>
                     <editor role="translator">D. M. G. C.</editor>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Mexico</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Zuniga y Ontiveros</publisher>
                        <date>1806</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Easton, William Edgar</author>
                     <title level="m">Dessalines: A Dramatic Tale (A Single Chapter From Haiti’s
                        History)</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <publisher>J. W. Burson-Company, Publishers</publisher>
                        <date>1893</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Harvey, W. W</author>
                     <title level="m">Sketches of Hayti: from the Expulsion of the French to the
                        Death of Christophe</title>
                     <edition>1827</edition>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Frank Cass &amp; Co. Ltd.</publisher>
                        <date>1971</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Heinl, Robert</author>
                     <author>Nancy Gordon Heinl</author>
                     <title level="m">Written in Blood: The Story of the Haitian People,
                        1492-1971</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Houghton Mifflin</publisher>
                        <date>1978</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
                  <relatedItem type="otherEdition">
                     <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                           <edition>2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed</edition>
                           <editor role="reviser">rev by Michael Heinl</editor>
                           <imprint>
                              <pubPlace>Lanham</pubPlace>
                              <publisher>University Press of America</publisher>
                              <date>1996</date>
                           </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                     </biblStruct>
                  </relatedItem>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Hill, Errol G.</author>
                     <author>James Hatch</author>
                     <title level="m">A History of African American Theatre</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                        <date>2003</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author>Hughes, Langston</author>
                     <title level="m">Emperor of Haiti</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="m">Black Heroes: Seven Plays</title>
                     <editor role="editor">Errol Hill</editor>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Applause Theatre Book Publishers</publisher>
                        <date>1989</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <bibl>Langston Hughes Papers. James Weldon Johnson Collection in the Yale Collection
                  of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale
                  University.</bibl>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>James, C.L.R</author>
                     <title level="m">The Black Jacobins: Toussaint L'Ouverture and the San Domingo
                        Revolution</title>
                     <edition>1938</edition>
                     <edition>Second Edition</edition>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Vintage Books</publisher>
                        <date>1989</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author>Johnston, Harry</author>
                     <title level="a">Haiti, the Home of Twin Republics</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">National Geographic</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol">38.6</biblScope>
                        <date>(December, 1920)</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">483-496</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>---</author>
                     <title level="m">The Negro in the New World</title>
                     <edition>1910</edition>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Johnson Reprint Corporation</publisher>
                        <date>1969</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author>Largey, Michael</author>
                     <title level="a">Recombinant Mythology and the Alchemy of Memory: Occide
                        Jeanty, Ogou, and Jean-Jacques Dessalines in Haiti</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">Journal of American Folklore</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol">118.469</biblScope>
                        <date>(Summer 2005)</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">327-353</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <title level="a">The Latest Revolution in Haiti</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">New York Times</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date>29 July 1915</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">8</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr><author>Matheus, John Frederick</author>
                     <title level="m">Ouanga: a Haitian Opera in Three Acts</title><imprint><distributor>Clarence Cameron
                     White Collection. Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture. New York
                     Public Library</distributor></imprint></monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Nicholls, David</author>
                     <title level="m">From Dessalines to Duvalier: Race, Colour and National
                        Independence in Haiti</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New Brunswick</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Rutgers University Press</publisher>
                        <date>1996</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Prichard, Hesketh</author>
                     <title level="m">Where Black Rules White</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner’s Sons</publisher>
                        <date>1900</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Rampersad, Arnold</author>
                     <title level="m">The Life of Langston Hughes, 1902-1941: I, Too, Sing
                        America</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                        <date>1986</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>St. John, Spenser</author>
                     <title level="m">Hayti or The Black Republic</title>
                     <edition>2nd ed</edition>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Scribner &amp; Welford</publisher>
                        <date>1889</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl></div>
         

         <div><head>List of Images</head>
            <figure n="1">
               <graphic url="../images/1228948u_format.jpg" width="400px"></graphic>
               <figDesc>Normil Charles, <title level="m">The Statue to Dessalines on the Champ de Mars,
               Port-au-Prince</title>, 1904. Photograph by Sir Harry Johnston, c. 1908-09. First
            published in Sir Harry Johnston, <title level="m">The Negro in the New World</title> (London: 1910);
            reprinted unattributed, <title level="m">Statue of Dessalines, Erected 1904</title> in Anonymous,
            <title level="a">Wards of the United States: Notes on What Our Country is Doing for Santo Domingo,
            Nicaragua, and Haiti,</title> <title level="m">National Geographic Magazine </title>30 (August 1916): 173.
                  Photograph available <ref target="holder">through the New York Public Library Schomburg Center for Research
                  in Black Culture</ref></figDesc></figure>
           
            <figure n="2">
               <graphic url="../images/1169858u_format.jpg" width="400px"></graphic>
               <figDesc>Anonymous, <title level="m">General Jean-Jacques Dessalines (1758-1806)</title>, from
            series: <title level="m">Heros de l’independence d’Haiti (1804-1806)</title>, painting in the
            National Palace, Port-au-Prince. Published through Haitian tourist bureau, special
            issue: <title level="a">Tricinquantenaire de l’Indépendance d’Haïti,</title> <title level="m">Formes et Couleurs</title>
            12.1 (1954). W. E. B. Du Bois Collection, Special Collections Fisk University,
            Nashville. Photograph <ref target="holder">available through the New York Public Library Schomburg Center for
            Research in Black Culture</ref></figDesc></figure></div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
