<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">How and Why to Teach the History of Women’s Dramatic
					Writing</title>
				<author>
					<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				</author>
				<editor role='editor'>
					<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Pedagogies Editor</resp>
					<name>Kate Singer</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>commons4.2011.crochunis</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
					Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
						or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
						purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
						use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
						are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
						with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
						permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
						requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
						forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
						conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
						them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
						have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
						Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
						continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
						a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
						use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">How and Why to Teach the History of Women’s
							Dramatic Writing</title>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename>Thomas</forename>
								<surname>Chrochunis</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Teaching Romantic Drama: </title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Pedagogies Commons Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
								Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
							<biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for
						‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
						keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
						such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
						been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
					12pt;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
						on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g18" scheme="#genre"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<date>2011-02-18</date>
				<list>
					<item>revised TEI</item>
					<item>XSLT</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Dave Rettenmaier</name>
				<date>2010-06-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				<date>2009-11-01T15:01:00</date>
				<list>
					<item>Proofed issue in Open Office Format</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">
				<head>
					<title level="a">How and Why to Teach the History of Women’s Dramatic
						Writing</title>
				</head>
				<byline>
					<docAuthor>Thomas C. Crochunis</docAuthor>
					<affiliation>Shippensburg University</affiliation>
				</byline>

				<p>In spring 2007, I taught a special topics course at Shippensburg University with
					the same title as this essay. In the course, I examined with students both the
					dramatic writing of women writers of the British seventeenth through twentieth
					centuries and the meta-historical questions raised by the course’s title. In the
					following remarks, I suggest some of the directions that I tried in the course
					and some of the ideas I would try in the course after seeing how the students
					responded.</p>
				<!--[Layout Note: Ideally, I would like the “How” remarks to exist in a main page list of
            bulleted statements and then click through to open or unfold to the “Why” commentary. I
            like the idea of creating a small amount of hypertextual navigation by the reader.]-->
				<p><hi rend="bold">How:</hi> Tell the students to look for the plays written by
					women. Don’t just hand them to them; tell them that they have to go find one to
					read. Give them a time frame; maybe (or maybe not) suggest particular
					playwrights. Maybe gesture towards a reference source…but don’t hand it to
					them.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Why:</hi> Students may be surprised to find that it might not be
					easy to find a text to read. Much depends on what kind of library they use,
					whether they mind reading text online, how adroit they are in digging into
					online tools to find scanned texts. When I first taught this course in 2007, the
					landscape was quite different online. Then, the Googlebooks phenomenon took off,
					and now there are many, many relevant texts online. But regardless of what
					students find, their various paths to finding texts to read…and what they find
					and choose to read…provide a basis for good discussion about why these texts
					have the status they have, what the history of their publication has been, and
					how the students made their decisions about how to excavate the history.</p>
				<p> In other words, this is one of those cases where professorial expertise can
					productively be withheld for pedagogical purposes.</p>
				<p> The plays found can be returned to a bit later for discussion of their style and
					content. There’s a good chance that “what women wrote about” may be represented
					in interesting patterns by what students will find hidden in plain sight. But
					you might ask them to make some guesses about what women wrote about in the era
					in question and why. If they’re catching on to your game, they may cannily
					resist, but no matter…you can ask them <emph>why</emph> they resist. Why, after
					all, shouldn’t the sample we find be used to determine what the larger
					phenomenon of women’s playwriting consists of? Hey, I thought this was a
					literature class, not social science. </p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">H:</hi> Ask students to look for reviews of plays by women
					playwrights of the era you’re focusing on. Again, like looking for texts, they
					will encounter something of the landscape of available information. Depending on
					whether they go the route of publications or online resources, and depending on
					how they construct their searches, they may run into some frustrations. This
					assignment effectively encourages collaborative work and provides coaching and
					suggestions. Again, the idea is not simply to show them the best repositories of
					information you know. See what they find.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">W:</hi> What students may find when they do this is that the
					double concealment of minimal productions and limited access to review
					information can make it seem that there are few plays by women playwrights of
					certain eras that have been produced. If this is what is found, you might ask
					students why they suppose so little information seems to be available. But if
					they find a few valuable sources, you might follow up by asking them to
					determine what purposes led to the creation of the source. Students might then
					begin to examine assumptions about how history comes to exist as an available
					resource for our use. A first assumption may be that “durability” (aesthetic,
					probably) creates the archive of information. But many of the resources they
					will find likely will exist for other reasons than that they survived and were
					gathered together. In fact, digital materials typically have their own sorts of
					purposes for existing and being maintained, and these can be productively
					examined. Pose the question to students, “How are the purposes of digital
					archives similar to or different from those of material archives?” The question
					might seem to stump them at first, but they can go back to some of what they
					found in their first two experiments, maybe in working groups, and examine the
					materials to see if they can find any clues.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">H:</hi> Show them how women responded to the dramatic writing of
					other women in developing their own dramatic voices.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">W:</hi> Women playwrights understood that the ways predecessor
					women navigated tricky genres, subjects, professional identities, and
					institutions had something to teach them. They may not have assumed that they
					should make the same choices as a woman dramatist who came before, but
					understanding earlier writers alerted Romantic-era playwrights to the
					distinctive gendered landscape they needed to navigate. <name ref="CowleyHannah"
						>Cowley</name> looked back to <name ref="BehnAphra">Behn</name> and
					Centlivre, as did <name ref="InchbaldMrs">Inchbald</name>. Women who wrote
					tragedies and histories—from Burney to <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>
					to Mitford—read widely in the unperformed published tragedies of other
					women.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">H:</hi> Place women’s dramatic writing in the context of men’s
					writing of their era, in similar genres, and for the same theatrical houses and
					actors.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">W:</hi> While women theatre writers may participate in a
					counter-tradition that has its own historical significance apart from their
					public recognition, how women dramatists wrote in relation to the male writers
					of their era provides a crucial lens through which to view women’s choices of
					form, subject, and social process. With men often in control of the business end
					of theatre management in the Romantic era (but not always, consider Jane Scott),
					women’s ways of “writing their way in” can be seen for all its pragmatic or
					self-assertive ingenuity. Some women playwrights—such as <name ref="InchbaldMrs"
						>Inchbald</name>—needed to succeed financially, while others had greater
					freedom to test the limits of male dramatic conventions—<name
						ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>, for instance. But it is always worth
					considering how women dramatists position themselves in relation to men’s
					dramatic writing of their era. Doing so helps to estrange the aesthetic of the
					male tradition, to contextualize it historically, and at the same time to see
					the strategic dimension of women’s dramatic aesthetics.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">H:</hi> Look at how women dramatists and actresses contributed to
					each other’s aesthetic and professional development.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">W:</hi> In some ways, women dramatists and actresses were two
					aesthetic “species” that constituted the two aspects of the theatrical female of
					the Romantic era. While the dramatist could lay some claim to literary
					authority, the actress could sustain a kind of public persona through careful
					reputation management, self-marketing, and selection of repertoire. But, of
					course, the two different female theatrical roles also had ways of teaching each
					other. Actresses learned to “author” their theatrical personae from women
					dramatists, fashioning ways of developing their professional character
					performance by performance. Playwrights “performed” their authorship, learning
					from actresses how they might influence public perception through staging
					particular moments of authorial utterance within the public sphere. Even more
					fascinating, women dramatists wrote plays with particular actresses in
						mind—<name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s Jane DeMonfort for Siddons,
					for example—but even beyond practical casting considerations, actresses served
					to flesh out the imagination of the stage writing of women who wrote without
					intimate knowledge of the backstage world or who sought in the persona of an
					actress a way of moving beyond their own personal style of feminine performance.
					At the same time, actresses valued the roles written by women for women’s
					performance. </p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">H:</hi> Consider the continuum of venues for which women wrote
					drama—from private circulation of closet drama to <name ref="London"
						>London</name>’s patent theatres and all spaces in between.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">W:</hi> The early phase of research on women dramatists focused
					on the far extremes of these venues, the closet and the patent-theatre stage.
					But as a greater variety of scholarship has developed, more work on alternative
						<name ref="London">London</name> stages, provincial stages, private
					theatres, and any number of alternative venues has complicated the picture of
					women’s dramatic writing. What makes consideration of different venues such an
					interesting dimension of our historicization of women’s dramatic writing is that
					it forces us to reexamine dramatic forms and subjects in the context of variable
					social dimensions—which audiences directly experienced the works, in what
					contexts they experienced the works, and how a drama’s aesthetic reception was
					surrounded in varied ways by other forms of publicity, knowledge, and social
					circulation. For instance, a play like Ann Yearsley’s <emph>Earl Goodwin</emph>,
					performed in Bristol and Bath in 1789, hits its regional audience and local
					readers of newspapers differently than the same play might have had it been
					performed, as Yearsley originally hoped, on a <name ref="London">London</name>
					mainstage. The social acoustics of varied venues of performance affect how
					women’s plays are heard and how they resonate in the culture surrounding
					them.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">H:</hi> Study the theatre theory women of the era wrote, not just
					as explanations of their dramatic praxis but also as further ways in which they
					performed in the theatre of authorship and in which they created new
					possibilities for dramatic thinking.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">W:</hi> In any form of commentary on theatre or drama, women
					writers envision ways that plays might be received—empathically, ethically,
					politically. When <name ref="InchbaldMrs">Inchbald</name>, for example, responds
					to the plays of women writers included in <emph>The British Theatre</emph>, she
					cannily does so as much as a characterized type of critic as she does as a
					private citizen. A reader of her commentary is thereby given a kind of stance to
					respond to: “This critic raises an eyebrow about this play’s moral commitments,
					but I might not share those concerns,” one might think. But in this stance
					taking, <name ref="InchbaldMrs">Inchbald</name> opens up dialogue with the plays
					she discusses, and that dialogue with a play is an opening to further thought.
					Likewise, when <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>—in all earnestness, it
					seems—critiques the practices of theatre production of her time, she, too, does
					more than propose an alternative production style. She reframes the very idea of
					theatrical convention, inviting us to consider what kinds of aesthetics of
					character, plot, and theme current practices advance. </p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">H:</hi> Consider women’s dramatic writing as more than pragmatic
					literary professionalism—consider its psychological and self-revelatory
					dimensions and the ways it allowed for new kinds of envisioning by women to
					become public.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">W:</hi> There are times when I reread one of <name
						ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>’s plays and I suddenly can only
					see its monodramatic qualities. I see only Joanna—both her young and her older
					self—playing all the parts, reading all the lines, channeling all the emotions.
					And then I think about the psychological freedom that envisioning oneself acting
					the play on a <name ref="London">London</name> stage could have represented to
					her. And then I think about what imagining her doing so could have represented
					to a woman (or a man) reading the play. The pleasure of dashing one’s head
					against the side of the stage, of tossing a coffee cup to the floor, of
					comforting a distraught brother, of disarming a crazed rival! <name
						ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>, like so many women dramatists of the
					era, had discovered the power of interventionist acting out.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">H:</hi> Introduce contemporary women dramatists and writers who
					employ dramatic elements in all kinds of contemporary forms of writing.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">W:</hi> In my course, I connected women dramatists of the
					Romantic era to contemporary screenwriters and graphic novelists. We looked at
						<emph>My So-Called Life</emph>, Winnie Holzman’s mid-1990s television
					series, as well as Alison Bechdel’s graphic memoir <emph>Fun Home</emph>. After
					reading many different women writers’ treatments of family life in dramatic
					form, these two uses of dramatic elements in very different media suggested
					interesting parallels. But perhaps more importantly, the contemporary works sent
					us back to re-see such features as <name ref="InchbaldMrs">Inchbald</name>’s
					tonal shifts or <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s social contexts for
					the passions. It is valuable to look back to see what came before, but sometimes
					what comes after sheds light on the forms and strategies of predecessor texts. </p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">H:</hi> Ask whether teaching women’s dramatic writing of the
					British Romantic era has any curricular patterns in common with teaching other
					minority literatures.</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">W:</hi> One of the questions I raised repeatedly in the course
					had to do with what kinds of rationales we can use to justify the teaching of
					“minority literatures.” Because some of my students were English education
					majors, and because I think about the concerns of future and current teachers
					whenever I teach literature these days, I was curious to probe the rationales we
					use to bring new books into the book room, new texts and aesthetic forms into
					our classrooms. After all, school can often be about transmitting the received
					forms and aesthetics—how else to explain the fetishization of Ibsen’s <emph>A
						Doll House</emph> in American public high schools to the exclusion of almost
					all other 19<hi rendition="#sup">th</hi> century European drama? Why change what
					we teach? I know that in a faculty-research-driven environment, faculty’s
					continuing quest for a new margin to explore can provide the answer. But when
					the default rationale is celebration of the already valued, and when the
					logistics of getting new texts before the students can be complicated, other
					rationales need to be explored—if not necessarily unproblematically endorsed.
					Why, after all, teach undergraduates a course in “How and Why to Teach the
					History of Women’s Dramatic Writing” in the first place? Why indeed….</p>
				<div type="section" n="2">

					<ab>
						<emph>For historical representation</emph>
					</ab>
					<p> This rationale would depend on the idea that literature is taught to
						represent the history of culture. Therefore, to give an accurate picture of
						history would demand that major producers of cultural forms must be part of
						what we consider in historical studies to get an accurate picture. This
						rationale depends, however, on viewing women’s dramatic writing as
						significantly varied from men’s in ways that make it represent something
						slightly different, a significant minority variation. And the overall
						rationale for literature teaching that undergirds this reason is a kind of
						representational politics of culture. Questions might be raised about
						whether within the vast scheme of things that is a British culture
						curriculum women’s plays—given how much many of them partake of the same
						industry protocols as men’s plays—are a significant and variant enough
						subset to merit special consideration. Would we teach women’s newswriting,
						television screenplays, and so forth? The representational rationale is one
						that has its limits, though when linked to more pragmatic reasons—such as
						allowing contemporary women who (might) write drama to reflect on women’s
						previous dramatic writing—can have power.</p>
					<ab>
						<emph>For stylistic and thematic distinctiveness</emph>
					</ab>
					<p> As I’ve already suggested, this rationale ultimately has to be addressed
						within the historical rationale as well. There, the question becomes whether
						women’s writing of drama is representative of anything distinct that must be
						accounted for. Here, elements of dramaturgy (central female characters given
						new agency, for example) and of thematic focus (the problematics of
						marriage, women’s filial obligations, social pressure toward respectability)
						provide the main reasons for studying the history of women’s drama. Of
						course, these elements may either be seen as essentially different from
						other drama for reasons of women’s fundamental differences in interests from
						men’s, or as primarily a market niche that women dramatists occupied. The
						primary dilemma for this rationale is that convenience sampling of women’s
						drama overall may be the only way to claim an essential difference.
						Considering only women's plays that differ from the main body of a period’s
						drama seems a good way to ensure minority status that is both misleading and
						limiting to fuller consideration of the plays.</p>
					<ab>
						<emph>For its value in troubling existing aesthetics and histories</emph>
					</ab>
					<p> I’ve saved this one for last because it seems to me most compelling. When we
						look closely at the plays of women dramatists and at their careers as
						writers, we are often forced to see the complex interplay between dramatic
						writer and historical situation in new ways. Sidestepping the sociology of
						dramatic authorship no longer makes sense—and we begin to wonder whether it
						ever did. Our current ideas about how art treats some of the themes familiar
						to us—love, tragedy, economic struggles, etc.—are often turned around. For
						instance, we may leave to doubt whether any love story can confidently be
						taken as representational of a particular persona’s situation rather than as
						a structural device for examining identity, desire, and social priorities
						within the rigors of an art form centered on enactment rather than
						reflection.</p>
					<p>This last rationale seems to me most appealing when we talk about
						marriage comedies of playwrights such as Centlivre, <name ref="CowleyHannah"
							>Cowley</name>, and <name ref="InchbaldMrs">Inchbald</name> since our
						own insistence on love as a personal emotion and set of choices seems
						problematized when characters’ personal actions in sorting out love matters
						test our credulity at the same time they might make some wonder, “Why
						doesn’t she just…?” or “Her actions seem rather tortuous and tangled.” While
						we can certainly choose to see the actions of the plays as less authentic
						and real than our own (aren’t they?), we might also scent the ways that our
						own beliefs in the personal directness of love, achievement, and ethical
						character might be a bit less inevitable were we to look at them in their
						full context of actions over a lifetime. Plays by women often create this
						trouble closest to home.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="3">
					
					<p><hi rend="bold">H:</hi> Raise questions for students about how and why our
						teaching, curriculum, and research choose their focuses, define and pursue
						their purposes, and determine their successes or failures.</p>
					<p><hi rend="bold">W:</hi> There is a certain tyranny in looking mainly forward
						in our humanities scholarship. Wait, how can I say that we mainly look
						forward? After all, isn’t our curriculum mostly about the past? In a way, we
						are never more neglectful of the past and how we constantly remake it than
						when we naturalize our work with cultural materials from the past that our
						scholarly and teaching practices remake. As we pursue our professions
						through working with the materials of earlier periods, we sometimes fail to
						ask, “Why these plays, these pedagogies, this curriculum?” Of course, it is
						not possible to remain perpetually meta-aware of the premises of our
						teaching and research, but returning again and again to the questions “How?”
						and “Why?” helps to keep us honest, alive to the possibilities of the past,
						and sensitive to the work our teaching and scholarship does today.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
