<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Teaching the Ridiculous: </title>
				<title type="subordinate">
					<title level="m">Harlequin and Humpo; or, Columbine by Candlelight!</title>
				</title>
				<author>
					<name>Elizabeth Fay</name>
				</author>
				<editor role='editor'>
					<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Pedagogies Editor</resp>
					<name>Kate Singer</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>commons4.2011.fay</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
								Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Teaching the Ridiculous: </title>
						<title level="a" type="subordinate">
							<title level="m">Harlequin and Humpo; or, Columbine by Candlelight!</title>
						</title>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename>Elizabeth</forename>
								<surname>Fay</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Teaching Romantic Drama: </title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Pedagogies Commons Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
							<biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g18" scheme="#genre"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<date>2011-02-18</date>
				<list>
					<item>revised TEI</item>
					<item>XSLT</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Dave Rettenmaier</name>
				<date>2010-06-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				<date>2009-11-01T15:01:00</date>
				<list>
					<item>Proofed issue in Open Office Format</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">
				<head>
					<title level="a">Teaching the Ridiculous: <title level="m">Harlequin and Humpo; or, Columbine by Candlelight!</title></title>
				</head>
				<byline>
					<docAuthor>Elizabeth Fay</docAuthor>
					<affiliation>University of Massachusetts Boston</affiliation>
				</byline>


				<p n="1">Several years ago I offered a graduate seminar in Romantic period drama, basing my choice of plays on <name
						ref="CoxJeffreyN">Jeffrey Cox</name> and <name ref="GamerMichael">Michael Gamer</name>’s <title
						level="m">Broadview Anthology of Romantic Drama</title>, which had recently appeared, as well as Peter Duthie’s edition of
						<name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>’s <title level="m">Plays on the Passions</title>.<hi
						rendition="#sup">
						<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="1">Jeffrey N. Cox and <name ref="GamerMichael">Michael Gamer</name>, <title
								level="m">Broadview Anthology of Romantic Drama</title> (Peterborough, Ontario: Broadview Press, 2003); <name
								ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>, <title level="m">Plays on the Passions</title>, ed. Peter
							Duthie (Peterborough, Ontario: Broadview Press, 2001).</note>
					</hi> I wanted to offer a broad range of plays to span the sublime-ridiculous axis within a fairly tight time span. My focus was
					on the material conditions of playwriting, acting, and even attending theatres during the period, with less attention given to the
					difficulties of producing a play and of doing so within physically challenging work spaces.<hi rendition="#sup">
						<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="2">My thanks to the superb graduate students in this seminar, especially but not only
							Christian Pulver, Elizabeth Thompson, Michael Neubeck and David Rogers.</note>
					</hi>
				</p>
				<p n="2"> Our mandate for the course was to consider Romantic-period <name ref="London">London</name> theatres to be the
					central cultural institution of the day. I present the genre of drama to my students by explaining that plays, whether written to
					be performed or to be read as “mental theatre,” were used to work through key issues of the day, and that letters and memoirs of
					the time often represented thoughts and behavior as if dramatized. Novels frequently contained references to the theatre or
					specific plays, and occasionally included scenes of amateur playacting in order to make social commentary. Playwrights and poets
					wanted to stage contemporary issues in visible confrontations, whether of politics (revolution versus maintaining the status quo,
					Whigs versus Tories, Parliament versus the monarchy); national identity (patriotism versus Jacobinism, British culture versus
					colonial culture, abolition versus the slave economy); and/or gender relations (feminism versus patriarchy, the marriage market,
					family structure). We also considered how theatres were managed, the difficulties facing playwrights who had only three main
					theatres to submit their work to, and how people used the theatre auditorium as a way to stage their own social performance. </p>
				<p n="3">Finally, we attempted to understand an audience experience so different from our own in which, for earlier Romantic plays,
					performances were held in lighted rather than darkened theatres. Sputtering candlewax, the heat generated by hundreds of candles
					and spectators, and the constant movement of lighting attendants only added to the confusion created by those audience members
					more concerned to display themselves or to visit their friends than to watch the actors on stage. Toward the end of the period
					enlarged theatres meant actors were too distant to hear well while the still brightly lit audience space made the stage hard to
					see as well. We were forced to reconsider the normative high value given to text-based literature, and to read these plays
					differently: to read them as staged, to appreciate each genre by its own terms, and to hear the confusion and hubbub that
					surrounded these plays as part of their cultural value. I wanted us to study representative plays of the period, from tragedies
					and sentimental comedies to melodrama and closet dramas, while paying attention to dramatic form and representation. Of course,
					this aspect of our discussions always spiraled into content analysis as students became engaged with characters’ struggles rather
					than the issues such fictions are meant to embody, but we tried to constantly remind ourselves of the material conditions
					surrounding dramatic production. </p>
				<p n="4"> We approached our topic through articles by key scholars in the field and relevant websites, and students were excited by
					how challenging the theoretical tools were that scholars use to analyze these plays, and yet how much fun people were having
					creating websites to document the material culture of late eighteenth-century and early nineteenth-century theatres and
					performances. With this discovery another set of <emph>x-y</emph> axes began to appear over the framework I had structured for the
					course of a sublime-ridiculous <emph>y-</emph>axis cut by a historical <emph>x-</emph>axis, each intersection providing a key to a
					cultural moment. We now had a multi-level coordinate system in which the <emph>x-y </emph>axis of history cut by genre was
					overlaid with an <title level="m">x-</title>axis of materiality cut by a <emph>y-</emph>axis of theory. Added to these
					coordinating vectors was our own axial supplement of difficulty cut by enjoyment. Difficulty was articulated by genre and theory;
					pleasure by history and materiality. As with any supplement, our own vectors held more truth-value for us. Out of the students’
					engagement with supplementary materials, the intersections of difficulty and pleasure began to chart our understanding and
					reconstruction of Romantic drama and stagecraft. It was not that the sublime and the difficult were synchronized against the
					ridiculous and pleasure, but rather that both the sublime and ridiculous were modulated by the cultural moment while pleasure
					showed us when difficulty was valuable and when it only interfered in our historical reconstruction. We learned to read more into
					the contradiction between the difficulty of a woman learning her craft while knowing the danger to her reputation for traveling to
					theatres alone at night—or, if her play was being staged, for staying alone with the dramatic company during rehearsals—and the
					fact that women wrote some of the most hilarious domestic comedies of the late eighteenth century. No longer could breeches parts
					and gender-bending be taken as anything other than social commentary, but we laughed all the harder at the jokes, mistakes, and
					misunderstandings that ensued from such masquerades. The axial pairs shifted and adjusted as we went, creating ways to chart our
					entrée into Romantic theatricality and its peculiar relation to British Romantic culture. </p>
				<p n="5">Our range of plays reflected both sets of axial descriptors: we went from the sit-coms of the day, such as <name
						ref="CowleyHannah">Hannah Cowley</name>’s <title level="m">A Bold Stroke for a Husband</title> (1783) and <name
						ref="InchbaldMrs">Elizabeth Inchbald</name>’s <title level="m">Every One Has His Fault</title> (1793), to the
					high tragic art of <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>’s <title level="m">Plays on the Passions</title>
					(1798) and <name ref="ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</name>’s <title level="m">The Cenci</title> (1819); from the
					orientalism of George Colman the Younger’s <title level="m">Blue-Beard; or, Female Curiosity!</title> (1798) to the absurdity of
					his burlesque <title level="m">Quadrupeds of Quedlinburgh</title> (1811). Our scholarly framing came from <name
						ref="BurroughsCatherineB">Catherine Burroughs</name>’<title level="m"> Women in British Romantic
							Theatre</title> and <title level="m"
								>Closet Stages</title>,
					<name ref="DonkinEllen">Ellen Donkin</name>’s <title level="m">Getting into the Act: Women Playwrights in <name
							ref="London">London</name> 1776-1829</title>, Daniel Watkins’ <title level="m">Materialist Critique of
						English Romantic Drama</title>, along with a slew of journal articles.<hi rendition="#sup">
						<note place="foot" n="3" resp="editors">Catherine Burroughs, <title level="m">Closet Stages: <name
									ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name> Baillie and the Theatre theory of British Romantic Women
								Writers</title> (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1997); <name ref="BurroughsCatherineB"
								>Catherine Burroughs</name>, ed. <title level="m">Women in British Romantic Theatre: Drama, Performance, and Society,
								1790-1840</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2000); <name ref="DonkinEllen">Ellen
								Donkin</name>, <title level="m">Getting into the Act: Women Playwrights in <name ref="London"
									>London</name> 1776-1829, Women and Playwriting in 19<hi rendition="#sup">th</hi>-Century Britain</title> (London:
							Routledge, 1995); and Daniel P. Watkins, <title level="m">A Materialist Critique of English Romantic Drama</title>
							(Gainesville: University of Florida Press, 1993).</note>
					</hi> For instance, we read Peter Thomson’s chapter on “The Early Career of George Colman the Younger” and Greg Kucich’s “‘A
					Haunted Ruin’: Romantic Drama, Renaissance Tradition, and the Critical Establishment” for George Colman the Younger’s <title
						level="m">Blue-Beard,</title> and then compared the Gothicism and the treatment of the grotesque in <title level="m"
						>Blue-Beard</title> to that of <title level="m">Manfred</title>, while also considering the implications of closet drama and
					gender through <name ref="BurroughsCatherineB">Burroughs</name>’ <title level="m">Closet Stages</title>. <hi
						rendition="#sup">
						<note place="foot" n="4" resp="editors">Peter Thomson, “The Early Career of George Colman the Younger,” in <title level="m"
								>Essays on Nineteenth-Century British Theatre</title>, ed. Kenneth Richards and Peter Thomson (London: Methuen,
							1971), 67-82; Greg Kucich, “‘A Haunted Ruin’: Romantic Drama, Renaissance Tradition, and the Critical Establishment,” in
								<title level="m">British Romantic Drama: Historical and Critical Essays</title>, ed. Terence Hoagwood and Daniel
							P. Watkins (London: Associated University Presses, 1998), 56-83.</note>
					</hi>
				</p>
				<p n="6">Students noted that <name ref="ByronGeorgeGordonByronBaron">Byron</name>’s use of the supernatural in <title
						level="m">Manfred</title> bore a striking resemblance to that of Colman’s <title level="m">Blue-Beard</title>, while his
					medievalism served the same purpose as Colman’s orientalism in defamiliarizing contemporary issues so that they could be
					resituated and put under pressure. <title level="m">Manfred</title>’s supernaturalism, they felt, revealed an indictment of the
					critical trappings at Drury Lane, as well as of the blossoming field of theatre review and literary criticism that hobbled <name
						ref="ByronGeorgeGordonByronBaron">Byron</name>’s dramatic freedom. Colman was used to the less restrictive
					atmosphere of Haymarket Theatre where his father was manager, a position he then took over, and preferred more popular forms to engage
						critique.<hi rendition="#sup">
						<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="5">
							<title level="m">Blue-Beard</title> had a more interesting history in that it was used as a substitute for the Christmas
							harlequinade, and so opened at Drury Lane, becoming tremendously successful.</note>
					</hi> Comparing a closet drama to an afterpiece was instructive, since in both forms questions of gender can be treated more
					ambiguously than in the hard give-and-take of domestic comedy or the dire consequences of tragedy. <title level="m"
						>Blue-Beard</title>’s melodramatic hippodrama with a gothically bleeding “Blue Chamber” used a different kind of specularity
					from <name ref="ByronGeorgeGordonByronBaron">Byron</name>’s, with live horses instead of ethereal spirits, and a
					Turkish locale instead of <name ref="ByronGeorgeGordonByronBaron">Byron</name>’s alpine sublime. Its fairy tale
					treatment of women’s subject-status and their right to knowledge provided a greater gender critique than did Manfred’s mysterious
					soul-mate Astarte whose absent presence haunts the play, yet whose unverifiable life and death settles the focus squarely on
					Manfred and his hallucinatory world. </p>
				<p n="7">Thomas John Dibdin’s pantomime <title level="m">Harlequin and Humpo; or, Columbine by Candlelight!</title> (1812) was our
					treat for the last day of class, its deliciousness savored by students traumatized by Beatrice’s fate in <title level="m">The
						Cenci</title>; unable to dismiss their technological sophistication enough to see why <title level="m">Manfred</title> was not
					stageable; and overwhelmed by this point with densely written scholarship. Yet it was not pure fun, crossed as it was by the very
					issues raised in the plays we had already read; in hindsight,<title level="m"> Harlequin and Humpo</title> provides the real key
					to our experience of the course. On the one hand, its inclusion in the Broadview anthology and in my syllabus demanded that we
					take it seriously; on the other hand, as social satire its antics lack the deeper cuts of Voltaire’s satiric plays or even <name
						ref="InchbaldMrs">Inchbald</name>’s domestic comedies. But I wanted to take seriously <name
						ref="CoxJeffreyN">Jeffrey Cox</name>’s questioning of long-held claims that melodrama caused the death of
					tragedy or foreshadowed modern drama<hi rendition="#sup">
						<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="6">“Melodramatic realisms, Romantic virtualities,” pre-conference lecture for NASSR 2006
							at Purdue University.</note>
					</hi>, and I also wanted to parse pantomime with both forms to find how the melodrama of everyday life rewrote the tragedy of
					history by allowing theatre-goers to simply have fun. </p>
				<p n="8">For my students I wanted to pose the question of how pantomime changes the understanding we had been developing of Romantic
					performance: was Dibdin’s play a devolution or a critique? Historically, the pantomime was first performed as a Christmas
					pantomime at Drury Lane, 26 December 1812, the year that saw the Luddite bill in Parliament for capital punishment against
					framebreakers, and <name ref="ByronGeorgeGordonByronBaron">Byron</name>’s maiden speech; the second year of the
					Regency amid George III’s increasing insanity; and Napoleon’s invasion and then retreat from Moscow. It was a year of chaos and
					madness, at the same time endowed with the Regency’s characteristic high-spirits and playfulness. Dibdin’s mishmash of genres
					captures the year’s contradictory aspects and sense of tumult. Its subtitle indicates mystery and revelation, surely also a hint
					at the unknowns to come regarding Napoleon, worker unrest, abolition and its effect on the sugar trade. Moreover, after the debut
					just a month later, January 23, 1813, of <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>’s tragedy <title
						level="m">Remorse: A Tragedy, in Five Acts</title>, it was often double-billed with Dibdin’s play as the afterpiece, surely a
					sign of the despair these unknowns could unfold. That was our first set of axial coordinates: 1812 cut by a harlequinade. </p>
				<p n="9">Our second set of axes confronted the materiality of putting on this bizarre performance (and wondering why it could be
					staged when <title level="m">Manfred</title> could not) cut by Bakhtin’s theory of the carnevalesque, but also theories of how
					theatre reflected revolution and war, and how women playwrights were losing out to male writers. Although <name
						ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>’s third volume of plays was also published in 1812, this did not
					signal success for women dramaturges since her dramas were for the most part read rather than performed. If the pairing of <title
						level="m">Remorse </title>with <title level="m">Harlequin and Humpo </title>contradicts the theory that serious dramaturgy
					suffered under the popularity of the ridiculous, the closeting of <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s plays
					does suggest a silencing of female voices, if not of tragedy itself. Columbine gained new significance in this comparative, and we
					wondered at the significance of her being closeted by the evil witch Owletta, and her forced marriage to the deformed Humpino.
					Finally, we were faced with the axes of difficulty and pleasure: a theatrical that is highly historicized, ephemeral, and
					non-transcendent that nonetheless made us laugh. How it did so became the puzzle to unpack, since understanding that allowed us
					back into plays we’d read earlier to see if our intellectual enjoyment there could now take on a more sincere pleasure in plays
					that are likewise historically situated and culturally distant, if closer to our standards of taste and literary norms. </p>
				<p n="10">The full title of Dibdin’s play is <title level="m">Sketch of the New Melo-Dramatick Comick Pantomime called Harlequin and
						Humpo; or, Columbine by Candlelight! </title>The reviews at first trashed it, yet it ran forty-eight nights and was, like
						<title level="m">Blue-Beard,</title> one of the great successes of its genre. Dibdin had an even freer rein with his pen than
					Colman since he began his career as an actor and writer for Sadler’s Wells, and also wrote for other secondary theatres before
					moving to Covent Garden and finally becoming manager of Drury Lane and then Surrey Theatre. If tragedy provides the sublime and
					Gothic yields the grotesque, pantomime gives us the ridiculous. How might the ridiculous provide the underside of the sublime? How
					might it reveal the Gothic as pretentious artifice rather than psychological insight? How could we make sense, in other words, of
					Regency humor? The pantomime’s origins in Italian <emph>commedia dell’arte</emph>, with its puppet-like character types,
					improvisational style, and slapstick orientation make it appear childish and rustic rather than sophisticated, but could we read
					it another way? In preparation for our last seminar meeting I gave the students background material on the <emph>commedia
						dell’arte</emph>, its importation into northern Europe and Britain, and the similar stylized use of character in the more
					recently imported opera. We needed to dig underneath stereotyped characters and set scenes to understand why audiences would have
					found these familiar formulae pleasurable, and how playwrights might motivate such characters and scenes for social critique. How
					might interruptive “laugh” devices increase emotional distance in order to make a point as much as to augment audience hilarity?
					How might absurd plot devices make us rethink our own lives and life trajectories? These together with the play’s unsparing use of
					mistaken identity and pantomimic features captured some of the saturnalian qualities of earlier British traditions surrounding
					Christmas, I told my students, when lords and peasants threw protocol to the winds for a few topsy-turvy hours. But the saturnalia
					was always already social commentary, a chance for the oppressed to turn rage to laughter. The difficulty lay in how to decode the
					laughter, how to understand the violence underlying Regency tastes in elite <emph>and</emph> bawdy subjects and acts.</p>
				<p n="11"> The pantomime always began with a ballet that describes a fairy tale set-piece, followed by a mid-scene centered on a fairy
					character such as Mother Goose, and ending with the harlequinade. All three sections were accompanied by music or had musical
					interludes when actors broke out into song, and music was always played during processionals. Music provided one of our biggest
					material difficulties: although the words are usually, but not always, recorded in scripts, typically there is no notation or
					indication of how the music would have sounded. Students were better able to imagine the pantomimed scenes from their familiarity
					with mime artists today, but they had trouble reconstructing the visual effects of this play’s pantomimic elements, as well as the
					aural effects of its sound technologies. In this case the ridiculous was cut both by history and by materiality; theory came to
					our historical aid in the guise of Bakhtin’s theory of the carnevalesque, which I had briefly introduced earlier in the semester,
					and once students made the connection some enlightening self-ridicule took place. We realized we had been reading at once too
					superficially and too deeply—frustrated at finding no meaning, we couldn’t see the meaning in front of us. Having got this far, we
					still needed help understanding the material aspects of the harlequinade. Nevertheless, we began to enjoy Harlequin and
					Columbine’s misadventures, chronicled through the series of improbable plots disastrously entangled, checked, and plied through
					with difficulties created by plotting maids, parasites and duplicitous characters, child-snatchers, braggarts and simpletons, to
					say nothing of mistaken identity and other plot interventions. We had to tell ourselves to let go of plot motivation, sequencing
					logic, and interpretive subtlety, but we also had to learn to look for layers of meaning, connections between the performance
					sections, and cultural significance. </p>
				<p n="12"> A peculiar quality of the pantomime is its exploitation of the stage’s visual conventions; this created another hurdle for
					students trained in the play-as-text, but also opened the door to understanding the material conditions of the performance.
					Dramatic productions usually submerge the artificiality of stage representation beneath the accepted norms for symbolic space,
					character stability, disguise, temporal movement, and role portrayal. Audience compliance with these norms generates expectations
					that playwrights and actors will adhere to certain formal and representational models. Like today’s cartoons, pantomime sets out
					to subvert these models, conventions and rules at every opportunity, an intention already encoded in its use of scenes as the
					principle unit rather than acts subdivided by scenes. Cartooning, then, offered us our first ‘theoretical’ intervention in
					understanding materiality. In our discussion of <title level="m">Harlequin and Humpo </title>students began to point out in
					particular the metacommentary at work in puns on visuality as the layers of the visual and the staged, of what we see and what we
					allow ourselves to see, become the interference factor in our understanding of everyday life. It is a factor that the play makes
					all too visible; it was easy for students to come up with examples of near-equal ridiculousness from our own political stage to
					the social drama of celebrity lives. </p>
				<p n="13"> A scene that quickly became central to our discussion was that made by a dumb show during a chase scene set in <name
						ref="London">London</name>’s market streets. Although it is morning, the Clown steals a telescope from the
					optician’s shop and uses it to view the just risen moon. After several musical pieces accompany more movement on stage, the Clown
					resumes his play with the telescope at which “the figures disappear and one like the Clown takes their place.” In the next musical
					piece “Presto. Harlequin from a window waves his sword. The telescope changes to a gun, goes off, shoots the Clown, who shams
					dead,” but when the gunsmith claims his gun “Harlequin enters, pursued, &amp; leaps through one Eye of the Spectacles at the
					Opticians. Clown in following leaps through the other and their faces appear (painted) thro’ each eye of the [Spectacles], which
					fall down like a yoke upon Pantaloon’s neck, which stands in place of a nose to them” (stage directions, Scene XIII). </p>
				<p n="14">Presto, like circus clowns the characters are miniaturized and displaced, substituted and reconstituted, and are as
					fantastical in their abilities and whims as genies and spirits. One student had been reading about late eighteenth-century
					advances in scientific instruments, providing a clue to the visual fascination with optics, from spectacles and telescopes to gun
					sights. We talked about how the pantomimed scene made us question what we see that we normally wouldn’t, whether a tiny moon in a
					telescope lens or even a mirrored image. Another student wondered about the connection between this play and <title level="m">The
						Travels and Surprising Adventures of Baron Munchausen</title> (1859) with its similar parodic effects and fascination with
					telescope-enhanced adventures. There the political commentary is more overt, allowing us to begin to consider the critique
					Dibdin’s play might be articulating. </p>
				<p n="15">As the spectacle scene demonstrates, space and time in <title level="m">Harlequin and Humpo</title> are more ambiguously
					related to normal frames of reference than is usual in drama so that scenes can shift in rapid succession from one location to
					another. In rapid succession we move from a king’s palace to a Dutch clockmaker’s to a country pub to a warehouse to a plumber’s
					shop to a fairy’s cave all at dizzying speed and often for no real reason except for that of the antic. Late in the play the Clown
					attempts to steal a hurdygurdy “Shew Box” or peep show after watching a performance by animals and dancers. Just as he is leaving
					with the shew box, “Harlequin strikes it and it encloses the Clown like a Box” (stage directions, Scene XIV). Sizes, physical
					properties and space-time dimensions change with the same ease as objects viewed alternately through a telescope and the naked
					eye. Instrumentation becomes a contemporary form of fairy dust, while subjectivity is ungrounded and put into freefall. Students
					just coming from <title level="m">The Cenci </title>found the freefall glibly problematic on the one hand, and yet on the other,
					what one student called “a kind of cardboard version” of Beatrici’s moral freefall. If stage space is arbitrary and artificial, so
					too might be our legal codes, or worse, our moral codes—for surely we had been hard put to condemn Beatrice if we could not quite
					condone her. Surely she had blurred our moral vision and made us reconsider what we were witnessing. Surely Harlequin’s antics
					were more than they appeared.</p>
				<p n="16">The fairy tale, we thought from the outset, would provide an apt terrain for political allusions, for social commentary and
					for plumbing the depths of the popular imaginary. Here was ground for my students to discover that all they had laboriously
					construed over the semester concerning Romantic drama could be subjected to a severe roasting. They noted in particular its
					antecedent in 1950s-era “Looney Tunes,” in which indestructible cartoon characters caricature prominent social and political
					figures. Sir Arthur, “a gallant Knight, afterwards Harlequin,” as the role list explains, provides a stock character of British
					legend: the knightly King Arthur. Humpo, by contrast, is King of the Dwarfs, denied regal decency by his signifying name and his
					transformation into the stock zanni Pantaloon (normally spelled Pantalone). He is a literally unenlightened ruler, whose daughter
					may not see the sun until she is eighteen due to the fairy Owletta’s curse, and the dupe of others. Sir Arthur’s antagonist is the
					Prince of the Dwarfs, Humpino, to whom the Princess has been promised in marriage; the anticipation of this disastrous wedding
					begins the rapid-paced action, in which the Princess is magically changed to Columbine and her lover Sir Arthur to Harlequin in
					order to escape the dire event. One student compared reading the play to seeing only the storyboards for a Hollywood film and then
					trying to imagine the movie in its finished state without being able to see it. Textually the play requires enormous leaps of the
					imagination.</p>
				<p n="17">Worse yet, Dibdin’s characters kept leaping back and forth between fairy tale and harlequinade, so that we kept falling into
					childhood memories of Grimm’s Fairy Tales just as we would enter the parodic world of <emph>commedia dell’arte</emph>. The rapid
					shifts in genre, discursive traditions, character expectations interfered with our ability to follow a basic plot since most of us
					did not have the cultural knowledge necessary to interpret each of these traditions as they arose in the play. The convergences,
					slippages, and disjunctures, I felt, were not too different from those of music videos but my students protested being asked to
					retro-fit our music industry aesthetic to Dibdin’s taller order of the absurd. Again we returned to cartoon animation, in which
					the two dimensions of the everyday world and the fairy world are also so interrelated that characters move between them almost
					seamlessly. We also discussed the relation between puppetry and harlequinades, and how the imaginative demands that each of these
					folk forms make on the audience are similar. Both the cartoon and puppetry frameworks made more palatable the conversion of the
					Princess and Sir Arthur into their recognizable forms as Columbine and Harlequin, rendering their story inevitable no matter how
					many plot turns or leaps between different worlds were required to fulfill it. In our favor was the fact that every play we had
					read seemed to dwell on the problems of star-crossed lovers, unfulfilled love, illicit love, misguided love. We revisited an
					earlier discussion of how the Austenian problem of the middle-class heroine in search of a husband saturated the theatrical
					dynamic as much as that of the domestic novel. Contextualizing our harlequinade in this way helped us orient Dibdin’s world of
					uncomplicated love, fraught, it is true, with barriers and disruptions but nevertheless secure in the primordial compact between
					Harlequin and Columbine. The play’s task is to resolve how this pair, who unquestionably belong to each other, ultimately survive
					the Shakespearean trials that constantly thwart their union. But if the play is about Harlequin and Columbine, why then, one
					student demanded, is the title character Humpo and not Harlequin’s rival Humpino? </p>
				<p n="18"> As <name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> and <name ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name> remark in their
					preface to the play, Humpo King of the Dwarves bears a striking resemblance to Napoleon the usurper. We decided that indeed his
					diminutive stature would visually invoke Napoleon the man, a blow at French visions of grandeur that we thought would be nearly
					requisite by 1812, while his name indicates a deformed body and deformity of psyche or soul that represents Napoleon’s
					megalomania. Humpo, providing the play’s political critique and villain, caricatures Napoleon in a manner recognizable in <name
						ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>’s <title level="m">Remorse</title>, which we had read. Yet he also
					recalls Tom Thumb, the subject of a highly popular satire by Henry Fielding that we had not read, but which I summarized for them.
					Fielding’s diminutive Tom is King Arthur’s giant-killer, an anti-Napoleon.<hi rend="sup">
						<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="7"> “Hero, Giant-killing Lad, / Preserver of my Kingdom” (I.ii). <title level="m">The
								Tragedy of Tragedies; or, The Life and Death of Tom Thumb the Great</title>. Edited by L. J. Morrissey under its more
							common title, <title level="m">Tom Thumb; and, The Tragedy of Tragedies</title> (Edinburgh, Oliver &amp; Boyd, 1970).
						</note>
					</hi> Here was confusion indeed: Humpo, the greatest of the dwarves, is tiny against the full physical, cultural, and heroic
					stature of Sir (or King) Arthur, but is he defender of the kingdom, as for Fielding, or a Napoleon? It is Humpo, in his grotesque
					co-role as Pantaloon, who wrecks havoc for Harlequin and Columbine, chasing them through the various scene sets and finally, in
					Scene XV, forcibly separating them with the aid of the evil fairy Owletta, who had originally benighted the Princess/Columbine.
					Harlequin is left alone in the fairy’s cavern to be tormented by the Gothic devices of hooting owls and passing specters. Throwing
					himself on the ground in his despair, Harlequin “recollects his sword, waves it, strikes the ground &amp; rocks without effect,
					throws it from him angrily—.” Which is to say Arthur’s legendary talent with stone and sword has failed him here and a stronger
					magic is needed. The sword instantly turns into a bow and arrow, the weapon that will aid him in defeating Owletta and Humpo, and
					return him as Sir Arthur to the land of fairy, where he is reunited with his beloved Princess, restored from her alternate
					identity of Columbine. </p>
				<p n="19"> At the end of the seminar we were left ruminating about alternative identities, alterity, the psychodynamics of id-ego
					embodiments, and cultural manifestations of all these imaginative projections. We read the spectacle scene as a commentary on
					Luddite framebreaking, Humpo as a bizarre Napoleon, and the land of dwarves, witches, and harlequins as our everyday world—but
					mostly we came away with a sense of an audience reveling in the reduction of political uncertainty to visual play. We could see
					that in <title level="m">Harlequin and Humpo</title> stock characters and masks achieve cultural critique without the high style
					of Romantic psychodrama, intensely fleshed out characters, or the ambiguities and questions necessary to the Romantic imagination
					and culturally invested art. </p>
				<p n="20"> For us, the difficulty of the piece resides in interpreting its dumb shows, connecting the layers of comic and conventional
					symbolism to a coherent narrative, and following the central themes through all the interpolations and transformations of the
					play. Dibdin’s foolery with space and time and the arbitrariness of representation is difficult enough to let us find its
					philosophical counterpart in <name ref="WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</name>’s <title level="m">The
					Borderers</title>, with its equally challenging disorientation of time and space. If for Dibdin the fateful interventions of good
					and bad fairies are unrelated to personal merit, in <title level="m">The Borderers</title> the ethical becomes another dimension
					that ambiguates location and temporality, so that personal integrity has everything to do with epistemological stability.
					Epistemological stability, of course, is what is supremely missing from <title level="m">Harlequin and Humpo</title>, where not
					even scientific instrumentation provides reliable information, and where if you thought you knew something about plot and
					characterization, just wait a minute for it all to be undone. In <title level="m">The Borderers</title>, plot and character appear
					to unveil each other, yet language continually gets in the way—as it does in <title level="m">The Cenci</title>—of our moral
					determination, our belief in our capacity to decode, interpret, translate literary art according to a strong moral code. Each of
					these plays—<name ref="WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</name>’s, <name ref="ShelleyPercyBysshe"
						>Shelley</name>’s, Dibdin’s—dramatize how morally chaotic a historical moment can be, how the verbal framing of events can
					swing our moral compass in dizzying ways. Taking a moment to rethink <title level="m">The Borderers</title> and <title level="m"
						>The Cenci</title> made us recalibrate our initially too-superficial approach to <title level="m">Harlequin</title> yet
					again.</p>
				<p n="21">We began to think that <title level="m">Harlequin and Humpo</title> provides a telling example of the ridiculous as an
					antidote to the sublime: it seemed to us that perhaps 1812 was a ridiculous year as well as a tragic one, or rather its tragedies
					turned everything upside-down. The play’s distillation of psycho-social relations into essential units symbolically represented
					and engaged in semiotic foolery, layered onto cultural biases and traditions but invoking more recent developments such as the
					Gothic as well, also made it easier to see in retrospect how similar features are at work in literary dramas such as <title
						level="m">Manfred</title> or <title level="m">Count Basil</title>. This required some distillation, of course, but it was
					easier to do with Dibdin’s play than it would have been if we had started with the sublimity of <title level="m">Count Basil,
					</title>unpacking it from this perspective without having gone through the absurdity of <title level="m">Harlequin and
						Humpo</title>. For my students the harlequinade’s fun struck like a sword through our disciplinary assumptions of literary
					value, genre expectations and valuations, and the aestheticization of fantasy. It cut through the heavy stone of highly theorized
					interpretations of such plays as well, giving my students back for a moment their sense of delight in the fantastical world that
					theatre makes possible. We thought it was perhaps for this reason, indeed, that theatre managers had begun sequencing <title
						level="m">Remorse </title>with <title level="m">Harlequin and Humpo.</title> Then we had a more post-modern moment, and ended
					the seminar with the idea that perhaps Dibdin’s spectacle should have come first in the sequence, preparing its audience for the
					moral challenge of <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>’s tragedy, and that for us, its heightening of
					so many intellectual and cultural cacophonies, disruptions, and sacrileges might more usefully have begun our semester than
					concluded it. </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
