<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Staging the 18<hi rendition="#sup">th</hi>-Century Prostitute for
					the 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>-Century: </title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Dramaturgical Approach to Teaching <name
						ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name>’s <title level="m">The Belle’s
						Stratagem</title></title>
				<author>
					<name>Melinda C. Finberg</name>
				</author>
				<editor role='editor'>
					<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Pedagogies Editor</resp>
					<name>Kate Singer</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>commons4.2011.finberg</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
					Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
						or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
						purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
						use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
						are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
						with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
						permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
						requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
						forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
						conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
						them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
						have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
						Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
						continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
						a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
						use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Staging the 18<hi rendition="#sup"
							>th</hi>-Century Prostitute for the 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>-Century: </title>
						<title level="a" type="subordinate">A Dramaturgical Approach to Teaching
								<name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name>’s <title level="m">The
								Belle’s Stratagem</title></title>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename>Melinda C.</forename>
								<surname>Finberg</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Teaching Romantic Drama: </title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Pedagogies Commons Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
								Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
							<biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for
						‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
						keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
						such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
						been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
					10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
						on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g18" scheme="#genre"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<date>2011-02-18</date>
				<list>
					<item>revised TEI</item>
					<item>XSLT</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Dave Rettenmaier</name>
				<date>2010-06-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				<date>2009-11-01T15:01:00</date>
				<list>
					<item>Proofed issue in Open Office Format</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">

				<head>
					<title level="a">Staging the 18<hi rendition="#sup">th</hi>-Century Prostitute
						for the 21<hi rendition="#sup">st</hi>-Century: A Dramaturgical Approach to
						Teaching <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name>’s <title level="m">The
							Belle’s Stratagem</title></title>
				</head>
				<byline>
					<docAuthor>Melinda C. Finberg</docAuthor>
					<affiliation>Swarthmore College</affiliation>
				</byline>


				<div type="section" n="1">
					<head>The Classroom Dramaturg</head>
					<p n="1">In most theater survey or dramatic literature classes, plays are
						treated as literature. The term “dramaturgy” never comes up, either as a
						theatrical discipline or as a critical tool for helping our students
						understand drama. I propose changing this situation, and I will use <name
							ref="CowleyHannah">Hannah Cowley</name>’s comic masterpiece, <title
							level="m">The Belle’s Stratagem</title> (1780), to demonstrate how
						looking at plays from a dramaturgical perspective can provide both students
						and teachers with a more dynamic relationship to Romantic dramatic
						texts.</p>
					<p n="2">As a dramaturg, scholar, and teacher working with historical
						playwrights, I seek to bridge the worlds of the academy and the professional
						theater. I find my scholarly background imparts a rigor to my dramaturgy and
						my dramaturgical perspective colors my approach in the classroom. The job of
						the dramaturg, when working on an historic play, has many facets. The
						dramaturg must advocate for the necessarily absent author, educate the
						director, cast, designers and audience about the language and historic
						background of the play, and keep the production true to the integrity of the
						work, while at the same time keeping in mind the artistic, physical, and
						economic realities of the theater. As a dramaturg, I consider it most
						important that my students be aware that drama is a form of literature not
						meant primarily to be read but to be heard and seen. </p>
					<p n="3">Theater is, by its very nature, a collaborative art. The text of a play
						is the skeleton, the bones of the work of art, that must be fleshed out by
						the joint efforts of actors, directors, designers, and even dramaturgs. The
						final collaborator is the audience. Every performance is individual and
						unrepeatable. Living, breathing actors embody a text and <hi rend="bold"
							>connect</hi> with a specific living, breathing audience, making the
						performance both a public and an intimate event. Part of a dramaturg’s
						function is to facilitate that connection. The dramaturg must always be
						asking, “What is the play’s relationship with the audience?”<note
							place="foot" resp="editors" n="1"> For those who have never worked on a
							historical production with a dramaturg, I wish to clarify some of the
							differences between the roles of director and dramaturg. The director
							chooses what the overall interpretation of the script will be and the
							dramaturg, actors and designers all serve the director to achieve his or
							her vision. By having a dramaturg keeping track of the story and making
							sure all the elements are clear to the audience, the director is freed
							to focus on the details of each scene and the moment to moment
							relationships between the characters. In addition to providing
							historical research the dramaturg may take notes during a rehearsal and
							pass them on to the director to help make sure the overall narrative
							doesn’t get lost in the development of a particular scene. </note>
					</p>
					<p n="4">To understand what that relationship is, more questions must be asked.
						What is left unsaid in the play? Are there assumptions the audience is
						supposed to make? Are these assumptions culturally or historically specific?
						If so, what can theater artists do to recreate the appropriate receptivity
						on the part of the audience? What are the silences in the play, the blanks
						in the script we must choose either to fill or elide, that will color our
						entire interpretation? (Whether we fill or elide these silences, we are
						making an interpretational choice, so we might as well make a conscious
						choice, while recognizing at the same time that other choices are equally
						possible.) How do we recognize the silences? All these are dramaturgical
						questions that broaden our understanding of a play beyond the simply
						literary perspective and lead us to a multidisciplinary approach to this art
						form that requires our active participation.</p>
					<p n="5">I propose to look at teaching <name ref="CowleyHannah">Hannah
							Cowley</name>’s comic masterpiece <title level="m">The Belle’s
							Stratagem</title> (1780) from a dramaturgical perspective, and that
						means that the first task is to shatter the preconception that a Romantic
						play is a dusty period piece from a quaint and less sophisticated time. I
						want to get our students to recognize that the script is alive and subject
						to multiple interpretations. This can be demonstrated by showing how
						portraying a minor aspect of the play from different perspectives will
						change the resonance of the play for today’s audience, while remaining true
						to the integrity of the text.</p>
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="2">
					<head>On the Margins of <title level="m">The Belle’s Stratagem</title></head>

					<p n="6">While <title level="m">The Belle’s Stratagem</title> is set firmly in
						the fashionable society of late eighteenth-century <name ref="London"
							>London</name>, and its style is reminiscent of <name ref="CowleyHannah"
							>Cowley</name>’s Restoration and Augustan predecessors, <name
							ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name>’s comedy demonstrates concerns about
						the laboring classes and their relationship to the moneyed elite. The title
						of <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name>’s comedy pays homage to one of her
						favorite Augustan playwrights, <name ref="FarquharGeorge">George
							Farquhar</name> (1677-1707), and his <title level="m">The Beaux’s
							Stratagem</title> (1707), and like many of these earlier comedies,
							<title level="m">The Belle’s Stratagem</title> juxtaposes two story
						lines: Letitia Hardy’s ingenious plot to win the heart of her betrothed,
						Doricourt, against the marital problems of jealous Sir George Touchwood and
						his wife, the naïve Lady Frances. Both plots concern men learning to respect
						the women in their lives both before and after marriage, and are further
						connected by questions regarding the nature and fluidity of identity.
						Interwoven with these plots are transitional scenes among servants,
						tradesmen and con artists who make their livings off the excesses of
						fashionable life.</p>
					<p n="7">The title plot revolves around Letitia Hardy and her fiancé Doricourt,
						who have been engaged since childhood, but who have not seen each other in
						years. Doricourt, back from his tour of the continent, has returned to <name
							ref="London">London</name> as its most fashionable and seemingly
						eligible bachelor. Abroad, he has learned to appreciate continental beauty
						and manners and he disparages Englishwomen (much to the disgust of his good
						friend, Saville). Letitia finds herself captivated by the man Doricourt has
						become, but dashed by his apparent indifference to her. She vows to “win his
						heart or never be his wife.”<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="2">
							<name ref="CowleyHannah">Hannah Cowley</name>, <title level="m">The
								Belle’s Stratagem </title> (1780), in <name ref="FinbergMelindaC"
								>Melinda C. Finberg</name>, <title level="m">Eighteenth-Century
								Women Dramatists </title> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2001),
							225 (1.4.145). All citations from play taken from this volume. </note>
						Her stratagem, as she confides to her doting father and her cousin, Mrs.
						Racket, is based on the maxim that it is “easier to convert a sentiment into
						its opposite than to transform indifference into tender passion” (p. 227
						[1.4.225-26]). Letitia plans to disgust Doricourt by posing as an ignorant,
						vulgar rustic and later to enchant him in masquerade as a cosmopolitan lady
						of mystery. In many ways, this plot is a reversal of <name
							ref="GoldsmithOliver">Goldsmith</name>’s <title level="m">She Stoops to
							Conquer</title>, in which Kate Hardcastle wins her lover by abasing
						herself. Kate is building up the confidence of a man too insecure to address
						women of his own class; Letitia, on the other hand, cuts Doricourt down to
						size and makes him acknowledge his own naïveté. </p>
					<p n="8"><name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name>’s secondary story line is a
						retelling of the Pinchwife plot of <name ref="WycherleyWilliam"
							>Wycherley</name>’s <title level="m">The Country Wife</title>. Sir
						George Touchwood, a man of the world and former avowed bachelor, has married
						the lovely but sheltered Lady Frances. He has been compelled to bring her to
							<name ref="London">London</name> to be presented at court, but aspires
						to keep her all to himself and away from the pernicious pleasures of the
						town that once made up his own life. While Sir George lacks Pinchwife’s
						overt cruelty, <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> uses his character to
						question whether jealousy and the concomitant infantilization of the beloved
						is not cruelty in and of itself. <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name>’s
						character Courtall, a rewrite of <name ref="WycherleyWilliam"
							>Wycherley</name>’s Horner, the man out to seduce the naïve bride, is a
						rake in the wrong century. His seduction plots backfire and sexual
						humiliation is his to receive, not to inflict.</p>
					<p n="9">Bridging the two stories are Mrs. Racket, a merry widow, and Villers, a
						debonair bachelor – a witty sophisticated pair who egg on the mischief, and
						each other – as well as Flutter, a gossipy fop who can be counted on to get
						every story wrong, and loyal Saville, Doricourt’s best friend, who still
						pines for Lady Frances.</p>
					<p n="10">The major plots of <title level="m">The Belle’s Stratagem </title>can
						be staged as an effervescent confection – fast-paced, intricately
						choreographed and filled with sparkling repartée. The transitional scenes
						ground the plot by revealing the sordid underpinnings of frivolous
						fashionable life. <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> gives us our first
						glimpse of laboring life in the second scene of the comedy, among
						Doricourt’s servants. A tabloid reporter bribes Doricourt’s porter for
						information on any romantic liaisons involving his quasi-celebrity master.
						They dicker over the value of the porter’s possible information. Their
						tète-á-tète is interrupted by the entrance of a horde of servants and
						tradesmen, who have bribed Doricourt’s valet for a view of the gentleman’s
							<foreign>haute couture</foreign> Parisian fashions with an eye to copy
						them for their masters and customers. Later there is a scene between an
						auctioneer and his shills. These lower-class hirelings pose as people of
						fashion, bidding on items to help drive up the prices. </p>
					<p n="11">Each of these scenes serves as a precursor to the later grand
						masquerade. Below stairs at Doricourt’s and at the auction house, we see the
						lower classes masquerading as the elite for various motives. In the first,
						they are creating a parallel world to those of the upper classes: just as
						Doricourt is preparing to attend the king’s levée and people of high fashion
						hang around the court to stay current on the latest gossip and trends, so
						the servants and the less socially prominent attend the households and
						servants of the fashionable. At the auction house, the auctioneer, Mr.
						Silvertongue, prepares his “puffers” to drive up the bids at the upcoming
						sale. He coaches them on jargon and the details of artists and items and he
						criticizes their clothing. They must appear like people of fashion to fool
						people of fashion. A female puffer complains Silvertongue doesn’t pay her
						enough to afford appropriate clothes and they argue about wages, comparing
						them to soldier’s wages. The behind-the-scenes scrapping reminds the
						audience that <name ref="London">London</name>’s fashionable life is based
						on a teetering economy: everyone at the auction is there to ogle or buy
						items seized to settle debts of those financially ruined by gambling and
						extravagance. </p>
					<p n="12">These scenes stand out from the general effervescence with their ugly
						glimpses of the economic realities behind the glamour. They have grit. They
						rub our noses into the fact that this is a society of many degrees of haves
						and have-nots. And some of these have-nots are finding and taking every
						opportunity to exploit their oblivious masters. They call our attention to
						the cannibalistic nature of this society, as we watch different classes prey
						upon each other and even on the remains of members of their own class who
						have fallen into financial ruin.</p>
					<p n="13">These transitional scenes present us with dramaturgical choices: how
						much attention should they be given in comparison to the scenes of the major
						action? Are they casual moments the audience catches in passing, or are they
						moments that deliberately stop the forward motion of the plot? How much do
						they infiltrate or color our perception of the fashionable society that
						dominates the plot? In some productions, historically as well as today, they
						are cut entirely.</p>
					<p n="14">There is no right or wrong answer, but whatever choice we make will
						color the audience’s understanding of the text. We can compare a dramatic
						work to a diamond: letting different facets catch the light changes our view
						of the stone itself – its color, its reflective capacities, even its beauty.
						In teaching a play, examining several of the different facets and their
						coloring of the interpretation of the piece will give students a richer
						understanding of how a dramatic text comes to life.</p>
					<p n="15">Furthermore, to understand the possible choices, we will need to
						encourage our students to do multidisciplinary research. In the case of
							<title level="m">The Belle’s Stratagem</title>, such research will
						involve cultural and economic history of the period. What did the people
						look like? Who are the servants to the upper classes? What are their
						backgrounds? What was a levée? How is a levée being parodied? What were the
						gossip columns of the day like? How do they compare to today’s tabloids?
						What was the role of the auction houses? What was being auctioned? Where and
						how did classes mix? There are so many topics that could be explored to shed
						light on the life the play assumes its audience will know that it is
						impossible for a teacher to cover them all in a class. One possible way to
						involve students in unearthing the social assumptions of the play would be
						to have them do individual reports or papers on different topics and then
						share them with the whole class. Once everyone has a substantial background
						in the social world of the play, discussions can take place about how to
						incorporate this new understanding into the staging of the play. </p>
					<p n="16">To demonstrate how a class might go about this process, I will use the
						example of one marginal character within <title level="m">Belle’s
							Stratagem</title> and the questions that are raised by <name
							ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name>’s employment of her. Kitty Willis comes
						to play an important role in one of <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name>’s
						major plots, although Kitty has very few lines. Courtall, the supposed rake,
						has taunted Saville, Doricourt’s best friend, over Saville’s chaste passion
						for Lady Frances Touchwood. Saville insults Courtall by casting doubts on
						Courtall’s self-proclaimed successes with women. An enraged Courtall plots
						his revenge by planning to deceive and abduct Lady Frances at the
						masquerade, but Saville gets wind of the plan and decides to outplot the
						plotter. Saville confides in Doricourt that he has found a woman “whose
						reputation cannot be hurt” (p. 256, [4.1.155]) to masquerade as Lady Frances
						and deceive Courtall. That woman is Kitty Willis. This is the only
						description we are given of Kitty. As <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam"
							>Shakespeare</name> would say, “The rest is silence.” (<title level="m"
							>Hamlet</title>, 5.2.360) But for drama to live, the silence has to be
						filled. How do we discover how to fill it?</p>
				</div>



				<div type="section" n="3">
					<head>Staging the Prostitute</head>
					<epigraph>
						<quote>
							<ab>Oh… to be Hamlet! Ahhh …to be Juliet! To be St. Joan, or Eliza
								Doolittle, or ’Enry ’Iggins for the few hours allotted by the
								playwright! If you really want to be, you’d better know who you are
								when the play begins, and how you got to be that way!</ab>
							<ab rend="#indent8">
								<bibl><name ref="HagenUta">Uta Hagen</name>, <title level="m"
										>Respect for Acting</title></bibl>
								<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="3"><name ref="HagenUta">Uta
										Hagen</name>, <title level="m">Respect for Acting</title>
									(New York: Macmillan Publishing Co., Inc. 1977), 152.</note>
							</ab>
						</quote>
					</epigraph>

					<epigraph>
						<quote>
							<ab>The purpose of analysis should be to study in detail and prepare
								given circumstances for a play or part so that through them, later
								on in the creative process, the actor’s emotions will instinctively
								be sincere and his feelings true to life.</ab>
							<ab rend="#indent8">
								<bibl><name ref="StanislavskiConstantin">Constantin
										Stanislavski</name>, <title level="m">Creating a
										Role</title></bibl>
								<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="4">
									<name ref="StanislavskiConstantin">Constantin
										Stanislavski</name>, <title level="m">Creating a
										Role</title>, Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood, trans. (New York:
									Theatre Arts Books, 1961), 9. </note>
							</ab>
						</quote>
					</epigraph>
					<p n="17"> To understand how to teach our students how to approach the dramatic
						text as the framework for a performance, I suggest starting with the
						language of theater practitioners. One of the first tasks a director, actor,
						designer, or dramaturg undertakes when beginning to work with a script is to
						to determine the “given circumstances” of the text or of an individual
						character. These “given circumstances” are the facts the author has provided
						for us through the words and actions of the play. They are the theater
						artist’s point of departure in analyzing the text, and they will vary
						depending on whether one is examining one specific character or the entire
						play. One character’s given circumstances will differ from another’s by
						virtue of what the character <emph>knows</emph> about the rest of the plot
						or characters, as well as who the character <emph>is</emph>. Differences
						about what each character knows are often the basis of comedy and farce.
						Differences about who characters are provide depth and variety to the life
						of the play. </p>
					<p n="18"> What are Kitty Willis’s given circumstances? <name ref="CowleyHannah"
							>Cowley</name> provides us with minimal information. Kitty: <list
							type="bulleted">
							<item>has a distinctive, diminutive name.</item>
							<item>is a woman whose reputation cannot be hurt.</item>
							<item>doesn’t believe many women can sustain a character of virtue
								throughout a masquerade.</item>
							<item>is not believed by Saville to know much about women of
								virtue.</item>
							<item>is in the plot for reward.</item>
							<item>is able to deceive Courtall into believing she is Lady
								Frances.</item>
							<item>is immediately recognized by all the men when she unmasks in
								Courtall’s rooms.</item>
							<item>is addressed merely as “Kitty” by the men.</item>
							<item>teases Courtall about his former adoration of her.</item>
						</list> From these given circumstances, we must make deductions and begin
						our research.</p>
					<p n="19"> Kitty appears to be a publicly known woman whose reputation seems to
						be beyond being able to be damaged, written by a publicly known woman who
						was always having to defend her respectability from damage. (By 1780 women
						novelists could be respectable, while actresses were still considered not
						much better than prostitutes. As a playwright, <name ref="CowleyHannah"
							>Cowley</name> found herself in disputed territory: did the public
						confer upon her the respectability of the novelist or the opprobrium of the
						actress/prostitute? Although she asserted her respectability – even when
						writing the words of disreputable characters – critics challenged “whether
						Mrs. <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> ought so to have expressed
							herself?”)<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="5">
							<name ref="CowleyHannah">Hannah Cowley</name>, <title level="m">A School
								for Greybeards; or, the Mourning Bride</title> (London: G. G. J.
							&amp; J. Robinson, 1786), Preface vii. In this preface, <name
								ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> defends herself from attacks from
							her critics based not on her talent and the realism of her character
							creations, but on her gender and whether she should write such
							characters so well. <name ref="ToddJanet">Janet Todd</name> (in <title
								level="m">The Sign of Angellica: Women, Writing and Fiction, 1660 –
								1800 </title>(New York: Columbia University Press, 1989) traces the
							woman writer’s concern with being a public woman, and thus being equated
							with the disreputable prostitute, back to <name ref="BehnAphra">Aphra
								Behn</name>’s character of Angellica Bianca, in <title level="m">The
								Rover</title>, who hangs her picture with her price outside her door
							and tries to claim the same sexual freedom as men. </note> Kitty’s very
						name suggests animality, sexuality and lack of will. Her circumstances
						suggest that she is some kind of prostitute, courtesan, or actress, but what
						kind? Research into the topic of eighteenth-century British prostitution
						yields many different possible answers to this question, each of which
						provides us with different approaches to staging Kitty. Any production must
						make one strong choice about Kitty and allow that choice to influence the
						staging of her relationships with each of the characters she encounters,
						including the effect her presence brings to the central masquerade scene. </p>
					<p n="20">During the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, prostitution was the
						subject of much public debate and fascination. It not only played a part in
						many of the novels of the day, but prostitute narratives, purported to be
						the true histories or memoirs of real prostitutes and courtesans,
						proliferated and were vastly popular. In her recent study, <title level="m"
							>Infamous Commerce: Prostitution in Eighteenth-Century British
							Literature and Culture</title>, <name ref="RosenthalLaura">Laura
							Rosenthal</name> points out that these novels and narratives took
						primarily two different approaches to the profession. The first took the
						form of libertine narrative in which a woman rises through her labors to
						fame (or infamy) and fortune. There is a quality of entrepreneurship to her
						profession and ownership of her body. Such narratives describe a woman
						rising from the brothel to the life of celebrity as a courtesan; sometimes
						they show her fall back into degradation and poverty, but still she remains
						a sympathetic representative of upward mobility, using what she has to
							succeed.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="6"> For this discussion of
							prostitute narratives, I am indebted to <name ref="RosenthalLaura">Laura
								J. Rosenthal</name>, <title level="m">Infamous Commerce:
								Prostitution in Eighteenth-Century British Culture and Fiction
							</title>(Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2006), 97-105. Future
							references are cited in the text. </note>
					</p>
					<p n="21"> The second type of prostitution narrative shows the prostitute as
						tragic victim. She is driven by economic necessity to degradation and her
						feelings are sentimentalized. As one such writer describes, <quote>There are
							not perhaps on Earth greater Objects of Compassion; all Sense of
							Pleasure are lost to them, the whole is mere Labour and Wretchedness,
							they are Slaves to, and buffeted by every drunken Ruffian, they are the
							Tools of, and tryrannized over by the Imps of Bawds.<note place="foot"
								resp="editors" n="7">
								<title level="m">The Vices of the Cities of <name ref="London"
										>London</name> and <name ref="Westminster"
										>Westminster</name></title>, (Dublin: Printed for G.
								Faulkner and R. James, 1751), 21-22. </note>
						</quote> This sentimental view was pervasive in the mid-eighteenth century,
						as is evident in the wide public support given to the founding, in 1758, of
						the famous <name ref="London">London</name> Magdalen Hospital for Penitent
						Prostitutes, dedicated to restoring these victimized women to their natural
							virtue.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="8"> For a full discussion of
							the founding of Magdalen Hospital and the varying views of its inmates,
							see <name ref="PeaceMary">Mary Peace</name>, “The Magdalen Hospital and
							the Fortunes of Whiggish Sentimentality in Mid-Eighteenth-Century
							Britain: ‘Well-Grounded’ Exemplarity vs. ‘Romantic’ Exceptionality” in
								<title level="m">The Eighteenth Century: Theory and
								Interpretation</title> 8.2 (Summer 2007): 125-148. </note></p>

					<p n="22">That two seemingly disparate views of prostitution could be held
						synchronously reflected the ambivalence with which the British viewed the
						institution. Contemporary travel writer <name ref="ArcheholzJW">J. W.
							Archeholz</name> commented in his <title level="m">A Picture of England:
							Containing a Description of the Laws, Customs, and Manners</title>, that
						the British had no real stake in ending prostitution. While English laws
						“are not favourable to the fair sex,” successful prostitutes enjoy
						independence and add glamour to <name ref="London">London</name>.<note
							place="foot" resp="editors" n="9">
							<name ref="ArcheholzJW">J. W. Archeholz</name>, <title level="m">A
								Picture of England: Containing a Description of the Laws, Customs,
								and Manners, </title>(London: Edward Jeffrey, 1789) 2:90, as quoted
							in <name ref="RosenthalLaura">Rosenthal</name>, 99. </note> While social
						reformers might call attention to the degraded streetwalker, abandoned by
						her family to the horrors of poverty and violence, the courtesans of the day
						were the objects of insatiable voyeurism, much like celebrities in our
						tabloids today. <name ref="HogarthWilliam">Hogarth</name> painted the former
						in his scenes of <name ref="London">London</name> life; <name
							ref="ReynoldsJoshuaSir">Reynolds</name> glorified the latter.</p>
					<p n="23">In fact <name ref="ReynoldsJoshuaSir">Sir Joshua Reynolds</name>
						painted several magnificent portraits of Kitty Fisher (d. 1767), who may
						have been the namesake of Kitty Willis. Kitty Fisher was one of the most
						famous courtesans of the 1760’s and a great favorite of <name
							ref="ReynoldsJoshuaSir">Reynolds</name>. <figure n="1">
							<figDesc>Reynolds, Joshua. <title level="m">Kitty Fisher as Cleopatra
									Dissolving the Pearl</title> (1759), “Painted Ladies,” <title
									level="m">Reynold: Joshua Reynolds and The Creation of
									Celebrity</title>. Tate Online.
								http://www.tate.org.uk/britain/exhibitions/reynolds/roomguide7.shtm</figDesc>
							<graphic url="../images/reynolds-fisher.jpg"/>
						</figure>
						<name ref="HoneNathaniel">Nathaniel Hone</name> also painted her in 1765 in
						a portrait which made a visual pun on her name.  In <ref target="http://www.npg.org.uk/collections/search/portrait/mw02230/Catherine-Maria-Kitty-Fisher">Hone’s portrait of Kitty Fisher</ref>, he seats her next to a kitten trying to fish a goldfish out of its
						bowl. Kitty had begun her career as an actress, but found more lucrative
						work and celebrity as a courtesan. Her narrative reflects the typical view
						of both reformers and libertine writers that some young women believed their
						beauty and accomplishments made them eligible to rise socially and turned to
						prostitution as a business to make the most of their talents. Kitty Fisher
						was one of those who succeeded.</p>
					<p n="24"><name ref="HogarthWilliam">Hogarth</name>, on the other hand,
						portrayed <title level="m">The Harlot’s Progress</title> in a series of
						paintings dating from 1732 in which the painter satirizes <name ref="London"
							>London</name> corruption by tracing the history of a young country girl
						who is accosted by a bawd upon her arrival in <name ref="London"
							>London</name> to seek work. She rises as high as a kept mistress, but
						then is reduced to a common prostitute, an inmate in debtor’s prison, and
						finally she dies of venereal disease. Such a degraded woman is also
						described by <title level="j">The Spectator</title>: <quote>I could observe
							as exact Features as I had ever seen, the most agreeable Shape, the
							finest Neck and Bosom, in a Word, the whole Person of a Woman
							exquisitely beautiful. She affected to allure me with a forced
							Wantonness in her Look and Air; but I saw it checked with Hunger and
							Cold: Her eyes were wan and eager, her Dress thin and Tawdry, her Mein
							genteel and childish. This strange Figure gave me much Anguish of Heart,
							and to avoid being seen with her I went away, but could nor forbear
							giving her a Crown. The poor thing sighed, curtsied, and with a
							Blessing, expressed with the utmost Vehemence, turned from me.<note
								place="foot" n="10"> Joseph Addison and Richard Steele, <title
									level="j">The Spectator,</title> ed. Donald F. Bond, 2:534 – 535; no. 266, Friday, January 4, 1712. </note>
						</quote>
					</p>
					<lb/>
					<figure n="3">
						<figDesc>Hogarth, William. <title level="m">Harlot’s Progress: Scene in
								Bridewell</title>, 1732. British Museum, The Image Gallery, Data
							from University of California, San Diego. </figDesc>
						<graphic url="../images/hogarth-harlot.jpg"/>
					</figure>

					<p n="25"> Even some of the libertine narratives show how the most successful
						and celebrated courtesan can be vulnerable to a fall into want, degradation,
						and decrepitude. “Simon Trusty” wrote a public letter to Kitty Fisher
						herself to warn her of such a possibility:</p>
					<quote>
						<ab>You, Madam, are become the Favourite of the Public and the Darling of
							the Age…Your Lovers are the Great Ones of the Earth, and your Admirers
							among the Mighty: they never approach you but, like <emph>Jove</emph>,
							in a Shower of Gold….</ab><lb/>
						<ab>Say, Madam, for surely Experience inables [<emph>sic</emph>] you to do
							it, what Satisfaction there is in receiving to your Arms one you
							secretly loathe; the very Reflection makes you sigh: You press him to a
							joyless Bosom; the Night is tedious and irksome; the Morning comes to
							your Deliverance, and finds you dejected, and that Eye which should be
							filled with Joy, ready to start with a Tear….</ab><lb/>
						<ab> Tell me then, in the Name of Beauty tell me! Was that fair Form made
							for Pollution, for the ruffian Embrace of the Great Vulgar, and, ’ere
							long, perhaps, of the Small? To be for a While what
								<emph>Shakespeare</emph> calls</ab>
						<quote>
							<emph>The cull’d Darling of the World,</emph>
						</quote>
						<ab>And, at last, the hackneyed Prostitute of every Passenger?<note
								place="foot" resp="editors" n="11">
								<name ref="TrustySimon">Simon Trusty</name>. <title level="m">An odd
									letter, on a most interesting subject, to Miss K---- F--h--r.
									Recommended to the perusal of the ladies of Great Britain. By
										<name ref="TrustySimon">Simon Trusty</name>, Esq.</title>
								(London, 1760), <title level="s">Eighteenth Century Collections
									Online</title>, Gale Group,
								http://galenet.galegroup.com/servlet/ECCO . Gale Document
									Number:<hi> </hi>CW3305850508 </note></ab>
					</quote>
					<p> So into which of these categories will we place Kitty Willis? Is she a
						well-known courtesan? A former courtesan or kept woman, known to all the men
						as last season’s fashionable face, but now down on her luck? Is she
						destitute and desperate? Or is she an actress? And once we have decided what
						kind of public woman she is, how will we stage her and how will she fit into
						the ensemble of other characters?</p>
					<p n="26"> As is typical of many skilled dramatists, <name ref="CowleyHannah"
							>Cowley</name> provides us with information that can be interpreted in a
						number of ways. On the one hand, Kitty’s name recalls the late famous <name
							ref="FisherKitty">Kitty Fisher</name>, but on the other hand, another
						famed “Kitty” was the great actress <name ref="CliveKitty">Kitty
							Clive</name> (1711-85). Both <name ref="FisherKitty">Kitty Fisher</name>
						and <name ref="CliveKitty">Kitty Clive</name> were well-known celebrities
						and women of wit, intelligence and ambition, but <name ref="CowleyHannah"
							>Cowley</name>’s Kitty is “Willis” or perhaps, “will-less,” that is
						without inner strength or ambition, a woman who has simply “fallen” into her
						line of work because of her lack of discipline or fortitude. <name
							ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> even makes a subtle allusion to the
						desperation of this latter kind of prostitute when she has the fop Flutter
						entertain Lady Frances with the description of a family at the masquerade:
							<quote>In the next apartment there’s a whole family, who, to my
							knowledge, have lived on watercresses this month to make a figure here
							tonight; but, to make up for that, they’ll cram their pockets with cold
							ducks and chickens for a carnival tomorrow. (4.1.82-86)</quote>
						<name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> here alludes to Henry Fielding’s
						poetic description in his <title level="m">The Masquerade</title>: <quote>
							<lg>
								<l>Below stairs hungry whores are picking</l>
								<l>The bones of wild-fowl and of chicken;</l>
								<l>And into pockets some convey</l>
								<l>Provisions for another day.<note place="foot" resp="editors"
										n="12"><name ref="FieldingHenry">Henry Fielding</name>,
											<title level="m">The Masquerade</title> (London, 1728.
										Reprinted in <name ref="FieldingHenry">Henry
										Fielding</name>, <title level="m">The Female Husband and
											Other Writings,</title> ed. Claude E. Jones, English
										Reprint Series, 1960), p. 32 (lines 191-94).</note>
								</l>
							</lg>
						</quote> Might Kitty be a desperate woman eager to take this job for the
						free food at the masquerade, like the provident family and hungry whores, in
						addition to her pay for the deception at Courtall’s?</p>
					<p n="27">And how precisely do the men “know” Kitty? They are all on familiar
						enough terms with her to address her simply as “Kitty,” when they discover
						her in Courtall’s rooms, while they address none of the women of their own
						class so informally. Is she communal property? As a whore or as a celebrity?
						Is there anything particular about her relationship with Courtall that might
						add to her enjoyment of the joke? </p>
					<p n="28">Again, I reiterate, there is no one right answer to this question,
						only choices – although some choices are more interesting than others. These
						are more places where <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> is silent and
						where the script must be fleshed out. This is where actors and directors
						ask, “What if?” What if Courtall was Kitty’s original seducer? Or what if he
						had formerly kept her? How would such possibilities contribute to deepening
						Courtall’s sense of humiliation in mistaking Kitty for Lady Frances when he
						has her in his bedroom? What would such an interpretation add to the
						significance of Kitty’s line to Courtall after he has damned those present
						for humiliating him, “What! Me, too, Mr. Courtall? Me, whom you have knelt
						to, prayed to, and adored?” (4.2.61-62). Is Kitty just adding to the banter
						or is she getting her own revenge?</p>
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="4">
					<head>Applying Dramaturgical Theory</head>
					<p n="29">When staging a performance of <title level="m">Belle’s
							Stratagem</title>, one has to make one choice and commit to it. All
						further choices build upon those that have gone before. How should Kitty be
						costumed? If she is wearing a domino, as <name ref="CowleyHannah"
							>Cowley</name> describes, do we see her own clothes under it when she
						unmasks? If so, will they be the equivalent of the society women’s we have
						seen. More ornate? Will they be shabby or dirty? Who is revealed when Kitty
						unmasks? A proud woman of the world or one closer to the prostitute
						described by the uncomfortable <title level="j">Spectator</title> on an
						evening in the early part of the century? Kitty’s unmasking prefigures
						Letitia’s unmasking at the conclusion of the play. How do they connect to
						each other? </p>
					<figure n="4">
						<figDesc>Cooper, David, photographer. Kitty Willis (Aisha Kabia) taunts
							Courtall (Mirron E. Willis), <title level="m">The Belle’s
								Stratagem</title>, Oregon Shakespeare Festival, 2005. </figDesc>
						<graphic width="600px" url="../images/kitty's_revenge.jpg"/>
					</figure>

					<p n="30">Understanding who prostitutes were in the <name ref="London"
							>London</name> of the late eighteenth century as well as understanding
						who the women of high society were and what was expected of them, gives
						students a grasp of the visceral reaction an audience would have to seeing
						both respectable and disreputable women in the same public place or
						confusing them. It calls their attention to questions the play is raising
						about how women are categorized and about the fluidity of anyone’s identity.
						When <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> dresses Sir George, Lady
						Frances, Courtall, and Kitty in interchangeable costumes, she suggests with
						the different pairings that result in the course of the ball, the ease with
						which the rake can be confused with the devoted husband and the harlot with
						the virtuous wife. Does Kitty becomes Leah to Lady Frances’s Rachel, sisters
						under the veil, in some ways indistinguishable? Does Courtall’s inability to
						distinguish between the masked Kitty Willis and Lady Frances reflect on
						Doricourt’s inability to distinguish the real Letitia behind her many masks?
						If so, how?</p>
					<p n="31">When teaching the play in class, however, I advocate exploring as many
						of the choices as time permits. Asking our students to look at a variety of
						perspectives increases their understanding of a play as a living art. Each
						choice is an interpretation of the play. How do we come to see how examining
						a particular facet of a play from a particular angle reflects throughout the
						whole gem of the play? How do we consciously lead an audience to view a play
						based on a particular interpretation? For this, I recommend further readings
						about the art of dramaturgy and ideas and theories about how to connect
						audiences with classic productions.</p>
					<p n="32">One of the best texts for introducing students to dramaturgy as a
						discipline is <title level="m">Dramaturgy in American Theater: A Source
							Book</title>, a collection of essays on various aspects and uses of
						dramaturgical theory and practice. Selected essays from the section entitled
						“New Contexts” are especially appropriate for teachers and students of
						Romantic Drama. In her essay, “Aiming the Canon at Now: Strategies for
						Adaptation,” <name ref="JonasSusan">Susan Jonas</name> examines “how
						theatermakers can employ the canon to <hi>reveal</hi> its own biases” <note
							place="foot" resp="editors" n="13">
							<name ref="JonasSusan">Susan Jonas</name>, “Aiming the Canon at Now:
							Strategies for Adaptation,” in <name ref="JonasSusan">Susan
							Jonas</name>, Geoffrey Proehl, and Michael Lupu, <title level="m"
								>Dramaturgy in American Theater: A Source Book.</title> (Orlando,
							FL: Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1997), 244. Future references are cited
							in the text. </note>(emphasis hers). One technique <name
							ref="JonasSusan">Jonas</name> suggests to amplify marginalized voices
						from an historical text is one she terms “simultaneity” (255). Simultaneity
						refers to seeing a silenced aspect of the play at the same time as the play
						proceeds as scripted. Such a technique encourages the audience to view the
						play from the perspective of the less-privileged characters and thus
						critically comments on the actions of the central characters and expands our
						understanding of the world of the play. I will use this technique to suggest
						one possible way of exploring <title level="m">Belle’s Stratagem</title>
						dramaturgically. </p>
					<p n="33">While there are several scenes of lower-class characters used as
						transitions in <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name>’s comedy, there are
						also public scenes for which little description is provided. The play opens
						with Saville arriving with his servant at Lincoln’s Inn, one of the inns of
						court where lawyers keep offices. Courtall describes the place as “the most
						private place in town” (1.1.39-40) of a morning because no fashionable
						person would be seen there – unless on legal business. But Lincoln’s Inn is
						inhabited by lawyers, their families, their servants and their clients.
						People indeed may be coming and going during the scene, just not people of
						high society. Saville begins the scene at a loss for where to go and is
						talking with his servant before he sees Courtall. What if before he sees
						Courtall, the audience sees Courtall being accosted by or in conversation
						with Kitty – perhaps trying to extricate himself from her; perhaps giving
						her money? If we have made the choice that Kitty has seen better days, how
						will this contribute to their later confrontation? There is nothing in the
						script to prevent such a meeting. Might Courtall be a poseur? Are his
						vaunted relationships with “women of quality” really only assignations with
						prostitutes or seductions of young girls? How might such a choice play out
						over the production? Or is Kitty some relic from his past? Is he in her
						debt? Does he owe her money? No dialogue needs to be spoken, yet questions
						can be raised in the audience’s mind. </p>
					<p n="34">Other public scenes include the auction and the masquerade. Are there
						possibilities for simultaneous actions in any of these? <name
							ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> provides dialogue for the auctioneer
						and his puffers before the gentry enter, yet she doesn’t account for the
						actions of the shills once the fashionable characters arrive. What are they
						doing? Are they interacting? Pickpocketing? Are they successful in
						impersonating the visitors? Does Kitty Willis make an appearance? Is she the
						celebrated, wealthy courtesan, shunned by the women but fawned over by the
						men? Or is she, like the puffers, trying to appear fashionable, but coming
						up short? Does she make any connection with Courtall here? If so, what kind?
						What about the masquerade? What is Kitty’s relationship to Saville? Is he
						hiring an impoverished whore, a moderately successful one, a kept woman, or
						a courtesan out for a lark? Do we recognize any of the servants or tradesmen
						at the masquerade? Is the tabloid writer lurking there (or at the auction,
						for that matter)? Simultaneous actions fill in the world of the play.</p>
					<p n="35">Other possible dramaturgical approaches might be to create framing
						devices or to utilize Brechtian alienation techniques. In the first
						transitional scene in the play, <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> shows
						us servants and tradespeople actively observing and feeding off the lives of
						the fashionable. Might these working-class people observe, judge and/or
						profit from their masters throughout the play? Might they be watching
						everything from the sidelines or margins? Might we see their reactions to
						the stratagems and counter-stratagems of those who live the high life? <name
							ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> embeds many metatheatrical elements
						within the comedy of various characters performing for others. Could we
						expand on the metatheatrics and create a variation of the Shakespearean
						conceit of one set of characters watching and reacting to another set
						performing a play for them? When she is not part of the action, could Kitty
						be watching and forming her own judgments that color her responses within
						her scenes? </p>
					<p n="36">Might some, or all, of the actors be playing their lines to the
						audience by calling attention to their own judgment of the characters? This
						type of approach deliberately distances the audience from the action of the
						play rather than draws it into a suspension of disbelief. It is part of the
						technique <name ref="BrechtBertolt">Bertolt Brecht</name> uses to create
						what he calls the “alienation effect,” and its purpose is to call attention
						to the economic, political and class issues inherent in a dramatic text.
							<name ref="BrechtBertolt">Brecht</name> does not want the audience to
						“feel” for the characters so much as to “think” about them and the
						significance of what they do. <name ref="BrechtBertolt">Brecht</name> lays
						forth his theories in <title level="m">The Messingkauf Dialogues.</title>
						<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="14"><name ref="BrechtBertolt">Bertolt
								Brecht</name>, <title level="m">The Messingkauf Dialogues
							</title>(London: Methuen, Ltd., 1965).</note> A useful assignment to
						help students understand how Brechtian theory can be applied to historical
						drama, is to have them read and compare <name ref="GayJohn">John
						Gay</name>’s <title level="m">The Beggar’s Opera</title> (1728) to <name
							ref="BrechtBertolt">Brecht</name>’s adaptation of it, <title level="m"
							>The Threepenny Opera</title> (1928). What if the actress playing Kitty
						plays her as if she is an observer commenting on her character and the
						actions of the scene in Brechtian fashion?</p>
					<p n="37">All of the questions I have suggested derive from the initial question
						of how to stage the character of Kitty Willis, a character who appears in
						only two scenes of <title level="m">The Belle’s Stratagem</title> and who
						only speaks five lines in those scenes, and yet the choices we make about
						this character color the interpretation of the entire play. Such
						dramaturgical questions must be asked about every character and every scene
						in every production of a dramatic text, and so infinite interpretations are
						possible and valid. Each staging must simply be consistent within itself. </p>
					<p n="38">Teaching our students to approach Romantic Drama dramaturgically
						teaches them to work in a multidisciplinary fashion and create a dynamic
						relationship with the text. It encourages them to perform primary research
						into the period and to track down images, music and cultural artifacts of
						the period, including gossip columns, broadsides, and other records of
						popular culture. Understanding what connected and still connects an audience
						to a play helps them to make personal connections as well. Our goal is to
						help students see Romantic Drama as a multi-faceted art form as alive and
						open to interpretation today as it was two hundred years ago.</p>
				</div>

			</div>
			<div type="citations">
				<head>Bibliography/Suggested Reading</head>
				<listBibl>
					<biblStruct xml:id="JARS">
						<monogr>
							<author>Addison, Joseph</author>
							<author>Steele, Richard</author>
							<title level="m">The Spectator</title>
							<editor role='editor'>Bond, Donald F.</editor>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
								<date>1965</date>
							</imprint>
							<extent>5 vols</extent>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Archenholz, J[ohann] W[ilhelm von]</author>
							<title level="m">A Picture of England: Containing a Description of the
								Laws, Customs, and Manners of England</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Edward Jeffrey</publisher>
								<date>1789</date>
							</imprint>
							<extent>2 vols</extent>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Brecht, Berthold</author>
							<title level="m">The Messingkauf Dialogues</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Methuen</publisher>
								<date>1965</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Castle, Terry</author>
							<title level="m">Masquerade and Civilization: The Carnivalesque in
								Eighteenth-Century English Culture and Fiction</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Stanford UP</publisher>
								<date>1986</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Cattaneo, Anne</author>
							<title level="a">Dramaturgy, An Overview</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<ref target="#JPL"/>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="pp">3-15</biblScope>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Cowley, Hannah</author>
							<title level="m">The Belle’s Stratagem</title>
							<title level="m">Eighteenth-Century Women Dramatists</title>
							<editor role='editor'>Finberg, Melinda C</editor>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
								<date>2001</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Defoe, Daniel</author>
							<title level="m">Roxana</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
								<date>1964</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Fielding, Henry</author>
							<title level="m">The Masquerade</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
								<date>1728</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
						<relatedItem type="otherEdition">
							<biblStruct>
								<monogr>
									<title level="m">The Female Husband and Other Writings</title>
									<editor role='editor'>Jones, Claude E</editor>
									<imprint>
										<pubPlace>Liverpool</pubPlace>
										<date>1960</date>
									</imprint>
								</monogr>
								<series>
									<title level="s">English Reprint Series</title>
								</series>
							</biblStruct>
						</relatedItem>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Gay, John</author>
							<title level="m">The Beggar’s Opera</title>
							<editor role='editor'>Roberts, Edgar V.</editor>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>
								<publisher>U of Nebraska P</publisher>
								<date>1969</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Hagen, Uta</author>
							<title level="m">Respect for Acting</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Macmillan</publisher>
								<date>1977</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Jonas, Susan</author>
							<title level="a">Aiming the Canon at Now: Strategies for
								Adaptation</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<ref target="#JPL"/>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="pp">244-265</biblScope>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct xml:id="JPL">
						<monogr>
							<editor role='editor'>Jonas, Susan</editor>
							<editor role='editor'>Proehl, Geoffrey</editor>
							<editor role='editor'>Lupu, Michael</editor>
							<title level="m">Dramaturgy in American Theater: A Source Book</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Orlando, FL</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Harcourt Brace</publisher>
								<date>1997</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Mandeville, Bernard</author>
							<editor role='editor'>Cook, Richard I.</editor>
							<title level="m">A Modest Defence of the Public Stews</title>
							<edition>
								<date>1724</date>
							</edition>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Los Angeles</pubPlace>
								<publisher>William Andrews Clark Memorial Library</publisher>
								<date>1973</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Mazer, Cary M</author>
							<title level="a">Rebottling: Dramaturgs, Scholars, Old Plays, and Modern
								Directors</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<ref target="#JPL"/>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="pp">292-307</biblScope>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Peace, Mary</author>
							<title level="a">The Magdalen Hospital and the Fortunes of Whiggish
								Sentimentality in Mid-Eighteenth-Century Britain:
								&apos;Well-Grounded&apos; Exemplarity vs. &apos;Romantic&apos;
								Exceptionality</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<title level="j">The Eighteenth Century: Theory and
								Interpretation</title>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="vol">8</biblScope>
								<biblScope type="pp">125-48</biblScope>
								<biblScope type="no">2</biblScope>
								<date>Summer 2007</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Rosenthal, Laura J</author>
							<title level="m">Infamous Commerce: Prostitution in Eighteenth-Century
								British Literature and Culture</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>Ithaca</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Cornell UP</publisher>
								<date>2006</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Shakespeare, William</author>
							<title level="m">Hamlet</title>
							<title level="m">The Complete Signet Shakespeare</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Harcourt, Brace, Jovanovich</publisher>
								<date>1972</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Stanislavski, Constantin</author>
							<editor role="translator">Hapgood, Elizabeth Reynolds</editor>
							<title level="m">Creating a Role</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Theatre Arts Books</publisher>
								<date>1961</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<analytic>
							<author>Steele, Richard</author>
							<title level="a">No Vice or Wickedness</title>
						</analytic>
						<monogr>
							<title level="j">The Spectator</title>
							<imprint>
								<biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
								<biblScope type="no">266</biblScope>
								<date>Friday, January 4, 1712</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
						<relatedItem type="otherEdition">
							<biblStruct>
								<monogr>
									<ref target="#JARS"/>
									<imprint>
										<biblScope type="vol">[vol. #?]</biblScope>
										<biblScope type="pp">534–535</biblScope>
									</imprint>
								</monogr>
							</biblStruct>
						</relatedItem>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Todd, Janet</author>
							<title level="m">The Sign of Angellica: Women, Writing and Fiction,
								1660-1800</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
								<publisher>Columbia UP</publisher>
								<date>1989</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
					</biblStruct>
					<biblStruct>
						<monogr>
							<author>Trusty, Simon</author>
							<title level="m">An odd letter, on a most interesting subject, to Miss
								K---- F--h--r. Recommended to the perusal of the ladies of Great
								Britain. By Simon Trusty, Esq</title>
							<imprint>
								<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
								<date>1760</date>
							</imprint>
						</monogr>
						<relatedItem type="otherEdition">
							<biblStruct>
								<monogr>
									<title level="m">
										<ref target="http://galenet.galegroup.com/servlet/ECCO"
											>Eighteenth-Century Collections Online</ref>
									</title>
									<imprint>
										<publisher>Gale-Cengage Learning</publisher>
										<date type="update">n.d. </date>
										<date type="access">2010-12-09</date>
										<biblScope type="no">CW3305850508</biblScope>
									</imprint>
								</monogr>
							</biblStruct>
						</relatedItem>
					</biblStruct>
				</listBibl>
			</div>
			<!-- 
            <p>
               <hi>Illustrations </hi>(attached separately)</p>
            <p>Cooper, David, photographer. Kitty Willis (Aisha Kabia) taunts Courtall (Mirron E.
               Willis), <emph>The Belle’s Stratagem</emph>, Oregon <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name> Festival, 2005.</p>
            <p>Hogarth, William <emph>Harlot’s Progress: Scene in Bridewell</emph>, 1732. British
               Museum, The Image Gallery, Data from University of California, San Diego.</p>
            <p>Hone, Nathaniel. <emph>Catherine Maria (‘Kitty’</emph>)<emph> </emph>Fisher, 1765,
               National Picture Gallery, London (will need permission)</p>
            <p>Reynolds, Joshua. <emph>Kitty Fisher as Cleopatra Dissolving the Pearl</emph> (1759),
               “Painted Ladies,” <emph>Reynolds: Joshua Reynolds and The Creation of Celebrity.
               </emph>Tate Online.<emph
               > </emph>http://www.tate.org.uk/britain/exhibitions/reynolds/roomguide7.shtm</p> -->


		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
