<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Teaching British Romantic Drama: </title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Senior Seminar in Studies in Drama</title>
				<author>
					<name>Marjean D. Purinton</name>
				</author>
				<editor role='editor'>
					<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Pedagogies Editor</resp>
					<name>Kate Singer</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>commons4.2011.purinton</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
					Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
						or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
						purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
						use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
						are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
						with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
						permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
						requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
						forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
						conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
						them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
						have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
						Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
						continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
						a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
						use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Teaching British Romantic Drama: </title>
						<title level="a" type="subordinate">A Senior Seminar in Studies in
							Drama</title>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename>Marjean D.</forename>
								<surname>Purinton</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Teaching Romantic Drama: </title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Pedagogies Commons Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
								Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2011-02-23">February 23, 2011</date>
							<biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for
						‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
						keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
						such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
						been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
					10pt;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
						on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Dave Rettenmaier</name>
				<date>2010-06-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name>Thomas Crochunis</name>
				<date>2009-11-01T15:01:00</date>
				<list>
					<item>Proofed issue in Open Office Format</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>

			<div type="essay">
				<head>
					<title level="a">Teaching British Romantic Drama: A Senior Seminar in Studies in
						Drama</title>
				</head>
				<byline>
					<docAuthor>Marjean D. Purinton</docAuthor>
					<affiliation>Texas Tech University</affiliation>
				</byline>


				<div type="section" n="1">
					<head>Background</head>
					<p> During the spring 2006 semester, I taught a senior-level course in British
						Romantic Drama for English majors, a course that satisfied for them a genre
						upper-division requirement. My first-day assessments of my students revealed
						that several had taken an introductory course in drama, and some had taken a
						junior-level course in <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>,
						but no one enrolled in the course had pursued a course in the Romantic
						period. This course was, therefore, the students’ only contact with the
						Romantic period as well as a course involving the reading, discussing,
						writing, and performing of drama from the 1780s to the 1830s. </p>
					<p> During the spring 2005, when I was teaching the senior capstone course in
						English, I included <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>’s 1798
							<title level="m">Plays on the Passions</title> (<title level="m">Count
							Basil, The Tryal, and De Monfort</title>) in a culminating activity I
						termed “The <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name> Project,” and during
						the fall 2006 semester, I included <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
						>Baillie</name>’s <title level="m">Count Basil</title> in a sequence of
						plays for an Honors College course entitled Introduction to Drama:
						Tragically Monstrous, a course that is offered as a First-Year Experience
						requirement for incoming Honors College students. The first-year students
						read <title level="m">Count Basil</title> in tandem with Euripedes’ <title
							level="m">Medea</title> and <name ref="ShakespeareWilliam"
							>Shakespeare</name>’s <title level="m">Othello</title>. When I teach the
						junior-level course in the British Romantic period, I routinely include two
						or three dramas, including <title level="m">Count Basil</title> and Thomas
						Bellamy’s 1789 <title level="m">The Benevolent Planters</title> (both are
						anthologized in Mellor and Matlak’s <title level="m">British Literature
							1780-1830</title>). And when I teach the graduate-level course in
						British Romantic literature, I add <name ref="ShelleyPercyBysshe">P. B.
							Shelley</name>’s 1819 <title level="m">The Cenci</title> and <name
							ref="ByronGeorgeGordonByronBaron">Lord Byron</name>’s 1822 <title
							level="m">Manfred</title> to the two plays from the undergraduate
						course. My point is that while I had integrated Romantic drama into other
						courses I had taught, I had never taught an entire course devoted to
						Romantic drama until the spring of 2006. In spring, 2007, I taught the
						graduate version of the course as an Advanced Problems topic entitled
						British Romantic Drama. This course was actually a “piggy-back” course in
						that it was taught as a graduate seminar and an Honors College seminar for
						4000-level credit for English majors and minors with the appropriate
						prerequisites. </p>
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="2">
					<head>Course Description</head>
					<p> To help students identify what a course entitled Senior Seminar in Studies
						in Drama: British Romantic Drama was about, I supplied the following
						description, which provided them a sense of the cultural and political
						aspects of the course we would emphasize as well as strategies they could
						use for reading the plays:</p>

					<p>After more than a decade of recovering and recontextualizing Romantic drama
						in Great Britain, we have come to recognize the central role that drama
						played during the period. Romantic drama, staged and read, was its culture’s
						most popular medium, crossing class, national, and gender divisions, as well
						as a serious literary form written by the period’s major writers. Manifested
						in diverse ways (melodrama, gothic, verse drama, opera, pantomime, puppet
						shows, children’s drama, monodrama, tragedy, comedy, burlesque), Romantic
						drama performed, reflected, and influenced the political, social, and
						cultural issues of its day. The Licensing Act of 1737, granting patents to
						the Royal Theatres of Drury Lane, Covent Garden, and the Haymarket, and the
						Lord Chamberlain’s censorship (willingness to grant performance licenses)
						meant that playwrights had to be clever in their stagings of controversial
						and taboo subjects.</p>
					<p> In this seminar, we will examine diverse plays from the period as
						negotiations of theatrical politics. We will look at the performative
						aspects of Romantic drama, including the role of the actor, the design of
						stages, non-dramatic performances (such as itinerant medical shows), and
						private theatricals. We will consider the thematic and dramaturgical
						handling of the revolutionary and changing Romantic culture from which its
						drama emanated. We will contextualize the ways in which Romantic drama
						engaged with the late-eighteenth and early-nineteenth centuries as British
						society became increasingly democratized, commercialized, and bourgeois. We
						will discover how the theatre was a site for performing gender and how
						playwriting was particularly problematic for women. We will situate Romantic
						drama in the history of theatre. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="3">
					<head>Textbooks</head>
					<list>
						<item><name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>, Joanna. <title level="m"
								>Plays on the Passions</title>. 1798. Ed. Peter Duthie.
							Peterborough, ON: Broadview, 2001. ISBN: 1-55111-185-3</item>
						<item><name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name>, Jeffrey N., and <name
								ref="GamerMichael">Michael Gamer</name>, eds. <title level="m">The
								Broadview Anthology of Romantic Drama</title>. Peterborough, ON:
							Broadview, 2003. ISBN: 1-55111-298-1</item>
					</list>
				</div>

				<div type="section" n="4">
					<head>Teaching Philosophy</head>
					<p rend="noCount"> I ask students to come to this seminar prepared to engage in
						interactive learning, to be willing to explore all dimensions of Romantic
						drama as reading and performance texts, as stage spectacles, as serious
						commentary on the period and its culture. I inform them during our first
						class meeting that because my pedagogy and scholarship are informed by
						feminism and feminist theory, they will encounter a learning environment of
						decentralized authority with an invitation to participate in their own
						learning/discovery process, their own knowledge- and meaning-making. I tell
						them that because Romantic drama is a genre that uses performance as well as
						the printed page, they should be prepared to engage in some reading and
						performance activities that will require them to learn affectively as well
						as intellectually. Students are given multiple opportunities to pursue their
						own interests and lines of inquiry involving the drama, and my writing and
						discussion prompts are directive but open-ended. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="5">
					<head>Learning Outcomes</head>
					<p rend="noCount">If you successfully complete this course, you should be able </p>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>To interpret knowledge of the human condition, as reflected in British
							Romantic drama, in its diverse generic manifestations and from various
							theoretical perspectives;</item>
						<item>To identify current and historical developments in studies of British
							Romantic drama;</item>
						<item>To analyze theoretical and critical arguments about British Romantic
							drama and the Romantic theatre;</item>
						<item>To integrate primary and secondary source evidence into analytical
							writing that presents close textual readings;</item>
						<item>To assess the ways in which British Romantic drama and scholarship
							about it have contributed to our understanding of Romanticism.</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="6">
					<head>Learning Outcomes Assessments</head>
					<ab>If you successfully complete this course, you should be able to demonstrate
						the above learning outcomes by</ab>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>Writing response papers that require you to summarize, to explicate,
							and to judge the content of assigned Romantic dramas;</item>
						<item>Contributing to seminar discussions with analyses, comparisons,
							contrasts of Romantic dramas as well as the scholarship on Romantic
							dramas;</item>
						<item>Conducting a brief literature search of relevant secondary materials
							and assessing their importance to close readings of Romantic
							dramas;</item>
						<item>Reading and responding to contemporary performance reviews of assigned
							Romantic dramas;</item>
						<item>Writing a research-based project that requires you to weigh, select,
							and apply close textual readings and critical studies of Romantic drama.
						</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="7">
					<head>Other Course Objectives</head>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>To consider the ways in which Romantic drama has affected the field of
							Romantic literary studies and our understandings of late eighteenth- and
							early nineteenth-century British culture;</item>
						<item>To recognize and validate diverse perspectives and experiences that
							inform our readings of Romantic drama; </item>
						<item>To work out the particular performance dimensions of Romantic drama
							that are important to our understandings and appreciations of it as a
							unique cultural expression;</item>
						<item>To foster professional development;</item>
						<item>To collaborate in the learning/discovery/sharing process;</item>
						<item>To learn something about ourselves and our responses to literary
							expressions;</item>
						<item>To enjoy reading Romantic drama and the discovery activities which
							enrich our understandings and appreciation of Romantic literature.
						</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="8">
					<head>Course Policies</head>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>Come to class ready to share and to learn. Read assignments and bring
							texts of the plays with you to class;</item>
						<item>Attendance is required for you to pass this course;</item>
						<item>All assignments must be submitted for you to receive a passing
							grade;</item>
						<item>All assignments must be prepared according to my instructions;</item>
						<item>Maintain academic integrity. The deliberate use of someone else’s
							language, ideas, or original material without acknowledging its source
							constitutes plagiarism. Plagiarism is intellectual dishonesty and
							thievery. If you plagiarize, you will fail the course, and the incident
							will be reported to the university. </item>
						<item>If because of a disabling condition, you require some special
							arrangements in order to meet course requirements, you should let me
							know. Please present appropriate verification from Student Disability
							Services, Access TECH.</item>
						<item>If you are absent from class for the observation of a religious holy
							day, you shall be allowed to make up assignments scheduled for that day
							within a reasonable time after the absence if, no later than the
							fifteenth day after the first day of the semester, you have notified me
							of each scheduled class that you will miss for a religious holy day.
						</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="9">
					<head>Learning Environment</head>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>This is a discussion/participation seminar. Everyone should feel free
							to contribute ideas, experiences, knowledge, reactions; therefore, we
							need to maintain an environment in which everyone’s opinions and
							perspectives are respected and valued. From our diversity, we can
							multiply what we share and learn. Help us to maintain an environment
							conducive to interactive learning by turning off cellular phones and
							beepers, by arriving on time, and by avoiding distracting
							behaviors.</item>
						<item>In this seminar, your voice is valuable and valued. Be willing to
							assume an active role in your learning/discovery process.</item>
						<item>Our reading, activities, and schedule will be fluid and flexible, and
							you are invited to help shape what we pursue and emphasize.</item>
						<item>Because Romantic drama is a genre that uses performance as well as a
							kind of literary text, we will engage in some reading and performative
							activities that will require you to be willing to engage with our
							readings in more than intellectual ways. Be open to new ways of reading,
							learning, and responding. </item>
						<item>Because some of the topics at the heart of Romantic drama involve
							gender, class, and race, you may discover materials in this course that
							present issues, language, and affective areas that are sensitive. It is
							important, therefore, for us to be sensitive to our colleagues’ needs,
							feelings, and responses to these matters. </item>
						<item>Enjoy the community, personal growth, and professional development
							this seminar hopes to engender. </item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="10">
					<head>Course Requirements and Grade Determination</head>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>3 Response Papers (3-5 pages each) = 300 points (100 points
							each)</item>
						<item>2 Discovery Activities = 300 points (150 points each)</item>
						<item>Attendance/Participation/Performance = 100 points</item>
						<item>Researched Critical Analysis = 300 points</item>
						<lb/>
						<item>Total Points = 1000 points</item>
						<item>Grading Scale: 90% = A, 80% = B, 70% = C, 60% = D</item>
					</list>
				</div>

				<div type="section" n="11">
					<head>Tentative Assignments Schedule</head>
					<table>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Response Paper #1</cell>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, January 31</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Response Paper #2</cell>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, March 23</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Response Paper #3</cell>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, April 25</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Discovery Activity #1</cell>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, March 2</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Discovery Activity #2</cell>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, April 11</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Researched Critical Analysis Proposal</cell>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, February 14</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Research Critical Analysis</cell>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, May 4</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="12">
					<head>Tentative Reading Schedule</head>
					<table cols="2">
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, January 12</cell>
							<cell width="400"><name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> &amp; <name
									ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name>, pp. vii-xxxiv and 325-329 <lb/>
								<title level="m">A Bold Stroke for a Husband</title> (C&amp;G
								1-38)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, January 17</cell>
							<cell width="400"><name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> &amp; <name
									ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name>, pp. 311-317</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, January 19</cell>
							<cell width="400"><title level="m">Every One Has His Faults</title>
								(C&amp;G 39-74)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, January 24</cell>
							<cell width="400"><name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> &amp; <name
									ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name>, pp. 318-325</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, January 26</cell>
							<cell width="400"><title level="m">The Tryal</title> (Duthie
								217-298)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, January 31</cell>
							<cell width="300">Catch Up</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, February 1</cell>
							<cell width="400"><title level="m">De Monfort</title> (Duthie
								301-387)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, February 7</cell>
							<cell width="400"><name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> &amp; <name
									ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name>, pp. 380-383</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, February 9</cell>
							<cell width="400">Duthie, pp. 424-458</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, February 14</cell>
							<cell width="400">Catch Up</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, February 16</cell>
							<cell width="400"><title level="m">Orra</title> (C&amp;G 133-64)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, February 21</cell>
							<cell width="400"><name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> &amp; <name
									ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name>, pp. 370-378</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, February 23</cell>
							<cell width="400"><title level="m">Remorse</title> (C&amp;G
								165-204)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, February 28</cell>
							<cell width="400"><name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> &amp; <name
									ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name>, pp. 389-392</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, March 2</cell>
							<cell width="400">Catch Up</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, March 7</cell>
							<cell width="400">Catch Up</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, March 9</cell>
							<cell width="400"><title level="m">The Cenci</title> (C&amp;G
								221-259)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, March 14</cell>
							<cell width="400">Spring Break</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, March 16</cell>
							<cell width="400">Spring Break</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, March 21</cell>
							<cell width="400"><name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> &amp; <name
									ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name>, pp. 393-398</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, March 23</cell>
							<cell width="400">Catch Up</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, March 28</cell>
							<cell width="400">Catch Up</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, March 30</cell>
							<cell width="400"><title level="m">Count Basil</title> (Duthie
								117-213)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, April 4</cell>
							<cell width="400">Catch Up</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, April 6</cell>
							<cell width="400">Catch Up</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, April 11</cell>
							<cell width="400">Catch Up</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, April 13</cell>
							<cell width="400"><title level="m">Sardanapalus</title> (C&amp;G
								261-309)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, April 18</cell>
							<cell width="400"><name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> &amp; <name
									ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name>, pp. 398-392</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, April 20</cell>
							<cell width="400"><title level="m">Blue-Beard</title> (C&amp;G 75-96)
								and <title level="m">Timour the Tartar</title> (C&amp;G
								97-116)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, April 25</cell>
							<cell width="400">Catch Up</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Thursday, April 27</cell>
							<cell width="400"><name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> &amp; <name
									ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name>, pp. 329-351</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell width="300">Tuesday, May 2</cell>
							<cell width="400">Last Day of Class</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="13">
					<head>Descriptions of Assignments</head>
					<ab>
						<emph>Response Papers</emph>
					</ab>
					<ab> Brief (3-5 pages) “informal” responses to readings, discussions, videos,
						performances, issues, controversies, activities generated during the
						seminar. I will offer specific prompts for each paper. I want you to engage
						conceptually with the drama and the theatre of the Romantic period, and this
						activity is a kind of “thinking-on-paper” writing in which you are still its
						primary reader, but I am dropping in on the thinking process. Make your
						reflections honest, useful, and specific. These responses may serve you well
						later in your reshaping of initial reactions and ideas into more
						reader-based discourse for the researched critical analysis assignment. (See
						the Appendix with specific writing prompts for the three response
						papers.)</ab>
					<lb/>
				</div>

				<div type="section" n="14">
					<head>Discovery Activities</head>

					<ab>
						<emph>Discovery Activity #1: Secondary Sources Activity</emph>
					</ab>
					<ab> To augment your Critical Analysis with secondary sources (research), you
						will need to do some library work. </ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab> Locate five secondary sources germane to your project. Remember that at
						least one source must be a journal article and that only two sources may be
						derived on-line. </ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab> Once you have located relevant secondary materials, here’s what you need to
						do:</ab>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>Write the working title and thesis of your Critical Analysis;</item>
						<item>Outline your major points of development as you see them at this
							time;</item>
						<item>Provide complete bibliographical entries for your secondary sources in
							MLA Style. If you need to review MLA Style specifications for your
							sources, use this website: <ref
								target="http://www.lib.ttu.edu/reference/style/htm"
								>www.lib.ttu.edu/reference/style/htm</ref>;</item>
						<item>Indicate briefly how each source will be useful to your Critical
							Analysis, support or refute your thesis, demonstrate points of
							development, explain evidence, etc. </item>
					</list>
					<ab>Here are the website and linked websites that will be useful for on-line
						secondary sources. You will also find bibliographies on these websites:</ab>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>Romanticism on the Net: <ref target="http://www.ron.umontreal.ca/"
								>www.ron.umontreal.ca</ref>
						</item>
						<item>Romantic Circles: <ref target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/"
								>www.rc.umd.edu</ref>
						</item>
						<item>British Women Playwrights Around 1800: <ref
								target="http://www.etang.umontreal.ca/bwp1800"
								>www.etang.umontreal.ca/bwp1800</ref>
						</item>
						<item>Romantic Chronology: <ref target="http://www.english.ucsb.591/rchrono"
								>www.english.ucsb.591/rchrono</ref>
						</item>
					</list>
					<ab>Here are some journal titles that will be useful for articles:</ab>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>Studies in Romanticism</item>
						<item>Nineteenth-Century Contexts</item>
						<item>The <name ref="WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</name> Circle</item>
						<item>Romanticism</item>
						<item>Women’s Writing</item>
						<item>The Keats-Shelley Journal</item>
						<item>The Byron Journal</item>
						<item>Studies in Nineteenth-Century Literature</item>
						<item>European Romantic Review</item>
						<item>Prism(s): Essays in Romanticism</item>
						<item>The Keats-Shelley Review</item>
						<item>Gothic Studies</item>
					</list>
					<ab>Remember that secondary sources can be critical, theoretical, or
						extra-literary in nature.</ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab>Remember that works published before 1985 are generally not as useful to us
						as recently published work, especially if the secondary source is critical
						in nature. Look for something current, whether your secondary source is a
						monograph, an essay in a collection of essays, or a journal article. Try to
						discover the <emph rend="bold">best and most relevant </emph>secondary
						sources for your project. </ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab>
						<emph>Discovery Activity #2: Contemporary Reviews Creative Activity</emph>
					</ab>
					<ab> This Discovery Activity requires two parts.</ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab rend="under">Part 1</ab>
					<ab>Select a set of reviews for a play we have read and discuss what they reveal
						about the performance(s) of that play. Refer to specific reviews, and cite
						direct quotations parenthetically in-text. Use the following questions to
						guide your thinking and writing.</ab>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>What do we learn about scenery, costuming, actors, audience, critical
							opinions, and the entertainment value of the play?</item>
						<item>What about the play was especially popular and/or
							controversial?</item>
						<item>How do the reviews offer us insights about the play that we might not
							otherwise perceive from our reading of the text?</item>
					</list>
					<ab rend="under">Part 2</ab>
					<ab>Next, imagine that you were staging the play, or reworking the play for
						cinema or Video/TV, and describe/discuss what obstacles or challenges you
						would have with this project. Use the following questions to guide your
						thinking and writing.</ab>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>Who would be your primary audience? Why?</item>
						<item>Would you stage or shoot the entire play, or would you make cuts?
							Where and why?</item>
						<item>How might you make the play relevant to contemporary audiences, such
							as manipulating the special effects, casting star performers, creating
							fantastic scenery and music?</item>
						<item>What do you learn about the play by imagining it from a director’s
							point of view or from the perspective of performance rather than from
							the position of literary student/scholar?</item>
					</list>
					<ab>This activity is designed to tap into your creative and imaginative
						responses to Romantic drama, so have fun with it. Remember that you do not
						have to re-write the script, but you do want to detail how the staging or
						shooting of the play might be rendered. </ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab>
						<emph>Researched Critical Analysis Proposal</emph>
					</ab>
					<ab> Write an informal (1-2 pages) proposal in which you indicate what you are
						planning to develop in your Researched Critical Analysis. I am your
						audience. Include the following information:</ab>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>Working title and thesis (argument or position) of your
							project;</item>
						<item>Play(s) that will be included as primary source material;</item>
						<item>Working major points of development and critical approach (i.e.,
							historical, feminist, Marxist, post-colonial);</item>
						<item>Tell me what you hope to accomplish (beyond the grade) in this
							project. (Can it be useful for you beyond this course, for
							example?)</item>
						<item>List the secondary sources you have investigated as relevant to your
							project and indicate how you plan to use these materials (rely on
							Discovery Activity #1 here);</item>
						<item>List any difficulties or questions you perceive at this point in the
							planning and development of your Researched Critical Analysis.</item>
					</list>
					<ab>
						<emph>Researched Critical Analysis</emph>
					</ab>
					<ab> The culminating project for this seminar on British Romantic Drama will be
						a critical analysis (research, literary, and persuasive) featuring one or
						more plays that we have read.</ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab> While I recognize that what you may submit may well represent work in
						progress more than a “finished” product, you want to think about this
						project as one that can offer you a writing sample for your professional
						dossier (e.g., application to graduate school, law school, scholarships), a
						potential paper for a conference presentation, an essay that you can return
						to and expand as a senior thesis or in graduate courses. Strive for about
						7-10 pages of discourse followed by notes (if applicable) and your works
						cited listing. </ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab> Your audience will be your classmates (including me), and so before you
						write, do an audience analysis. Here are some helpful questions to ask about
						your audience.</ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab>What do they know about the issue and the play(s) at the center of my
						analysis? How can I get them engaged in my discussion? How can I communicate
						clearly and persuasively, using primary and secondary evidence? Remember
						that we share the reading and understanding of the dramas, but in order to
						access your arguments and evidence, you will have to supply contextual clues
						and connections. </ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab> Here are some recommendations as you engage in the process of writing:</ab>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>Make your position (thesis) focused, directional, argumentative, and
							specific;</item>
						<item>Discuss a limited number of supporting or major points of
							development;</item>
						<item>Draft a 3-5-page position paper using your own knowledge (including
							all class-derived materials) and the play(s) you are analyzing or
							including in your project—exhaust what you know in this draft that
							involves a close reading of your text(s)—here’s where one or more of
							your Response Papers may be useful;</item>
						<item>Begin each supporting point with a clear topic sentence, and practice
							good paragraph development;</item>
						<item>Select evidence from the play(s) you are including in your analysis
							(primary-source evidence);</item>
						<item>Analyze your audience carefully, for it is crucial to your argument.
							Select the best quotations and paraphrases from primary and secondary
							sources to support your major points of development and your argument
							(thesis);</item>
						<item>Set up the context of evidence (primary and secondary) for your
							audience and make reasonable connections between evidence and your major
							points of development, and then between that supporting point and your
							thesis;</item>
						<item>Contextualize adequately the evidence for your readers—help them to
							access it and then to see its importance to your argument;</item>
						<item>Insert primary-source evidence correctly (use MLA Style for in-text
							citations) and explain it thoroughly;</item>
						<item>Turn to your five secondary sources to supplement your discussion (at
							least one must be a journal article, and only two may be derived from
							online sites);</item>
						<item>Follow MLA Style (in-text or endnotes) in citing secondary source
							materials (summaries, paraphrases, quotations);</item>
						<item>Use secondary sources only to supplement your discussion, to
							demonstrate your knowledge of current scholarly discourse about British
							Romantic drama. Points of agreement or disagreement might be included in
							your discussion or packaged as endnotes. Remember that the analysis
							should reflect your thesis, arguments, developments, and discussion.
							Keep the number and length of all direct quotations to a minimum. You
							are the primary author of this researched critical analysis.</item>
					</list>
					<ab>If you need assistance with your writing or revising process and inserting
						and documenting secondary sources, seek help at the University Writing
						Center, in the English Building, first floor of the east wing. You may make
						an appointment to visit a tutor there, and you can submit online work in
						progress. There is no fee.</ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab> Hours: Monday -- Friday 9:00-5:00</ab>
					<ab> Telephone: 742.2476, x 269</ab>
					<ab> Email: <ref target="mailto:w.center@ttu.edu">w.center@ttu.edu</ref>
					</ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab>If you need to review MLA Style specifications, use this website: <ref
							target="http://www.lib.ttu.edu/reference.style.htm"
							>www.lib.ttu.edu/reference.style.htm</ref>
					</ab>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="15">
					<head>Attendance/Participation/Performance</head>
					<ab> Come to each seminar prepared to participate in your own learning process.
						Read the assigned plays and reviews. Bring questions to share and to
						stimulate discussion. In this seminar, we want to build a community of
						teachers/learners/scholars, and so be willing to talk to each other and not
						just to me. </ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab> We want our exchanges to be thoughtful, responsible, and professional. As
						with good writing, specific comments and questions yield better responses.
						Try to ground and situate your comments and responses within our readings,
						cultural or theoretical contexts, or experiential knowledge. In other words,
						we want to avoid communication that is the more student-based
						“shooting-from-the-hip” form and to strive for the more scholarly,
						professional, informed, and critical discussion during our seminar
						meetings.</ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab> You may also find yourself led outside your “comfort zone” a bit by seminar
						activities that require our reading aloud or enacting parts of the plays we
						read and discuss, experimenting with staging and voice that generally do not
						occur in conventional English courses. Be willing to take risks and to
						exercise creative aspects of “reading” and “learning” that you might
						otherwise leave latent. You get credit for your willingness to participate,
						so enjoy this opportunity, for you have nothing to lose and possibly some
						interesting things to learn about yourself by engaging in a form of
						participation that is vital to our understand and appreciation of British
						Romantic drama. </ab>
					<lb/>
					<ab> Any co-curricular activities you attend or participate in (e.g., TTU
						Theatre, Women’s History Month, music department recitals) will be
						acknowledged and considered in the formulation of your final semester grade.
						Simply bring me a playbill, a program, or other proof of attendance. </ab>
					<lb/>
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="16">
					<head>Discussion of Course Sequence and Pedagogical Strategies</head>
					<ab>
						<emph>Course Sequence</emph>
					</ab>
					<p> The selection and sequencing of the dramas for the course reflects
						quasi-chronological progression, quasi-generic groupings, and thematic
						clustering so that plays can be read dialogically.<note place="foot"
							resp="editors" n="1">For another syllabus and discussion of teaching
							British Romantic drama by women, see <name ref="BurroughsCatherineB"
								>Catherine Burroughs</name>, “Teaching the Theory and Practice of
							Women’s Dramaturgy,” <title level="j">Romanticism on the Net</title> 12
							(November 1998) [22 February 2010]
							http://www.erudit.org/revue/ron/1998/v/n12/005823ar.html</note> One
						reason for my including so much drama by <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna
							Baillie</name> is that about one third of my students needed to satisfy
						a major requirement for a single author, and so they were able to do so by
						taking this course that highlighted <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>
						as its major playwright. I tried to include representative plays by male and
						female playwrights, but we began with three late eighteenth-century comedies
						by women: <name ref="CowleyHannah">Hannah Cowley</name>’s <title level="m">A
							Bold Stroke for a Husband</title> (1783), <name ref="InchbaldMrs"
							>Elizabeth Inchbald</name>’s <title level="m">Everyone Has His
							Fault</title> (1793), and <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna
							Baillie</name>’s <title level="m">The Tryal</title> (1798). These
						comedies opened onto discussions of Georgian courtship and marriage customs
						that cast men and women in stereotypical relationships that favored men. We
						discovered how <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> displaces British
						manner and customs onto Madrid, and, like <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
							>Baillie</name>, relies on disguise and cross-dressing to suggest
						gender-bending in which women gain control over their lives. <name
							ref="InchbaldMrs">Inchbald</name>’s comedy, we agreed, brings the legal
						issues of divorce, custody, adoption, bankruptcy, and robbery into the
						contexts of women’s rights and gender stereotypes. While <title level="m">A
							Bold Stroke for a Husband</title> is also a play that stages ambivalent,
						gender-bending heroines, we looked at how gender was even more complicated
						in performances featuring Mary Robinson as Victoria. All three plays show
						the centrality of marriage for women of Georgian Britain. All three comedies
						also push generic bounds. <name ref="CowleyHannah">Cowley</name> deploys
						conventions of Spanish intrigue and recycles the motifs of the comedy of
							manners.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="2">See my essay “On
							Teaching <title level="m">A Bold Stroke for a Husband</title> and Other
							Comedies by Romantic Women Playwrights,” <title level="j">European
								Romantic Review</title> 17.3 (July 2006): 351-60, for an extended
							discussion of teaching <name ref="CowleyHannah">Hannah Cowley</name>’s
							comedy.</note>
						<name ref="InchbaldMrs">Inchbald</name>’s play resonates with pathos of
						character and novel-like structure. <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
						>Baillie</name>’s comedy revolves around subplots of play-making; Marianne
						and Agnes are themselves playwrights in this metadramatic comedy. Because
						these comedies are critical of the culture’s dominant practices, the
						students find them fun, but they help to draw students into Romantic period
						culture as well as into the playwrights’ resistance to its dominant
						ideologies.</p>
					<p> We next turned to tragedies, beginning the next cluster of plays with <name
							ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s <title level="m">De Monfort</title>
						(1798), <title level="m">Orra</title> (1812), and <name
							ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</name>’s <title
							level="m">Remorse</title> (1813)—three plays that address sensibilities
						of the early nineteenth-century, including the Gothic. In <title level="m"
							>De Monfort</title>, we continued our exploration of gender-bending
						strategies, but here in tragic forms, and we considered whether or not the
						play holds up a tragic hero for emulation or admiration, whether it hints at
						homoerotic or incestuous relationships, and whether it presents the tragic
						consequences of immoderate passions, especially hatred.<note place="foot"
							resp="editors" n="3">For a discussion of the teaching of <name
								ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>’s dramas, see my essay,
							“Pedagogy and Passions: Teaching <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna
								Baillie</name>’s Dramas,” in <title level="m">Joanna Baillie,
								Romantic Dramatist: Critical Essays</title>, ed. <name
								ref="CrochunisThomasC">Thomas Crochunis</name> (New York: Routledge,
							2004), 315-47.</note> We learned how <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
							>Baillie</name> stages the Gothic, more fully developed, in the
						kidnapping and brainwashing of the tragic heroine in <title level="m"
							>Orra</title>. Like the other plays we had read, <title level="m"
							>Orra</title> puts marriage center stage, as well as the heroine’s
						resistance to patriarchal control. We found that <title level="m"
							>Orra</title> also demonstrates the power of storytelling and the
						consequences to those whose naïve understandings of the world give them
						limited critical ability to discern reality from fiction. Similarly, <title
							level="m">Remorse</title>, we agreed, explores gender-bending and
						mistaken identities so as to expose the fallacies and inconsistencies in
						social orders that are shaped by misogyny. While <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
							>Baillie</name>’s tragedies explore the crises for female identity and
						expose the subjection of femininity within patriarchal structures, <name
							ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</name>’s tragedy brings early
						nineteenth-century constructions of masculinity under scrutiny. All three
						plays can be read through postmodern lenses as historically specific—both in
						terms of their medieval settings and their Romantic-era contexts of
						composition—enactments of gender; the tragedies’ theatricality and
						performance, furthermore, expose the artificiality and even the fluidity of
						gender roles and gendered behaviors at the very time when codifications of
						those roles were being scripted off-stage as well as on-stage. </p>
					<p> The next grouping of tragedies—<name ref="ShelleyPercyBysshe">P. B.
							Shelley</name>’s <title level="m">The Cenci</title> (1816), <name
							ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s <title level="m">Count
							Basil</title> (1798), and <name ref="ByronGeorgeGordonByronBaron">Lord
							Byron</name>’s <title level="m">Sardanapalus</title> (1821)—took us into
						deeper and darker spaces of Romantic thought by way of historically based
						incidents and characters. All three of these plays involve despotic rulers
						of corrupt governments, but they similarly feature stories of dysfunctional
						families, thus bringing the crises of public and private spaces together in
						shared space on the stage. <title level="m">The Cenci</title>, like <title
							level="m">De Monfort</title> from the previous cluster, is a play that
						opens onto discussions of censorship and licensing of plays in the Romantic
						period. The settings of Italy for <title level="m">Cenci</title> and <title
							level="m">Basil</title>, and Assyria for <title level="m"
							>Sardanapalus</title> offer spaces where taboo and disturbing issues
						affecting early nineteenth-century British culture could be displaced and
						displayed. These three tragedies open onto explorations of criminal behavior
						and punishment, the efficacy of language, the function of the public body,
						and the pathology of madness. <title level="m">Count Basil</title> exposes
						the folly of excessive passions, coded masculine or feminine, and the
						segregated and gendered spaces that impede an individual’s healthy
						participation in the public sphere. <name ref="ShelleyPercyBysshe">P. B.
							Shelley</name>’s tragedy presents us also with the problem of morality
						sanctioned by state and religion. <title level="m">Sardanapalus</title> adds
						layers of colonialism and orientalism to its questioning of gendered agency
						and effective leadership. All three tragedies hint at Romantic
						preoccupations with transgressive public figures under surveillance and then
						put on trial for their moral and legal infractions. </p>
					<p> As afterpieces to the course, we read George Colman the Younger’s <title
							level="m">Blue-Beard; or Female Curiosity! </title>(1798), and Matthew
						Lewis’s <title level="m">Timour the Tartar; A Grand Romantic Melo-drama in
							Two Acts</title> (1811), two plays that demonstrate to students the kind
						of experimentation that was occurring with drama, particularly staged drama,
						during the Romantic period. These two fantasies are fanciful but disturbing
						in their staging of the abuses of misogyny and of orientalism (both set in
						the Near East) under the guise of children’s theatre, harlequinade,
						pantomime, and spectacle. Both Bluebeard and Timour are representations of
						actual figures whose stories become thoroughly mythologized and fantasized.
						Their stories and depictions, like that of Beatrice Cenci, have been
						replayed in multiple forms—theatre, novels, visual arts, opera, and film—and
						we talked about why Romantic theatergoers would find these characters so
						interesting and engaging. </p>
					<p> To supplement each clustering of dramas, we read, as the schedule above
						indicates, the performance reviews that <name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name>
						and <name ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name> have included in the Broadview
						anthology and that Duthie has included in his edition of <title level="m"
							>Plays on the Passions</title> and that are relevant to the play we are
						discussing. The creative discovery activity enables students to work closely
						with these reviews and to think critically about performance aspects of the
						plays. Graduate students work beyond the reviews of the anthology, seeking
						additional performance information and reviews from online and traditional
						scholarly sources in the preparation of their assignment. They may also look
						at reviews of contemporary stagings of Romantic plays.<note place="foot"
							resp="editors" n="4">See, for example, <name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Jeffrey
								N. Cox</name>, “Theatrical Forms, Ideological Conflicts, and the
							Staging of <title level="m">Obi</title>,” <title level="j">Romantic
								Circles Praxis Series</title>, ed. Charles Rzepka (February 4,
							2005), [March 24, 2006] <ptr
								target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/prasix.obi/cox/cox.html"/> and Jerrold
							E. Hogle, “Directing <title level="m">Obi</title> in 2000,” <title
								level="j">Romantic Circles Praxis Series</title>, ed. Charles Rzepka
							(February 4, 2005) [March 24, 2006] <ptr
								target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/praxis/obi/hogle/hogle.html"/></note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="17">
					<head>Pedagogical Strategies</head>
					<p> As the syllabus indicates, our class frequently read parts aloud (often in
						character) to get a feel for the language and the performance aspects of the
						play. For example, </p>
					<list type="unordered">
						<item>From <title level="m">A Bold Stroke for a Husband</title>, we read
							aloud act 2, scene 2 (pp. 12-15 from the <name ref="CoxJeffreyN"
								>Cox</name> and <name ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name> edition) and
							act 4, scene 1 (pp. 25-27) </item>
						<item>From <title level="m">Everyone Has His Fault</title>, we read aloud
							act 2, scene 1 (pp. 46-54) and act 3, scene 1 (pp. 55-57) </item>
						<item>From <title level="m">The Cenci</title>, we read aloud act 5, scene 4
							(pp. 253-55) and act 5, scene 4 (pp. 257-59) </item>
						<item>From <title level="m">The Tryal</title>, we read aloud act 1, scene 1
							(pp.219-228 of the Duthie edition) </item>
						<item>From <title level="m">De Monfort</title>, we read aloud act 2, scene 1
							(pp. 320-28) and act 5, scene 2 (pp. 373-79) </item>
					</list>
					<p>Sometimes for these oral readings, we wear masks. I have a collection of
						paper cardboard masks that can be easily distributed and worn from such
						sources as <title level="m">Madame Tussaud’s Book of Victorian Masks,
							Venetian Masks</title>, and <title level="m">Famous Figures Historical
							Masks</title>.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="5">Lionel Lambourne,
								<title level="m">Madame Tussaud’s Book of Victorian Masks</title>
							(New York: E.P. Dutton, 1987).</note> Occasionally, students make their
						own masks for the parts they are reading. </p>
					<p> Additionally, I rely on a select but valuable collection of AV materials to
						supplement our readings and discussions of these plays. When students
						entered the classroom on the first day of class, they were greeted by the
						sounds of the CD <emph>Playhouse Aires: 18<hi rendition="#sup"
							>th</hi>-Century English Theatre Music</emph>, performed by The <name
							ref="London">London</name> Oboe Band to set the stage for the
						Introductory reading in the <name ref="CoxJeffreyN">Cox</name> and <name
							ref="GamerMichael">Gamer</name> Broadview anthology.<note place="foot"
							resp="editors" n="6"><emph>Playhouse Aires: 18<hi rendition="#sup"
									>th</hi>-Century English Theatre Music</emph>, The <name
								ref="London">London</name> Oboe Band, lead by Paul Goodwin (France:
							Harmonia Mundi, 1996).</note> With <title level="m">A Bold Stroke for a
							Husband,</title> I played excerpts from the CD <title level="m">A Bold
							Stroke for a Husband</title>, from the production directed by Frederick
						Burwick, original music composed by Brian Holmes. Burwick and Paul Douglass
						have created an invaluable resource, a website entitled “Theatre and Popular
						Songs, Catches, Airs, and Art Songs of the Romantic Period,” which features
						CD recordings at nominal cost, thereby making them accessible for
						pedagogical use.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="7">See <title level="s"
								>Romantic-Era Songs: A site Devoted to Theater and Popular Songs,
								Catches, Airs, and Art Songs of the Romantic Period</title>,
							maintained by Paul Douglass and Frederick Burwick: <ptr
								target="http://www2.sjsu.edu/faculty/douglass/music/index.html"
							/></note>Two other recordings Burwick and Douglass have made and that
						are useful for the teaching of British Romantic drama are the recording of a
						live performance of Thomas Lovell Beddoes’s <title level="m">Death’s
							Jest-Book: A Grotesque Musical Comedy</title> and <name
							ref="InchbaldMrs">Inchbald</name>’s <title level="m">Animal
							Magnetism</title>. </p>
					<p>As we moved to the cluster of tragic plays with gothic overtones, I
						introduced the cluster with a small segment of the video of the Readers’
						Theatre production of <title level="m">A Tale of Mystery</title> (1806) that
						was performed and video-taped at the 2003 meeting of the International
						Conference on Romanticism at Marquette University in Milwaukee, Wisconsin.
						The setting of the reading in the St. Joan of Arc Chapel on the Marquette
						University campus was a spectacular way for students to get a visual clue
						about how to read settings in <title level="m">De Monfort, Orra, </title>and
							<title level="m">Remorse</title>. The live accompaniment of the reading
						gave students a sense of how music was, in fact, a vital component to the
						play—something I asked them to pay close attention to in their readings of
						the plays’ stage directions. Likewise, our reading and discussion of <title
							level="m">Count Basil</title> was enriched by two video supplements. In
						March of 2002, in celebration of Women’s History Month, the Women’s Studies
						Program and the Theatre Department at Texas Tech University worked together
						to present a parlour reading of Romantic period dramas by <name
							ref="HemansFeliciaDorotheaBrowne">Felicia Hemans</name>, <name
							ref="InchbaldMrs">Elizabeth Inchbald</name>, and <name
							ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>. We held the reading in the
						parlor of a local, private home, and relied on student and faculty volunteer
						performers, and I served as dramaturg for the production. We videotaped the
						performance, and thus, I have a segment of <title level="m">Count
							Basil</title> as amateur readers’ theatre that I can show the students.
						In August of 2003, the North American Society for the Study of Romanticism
						brought a Horizons Theatre production of <title level="m">Count
							Basil</title> to Fordham University, Lincoln Center Campus for the
						association’s annual meeting. Having procured a DVD recording of that
						professional production, I can show my students parts of the play or the
						entire performance of <title level="m">Count Basil</title>. I can also refer
						students to reviews of that production that were published in <title
							level="j">European Romantic Review</title>.<note place="foot"
							resp="editors" n="8">See Reviews of the Horizons Theatre Production of
								<name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>’s <title level="m"
								>Count Basil</title>, New York City, August 2003, edited by <name
								ref="BurroughsCatherineB">Catherine B. Burroughs</name> in <title
								level="j">European Romantic Review</title> 15.2 (June 2004):
							351-85.</note>
					</p>
					<p>To enrich our readings of <title level="m">The Cenci, Sardanapalus,</title>
						<title level="m">Blue-Beard, </title>and <title level="m">Timour the
							Tartar,</title> I relied on reproductions of artwork, all of which are
						easily available online for showing in class or for reproducing as handouts.
						In particular, we looked at the “Sirani Elisabetta Portrait of Beatrice
						Cenci” attributed to Guido Reni that <name ref="ShelleyPercyBysshe">P. B.
							Shelley</name> saw in Palazzo Colonna in 1818. This visual served as a
						starting point for our discussion of the enduring interest in Beatrice
						Cenci, as demonstrated by the many revisions of her life story in plays,
						operas, novel, and film. For <title level="m">Sardanapalus</title>, we
						looked at Eugène Delacroix’s painting <title level="m">The Death of
							Sardanapalus</title>, 1827-1828 which is on display at the Louvre. For
						Colman the Younger’s play, we viewed Gustav Doré’s nineteenth-century
						illustrations of Bluebeard. <title level="m">Timour the Tartar</title>
						became more accessible for the students with the visual enrichment of
						Skelt’s Scenes from the novel version of Timour’s story, J.K. Green’s
						illustrations of the characters and scenes of the play, and the playbill of
						Mrs. H. Johnston in the melodrama of <title level="m">Timour the Tartar.
						</title>We also looked at a picture of the statue of Timur in Shahrisabz,
						Uzbekistan. </p>
					<p>We rely on the online sites <title level="m">Romantic Circles</title>, <title
							level="m">Romanticism on the Net</title>, <title level="m">British Women
							Playwights around 1800</title>, and <title level="m">Romantic
							Chronology</title> for the enriching materials, scholarship, and visuals
						that these sites bring to students. For my graduate seminar, students work
						with at least one hypertext found on <title level="m">British Women
							Playwrights around 1800</title>, or they work with a novel and its
						dramatic adaptation.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="9">For a discussion
							of teaching gothic dramas adapted from gothic novels, see my essay
							“Teaching the Gothic Novel and Dramatic Adaptations,” in <title
								level="m">Approaches to Teaching Gothic Fiction: The British and
								American Traditions</title>, ed. Diane Long Hoeveler and Tamar
							Heller (New York: Modern Language Association, 2003), 326-42. See also
							Susan J. Wolfson, “Teaching <name ref="HemansFeliciaDorotheaBrowne"
								>Hemans</name> with <name ref="ByronGeorgeGordonByronBaron"
								>Byron</name>,” <title level="j">European Romantic Review</title>
							17.1 (January 2006): 93-99 and Tricia Lootens, “New Criticism and New
							Classrooms: Teaching <name ref="HemansFeliciaDorotheaBrowne">Felicia
								Hemans</name>,” <title level="j">European Romantic Review
							</title>17.1 (January 2006): 101-109.</note>
					</p>
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="18">
					<head>Sample Student Responses</head>
					<p> In the creative discovery activity #2, one student took the reviewers of
							<name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name>’s <title level="m">Plays
							on the Passions</title>, in particular of an 1804 staging of <title
							level="m">Count Basil</title>, to task. She writes: “…I find Baillie’s
						endeavors to capture the state of one passion incredibly impressive and
						thought provoking. The reviewers seemed to have missed some of the points of
							<name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name>’s unchecked and exaggerated
						passions.” A researched critical analysis of <name ref="BaillieJoanna"
							>Baillie</name>’s <title level="m">Orra</title> explores the
						“patriarchal-taught self-fear” that Orra experiences and its contribution to
						her madness. The student writes: “This self fear is beneficial to the
						patriarchal, hierarchal society because it keeps women in their ‘place’ by
						making them emotionally weak and easily scared. They either run to men for
						help and/or readily submit to men without question.” Another student
						astutely observes gender dichotomies: “[v]iolence directed at women in
						Romantic drama serves the masculine standard by placing the dramatic burden
						firmly on the shoulders of the female characters—both as actor and acted
						upon.… Clearly, <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Baillie</name> is interested in
						how her contemporaries utilized violence and gender both to control action
						on stage and, in many ways, to control the making of this action.” </p>
					<p> For the re-staging of <title level="m">The Cenci</title>, one student
						elaborates on the scenery and costuming: “Lighting would be very warm, reds,
						oranges, and yellows…Once Count Cenci reveals the demise of his sons and
						openly celebrates their death, the brightness of the stage will begin to
						diminish and the darkness of the Palace will take over, like a foreboding
						shadow. Beatrice would, like the other characters, begin the play, except
						for Cenci, in drab and colorless apparel, but when she starts to plan her
						father’s murder, she changes to richly colored costumes so that by the
						height of her madness, she would be donning apparel almost equal to the
						richness and color of the costuming worn by Cenci.” Another student proposes
						a contemporary cast for a new film version of <name ref="ShelleyPercyBysshe"
							>P. B. Shelley</name>’s tragedy: Scarlet Johansen as Beatrice, Michael
						Douglas as Count Cenci, Jessica Lange as Lucretia, and Anthony Hopkins as
						Cardinal Camillo. As for an interesting stage effect at the end of the play,
						another student writes: “The Hall of Justice would be a long hallway, with
						the prisoners positioned at one end, each seated in a rolling office chair,
						and Camillo and the judges at the other. As characters are given their turns
						to speak, their chairs roll forward toward the judges, and as they are
						dismissed, their chairs will roll into a doorway off to the side of the
						hall.”</p>
					<p> A response to 1813 reviews of <name ref="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor"
							>Coleridge</name>’s tragedy <title level="m">Remorse</title> indicates
						how the student better appreciates the importance of the play’s scenery for
						spectators. He writes: “With these reviews, it was somewhat easier to
						imagine what key scenes would have looked like, the sorcery scene
						specifically. They also gave me a sense of what early nineteenth-century
						audience thought of acting capabilities. By giving our imagination a
						direction, the reviews let me see different perspectives, things I can’t see
						from merely reading the play.” Another student recommends <title level="m"
							>Remorse</title> for a made-for-TV movie, recast as a story about
						high-school kids and cliques. The outsider Alvar would be chunky and nerdy,
						and Ordonio would be thin and popular. Ordonio teases Alvar and spreads
						malicious rumors about his brother, eventually causing Alvar to transfer
						schools, despite the fact that Teresa finds him attractive. When Alvar
						returns to the school months later, he has lost weight, wears contacts, and
						is immediately a hit with the popular crowd.” Another student recommends
						filming <name ref="ByronGeorgeGordonByronBaron">Byron</name>’s <title
							level="m">Sardanapalus</title> for the big screen, with a setting in the
						1940s in Washington, D.C. and involving a congressional scandal with a
						closeted effeminate male and a press leak, so that the story would be about
						the fall of democratic leadership rather than the fall of the Assyrian
						empire. Another student, however, sees contemporary appeal for a movie that
						retains <name ref="ByronGeorgeGordonByronBaron">Byron</name>’s Near East
						setting, particularly given our political interests in the very region that
						was seen as vital to the emerging commercial economy of early
						nineteenth-century Britain. A passage from a researched critical analysis of
							<title level="m">Sardanapalus</title> reveals how clothing becomes code
						for sexuality for this reader: “Clothing is used in this play to reveal
						Sardanapalus’ femininity, and Sardanapalus’s preoccupation with battle
						clothing makes him seem less of a man. When Sardanapalus orders his servant
						to bring him a mirror, we see his narcissism, his feminine concern with
						appearances rather than the impending battle for control of Nineveh.” </p>
					<p> In general, the course evaluations for British Romantic Drama were similar
						to what I receive from other courses I teach, but here are some comments
						that are particularly relevant to the content and delivery of the seminar
						and that indicate how students were able to integrate the learning
						experiences. One student writes: “This class taught me something very
						different; reading drama can be just as fulfilling or more fulfilling than
						actually seeing a play read.” Another student points to the ways in which
						the drama contributed to his self-awareness: “I learned a lot about myself
						over the course of this semester in class. It took me a while to learn how
						to read the plays, but once I learned what worked, I fell in love with some
						of the plays we read. I wish I had taken a course in Romanticism before my
						senior year.” Another student emphasizes connections between
						self-actualization and the drama we read: “Through this class, I have been
						exposed to literature and drama that, up until this point, I had not heard
						of and I was able to learn. I think that the most important thing that I
						have learned about myself this semester is that I really enjoy reading drama
						and that I am drawn to these plays because of their interesting content. I
						think that groupings of the plays are helpful since it allows for
						progression through the semester with smooth transition between plays.” And
						finally, a student admits ending up in this course quite by happenstance,
						but finds it a surprisingly pleasant and instructional experience: “This
						class has been an invaluable learning experience for me. I thoroughly
						enjoyed the curriculum and loved learning about, for me, a new kind of
						drama. <name ref="BaillieJoanna">Joanna Baillie</name> was my favorite
						dramatist, and I must confess that I took this course because the <name
							ref="ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name> class was full, but I am
						very glad that I had this opportunity.” </p>
				</div>


				<div type="section" n="19">
					<head>Expected Outcomes</head>
					<p>At the end of the semester, I was able to report to my department chair that
						students who successfully completed English 4312: Studies in Drama: British
						Romantic Drama during the spring 2006 were able to write analytical essays
						that summarized, explicated, and judged diverse cultural expressions in the
						plays we read. The students contributed to class discussions with analyses,
						comparisons, contrasts, and presentations of experiential knowledge informed
						by close textual readings of Romantic drama and reviews. The students
						demonstrated generic and periodic understandings of how literary and
						language studies function through their response papers and the researched
						critical analysis. The students integrated understandings and applications
						of skills acquired through the study of literature and language as part of
						their last response paper (see Appendix), which required them to perform a
						self-assessment and to discuss the ways in which the skills and strategies
						they had acquired in this course would be helpful to them in the future.
						Finally, the students composed a research essay in which secondary materials
						supplement and support close readings of the drama, an essay that was built,
						in part, by the cumulative assignments of the secondary source discovery
						activity, the response papers, the critical analysis proposal, and class
						discussions. By the end of the course, most students were able to identify
						historical and current developments in the study of British Romantic drama
						and were cognizant of the ways in which British Romantic drama reflected the
						cultural and historical issues of the late-eighteenth and early-nineteenth
						centuries. </p>
				</div>

			</div>



		</body>

	</text>
</TEI>
