<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author>Conor Hilton</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2022-09-09</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2022-09-09T22:24:47Z</date><name>Conor Hilton</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:14.5pt">Version A of “Ullswater Excursion”: DCMS 51 (1805)</hi></p><p style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="bold">Edited by Paul Westover</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">[Editor’s Note: </hi>T<hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">he notebook known as DCMS 51 includes the earliest extant version of Dorothy’s “Ullswater Excursion” plus fragments and draft introductions for the Ullswater text published in William’s </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Guide to the Lakes</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (1823)</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">.</hi><hi rend="endnote_reference"> <note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"> <hi style="font-family:PT Sans;font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Related fragments—not included in our edition—appear on pp. 1–5 of the notebook. Owen and Smyser account for them in the apparatus of </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-family:PT Sans;font-size:11pt">Prose</hi><hi style="font-family:PT Sans;font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, 2:368–78. </hi> </p></note></hi> <hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Here, we transcribe Dorothy’s complete version, headed “November 1805.” To the extent possible, we represent exactly what appears on the notebook’s pages; however, we ignore marks in pencil, which belong to a later date and serve to shape the text for publication. In doing so, we prefer so far as possible Dorothy’s “original” text to the adapted version prepared for William’s </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Guide</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">. For ease in comparing the transcription to the manuscript, we maintain the notebook’s lineation; however, long insertions sometimes cause lines to spill over. Unusually difficult passages are discussed in the notes.] </hi> </p><p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:11pt">Key:</hi></p><p><hi rend="strikethrough" style="font-size:11pt">Strikethrough</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> = a cancellation</hi></p><p><hi style="font-size:11pt">[scribbled out] = editor’s description of text</hi></p><p><hi style="font-size:11pt">[bracketed text] = insertions or deletions that are uncertain or difficult to read</hi></p><p><hi style="font-size:11pt">[?] indicates completely illegible text.</hi></p><p><hi style="font-size:11pt">^ marks insertion at beginning and end (no distinction made between insertions above or below the main line of text)]</hi></p><p style="text-align: center;"></p><p><hi rend="bold">DCMS 51, pp. 21–34, 12r–18v</hi></p><p style="text-align: center;">November 1805</p><p>William and Mary returned from Park House by the Patterdale</p><p>road on Sunday Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Actually, November 3. </hi></p></note></hi> (along with Mr &amp; Mrs Clarkson)</p><p>having made a delightful excursion of three days. They had</p><p>engaged that W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> and I would go to Mr Luff’s on the Wed-</p><p>nesday or Thursday if the weather continued favorable. It was</p><p>not very promising on Wednesday; but having been fine for</p><p>so long a time we thought there would not be an entire</p><p>change <hi rend="strikethrough">all</hi> at once; therefore, on a damp &amp; gloomy</p><p>morning we set forward; W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> on foot, and I upon the </p><p>pony, with W’s great coat slung over the saddle crutch, </p><p>and a wallet containing our bundle of needments. As we</p><p>went along the mists gathered upon the vallies, &amp; it even</p><p><hi rend="underline" xml:space="preserve">rained </hi>all the way to Patterdale; but there was never a</p><p>drop <hi rend="strikethrough">upon</hi> on my habit larger than the smallest pears<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> This is an error for “pearls.” Someone (likely WW or DW) made the correction later in pencil. </hi></p></note></hi></p><p><hi rend="strikethrough">up</hi>on a Lady’s ring. The trees upon the larger Island</p><p>on Rydale Lake were of the most gorgeous colours,</p><p>the whole Island reflected in the water, and I remem-</p><p>ber once, in particular, to have seen it with [<hi rend="strikethrough">dear C</hi>] Cole-</p><p>ridge when either he or W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> observed that the rocky shore,</p><p>spotted &amp; streaked with purplish brown heath, &amp; its image</p><p>in the water <hi rend="strikethrough">together</hi> ^indistinguishably blended^ were like an immense caterpillar,</p><p>such as when we were children we used to call</p><p><hi rend="underline" xml:space="preserve">Woolly Boys </hi>from their hairy coats. I had been a little </p><p>cowardly when we left home, fearing that heavy rains</p><p>might detain us at Patterdale; but, as the mists </p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 21, 12r]</hi></p><p>thickened our enjoyment<hi rend="strikethrough">s</hi> encreased &amp; my hopes grew bolder, </p><p>and when <hi rend="strikethrough">we were</hi> at the top of Kirkstone, though we </p><p>could not see fifty yards before us, we were as happy Travelers</p><p>as ever paced side by side on a holiday ramble. At such </p><p>a time, and in such a place every scattered stone the size</p><p>of one’s head becomes a companion. There is a fragment of</p><p>an old wall at the top of Kirkstone, which, magnified</p><p>yet obscured as it was by the mist, was scarcely less interest-</p><p>ing to us, [long set of scribbles, illegible cancellation] than the view</p><p>of <hi rend="strikethrough">[a noble]</hi> ^some^ monument of ancient grandeur <hi rend="strikethrough">has been</hi> —yet</p><p>this same pile of stones we had never before ever observed.</p><p>When we had descended considerably, the fields of Hartsop </p><p>below Brothers water were first seen, like a lake <hi rend="strikethrough">coloured</hi> ^tinged^ by</p><p>the reflection of yellow clouds. I mistook them for the water, </p><p>but soon after we saw the lake itself gleaming faintly</p><p>with a <hi rend="strikethrough">grey</hi> steelly brightness; then ^as we descended^ appeared the brown oaks</p><p>and the birches of <hi rend="strikethrough">splendid colour</hi> ^lovely yellow^, and, [<hi rend="strikethrough">when we came near</hi></p><p><hi rend="strikethrough">to the valley</hi>] the cottages, and <hi rend="strikethrough">the</hi> lowly <hi rend="strikethrough">old</hi> Hall of Hartsop </p><p>with its long roof and <hi rend="strikethrough" xml:space="preserve">elegant </hi>^[ancient]^ chimnies. We had eaten our</p><p>dinner under the shelter of a sheep-fold by a bridge near</p><p>the foot of the mountain, having tethered the pony at the </p><p>entrance, where it stood without one impatient beating of a </p><p>foot. I could not but love it for its meekness, and in-</p><p>deed I thought we were selfish to enjoy our meal so</p><p>much while its poor jaws were confined by the curb </p><p>bridle. We reached Luff’s ^in the afternoon^ about two hours before tea time.</p><p style="text-align: center;">Thursday Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Note that DW’s dating is consistently off by a day. The correct date for Thursday is 7 November. </hi></p></note></hi></p><p>The next morning incessant rain ill eleven o’</p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 22, 12v]</hi></p><p>o’clock when it became fair, and W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> and I walked to Blow-</p><p>ick. Luff joined us by the way. The wind [<hi rend="strikethrough">was</hi>] ^blew^ strong; and drove</p><p>the clouds forward along the side of the hill above our heads – four </p><p>or five goats were bounding among the rocks; the sheep mov-</p><p>ed about more quietly; or cowered under their sheltering places:</p><p>Two storm-stiffened black Yew trees on the Crag above<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> The manuscript is difficult in this section. DW does not cancel the reading we have reproduced; however, she adds, between lines, “Our friends fixed our notice as they were seen.” Perhaps “Luff’s house” was to become “our friends’ house” so that the whole revised sentence would read as follows: “Two storm-stiffened black yew trees on the Crag above our friends’ house fixed our notice as they were seen through the flying mists.”</hi></p></note></hi></p><p>Luff’s house were striking objects close under, or seen through</p><p>the flying mists. I do not know what to say of Blowick; for</p><p>to attempt to <hi rend="underline">describe</hi> the place would be absurd, when you</p><p>for whom I write have either been there, or may go thither</p><p>as soon as you like. When we stood under the naked Crag</p><p>upon the Common over looking <hi rend="strikethrough">its</hi> ^the^ woods and bush-besprin-</p><p>kled fields, the Lake, Clouds, and Mists were all in motion </p><p>to the sound of sweeping winds, the Church &amp; Cottages of</p><p>Patterdale scarcely visible from the brightness of the mist.</p><p>Looking <hi rend="strikethrough">backwards towards the foot of</hi> ^down^ the Lake, the scene</p><p>less visionary. Place Fell steady and bold <hi rend="strikethrough">as a lion</hi> the whole</p><p>Lake driving <hi rend="strikethrough">down</hi> ^onward^ like a great river – waves dancing</p><p>round the small islands. We walked to the house; the</p><p>Owner was salving sheep in the Barn – an appearance of</p><p>poverty &amp; decay every where <hi rend="strikethrough">visible</hi>: he asked us if we want-</p><p>ed to purchase the Estate. We could not but stop frequent-</p><p>ly, both in going &amp; returning, to observe the exquisite</p><p>beauty of the woods on the opposite side of the Lake.</p><p>The general color of the trees was brown, rather that of</p><p>ripe hazle nuts; but towards the water there were yet</p><p>beds of green; and in some of the hollow places in the </p><p>highest parts of the woods the trees were of a yellow</p><p>colour, and, through the glittering light, they looked like</p><p>masses of clouds, as you see them gathered together in</p><p>the west and tinged with the golden light of the sun.</p><p>After dinner we walked with M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Luff <hi rend="underline">up</hi> the Vale;</p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 23, 13r]</hi></p><p>I had never ^[<hi rend="strikethrough">before</hi>]^ had an idea of the extent and width of it</p><p>in passing through on the other side. We walked along the </p><p>path which leads from house to house – two or three times it</p><p>took us through some of those copses or groves that cover <hi rend="strikethrough">every</hi></p><p>little hillock^s^ in the middle of the lower part of the vale,</p><p>making an intricate and beautiful intermixture of lawn </p><p>^Our fancies could not resist the temptation &amp; we^<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Beginning here, DW adds material between the next three lines of text. The result is difficult to make intelligible in a transcription, but the intended final reading must be something like this: “Our fancies could not resist the temptation &amp; we fixed upon a spot for a cottage which we </hi><hi rend="strikethrough" style="font-size:11pt">built</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> began to build &amp; finished as easily as castles are raised in the air. We visited the same spot by moonlight that evening.” </hi></p></note></hi> </p><p>and wood. We left William to prolong his walk, and when</p><p>^ fixed upon a spot for a cottage which we <hi rend="strikethrough">built</hi> began to^</p><p>he came into the house he told us he had pitched upon a </p><p>^build &amp; finished as easily as castles are raised in the air^</p><p>spot where he should like better to build a cottage than</p><p>^We visited the same spot by moonlight that evening.^ </p><p>in any other he had yet seen. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Luff went with him</p><p>by moonlight to view it. The Vale looked ^at that time^ as if it were</p><p>filled with white light <hi rend="strikethrough">when</hi> the moon <hi rend="strikethrough">had</hi> ^having^ climbed </p><p>up ^[two cancelled words]^ to the middle of the sky; but <hi rend="strikethrough">long</hi> before we <hi rend="strikethrough">could</hi> ^had been able to^ see her</p><p>face, while all the near hills were <hi rend="strikethrough">in</hi> ^[covered with]^<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Possibly “covered by the.”</hi></p></note></hi> black shade, those on </p><p>the opposite side were almost as bright as snow. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Luff’s</p><p>large white Dog lay in the moonshine upon the round knoll</p><p>under the old Yew Tree – a beautiful and romantic image – </p><p>the dark Tree with its dark shadow, and the elegant</p><p>creature as fair as a Spirit.</p><p>Friday 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> ^Rain as before^ ^We [visited] the same spot by moonlight^<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> This is another difficult section of the manuscript. New writing enters crookedly, large portions of text are scribbled over in pencil, and it is hard to discern where insertions are meant to belong. DW adds, “We [illegible verb that ends with </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">tted</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">] for to visit the [?],” but unsure how to place this rejected text, we omit it from the transcription. </hi></p></note></hi></p><p>Next day. <hi rend="strikethrough">It r</hi>Rained till <hi rend="strikethrough">near</hi> ten o’clock, <hi rend="strikethrough">but a</hi>A<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Here, DW overwrites the lowercase </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">a</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> with a capital </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">A</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt">.</hi> </p></note></hi> </p><p>little after that time, it being likely for a tolerably fine</p><p>day, we packed up bread and cold meat, and, with ^a friend’s^ Luff’s</p><p>Servant to help to row, set forward in the Boat. As we ad-</p><p>-vanced the day grew finer – clouds and sunny gleams on</p><p>the mountains. In the <hi rend="strikethrough">grand</hi> Bay under Place Fell</p><p>we <hi rend="strikethrough" xml:space="preserve">saw </hi>^T^three Fisherman dragging a net, <hi rend="strikethrough">and rowed up to</hi></p><p><hi rend="strikethrough" xml:space="preserve">them. </hi>They had just brought the net ashore; and </p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 24, 13v]</hi></p><p>hundreds of fish were leaping in their prison. They were <hi rend="strikethrough">all</hi></p><p>of <hi rend="strikethrough">one</hi> ^the^ kind; <hi rend="strikethrough">what are</hi> called Skellies. <hi rend="strikethrough">After we had left</hi></p><p><hi rend="strikethrough">them</hi> The Fishermen <hi rend="strikethrough">continued their work</hi>, a picturesque group</p><p>under the lofty and bare crags. ^around which^ <hi rend="strikethrough">The whole scene was very grand</hi></p><p>– a raven ^was^ croaking <hi rend="strikethrough">on the mountain above our heads</hi>. Landed</p><p><hi rend="underline">at</hi> ^<hi rend="strikethrough">near to</hi>^ ^in the Bay of^ Sanwick; <hi rend="strikethrough">the Man took the Boat home,</hi> and we pur-</p><p>sued our journey towards the Village along a beautiful</p><p>summer path – at first through a coppice by the Lakeside;</p><p>then through green fields. The Village and Brook <hi rend="strikethrough">very</hi></p><p><hi rend="strikethrough">pretty;</hi> shut out from Mountains and Lakes – <hi rend="strikethrough">it reminded</hi></p><p><hi rend="strikethrough">me of Somersetshire</hi>. Passed by Harry Hibson’s House. I longed</p><p>to go in for the sake of old times. W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> went up one side of </p><p>the Vale and we up the other, and he joined us again after</p><p>having crossed the one-arched Bridge below the Church, with</p><p>^[?] according to the custom of the season^ its “bare ring of mossy wall,” and simple yew tree. At the </p><p>last house in the Dale we were <hi rend="strikethrough">kindly</hi> greeted by</p><p>the Master, who was sitting at the door ^<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"> <hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">In this passage, presenting insertions as they appear on the page makes the transcription slightly confusing. Obviously, DW means the fragments to stick together: “with sheep collected around him one of which he was smearing with tar for protection against the winter cold.” </hi> </p></note></hi>with sheep collected around him one of which he was smearing^ <hi rend="strikethrough">salving</hi> sheep –</p><p>^with tar for protection against the winter cold^ He invited us to <hi rend="strikethrough">go in</hi> ^enter his house^ and see a room built by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> </p><p>Hazel for his accommodation ^of his friends^ at the yearly Chace</p><p>of Red Deer in his Forests at the head of these</p><p>Dales. The Room is fitted up in the Sportsman’s style,</p><p>with a simple cupboard for bottles and glasses &amp;c.</p><p>Some strong chairs, and a large dining-table, and or-</p><p>namented with the Horns of the Stags caught at these</p><p>Hunts for many years back, with the length of the </p><p>Last race <hi rend="strikethrough">they</hi> ^each had^ run recorded under <hi rend="strikethrough">each</hi> ^his stately antlers^. We ate </p><p>our dinner here. The good woman treated us with</p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 25, 14r]</hi></p><p>excellent butter and <hi rend="strikethrough">new</hi> oaten <hi rend="strikethrough">Bread</hi> ^Cakes, new &amp; crisp^, <hi rend="strikethrough" xml:space="preserve">and after </hi>drink</p><p>-ing <hi rend="strikethrough">of M</hi><hi rend="superscript strikethrough">r</hi><hi rend="strikethrough" xml:space="preserve"> Hazel’s strong ale we were well</hi> prepared</p><p><hi rend="strikethrough">to</hi> ^We^ faced the mountain, which we began to climb almost</p><p>immediately. Martindale divides itself into two dales at the</p><p>head. In one of these (that to the left) there is no house</p><p>nor any building to be seen but a cattle-shed on the side</p><p>of a hill which is sprinkled over with wood, evidently</p><p>the remains of a Forest; formerly a [illegible cancellation] very</p><p>extensive one. At the bottom of the other dell is the house</p><p>I have mentioned; and beyond the enclosures of this Man’s</p><p>Farm there are no other. A few old trees remain, relicks</p><p>of the Forest, a little stream passes in serpentine wind</p><p>-ings through the uncultivated valley, where many cattle</p><p>were feeding. The Cattle of this country are generally</p><p>white, or light-coloured, but these were mostly dark</p><p>brown or black which <hi rend="strikethrough">made the scene resemble</hi> ^heightened the resemblance which this scene bears to^ many parts of Scotland.</p><p>When we <hi rend="strikethrough">sate on</hi> ^paused to rest upon^ the hill-</p><p>side, though we were well contented with the quiet</p><p>every-day sounds – the lowing of the Cattle, bleating of</p><p>sheep, &amp; the very gentle murmuring of the valley-Stream,</p><p><hi rend="strikethrough">yet</hi> we could not but think what a grand effect the </p><p>sound of the bugle horn would have among these Moun-</p><p>tains. It is still heard once every year at the Chace</p><p>I have spoken of, a day of festivity for all the Inhabi-</p><p>tants of this district, except the poor Deer, the most </p><p>ancient of them all. The ascent, even to the very top </p><p>of the mountain is very easy. When we had accomplished</p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 26, 14v]</hi></p><p>it we had <hi rend="strikethrough">some</hi> exceedingly fine <hi rend="strikethrough">mountain</hi> views, some of the</p><p>mountains being resplendent with sunshine &amp; others partly hid</p><p>-den by clouds. Ulswater was of a dazzling brightness bordered</p><p>by black hills. The Plain beyond Penrith smooth &amp; bright</p><p>or rather gleamy, as the Sea or Sea-sands. Looked ^down^ into Boar</p><p>Dale, <hi rend="strikethrough">above Sanwick</hi> – deep and bare – a stream winding</p><p>through it. After having walked a considerable way along</p><p>the tops of the hills came in view of <hi rend="strikethrough">Sanwick</hi> Glenridden,</p><p>and the Mountains at the head of Grisdale. <hi rend="strikethrough">Luff then</hi> ^Our companion^</p><p><hi rend="strikethrough">took us</hi> turned aside before we had begun to descend to a small</p><p>Ruin, which was formerly a Chapel, or place of worship,</p><p>where ^it is said^ the Inhabitants of Martindale and Patterdale were</p><p>accustomed to meet on Sabbath days. There are now</p><p>no traces by which you could distinguish that the</p><p>Building had been different from a common Sheep fold; </p><p>the loose stones, &amp; the few which yet remain piled up</p><p>are the same ^in appearance^ as those which lie elsewhere on the</p><p>mountain, but the shape of the Building, being oblong,</p><p>is not that of a common Sheep-fold; and it stands</p><p>East &amp; West. Whether it was ever consecrated ground</p><p>or not, I do not know; but the place may be kept </p><p>holy in the memory of some now living in Patter-</p><p>dale; for it was the means of preserving the</p><p>life of a poor old Man last summer who, having gone up</p><p>the mountain to gather peats together, had been overtaken</p><p>by a storm, and could not find his way down again.</p><p>He happened to be near the remains of the old Chapel</p><p>and in a corner of it he contrived, by laying turf, &amp; ling,</p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 27, 15r]</hi></p><p>and stones in a corner of it from one wall to the other, to make</p><p>a shelter from the wind, and there he sate all night.</p><p>The Woman who had sent him on his errand began to</p><p>grow uneasy towards evening, &amp; the Neighbours went to</p><p>seek him. At that time the old Man had housed himself</p><p>in his nest, &amp; he heard the voices of the men; but could not</p><p>make himself heard, the wind being so loud; &amp; he was afraid </p><p>to leave the spot, least he should not be able to find it</p><p>again, so he remained there all night, and they return-</p><p>ed to their homes, giving him up for lost; but the next</p><p>morning the same persons discovered him, huddled up in</p><p>the sheltered nook. He was at first stupefied, &amp; unable</p><p>to move, yet after he had eaten and drunk, &amp; recollected</p><p>himself a little he walked down the Mountain, and his </p><p>health did not afterwards seem to have suffered. As we</p><p>descend the Vale of Patterdale appears very simple</p><p>and grand with its two heads, Deep dale, &amp; Brothers-water</p><p>or Hartsop. It is remarkable that two pairs of Brothers</p><p>should have been drowned in that Lake. There is a traditi-</p><p>on, at least, that <hi rend="strikethrough">two were drowned there</hi> it took its</p><p>name from two who were drowned there many years</p><p>ago; and it is a fact that two others did meet that</p><p>melancholy fate about twenty years since. It was after </p><p>a New-year’s-day. Their Mother had sent them to thresh</p><p>some corn, and they (probably thinking it hard to be so </p><p>tasked when all others were keeping holiday) stole out</p><p>to slide upon the ice, and were both drowned. A neighbour</p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 28, 15v]</hi></p><p>who had seen them fall through the ice, though not near</p><p>enough to be certain, <hi rend="underline">guessed who</hi> they were, &amp; went to the Mother</p><p>to enquire after her Sons. She replied that “they were threshing</p><p>in the Barn.” “Nay,” said the Man, “they are not there, nor is </p><p>it likely today.” The Woman went with him to the Barn,</p><p>and the Boys were gone. He was then convinced of the truth,</p><p>and told her that they were drowned. It is said that they</p><p>were found locked in each other’s arms. I was exceedingly</p><p>tired when we reached M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Luff’s house, owing to the </p><p>steepness and roughness of the peat track down which</p><p>we descended. I lay down on the Sofa, &amp; was asleep in</p><p>three minutes. – A fine moonlight night – a </p><p>thick fog in the middle of the Vale, which dishear-</p><p>tened William respecting the situation of his house.</p><p>—Supped upon some of the Fish caught by the Fish</p><p>-ermen under Place Fell, &amp; thought them excellent.</p><p>Saturday 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> </p><p>		A beautiful morning. When we</p><p>were at breakfast heard the tidings of Lord Nelson’s </p><p>Death, &amp; the Victory at Trafalgar – Went to the Inn</p><p>to make further inquiries. I was shocked to hear that there </p><p>had been great rejoicings at Penrith. Returned by</p><p>William’s rock &amp; grove; &amp; were so much pleased with </p><p>the spot that he determined to buy it, if possible, therefore</p><p>we prepared to set off to Park House, that W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> might</p><p>apply to Thomas Wilkinson to negotiate for him with</p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 29, 16r]</hi></p><p>the Owner. ^[At the same hour as the day before]^ We went down that side of the Lake opposite to</p><p>^At 10 o’clock we pursued our way on foot on the on the same side^ </p><p>Sty barrow Crag. I dismounted &amp; we sate some time on the</p><p>^of the Lake which we had coasted in a Boat the day before.^</p><p>same Rock as before above Blowick. <hi rend="strikethrough">Owing to t</hi>The<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> To make “The” the beginning of the revised sentence, DW overwrites her lowercase </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">t </hi><hi style="font-size:11pt">with a capital one.</hi></p></note></hi> bright</p><p>^[?] above the Farm of^ -ness of the sunshine ^concealed from us^ the Church and other buildings <hi rend="strikethrough">were</hi></p><p>even more ^than the haze &amp; vapour had done the <hi rend="strikethrough">day before</hi>^ <hi rend="strikethrough">concealed from</hi> us than by <hi rend="strikethrough">the</hi> mists two days</p><p>before. It had been a sharp frost in the night and</p><p>the grass and trees were yet wet. We observed the lemon-colour-</p><p>ed leaves of the birches in the wood below, as the wind turn-</p><p>ed them to the sun, sparkle or rather <hi rend="underline">flash</hi> like diamonds.</p><p>The day continued unclouded to the end. ^&amp; I <hi rend="strikethrough">shal</hi>l not^ We had a delight-</p><p>^describe <hi rend="strikethrough">either</hi> the scene or relate our little adventures but will^<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Despite the confusing placement of the insertions, DW obviously intends, “I shall not describe the scene or relate our little adventures, but will only add,” and so forth. </hi></p></note></hi> </p><p>ful Ride and walk, for it was both to both of us. We led</p><p>^only [add?]^ the horse under Place Fell, and though I mostly rode when</p><p>the way was good, yet William sometimes mounted to rest</p><p>himself. Called at Eusemere, the Miss Greens not yet </p><p>settled in their house. Went by Bower Bank, intending </p><p>to ford the Emont at the Mill, but the Pony could not</p><p>carry us both; so after many attempts, I rode over myself</p><p>&amp; a Girl followed upon another Horse to carry back the Pony</p><p>to William. Very cold before we reached Park House</p><p>– Carpets &amp; chairs spread upon the grass. Derwent ran </p><p>out to meet us. Sate in the kitchen till the parlour fire </p><p>was lighted; &amp; then enjoyed a comfortable [<hi rend="strikethrough">dish]</hi> ^cup^ of tea.</p><p>After tea W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> went to Thomas Wilkinson’s &amp; to Brougham.</p><p>Monday Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> </p><p>			The morning being fine, we resolved to </p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 30, 16v]</hi></p><p>go to Lowther, &amp; accordingly Sara mounted Tom’s horse, I the pony,</p><p>&amp; William &amp; Miss Green set out on foot; but she had not </p><p>walked far before she took a seat behind Sara. – Crossed</p><p>the Ford at Yanworth. We found Thomas Wilkinson at work</p><p>in one of his fields: he chearfully laid down his spade, &amp;</p><p>walked by our side with William. We left our horses at</p><p>the Mill below Brougham &amp; walked through the woods</p><p>till we came to the [illegible cancel] Quarry where the road ends, the</p><p>very place which has been the Boundary of some of the hap-</p><p>piest of the walks of my youth. The sun did not shine</p><p>when we were there; &amp; it was midday, therefore if it <hi rend="underline">had</hi></p><p>shone, the light could not have been the same; yet so vivid</p><p>-ly did I call to mind those walks, that when I was in the </p><p>wood I almost seemed to see the same rich light of</p><p>evening upon the trees which I had seen in those happy</p><p>hours. [Cancelled sentence, illegible.]<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> The heavily canceled sentence must be similar or identical to one that appears in the Coleorton Manuscript: “My heart was full; and I could not but grieve that any strangers were with us.” </hi></p></note></hi></p><p>At this time the</p><p>Path was scarcely traceable by the eye, all the ground</p><p>being obscure with withered leaves, which I was very sorry for,</p><p>William having described the beauty of it with so much de-</p><p>light after having been at Lowther in the summer.</p><p>Scrambled along, under the Quarry – then came to T.</p><p>Wilkinson’s new path. We spent three delightful hours</p><p>by the Riverside &amp; in the woods. We were received </p><p>with much kindness by Richard Bowman &amp; his Wife</p><p>-dinner was presently prepared; &amp; we were officiously</p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 31, 17r]</hi></p><p>upon<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> No doubt DW intends this to read “waited upon by little Hannah” but accidentally skips a word on moving to the next page. </hi></p></note></hi> by little Hannah, whose light motions and happy</p><p>looks plainly expressed the hospitality of the house.</p><p>Went with Miss Green to Penrith – drank tea at M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></p><p>Ellwoods –Read Collingwood’s dispatches- went to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> James’s</p><p>Shop &amp; called upon Miss Monkhouse at M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Coupland’s.</p><p>Mary Monkhouse &amp; Sara mounted at the George. I</p><p>walked with W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> through the town to Mrs Ellwood’s door –</p><p>the first time I have been in Penrith streets [<hi rend="strikethrough">after day-]</hi></p><p>[<hi rend="strikethrough">light</hi>] at that time of the night since Mary &amp; her</p><p>Sister Margaret, and I used to steal out to each other’s</p><p>houses and when we had had our <hi rend="underline">talk</hi> over the kitchen</p><p>fire, to delay the moment of parting, paced up one street</p><p>and down another<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> DW inadvertently repeats “to delay the moment of parting, paced up one street and down another.” The second instance is canceled, but only in pencil (i.e., at a later date). </hi></p></note></hi> to delay the moment of parting, paced</p><p>up one street and down another by moon or star light.</p><p>S. and I stopped at Red Hills while William went over</p><p>the Ford to T. Wilkinson’s – the house untidy &amp; not</p><p>comfortable – a little Girl never ceased rocking a Baby</p><p>in the Cradle. We asked if it would not sleep without</p><p>being rocked, &amp; the Mother answered “No; for it was used</p><p>to it.” Reached Park House at ten o’clock. Joanna had</p><p>waited dinner and tea for us. </p><p>	Tuesday Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>   ^&amp; will only add that on the afternoon of the [13] we returned <hi rend="strikethrough">from</hi> [underneath] after [?] [?]^</p><p>A very wet morning – no hope </p><p>of being able to return home ^by the usual road^. W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> read in a Book</p><p>lent him by T. Wilkinson. I read Castle Rackrent.</p><p>The day cleared at one o’clock, &amp; after dinner, at a </p><p>little before three we set forward. The pony was bogged </p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 32, 17v]</hi></p><p>in Tom’s field, &amp; I was obliged to dismount. Went over Soulby</p><p>Fell. <hi rend="strikethrough">Before we reached Ulswater the sun</hi> shone, ^The morning had been wet but now the sun shone [?]^ and only </p><p>a few scattered clouds remained on the hills except at the </p><p>tops of the very highest – the Lake perfectly calm. We had</p><p>a delightful journey. At the beginning of the first Park</p><p>William got upon the pony, and, betwixt a walk and</p><p>a <hi rend="underline">run</hi>, I kept pace with him while he trotted to the</p><p>next gate – then I mounted again. We were joined by</p><p>two Travellers, like ourselves with one white horse be-</p><p>tween them. We went on in company till we came</p><p>near to Patterdale, trotting all the time. The trees in<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> DW injects material between the next several lines without indicating precisely where it belongs, though the insertion point seems to follow “The trees in Gowbarrow Park were.” While the additions are difficult to decipher, they seem to read more or less as follows: “in that state when what is gained in interest by the disclosure of their Bark and Brambles compensates almost for the loss of foliage; they exhibited that variety which characterizes the point of time between autumn &amp; winter.” </hi></p></note></hi></p><p>^[in interest]^ Gowbarrow Park were ^in that state when what is gained^ very beautiful, the hawthorns ^by the disclosure of their Bark &amp; Brambles compensates [?]^ </p><p>leafless, their round heads covered with rich red berries</p><p>and ^almost for the loss of foliage <hi rend="strikethrough">[? ? ?]</hi>^ adorned with arches of green brambles and Eglantine </p><p>hung with glossy ^they exhibited [<hi rend="strikethrough">?</hi>] that variety which^ hips – Many birches yet tricked out ^characterizes the point in time between autumn &amp; winter^</p><p>in full foliage of bright yellow – oaks brown or leafless</p><p>– the smooth ^[silver]^ branches of the Ashes bare – most of the </p><p>Alders green as in spring. I think I have more plea</p><p>-sure in looking at deer than any other animals; per</p><p>-haps chiefly from their living in a more natural</p><p>state. At the end of Gowbarrow Park a large troop</p><p>of them were either moving slowly or standing still</p><p>among the fern. I was grieved when <hi rend="strikethrough">our</hi> ^a chance^ Companions</p><p>^who had joined us by the way^ startled them with a whistle, disturbing a beautiful</p><p>image of grave simplicity &amp; thoughtful enjoyment,</p><p>for I could have fancied that even <hi rend="underline">they</hi> were partaking</p><p>with me a sensation of the solemnity of the closing</p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 33, 18r]</hi></p><p>day. The sun had been set some time ^but as the Lake <hi rend="strikethrough">though</hi> ^and^ <hi rend="strikethrough">we</hi> could <hi rend="strikethrough">only</hi></p><p>just perceive that the day-light was fading away from</p><p>the hills, <hi rend="strikethrough">and</hi> ^but^ the lake ^[Under a luminous sky]^ was more brilliant than before.</p><p>I dismounted again at Stybarrow Crag &amp; William rode</p><p>till we came almost to Glenridden. Found the Luffs</p><p>at Tea in the kitchen. After Tea ^at Patterdale^ set out again. Luff</p><p>accompanied me on foot unto the lane, &amp; W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> continued</p><p>to ride till we came to Brothers-water Bridge – a </p><p>delightful evening. The Seven Stars close to the hill</p><p>tops in Patterdale – All the stars seemed brighter than</p><p>usual. The steeps were reflected in Brother’s water; and</p><p>above the Lake appeared like enormous black perpen-</p><p>dicular walls. The torrents of Kirkstone had been swoln</p><p>by the rains, &amp; filled the mountain Pass with their </p><p>roaring, which added greatly to the solemnity of our</p><p>walk. Behind us, when we had climbed very high, we</p><p>saw one light in the Vale at a great distance, like</p><p>a large ^red^ star, a solitary one, in the gloomy region - all</p><p>the chearfulness of the scene was ^transferred^ in the sky above us.</p><p>	Found Mary &amp; the Children in bed – no fire – luckily</p><p>W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> was warm with walking, &amp; I not cold, having wrap-</p><p>ped myself up most carefully, &amp; the night being <hi rend="strikethrough">mild</hi></p><p>mild – Went to bed immediately after Supper. </p><p><hi rend="color(984806)">[Page Break—end p. 34, 18v]</hi></p></body></text></TEI>