<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author>Paul Westover</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-09-09</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2022-09-09T19:04:28Z</date><name>Paul Westover</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p style="text-align: center;"
                    ><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:14pt" xml:space="preserve">Introduction to </hi><hi
                    rend="italic bold" style="font-size:14pt">Dorothy Wordsworth’s Lake
                    District</hi>
            </p>
            <p style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="bold">A Romantic Circles Electronic
                    Edition</hi></p>
            <p style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="bold">Edited by Michelle Levy, Nicholas Mason,
                    and Paul Westover</hi></p>
            <p>On Christmas Day of 2021, admirers of Dorothy Wordsworth (1771–1855) around the world
                celebrated the sestercentennial of a writer who, after long years in her elder
                brother’s shadow, has at last gained an independent reputation. Dorothy (fig. 1) is
                now widely known as one of nineteenth-century England’s most perspicacious nature
                writers and keen-eyed chroniclers of the everyday. There has never been a better
                time to study her life and work, as besides an ever-growing body of biographical and
                critical studies, recent decades have seen the arrival of several important print
                collections of her writings, including the first-ever classroom anthology of her
                “greatest hits” as a diarist, travel writer, and poet.<hi rend="endnote_reference"
                        ><note place="end"><p rend="RJ notes"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> See Susan Levin’s classroom anthology </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Dorothy Wordsworth: A Longman
                                Cultural
                                Edition</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2009). Other important additions to the modern DW library include Pamela Woof’s Oxford World’s Classics edition of </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">The Grasmere and Alfoxden
                                Journals</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2002) and Carol Kyros Walker’s illustrated edition of DW’s</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Recollections of a Tour Made in
                                Scotland</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (1997).</hi></p></note></hi>
                And, thanks to Google Books and other digital libraries, anyone with an internet
                connection can now freely access scans of the late Victorian editions that first
                introduced Dorothy’s (nearly) complete works to a broad readership.<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> For our rationale in referencing the author throughout this edition as “Dorothy” rather than “Wordsworth” or “Dorothy Wordsworth,” see the separate prefatory essay on </hi>
                            <hi rend="color(0070C0)" style="font-size:11pt">Editorial Philosophies
                                and Guidelines</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt"
                >.</hi></p></note></hi></p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1001" width="4.817338888888889cm" height="5.941391666666667cm"
                    url="media/image1.jpg" rend="inline"/>
            </figure>
            <p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Figure
                    1:</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Silhouette of Dorothy Wordsworth, ca. 1806, one of only three known likenesses of her</hi><hi
                    style="font-size:10.5pt"
                >.</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Courtesy: Wordsworth Trust)</hi></p>
            <p>Even in the wake of such advances,
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Dorothy Wordsworth’s Lake District </hi>represents
                a major step forward for both the general availability and scholarly study of her
                remarkable journals, poems, and travel writings. While more a topical anthology than
                complete works edition, this Romantic Circles Electronic Edition offers by far the
                most extensively annotated and meticulously transcribed collection of Dorothy’s
                texts to date. Its central thematic focus is the deep connection, at once aesthetic,
                affective, and spiritual, that this most observant of writers felt with the people
                and scenery of her native Lake District. Yet, even while concentrated on a single
                region, this edition might also be taken as a general introduction to Dorothy’s
                writings, as it samples widely from her output in a range of genres and across all
                phases of her adult life, featuring both well-known works like her Grasmere journal
                notebooks and others that have either never before been published or never appeared
                in a reliable edition. Several texts, moreover, appear in multiple versions, and all
                are introduced with critical essays and headnotes explaining their composition,
                reception, and biographical and historical contexts. </p>
            <p>To cater to specialized scholars and general readers alike, we have divided our
                prefatory material into two parts. This introduction reviews the pertinent aspects
                of Dorothy’s life, our rationale for focusing on her Lakeland writings, and the
                edition’s contents. A separate essay on our <hi rend="color(0000FF)">“Editorial
                    Philosophy and Guidelines” [link]</hi> situates this project within the history
                of editing women writers in general and Dorothy Wordsworth in particular,
                articulates the advantages of publishing such an edition in an open-access digital
                format, and summarizes our editorial practices and principles of selection.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold color(0070C0)">A Life in the Lakes</hi></p>
            <p>The third of John and Ann Wordsworth’s five eventual children, and their only
                daughter, Dorothy Wordsworth was born on 25 December 1771 in Cockermouth,
                Cumberland, a town in the northwest corner of the English Lake District (fig. 2).
                After six happy years with her parents and brothers, she suddenly found her
                comfortable childhood upended by her mother’s passing in early 1778. While her
                brothers would remain in the Lakes, staying with relatives when not attending
                Hawkshead Grammar School, Dorothy would largely be exiled from the region for over
                two decades, spending most of her formative years with relatives in Halifax,
                Yorkshire (1778–1787) and Forncett, Norfolk (1788–1794). An 18-month stay with her
                maternal grandparents in Penrith in 1787–1788 did little to ease her sense of
                displacement, though it did rekindle her love for the region’s beauty and yield
                lifelong friendships, especially with her future sister-in-law, Mary Hutchinson. </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1002" width="16.51cm" height="8.537222222222223cm"
                    url="media/image2.jpeg" rend="inline">
                    <desc>A map of the world Description automatically generated with low
                        confidence</desc>
                </graphic>
            </figure>
            <p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Figure 2:</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Pullout “Map of the Lakes” (with north on the right and west on the top) from Thomas West’s </hi><hi
                    rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">A Guide to the Lakes, in Cumberland,
                    Westmorland, and Lancashire</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 5th ed. (London: W.
                    Richardson, 1793). Cockermouth is in the upper right corner and Ambleside, Rydal
                    Water, and Grasmere are slightly right of center.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For good reason, then, virtually every biographer has stressed the joy and relief
                Dorothy felt in her mid-to-late 20s upon reconnecting with her siblings and
                returning to her native Cumbria. What is generally considered the happiest period of
                her life began in 1795, when she and William, the brother 20 months her senior to
                whom she had always felt especially close, were finally able to live under the same
                roof. Four years later, after sojourns in the south of England and in Germany, they
                and their younger brother John began planning to establish a permanent home in the
                Lakes. While touring the Lake District with Samuel Taylor Coleridge in November
                1799, William reported to Dorothy that “C[oleridge] was much struck with Grasmere
                and its neighbourhood and I have much to say to you[;] you will think my plan a mad
                one, but I have thought of building a house there by the Lake side. John would give
                me £40 to buy the ground, and for £250 I am sure I could build one as good as we can
                    wish.”<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="RJ notes">
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Letters</hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">, 1:272.</hi></p></note></hi> This vision
                clearly outpaced their finances, as William and Dorothy were tight on funds and John
                was just launching his career as a merchant sailor. Nevertheless, the siblings were
                so taken with the prospect of making a home together in Grasmere that by the year’s
                end William and Dorothy had taken a lease on the home now known as Dove Cottage and
                John had promised to join them on his next shore leave.</p>
            <p>Lucy Newlyn recently observed that, “returning to the Lake District to reclaim their
                regional identity and reestablish their family, the Wordsworths found themselves at
                one remove from their childhood origins—neither insiders nor quite outsiders in
                    Grasmere.”<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="RJ notes">
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Newlyn</hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">, 120.</hi></p></note></hi> Yet any such dual
                consciousness was likely felt more acutely by Dorothy than her brothers, as, unlike
                them, she had not spent her formative years attending school just south of Grasmere
                in Hawkshead. Accordingly, her distinctive position as an insider-outsider in the
                Central Lakes frequently shows through in earlier selections in this edition
                (especially the first journal notebook), which display a deep curiosity about the
                area’s society, topography, and plant and animal species and speak in the voice of
                one making the transition from tourist to longtime resident. </p>
            <p>While William and Dorothy would never build the dream house they began imagining in
                1799, their other wish, to establish a permanent home in the area, was fulfilled
                entirely. Dove Cottage served as their cramped but cherished abode from December
                1799 through May 1808, a period when the siblings composed many of their most iconic
                works and were joined first by Mary Hutchinson, whom William married in October
                1802, and then by the couple’s first three children. Famously, these were years of
                “plain living and high thinking,”<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="RJ notes"
                            ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Line 11 of WW’s sonnet “Written in London. September, 1802.”</hi></p></note></hi>
                blending domestic work, literary collaboration, and outdoor pursuits. Having
                outgrown Dove Cottage, the family spent three years at Allan Bank in Grasmere, where
                William and Mary’s two youngest children were born, followed by two years in the
                village rectory (figures 3–4). Then, in May 1813, after William secured a government
                post that significantly eased the family’s money worries, they moved two miles east
                of Grasmere to Rydal Mount, the spacious and comfortable home in which William,
                Mary, and Dorothy would reside until their respective deaths in the 1850s. </p>
            <p style="text-align: center;"><graphic n="1003" width="8.717794444444445cm"
                    height="5.2753861111111116cm" url="media/image3.png" rend="inline">
                    <desc>Map Description automatically generated</desc>
                </graphic><seg xml:space="preserve">  </seg>
                <graphic n="1004" width="6.979361111111111cm" height="5.287461111111111cm"
                    url="media/image4.png" rend="inline">
                    <desc>Diagram Description automatically generated</desc>
                </graphic></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Figures 3 and 4: </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Views of Grasmere from the 1897 Ordnance Survey of England and Wales, showing the Wordsworths’ three homes: Dove Cottage (top center of Fig. 3), Allan Bank (top center of Fig. 4), and The Rectory (bottom right of Fig. 4). </hi></p>
            <p>The Wordsworths’ Grasmere period is rightly celebrated in the annals of British
                literature. But if, as traditional accounts suggest, William’s peak years as a poet
                were behind him by 1813, the family’s first two decades at Rydal Mount saw Dorothy
                reach new heights both in her literary creativity and output. There she composed
                most of her poems and reworked for potential publication journals she kept on the
                Continent in 1820 and in Scotland in 1822. At Rydal she also returned to keeping a
                daily journal, ultimately filling 15 notebooks, known collectively as the <hi
                    rend="italic">Rydal Journals</hi>, between 1824 and 1835. Two of these
                notebooks, the first and last, appear in their entirety for the first time in this
                edition.</p>
            <p>Into her late fifties, Dorothy remained remarkably vigorous both in mind and body,
                frequently remarking that she felt even more energetic than in her twenties. But, as
                chronicled in the latter half of the <hi rend="italic">Rydal Journals</hi>, her
                health gradually but irreparably declined after she became severely ill in early
                1829. By the end of 1835 chronic pain, a lack of stamina, and intermittent dementia
                effectively ended her writing career, and she would spend her final two decades
                confined to the house and grounds of Rydal Mount. After her passing on 25 January
                1855, she was buried in the Grasmere churchyard alongside her brother William and
                numerous beloved friends and family members. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold color(0070C0)">Imagining “Dorothy Wordsworth’s Guide to the
                    Lakes”</hi></p>
            <p>Considering that in his later years William was widely seen as England’s greatest
                living bard and that he would eventually replace Byron as the face of British
                Romanticism, it was perhaps inevitable that his sister’s life and works would first
                be valued primarily for whatever insights they afforded into his writings. And,
                while just how willingly Dorothy played the handmaiden to William’s genius remains
                hotly contested, her letters and journals suggest she would have had few qualms
                about going down in literary history as her brother’s unwavering assistant and
                occasional collaborator.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="RJ notes"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> The ongoing debate over DW’s agency and WW’s treatment of her is front and center in two recent biographies. In Frances Wilson’s </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">The Ballad of Dorothy Wordsworth </hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">(2008), DW is cast as the victim of unrelenting emotional abuse at WW’s hands, which ultimately led to her early-onset dementia. More persuasively, Lucy Newlyn presents their relationship as undeniably collaborative and companionate, as reflected in her titling her 2013 joint biography </hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">William and Dorothy Wordsworth:
                                “All in Each Other</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt"
                    >.”</hi></p></note></hi> Moreover, it is abundantly clear from the trove of
                unpublished journals, travelogues, stories, poems, and commonplace books she left
                behind that she wrote primarily for herself or close family and friends. </p>
            <p>At the same time, as this collection repeatedly demonstrates, many of Dorothy’s
                literary efforts had a more public-facing and professional intent than has generally
                been acknowledged. Her longtime friend Thomas De Quincey, for one, attested to both
                her distinctive genius and bona fides as public author when he maintained in 1839,
                “Miss Wordsworth would have merited a separate notice in any biographical dictionary
                of our times, had there even been no William Wordsworth in existence.”<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="RJ notes">
                            <hi style="font-size:11pt">De Quincey, “Lake Reminiscences,
                            254.</hi></p></note></hi> Seconding De Quincey’s assessment, this
                edition shines the spotlight solely on Dorothy, showcasing her gifts in a variety of
                literary forms and her distinctive perspectives on the people and places of the
                English Lakes. </p>
            <p>The initial spark for this project can be traced to an earlier Romantic Circles
                collaboration, the scholarly edition of William Wordsworth’s <ref
                    target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/guide_lakes"><hi rend="italic"
                        style="font-family:PT Sans">Guide to the Lakes</hi></ref> that Nicholas
                Mason and Paul Westover, in collaboration with students and colleagues at Brigham
                Young University (BYU), published in 2015 and revised and expanded in 2020. While
                investigating the textual history of the five distinct editions of William’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Guide</hi>, we were routinely struck by his sister’s crucial, if
                largely unacknowledged, contributions. This led us to ponder what a “Guide to the
                Lakes” written entirely by Dorothy might look like, a question we soon took up with
                Michelle Levy of Simon Fraser University (SFU), a fellow Romanticist who had worked
                extensively with Dorothy’s manuscripts in researching her articles and books on
                women’s writing, manuscript culture, and family authorship. </p>
            <p>As we three began seriously considering how we might reverse engineer such a
                “guidebook” from Dorothy’s writings on the Lakes, we turned to Jeff Cowton, the
                longtime curator at the Wordsworth Trust, and several BYU and SFU students who had
                worked with the Wordsworths’ manuscripts while interning or studying in Grasmere.
                The result has been a collaborative process of over seven years, in which the three
                lead editors have worked with the Wordsworth Trust and student researchers to study,
                transcribe, and contextualize Dorothy’s works. Although, in their final forms, the
                critical apparatus and texts to follow were primarily authored or edited by an
                experienced scholar—with Michelle Levy leading out on the Grasmere Journal excerpts,
                the Greens narrative, and the poems; Paul Westover on the Ullswater and Scafell Pike
                excursions; and Nicholas Mason on the <hi rend="italic">Rydal Journals</hi>—every
                part of this edition has been deeply collaborative.<hi rend="endnote_reference"
                        ><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> For a complete list of students, colleagues, archivists, and others who assisted with this edition, see the </hi><hi
                                rend="color(0000FF)" style="font-size:11pt">Acknowledgments
                                [link].</hi></p></note></hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the early stages of this project, we informally called it “Dorothy Wordsworth’s
                Guide to the Lakes.” But, not wanting to confuse readers or perpetuate the image of
                Dorothy invariably following in her older brother’s footsteps, we eventually settled
                on the less allusive “Dorothy Wordsworth’s Lake District.” Whatever its liabilities,
                however, our working title still encapsulates our vision of gathering and showcasing
                Dorothy’s vivid portraits of this famously picturesque region, which ultimately
                became Lake District National Park (1951) and a UNESCO World Heritage Site (2017).
                Strictly speaking, apart from the substantial sections she supplied for William’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Guide</hi>, Dorothy never composed guidebook material as
                    such.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="RJ notes"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> For details on DW’s contributions to WW’s </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt"
                                >Guide</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, see the general introduction to Nicholas Mason, Paul Westover, and Shannon Stimpson, eds., </hi><ref
                                target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/guide_lakes/editions.2020.guide_lakes.introduction.html"
                                    ><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Wordsworth’s Guide to
                                    the
                                Lakes</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, 2nd ed. (Romantic Circles, 2020) and this edition’s </hi><hi
                                rend="color(0000FF)" style="font-size:11pt">introductions to her
                                Scafell Pike and Ullswater excursions [links].</hi></p></note></hi>
                In fact, in an amusing 1803 letter to her friend Catherine Clarkson, she ranted, “I
                think journals of Tours except as far as one is interested in the travellers are
                very uninteresting. Wretched, wretched writing!”<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                        place="end"><p rend="RJ notes">
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Letters</hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">, 1:421.</hi></p></note></hi> It’s all the
                more ironic, then, that travel writing—along with the notes, letters, and diary
                entries inspired by walks closer to home—would become central to her creative output
                and legacy. Works based on her experiences as a traveler or short-term resident
                include her journals from Alfoxden and Germany (both 1798), her <hi rend="italic"
                    >Recollections of a Tour Made in Scotland</hi> (1803–1806), her <hi
                    rend="italic">Journal of a Tour on the Continent</hi> (1820), her second tour of
                Scotland (1822), and large segments of the <hi rend="italic">Rydal Journals</hi>
                written on the road. While these texts encompass various literary traditions—nature
                diary, weather journal, travelogue, commonplace book, and so forth—they cohere as
                records of things observed and felt by a writer who, left to her own devices, would
                often walk over a dozen miles a day. Even when at home in Cumbria and drawing on
                daily experience, Dorothy might say, as Thoreau would years later, that she had
                “traveled a good deal” in the Lake District.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                        place="end"><p rend="endnote text"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> “I have travelled a good deal in Concord”: Thoreau, </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt"
                            >Walden</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, 6. </hi>
                        </p></note></hi></p>
            <p>Tellingly, we are not the first to note that both William and Dorothy serve as
                “guides” to the Lakes. Eric Sutherland Robertson, for instance, asked in his 1911
                book <hi rend="italic">Wordsworthshire</hi>, “Who wrote the noblest Guide to the
                Lakes—William or Dorothy? Let the reader study every page of the [Grasmere] Journal
                and of the other work before attempting to decide.”<hi rend="endnote_reference"
                        ><note place="end"><p rend="RJ notes"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Robertson, </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Wordsworthshire</hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">, 252.</hi></p></note></hi> As Robertson
                implies, while the brother’s poetry has undoubtedly shaped our perceptions of the
                Lake District, it has become equally impossible for the well-read traveler to
                imagine “Wordsworth Country” without considering Dorothy’s writing. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold color(0070C0)">Edition’s Contents</hi></p>
            <p>Our edition aims to bolster Dorothy’s growing reputation as one of the great
                chroniclers of this, or any, British region’s history and geography, people and
                customs, and flora and fauna. Accordingly, when selecting its contents, we typically
                excluded works that are set in or focused upon areas outside the Lakes (for
                instance, her tours of Scotland and the Continent and several sections of her <hi
                    rend="italic">Rydal Journals</hi>). Even then, however, there were more than
                enough texts to choose from for an edition of this scope, which forced us to leave
                several brilliant descriptions of the region on the cutting-room floor. Dorothy’s
                letters alone, for instance, with their recurring effusions on the joys of rambling
                throughout Westmorland fells and dales, could easily supply enough content for a
                substantial anthology of Lakeland writing.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                        place="end"><p rend="RJ notes">
                            <hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Fortunately, all of DW’s known letters are available in </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">The Letters of William and
                                Dorothy Wordsworth</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">. Among the contemporary admirers of her letters was her longtime friend Catherine Clarkson, who, after rereading “heaps” of them in 1833, gushed, “What a heart and what a head they discover!” and contemplated all the celebrated authors “whose thinkings and feelings are not to be compared with hers!” (Letter to Henry Crabb Robinson, in Robinson, </hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Diary, Reminiscences, and
                                Correspondence</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt">,
                        3:35).</hi></p></note></hi>
            </p>
            <p>Each section of this edition features a separate critical and editorial introduction
                and extensive illustrations and contextual materials, including manuscript
                facsimiles, maps, photographs, and biographical indices. Together, these resources
                offer a rich, multimodal vision of Dorothy Wordsworth’s writing life and the Lake
                District home she loved. The texts we ultimately selected can be grouped as follows: </p>
            <list rend="numbered">
                <item><hi rend="bold">The first Grasmere journal notebook (1800, DCMS 20).</hi>
                    While Dorothy’s entries from her early years at Dove Cottage are already the
                    most familiar of her writings, the first of her four Grasmere journal notebooks
                    is reintroduced here in an unfamiliar format. Specifically, we offer a
                    diplomatic transcription of this first notebook, presenting it in its raw
                    manuscript form to highlight both its material context and the complexity of
                    Dorothy’s writing practices. This notebook covers the seven months between 14
                    May and 22 December 1800, offering an intimate portrait of Westmorland life at
                    the moment when the Wordsworths returned to the area for good. It also captures
                    Dorothy’s love for walking, all but inviting us along on her daily rambles
                    through the Lakes. </item>
            </list>
            <list rend="numbered">
                <item><hi rend="bold">“A Narrative Concerning George &amp; Sarah Green, of the
                        Parish of Grasmere, addressed to a Friend” (1808, DCMS 64).</hi> In this
                    moving account, written to raise money for children orphaned by a tragic
                    accident, Dorothy offers a chapter of local history. Widely circulated in
                    manuscript, her chronicle of poverty, grief, and community relief efforts
                    highlights the informal social contract binding together people of all classes
                    in the valleys of the Central Lakes. This public-facing text also complicates
                    our understanding of Dorothy’s motives for writing, conceptions of audience, and
                    views about publication. </item>
            </list>
            <list rend="numbered">
                <item><hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">“Excursion on the Banks of Ullswater” (1805) and “Excursion up Scawfell Pike” (1818). </hi>Abridged
                    versions of Dorothy’s accounts of excursions she made with friends to different
                    parts of the Lake District were among her earliest published writings, appearing
                    (albeit without acknowledgment of her authorship) in the 1822 and 1823 editions
                    of her brother’s <hi rend="italic">Guide to the Lakes</hi>. Showcasing Dorothy’s
                    gifts for nature writing and her indefatigability as a Lakeland fell-walker and
                    mountaineer, these important texts represent Dorothy’s most direct contributions
                    to Lake District travel literature. While long available in print, they have
                    never before been annotated, illustrated, or contextualized as thoroughly as
                    they are here. This edition also details the accounts’ complex textual histories
                    and brings Dorothy’s adventures to life with a pair of interactive maps.</item>
            </list>
            <list rend="numbered">
                <item><hi rend="bold">Poems from the Commonplace Book (1805–1835?, DCMS 120).</hi>
                    Though Dorothy was self-effacing about her poetic abilities, verse became an
                    important genre for her, especially in later years. This is evidenced by what
                    the Wordsworth Trust labels her Commonplace Book (DCMS 120), which, along with
                    miscellaneous extracts and quotations, includes copies of most of her known
                    poems. Many of these poems, moreover, appear in multiple versions, thereby
                    displaying how serious she was about reworking and recopying her work. Besides
                    offering a diplomatic transcription of all of the verse in DCMS 120, whether
                    complete poems or fragments, this section also includes an introductory essay on
                    what we can learn from Dorothy’s poetry manuscripts and multiple “Tables of
                    Contents” modelling different sequences in which the poems might be
                    studied.</item>
            </list>
            <list rend="numbered">
                <item><hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Notebooks 1 and 15 of the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic bold">Rydal
                    Journals</hi><hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve"> (1824–1825, 1834–1835, DCMS 104.1 and 118.5)</hi>.
                    Despite the renown of Dorothy’s earlier journals, most of the 15 notebooks
                    recording her daily life between 1824 and 1835 remain unpublished. This
                    edition’s annotated texts of the first and last volumes of her
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Rydal Journals </hi>therefore represent a
                    watershed of sorts in offering a wealth of new perspectives on Dorothy’s daily
                    life in late middle age. Both notebooks included here reflect an abiding
                    affinity for the scenery and inhabitants of the Lakes; but, whereas Notebook 1
                    captures a period marked by boundless energy, Notebook 15 finds her confined to
                    a sickbed, reminiscing over past excursions and taking in whatever sights and
                    sounds she can from her upstairs room at Rydal Mount. </item>
            </list>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
