<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Stanley Cavell and the Event of Romanticism</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">Passing Judgment, Conceding Perfection: Third-Person Narration and Versions of the Cavellian Secular</title>
            <author>
               <name>Anne-Lise François</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">Eric Lindstrom</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <!-- This value must be unique and follow the convention section.year.resource.filename. This allows us to use this value as a unique id and to attach all of our xml files to a single folder -->
            <idno type="edition">praxis.cavell.2014.francois</idno>
            <!-- This id is present to distinguish items via a simple resource designator. For example, if we are importing people and places, we would concatenate this value with anchor value for a person to distinguish these from other imported people from other resources -->
            <idno type="resource">cavell</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Passing Judgment, Conceding Perfection: Third-Person Narration and Versions of the Cavellian Secular</title>
                  <author role="secondary">
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Anne-Lise</forename>
                        <surname>François</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Stanley Cavell and the Event of Romanticism</title>
                  <title level="s">Praxis Series</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2014-07-18">July 18, 2014</date>
                     <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/praxis/cavell/praxis.cavell.2014.francois.html</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#226;&#8364;&#339;,"
                  for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent11" scheme="css">margin-left: 6em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent12" scheme="css">margin-left: 6.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <!-- Visit the links in the corresp attribute to find all values for genre, type, and discipline -->
            <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E"
               xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                  20014-02-27</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E"
               xml:id="dcType">
               <bibl>NINES categories for document type at
                  http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E"
               xml:id="d">
               <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at
                  http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on
                  2014-02-27</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Criticism"/>
            <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
            <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
            <keywords scheme="http://www.rc.umd.edu/#tags">
               <term subtype="tags">acknowledgment</term>
               <term subtype="tags">last words</term>
               <term subtype="tags">perlocutionary utterances</term>
               <term subtype="tags">third-person narration</term>
               <term subtype="tags">Stanley Cavell</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2014-01-20</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>Passing Judgment, Conceding Perfection: Third-Person Narration and Versions of the
               Cavellian Secular</head>
            <byline>
               <docAuthor>Anne-Lise François</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>University of California, Berkeley</affiliation>
            </byline>
            <epigraph>
               <quote><ab>Les hommes nous doivent ce que nous imaginons qu’ils nous donneront. Leur
                     remettre cette dette.</ab>
                  <ab>Accepter qu’ils soient autre que les créatures de notre imagination, c’est
                     imiter le renoncement de Dieu.</ab>
                  <ab>Moi aussi, je suis autre que ce que je m’imagine être. Le savoir, c’est le
                     pardon.</ab><lb/>
                  <ab>Men owe us what we imagine they will give us. Forgive them this debt. </ab>
                  <ab>To accept that they are different than the creatures of our imagination is to
                     imitate the renunciation of God. </ab>
                  <ab>I too am other than what I imagine myself to be. To know this is forgiveness.
                  </ab></quote>
               <ab rend="indent4">—Simone Weil, <title level="m">Gravity and Grace</title></ab>
            </epigraph>

            <epigraph>
               <quote><ab>A judge should be able to decide, by hearing what was said, what
                     locutionary and illocutionary acts were performed, but not what perlocutionary
                     acts were achieved.</ab>
               </quote>
               <ab rend="indent4">—J.L. Austin, <title level="m">How to Do Things with
                  Words</title></ab>
            </epigraph>

            <epigraph>
               <quote><ab>There is no end to the things that happen to people. </ab>
                  <ab rend="indent1">. . . . . . . . . .</ab>
                  <ab>In the mode of passionate exchange there is no final word, no uptake or
                     turndown, until a line is drawn, a withdrawal is effected, perhaps in turn to
                     be revoked.</ab>
               </quote>
               <ab rend="indent4">—Stanley Cavell, <title level="m">Philosophy the Day After
                     Tomorrow</title></ab>
            </epigraph>

            <p> I begin with an acknowledgment of gratitude to Eric Lindstrom not simply for
               providing generous and illuminating comments on earlier drafts but for imagining an
               essay worthier than the one here presented. At the start of his own “Austen and
               Austin” Lindstrom juxtaposes the story of Jane Austen’s short-lived engagement to
               Harris Bigg-Wither—in which she gave her consent one day and retracted it the
               next—with J.L. Austin’s off-hand comment from <title level="m">Sense and
                  Sensibilia</title>: “There’s the bit where you say it and the bit where you take
               it back” (qtd. in Lindstrom 501). However indirectly, the following essay has been
               written as an extended meditation on the brilliance of this juxtaposition, which
               helps de-dramatize a consent no sooner given than withdrawn, where the consent and
               its withdrawal constitute a single, finished non-drama, and not an invitation for
               further courtship.</p>
            <p>"The verb needs modifying," is the lesson of Austin's "excuses"—their tenor "is that
               I did it but only <emph>in a way</emph>, not just flatly like that" (“A Plea for
               Excuses” 187).<note xml:id="ftn1" place="foot" resp="editors" n="1"> All further
                  citations from Austin refer to <title level="m">How to Do Things with
                     Words</title>.</note> Excuses do not deny or cancel a given action: they modify
               it, and potentially endlessly, as one might glean both from Austin's own many
               discriminations and from the multiple near synonyms—mitigate, extenuate, temper,
               etc.—for "alter[ation] in the direction of mildness or moderation"
               (<emph>OED</emph>). By contrast, third-person accounts of Austen's broken engagement
               (such as Deirdre Le Faye's, cited by Lindstrom) perhaps necessarily tend to retain
               something of the novelist's own flatness and model a different kind of tact:
               explanation for why Cassandra and Jane had to be fetched from the Bigg household
               sooner than expected may eventually be given, but none for the withdrawn consent.
               Somewhere between the rich insufficiency of the interminably proliferating Austinian
               excuse and the minimal sufficiency of unapologetic Austenian report lies the
               dialectic that this essay hopes to explore: on the one hand, the strangely generative
               powers of retraction-through-verbalizing modification; on the other, the even
               stranger generosity of another mode of recession that declines even to assume the
               work of articulation.</p>
            <ab rend="center">****</ab>
            <p>My first engagement with Cavell’s work concerned his tendency to identify
               “romanticism” with what he calls the “process of secularization,” whereby finite
               individuals are asked to play “God” to one another by verifying and bearing witness
               to one another’s separate existences. In this early work Cavell’s originality lies in
               reconverting into the passive voice a crisis of knowledge commonly expressed in the
               active: skepticism about other minds turns out to be a drama not of insufficient or
               unreliable or as yet imperfect levels of knowing but of too much being known—a tragedy that ensues when the skeptic refuses to allow himself to be found out by the other to be, like her, mortal and separate, and attempts to convert into a reparable “intellectual lack” the irreparable “metaphysical finitude” the other has already revealed in and for him.  From the start, then, Cavell implies that what seems the
               harder role—the active <emph>task</emph> of making oneself known—may be an evasion of
               the passive <emph>role</emph> of allowing oneself to be known.</p>
            <p>In <title level="m">Open Secrets</title> I argued that “romanticism” so defined—as
               the last, unfinished act of a drama called “secularization”—puts humans in the
               position of playing impossible roles for one another—my allowing myself to be known,
               your playing God to know me—each rife with heroic temptations toward “absolute
               activeness” and “absolute passiveness”: the Protestant emphasis on a law of the heart
               means that it is now up to me to determine what is asked of me, while what
               constitutes the acknowledgment of this unsummoned gift remains in turn equally
               unspecified (Cavell, <title level="m">Claim</title> 470).<note xml:id="ftn2"
                  place="foot" resp="editors" n="2">See François 212-217. </note> Such schematic
               stagings of something called “romanticism” or “secularization”—as a drama of
               revelation and abandonment that could never (and indeed need never) have happened to
               particular individuals—betray Cavell’s own preference for dramatic genres, a
               preference itself readable in terms of a Romantic desire to give dramatic form to
               human history.<note xml:id="ftn3" place="foot" resp="editors" n="3">For Cavell’s
                  indebtedness to Romanticism’s post-Kantian, necessarily failed project of giving
                  aesthetic form to what can have no form—the freedom that Kant had saved for humans
                  only by declaring impossible to intuit empirically—see the lecture “Unworking
                  Romanticism” in Critchley 85-140. </note> The impatience they may elicit from
               incredulous readers itself replays at the metalevel the difficulty of believing in
               acknowledgment as a decisive action.</p>
            <p>For again, as I argued in <title level="m">Open Secrets</title>, if for Cavell the
               “humanization” of acknowledgment places “infinite demands upon finite resources”
                  (<title level="m">Claim</title> 470), then assuming the burden of the power to
               confirm one another’s self image means, in large measure, renouncing these demands,
               as my acknowledgment of your capacity to sustain “infinite interest” inevitably
               shades into a sense of how little this can do for you (361). If we accept Cavell's
               account of the skeptic’s doubt as indicating not cognitive uncertainty but the
               disavowal of having already been found to be a mortal among other mortals,
               acknowledgment constitutes an advance on knowledge, but not in the sense of the
               discovery of a new and decisive piece of evidence, rather in that of a change in
               attitude—an adjustment whereby the questioner may simply stop questioning and let go
               not so much of the possibility of certainty as of a fantasy about what achieving
               certainty might mean.<note xml:id="ftn4" place="foot" resp="editors" n="4">See, for
                  example, Cavell’s summary of his previous arguments at the start of <title
                     level="m">In Quest of the Ordinary,</title> in which he addresses those who
                  have misread him as giving up on the philosophical project and advocating
                  acknowledgment as some kind of leap of faith beyond the limits of human knowledge:
                  “I do not propose the idea of acknowledging as an alternative to knowing but
                  rather as an interpretation of it” (8). </note> Acknowledgment in this sense can
               look more like relinquishment than resolution, but because he wants to preserve the
               distinction from cognitive advance, Cavell perhaps too strongly insists on
               “acknowledgment” as above all an expressive act, even if at other points he concedes
               that this attitudinal relaxation of the skeptic’s demand for proof may never in fact
               take definitive expression. Compare, for example, the following passages: <quote><p
                     rend="noCount">Acknowledgment “goes beyond” knowledge, not in the order, or as
                     a feat, of cognition, but in the call upon me to express the knowledge at its
                     core, to recognize what I know, to do something in the light of it, apart from
                     which this knowledge remains without expression, hence perhaps without
                     possession (<title level="m">Claim</title> 428).</p>
                  <p rend="noCount">If my attitude towards him expresses my knowledge that he has a
                     soul, my attitude may nevertheless not be very definitely expressed, nor very
                     readily. It may take ages; it may be expressed now in the way I live[. . .]. The
                     word “attitude” can be misleading here. It is not, in the matters at hand, a
                     disposition I can adopt at will. It will be helpful to take the English word in
                     its physical sense, as an inflection of myself toward others, an orientation
                     which affects everything and which I may or may not be interested in
                     discovering about myself. (360)</p>
               </quote> Such divergent passages bear witness to the difficulty of reconciling
               Cavell’s heroic investment in “acknowledgment” as the duty and burden of secular
               individuals, with the figures of “decline,” “lapse,” and “concession” by which one
               signals one’s disappointed acceptance of the other’s finite and fallible knowledge of
                  oneself.<note xml:id="ftn5" place="foot" resp="editors" n="5"> Underscoring the
                  redundancy of a phrase such as “mutual acknowledgment of separateness,” Eric
                  Walker indirectly points to this link between concession or retraction and
                  acknowledgment as an assertion or finding whose object is always
                  negative—something one does not want or is disappointed to find—so that
                  acknowledgment may be assertive as an expressive act but recessive as a
                  propositional statement: “‘acknowledgment,’ as I understand it, carries with it a
                  sense of the inescapable persistence of the separate self: to acknowledge in
                  Cavell’s lexicon, to respond to the disappointment of knowledge of the world and
                  of other minds, is to be by definition separate, both from the world and from
                  other minds” (<title level="m">Marriage, Writing, and Romanticism: Wordsworth and
                     Austen After War</title> 43). </note>
            </p>
            <p>When proposing this essay I’d originally promised to explore these tensions as they
               inform Cavell’s more recent work, where the ambiguous call for some kind of
               demonstrative, expressive act or sign acknowledging the unreliability of signs
               reappears, and where what was once the “secularizing process” is redescribed as the
               double project of meeting the demand for intelligibility while giving up on the
               fantasy of perfect expression. Here in terms that sound less “romantic” or
               post-secular than Habermasian, Cavell warns us that if we do not accommodate the
               imperative of expression to ordinary language, we are “stopped short in the
               obligation to make our desires, hence our actions, intelligible and hampered in our
               demand and right to be found intelligible in those desires and actions, to ask
               residence in the shared realm of reason” (<title level="m">Philosophy</title> 188).
               But as often happens with the promises one makes in an abstract and their somewhat
               inconsequent realizations, in the course of reading essays from Cavell’s <title
                  level="m">Philosophy the Day After Tomorrow</title>, my thoughts took a slightly
               different turn toward Cavell’s longstanding interest in marriage, and more
               particularly, in marriage as a daily or diurnal event—an event that, as Eric Walker
               also argues, Cavell frequently defines as essentially incapable of definitive
               achievement because it consists of the precarious sustaining (or not) of a
               conversation over time, one felicitous instance of which can never absolutely
               guarantee the dawn of another. Indeed “felicity” here, in direct contrast to the
               sense in which J. L. Austin uses the word to measure the successful performative, may
               be predicated on continued uncertainty as to whether full, exact communication has
               actually and finally occurred, whether the invitation to exchange has been accepted
               or rebuked. Thus, according to Cavell, in both the Hollywood remarriage comedies and
               melodramatic refusals of marriage discussed in his earlier <title level="m">Pursuits
                  of Happiness</title> and <title level="m">Contesting Tears</title>, <quote>nothing
                  legitimizes or ratifies marriage—not state, or church, or sex, or gender, or
                  children—apart from the willingness for reaffirmation, which is to say, for
                  remarriage [. . .] and what makes marriage worth reaffirming is a diurnal devotedness
                  that involves friendship, play, surprise, and mutual education, all manifested in
                  the pair’s mode of conversing with each other (not just in words). (<title
                     level="m">Philosophy</title> 121-22) </quote> In an earlier chapter in <title
                  level="m">Philosophy</title> he cites Benjamin’s enigmatic claim from the essay on
                  <title level="m">Elective Affinities</title> that “marriage is never justified in
               law (that is, as an institution) but is justified solely as an expression of
               continuance in love, which by nature seeks this expression sooner in death than in
               life” (qtd. in <title level="m">Philosophy</title> 86-87). Cavell offers the
               following parenthetical gloss: “perhaps Benjamin means this as a smack at a Romantic
               suggestion that it is easier to love eternally than diurnally” (87). </p>
            <p>Now, of course, marriage so conceived—as a never conclusively achieved diurnal
               continuance—works in tension with marriage as pronounced by law, whether civic or
               religious. Marriage in this latter sense constitutes perhaps the most famous example
               of Austin’s illocutionary performatives—speech acts supposed to occur once and for
               all and whose felicity is determinable according to clearly established conventions:
               I can’t be uncertain as to whether I’ve been married in the eyes of the law in the
               same way that I can doubt what counts as the renewal of the vows the next day and
               then the next. Although Cavell never quite explicitly says so, this potential
               disjuncture between the closure to progressive, iterative tenses of the Austinian
               performative “I do” and his conception of marriage as a kind of shorthand for the
               ongoing and difficultly evinceable project of acknowledgment more or less maps onto
               the comparison he makes in the chapter “Performative and Passionate Utterance”
               between illocutionary acts, where the doing lies in the saying (I do, I give and
               bequeath, I bet, I christen, etc.), and perlocutionary ones, where something
               happens—some strong emotional effect is released, whether inadvertently or
               intentionally—by virtue of the saying but where the doing and the saying don’t
               usually line up with the same first-person form: to take Cavell’s examples, to say “I
               seduce you” is no guarantee that I do, or an utterance may be extremely embarrassing
               or painful but not necessarily because its utterer says, “I now embarrass you, I now
               injure you” (<title level="m">Philosophy</title> 178).<note xml:id="ftn6"
                  place="foot" resp="editors" n="6"> Here as everywhere in Cavell communicativeness
                  is not a matter of imparting information but of exercising a capacity for
                  projecting and anticipating the expectable but never fully calculable response of
                  one’s listener, as the speaker “makes herself intelligible” only by imagining,
                  doubtless never quite precisely, her words as they will be heard by her
                  interlocutor: “if I could not rationally expect, by variously expressing myself to
                  you, to have the effect of alarming you or reassuring you, of offending or amusing
                  you, boring or interesting you, exasperating or fascinating you, [. . .] I would
                  lack the capacity to make myself intelligible to you. And what you would lack is
                  not some information I might impart to you” (172). </note>
            </p>
            <p>For both Austin and Cavell, perlocutionary speech acts differ from illocutionary ones
               in that with them “there is no accepted conventional procedure and effect. The
               speaker is on his own to create the desired effect” (180). In this respect, the
               “perlocutionary” belongs to the realm of the “secular” as Cavell uses the term to
               designate the sense of not knowing what the rules are, of having to make them up as
               one goes along, as if being finite or mortal were also being subject and subjecting
               oneself to potentially endless interpretation. Hence, if “a performative utterance is
               an offer of participation in the order of law,” then, “a passionate utterance is an
               invitation to <emph>improvisation</emph> in the disorders of desire” (185, emphasis
               added). And just as the appropriate agents cannot be determined beforehand, knowing
               when the speech drama is at an end is nearly impossible, since, unlike the
               definitiveness with which in Austin’s examples one may refuse to recognize a
               challenge or an offer of marriage and this is the end to the matter, “in the realm of
               the perlocutionary, refusal may become part of the performance” (183). Thus to cite
               again the line I took for another epigraph, “there is no end to the things that
               happen to people” (175). Yet in the midst of thus emphasizing the unstoppable and
               uncontrollable proliferation of responses that in turn elicit further responses,
               Cavell introduces an example of a line that he reads as exceptionally
               end-stopped—Carmen’s “No. You do not love me”—a response that listeners and
               performers alike usually hear as an invitation for Don José to contradict her but
               that Cavell takes as a mere constative: <quote>Every critic I have read on the
                  subject takes Carmen at that moment of refusal to be further seducing Don José,
                  ridiculing his sense of honor, enticing him to come with her into the life of
                  freedom from law. But the written score (it is not always performed so) marks her
                  line pianississimo (triple piano). She is at that moment, as I perceive her,
                  paradoxically, and as far as humanly possible, expressionless, without
                  implication, utters with no expression a pure constative, the simplest of truths,
                  that he does not love her. She stares blankly at the truth and is bewildered. The
                  unprecedented event, finding no love where she has commanded and returned love,
                  causes her to issue a flurry of invitations and taunts to cover her bewilderment,
                  confused and confusing gestures to which this man, in her eyes, has, within the
                  space of a song, a song she rejects, become irrelevant; she denies that it is she
                  who has been singled out in his song. That much has ended in her. But how will it
                  end between them, who will have the last word? Who does have the last word? (184)
               </quote> Under such conditions, there seems to be no choice but to rely on the
               “other”—the conversational partner or interlocutor to fill in the blanks—to finish
               off the unsaid, to read past the silences. We can see the appeal as well as treachery
               of this paradigm in which we are called upon to be active readers, readers capable of
               weighing the partial meanings with which a certain silence may be filled. The good
               “other” or marriage partner would be the one who helps us to expressiveness, and for
               an instance of this happy partnership, Cavell turns to Jane Austen’s <title level="m"
                  >Emma</title> at the end of the chapter. Most difficult to imagine, however, would
               be the interlocutor capable of assenting to the finality of Carmen’s constative.</p>
            <p>I will come to Austen myself momentarily, but for now by way of further exploring the
               impossibility of a statement such as “I persuade you,” I want to make a brief detour
               through perhaps the most operatic writer of third-person fiction, Stendhal. Cavell's 
               “Performative and Passionate Utterance” begins as a critique of Austin’s relative
               neglect of perlocutionary effects as symptomatic of his unease before the messiness
               of human passions, but the idea that “perlocutionary acts make room for, and reward,
               imagination and virtuosity, unequally distributed capacities among the species” (<title level="m">Philosophy</title> 173)
               might be part of what gave pause to the advocate of “plain saying,” since it evokes
               the familiar topos of the indeterminably elect—an aristocracy of the imagination
               whose special powers would be differently called into play by passionate utterances
               than by “illocutionary acts” where no such questions arise: “I do not, except in
               special circumstances, wonder how I might make a promise or a gift, or apologize, or
               render a verdict,” whereas persuading, consoling, confusing, and seducing you “may
               take talent” (<title level="m">Philosophy</title> 173). Stendhal’s 1827 novel <title level="m">Armance </title>offers a
               remarkable example not so much of the difficulty of persuasion per se as of the
               non-relation, or the unpredictability of relation, between effort and success.
               Stendhal’s young hero struggles to persuade his cousin of his indifference to the
               wealth into which he has recently come and which will enable him to marry well; after
               days of wondering how to defend himself against her accusation of his worldliness, an
               accusation she has, of course, never expressly addressed to him, he finally settles on
               this: <quote><p rend="noCount">J’ai longtemps cherché à me justifier auprès de vous,
                     non par de vaines paroles, mais par des actions. Je n’en trouve aucune qui soit
                     décisive; moi aussi, je ne puis avoir recours qu’à votre <emph>sens
                        intime</emph>. Or voici ce qui m’est arrivé. Pendant que je parlerai, voyez
                     dans mes yeux si je mens. (64)</p>
                  <p rend="noCount">I have long sought to justify myself to you, not by vain words
                     but by actions. I can find none that would be decisive; I, too, can have
                     recourse only to your <emph>intimate sense</emph>. Well, this is what has
                     happened [literally, come] to me. As I will speak, see in my eyes if I’m
                        lying.<note xml:id="ftn7" place="foot" resp="editors" n="7">The following
                        translations are my own, although I have consulted C.K. Scott-Moncrieff’s
                           <title level="m">The Shorter Novels of Stendhal</title>.
                        Scott-Moncrieff’s more idiomatic translation of the last sentence reads:
                        “While I am talking, look in my eyes and see whether I am lying” (78).
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </quote> Oddly juxtaposing past, present, and future, Octave’s proposal is hit upon
               in the past tense but offered—tendered—to the future of Armance’s reception, as if
               his speaking had not yet begun; irreducible to the irony of using speech to
               circumvent the unreliability of speech, his words amount to a surprisingly uncynical
               assumption of the disjuncture between intention and effect—a recognition that, while
               the content of his speech may be as good as empty, what happens while he is speaking
               isn’t. From the histrionic demand for action and not mere words as proof of a
               resolution to sacrifice, he falls back on the very vanity of these “mere” words, as
               if in inversion of Hippolytus’s “my tongue swore to, but my heart did not”;
               abandoning his attempt to persuade her, he gives in, with his impossible invitation
               that she “see in his eyes if he is lying,” not to a naive faith in the truth of
               physical presence, but to her powers to do something other than listen (while he
               babbles on).<note xml:id="ftn8" place="foot" resp="editors" n="8">For Austin the line
                  from Euripides’ <title level="m">Hippolytus</title> is emblematic of the hypocrisy
                  to which are inevitably led those who make the metaphysical mistake first of
                  thinking of words as outward pictures of inward mental acts and then of prizing
                  the inward performance above all else (9-10). Cavell returns to the line and to
                  Austin’s reading of it (among other places) in <title level="m">Philosophy the Day
                     After Tomorrow</title> (176). </note>
            </p>
            <p> Several pages earlier, the reader has in any case been informed that Octave’s
               fruitless search for the means to persuade Armance of his integrity has of itself
               already been effective in persuading her by its very desperation (of adequate means):
               if he searches in vain, it is because nothing can be good enough (for her? for him?)
               and this is enough to make him worthy of her: <quote><p rend="noCount">En cherchant
                     en vain les moyens de se justifier de l’accusation qu’Armance lui adressait en
                     secret, Octave laissait voir, sans s’en douter, combien profondément il en
                     était touché; c’était peut-être la manière la plus adroite de mériter son
                     pardon. (53-54)</p>
                  <p rend="noCount">While seeking in vain the means to justify himself before the
                     accusation that Armance addressed him in secret, Octave was unconsciously
                     revealing how deeply he was touched by it; this was perhaps the most adept way
                     of deserving her forgiveness. </p></quote> This same structure of a discourse
               whose emptiness or vanity at the level of content in no way determines its
               decisiveness or seriousness, and indeed whose status as mere babble in fact
               facilitates its import, will later define Armance’s discovery that Octave loves her
               (before he knows this himself) as he speaks to her about another woman whom he has
               been pretending to pursue in public: <quote><p rend="noCount">Il y avait dans
                     l’accent profond et presque attendri avec lequel Octave disait ces vaines
                     paroles, une si grande impossibilité d’aimer les grâces un peu hasardées de la
                     jolie femme dont il parlait, et un dévouement si passioné pour l’amie à
                     laquelle il se confiait, qu’elle n’eut pas le courage de résister au bonheur de
                     se voir aimée ainsi [. . .] Tout ce que sa prudence pouvait obtenir d’elle,
                     c’était de ne pas parler; le son de sa voix eût fait connaître à son cousin
                     toute la passion qu’il inspirait. (108)</p>
                  <p rend="noCount">There was in the deep and almost softened accent with which
                     Octave was saying these empty words so great an impossibility of loving the
                     somewhat chancy graces of the pretty woman of whom he spoke, and so passionate
                     a devotion for the friend to whom he was confiding himself, that she did not
                     have the courage to resist the happiness of seeing herself thus loved [. . .] All
                     her prudence could obtain from her, was not to speak; the sound of her voice
                     would have revealed to her cousin all the passion that he was inspiring.
                  </p></quote> Nothing, in a sense, could be further from the renewed commitment to
               ordinary language with which Cavell ends his essay, citing again Austin’s caution,
               “Accuracy and morality alike are on the side of the plain saying that our word is our
               bond” (<title level="m">Philosophy</title> 191), and for the remainder of this essay I will follow Cavell in turning to
               the more familiar psychological realism of Jane Austen’s fiction, whose characters
               (with the possible exception of the diffident Fanny Price) show a different
               (although, I would argue, not greater) faith in the possibility of communication than
               Stendhal’s histrionically hermetic heroes do. Yet, in the end, the directness with which point-blank
               declaration occurs for Octave and Armance in and through, as well as after, so many
               rounds of deferral, disguise, mutual deceit, and self-deception in the end does not so
               much differ from Cavell’s own movement of return to the ordinary through the
               passionate, charted in this essay and elsewhere in his work. The heady combination of
               directness and indirection, of trenchant circumlocution and perfected error
               characteristic of Stendhal’s prose, derives in large part, of course, from the flat
               definitiveness with which his third-person narration reports his protagonists’
               attempts to obfuscate and delay the crisis of mutual encounter and revelation such
               that every sentence performs the conclusion the characters would postpone. It is
               tempting in this context to cite again Cavell’s claim that the “book of philosophy”
               that Thoreau would find “suitable” to students “would be written with next to no
               forward motion” because it would “culminate in each sentence” (<title level="m">Quest</title> 18).<note xml:id="ftn9" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  n="9">Cavell concludes this speculation by suggesting that such prose would know
                  nothing of poetic enjambment or the continuance of thought from one line to the
                  next, which may explain why when paraphrasing this passage Critchley adds or
                  elaborates that we would “find no reason to continue reading from one sentence to
                  the next” (124). According to Critchley, Cavell praises writing that “knows when
                  to stop,” because such knowledge “opens a certain relation to finitude” (124). Yet
                  the irony of these multiple rephrasings of a sentence that would need no other—an
                  ideal supposed to be Thoreau’s even if it does not exist on his printed
                  page—suggests that the thought of the thought that would require no further
                  thought itself cannot come to term, whatever Critchley’s worries about Cavell’s
                  temptation to short circuit “the vertiginous forward motion without destination”
                  of Schlegelian irony. There is perhaps no sharper instantiation of the difficulty
                  of telling the “inertia” of the finished sentence from this “vertigo” than the
                  staccato of Stendhal’s prose. </note> How might third-person narration effect such
               singular stopping points? With this question in mind, I now return to Carmen’s “last
               word” and its possible equivalents in Austen’s prose.</p>
            <p> Indeed what if, instead of awaiting rescue from a patient Mr. Knightley, we were to
               introduce into this conversational paradigm, premised as it is on a model of language
               as communication between a sender and a receiver, the innovation for which Austen is
               perhaps most well known in the history of the English novel: free indirect style in
               which no one speaks?<note xml:id="ftn10" place="foot" resp="editors" n="10">For the
                  argument that no one speaks, see Banfield; for the extensive literature on Austen
                  and free indirect style, see as well, among others, Cohn; Ferguson; Finch and
                  Bowen; Andrew Miller, “Perfectly Helpless”; and D.A. Miller, <title level="m">Jane
                     Austen, or the Secret of Style</title>. </note> For this particular mode of
               narration frees protagonists from the burden that Cavell takes as the mark of secular
               individuals—that of making themselves known and accepting to be known by one another.
               In Cavell’s model, it is the good, discerning interlocutor—the rather preachy Mr.
               Knightley—who is capable of bestowing acknowledgment and simultaneously forgiving the
               heroine for her double failure with respect to adequate expression: her inability not
               to express herself all the time and her failure to express herself as she would
                  like.<note xml:id="ftn11" place="foot" resp="editors" n="11">Cavell gives the last
                  word to Knightley’s exclamation to the woman he can now sincerely and truthfully
                  call “his” Emma: “My Emma, does not everything serve to prove more and more the
                  beauty of truth and sincerity in all our dealings with each other?” (<title
                     level="m">Emma</title> 486; quoted in <title level="m">Philosophy </title>191).
                  But he thereby passes over an irony that Austen’s wry narration does not let
                  pass—namely that Emma at this point is still withholding from her future husband
                  her role in unwittingly redirecting Harriet Smith’s attentions toward him: “Emma
                  agreed to it, and with a blush of sensibility on Harriet’s account, which she
                  could not give any sincere explanation of.” </note> But I want to suggest that
               Austen’s novels—and third person narration in general—also afford another kind of
               forgiveness for the failure to arrive at fully articulate, transparent expression.
               Elsewhere I have described how free indirect style frees characters first from the
               work of speaking for themselves, giving accounts, and making themselves legible to
               others that constitutes the right and duty of Habermasian individuals, and then from
               the no less onerous burden of having to signal “deep” or unfathomable emotion.
               Cavell’s relative neglect of third-person narrative modes, which his late turn toward
               Jane Austen’s fiction makes all the more noticeable, belongs to his investments in
               dialogical, dramatic forms, investments themselves indicative of his commitment to
               self-expression as the measure of having assumed the burden of the other’s separate
               existence. Yet this neglect seems all the stranger in light of his claims for the
               ordinariness of desires that may remain without expression, or rather his ambivalence
               toward the “Rousseauian” or “Romantic” myth that I am essentially unknowable,
               incommunicable to others, and his wish <emph>not</emph> to exaggerate the gulf between the mystery
               of inchoate private experience and the formal articulations required of public life.
               If the double, contradictory injunction to invest the self with secret proprietary
               value and make it publicly accountable ends up faulting thoughts for not “ris[ing] to
               the level of the expressible” (Ferguson 167; François 14), no such negative judgments
               attend the experiences rendered by free indirect style—mental states no less achieved
               for not being said aloud by one speaker to another—because their realization is not
               predicated on their being claimed, voiced, and communicated.</p>
            <p>In other words, the silent agency of narration may do for a character what the
               musical notation “pianississimo” in Bizet’s opera does for Carmen, or
               indeed what Cavell’s speculative interpretation of what is happening within her at
               that moment does, which is not so much to supply the unspoken words as to explain the
               sufficiency of what she does utter. Transpose his “She stares blankly at the truth
               and is bewildered” to the past tense and it acquires the easy weight of a novelistic
               truth we would not hesitate to credit—a “pure constative” in its own right. The
               interchangeability of “pure” and “mere” and “simple” in such cases points to the
               sometimes but not always problematically unassuming character of the constative as a
               statement both beneath and beyond contestation. To take an example worlds apart from
               <title level="m">Carmen</title>, Austen’s sentence describing the situation of Fanny Price abandoned if only
               temporarily on her bench as the others wander Sotherton’s grounds together—“she
               seemed to have the little wood all to herself” (<title level="m">Mansfield
                  Park</title> 117)—repeats at the level of form the passing by or minimal notice of
               which Fanny is the object; or rather it transposes the other characters’ potentially
               ill-willed neglect into a kind of benign negligence. Fanny’s self-consciousness of
               herself as abandoned is registered as the illusion of possessing the little wood;
               something or someone in the sentence smiles wryly at this illusion, whether this
               smile belongs to Austen or Fanny herself does not really matter. </p>
            <p>Simultaneously unhesitating and unforthcoming, frankly assertive and closed to
               further elaboration, third-person psycho-narration promises to suspend the
               multiplying cascade-effect of perlocutionary utterances and bring to a term the
               potentially endless spiral of rejected rejections, inconclusive farewells, fallings
               silent, and resumed “no”s. This, of course, sounds a lot like the ideological use
               often attributed to impersonal narration—that of offering a measured mode of
               disclosure, a cool middle way between the sense of ourselves as utterly opaque and
               utterly exposed to one another. The long-standing association of free-floating,
               impersonal narrative agency with the similarly invisible divinity of textual
               monotheism, or the equally bodiless “voice” of ideological discourse, would also seem
               to cast the disclosure of unspoken thoughts made possible by free indirect style as a
               regression from the scene of secular judgment that so interests Cavell—a falsely safe
               retreat, then, from the loneliness and uncertainty of having to discern the other’s
               meaning on one’s own. Yet I hope in the readings that remain to suggest otherwise by
               distinguishing the kinds of resting-places precariously achieved from the false
               comfort of the illusion of total transparency and by emphasizing the sense of
               heightened proximity to unretractable error and incorrigible blindness. For Andrew
               Miller, who also addresses the relevance of the effects particular to Austen’s
               narrative style and Cavell’s project of acknowledgment, the “conversation” between
               her two narrative techniques—objective narration and free indirect
               discourse—simultaneously provokes our desire to complete a character’s near but
               fatally flawed self-understanding and leaves us powerless to do so (72). Miller shows
               remarkably little anger toward the double push and pull by which, he claims, Austen’s
               narration simultaneously goads and halts us, because he reads it through the lens of
               Cavellian perfectionism as an invitation for us both to wake up to the gap between
               ideal and actual self and <emph>not</emph> to experience this gap as a cause for despair (80-82),
               as if by helping us to a renewed sense of our helplessness Austen were rewriting in
               less stark terms Kant’s famous formulation of the predicament of human
               reason—solicited to attempt something it knows it cannot achieve.<note xml:id="ftn12"
                  place="foot" resp="editors" n="12">Cf. the famous opening, also cited by Joshua
                  Wilner in his “Afterword” to this collection, of Kant’s <title level="m">Critique
                     of Pure Reason</title>: “Human reason, in one sphere of its cognition, is
                  called upon to consider questions, which it cannot decline, as they are presented
                  by its own nature, but which it cannot answer, as they transcend every faculty of
                  mind” (xvii). </note> On this reading the erring human subject who reads and is
               read by Austen’s perfectly finished sentences cannot avail herself of their
               achievement, but where Miller assumes a subject who will always therefore try harder,
               I take the appeal of a “prose [that] never needs help but is unfailingly up to its
               aims” (71), as an invitation, in the other direction, to give up trying and happily
               resign oneself to the ready help of more capable hands. </p>
            <p>“Edmund, you do not know <title level="m">me</title>” (<title level="m">Mansfield
                  Park</title> 492)—Fanny exclaims to herself of her future husband, quickly
               dispensing of the illusion of marriage as an exercise in mutual knowability through
               witty or cutting repartée of the kind that Cavell idealizes. What would it mean to
               reimagine marriage as something occurring between novelist/narrator and protagonist
               rather than, according to heteronormative assumptions, between hero and heroine? What
               reparative work can we assign to the gently mocking maternal narrative voice who does
               the work of acknowledging Fanny’s bad faith and by the same gesture forgives or
               excuses it? In the following passage, for example, Austen’s judgment on Fanny as a
               moralizing prude doubles that of Fanny upon herself as hypocrite, but the one seems
               to cancel the other out, yielding in the place of moral heaviness, a sense of
               exhilarated exculpation (the “them” in question are Mary and Edmund whom Fanny is not
               displeased to see quarreling at her first ball): <quote>Fanny, not able to refrain
                  entirely from observing them, had seen enough to be tolerably satisfied. It was
                  barbarous to be happy when Edmund was suffering. Yet some happiness must and would
                  arise, from the very conviction, that he did suffer. (324)</quote> The middle
               sentence, which appears to belong more clearly to Fanny’s consciousness than the
               last, whose concluding and abstracting insight may or may not be hers, uses strongly
               moralizing language—“barbarous”—to condemn what it also presents as a mere temporal
               coincidence. The following sentence goes further in asserting an invidious causal
               connection between her happiness and Edmund’s suffering, but withdraws the moral
               condemnation. Yet it is not so easy to parcel out what here belongs to the subject of
               the happiness (Fanny) and what to its ironic reporter (whom we call Austen for
               shorthand). For if the impersonal, agentless construction—“it was barbarous”—and the
               use, specific to written language, of the auxiliary verbs “must” and “would” to refer
               to an indefinite happening in time, rather than an imperative or hypothetical
               condition, indicate narrative detachment from the character’s subjective experience,
               they also register this character’s own tendency toward queenly, self-absolving,
               analytic cool. If Fanny were to have written to some confidante, “It was barbarous
               [of me] to be happy when Edmund was suffering,” she might have been told she was
               sentimentally over-estimating her guilt but she could as easily have been taken as
               wittily and urbanely yoking moral hyperbole to the obviously unperturbed,
               deflationary “it was.” As it is, Fanny must accept to be happy, and to find her
               happiness where she does, at however tainted a source, exercising a kind of
               non-punitive self-knowledge in doing so without too loud a protest.<note
                  xml:id="ftn13" place="foot" resp="editors" n="13">See François 226. This unwilling
                  opportunism will also mark Fanny’s happiness at the novel’s end, for this too will
                  arise from a similarly tainted source: Henry’s re-seduction of and then entrapment
                  with Maria. </note>
            </p>
            <p>A few more examples will, I hope, round out the sense of this easing off of judging
               and relaxing into sufficiency, whether on the part of narrative agency or
               protagonist; perhaps appropriately, none of these passages quite meets the
               requirements of what I’m looking for: a judgment or last word that would simply lift
               the exacting pressure of the demand for an answer. A certain sly way of getting the
               last word, without in fact uttering it, is in any case the natural prerogative of
               free indirect style, whose ironic effects derive in large part from putting into play
               and leaving without comment the disjuncture between a character’s beliefs or meanings
               and the plot’s actual or imminent truth. So several chapters before the novel’s own
               dénouement, Chapter 11 of Volume III of <title level="m">Mansfield Park</title>
               concludes by markedly <emph>not</emph> resuming narration, ending instead with a rendering of
               Fanny’s growing excitement as she warms to what appears to her as the prospect of
               Henry Crawford’s soon desisting from his suit: <quote>Not considering in how
                  different a circle she had been just seeing him, nor how much might be owing to
                  contrast, she was quite persuaded of his being astonishingly more gentle, and
                  regardful of others, than formerly. And if in little things, must it not be so in
                  great? So anxious for her health and comfort, so very feeling as he now expressed
                  himself, and really seemed, might not it be fairly supposed, that he would not
                  much longer persevere in a suit so distressing to her? (479-80)</quote> As
               marriages go, the alliance between Austen’s narrative agency and Fanny’s point of
               view here would seem to strand the girl high and dry. For as if continuing the spring
               outing from which she has just returned, the passage, in its quick stringing together
               of questions and clauses, records a kind of quickening or thawing of Fanny’s
               speculative imagination, as she indulges in wishful thinking and begins to hope,
               admittedly for very little: that a man she does not love will simply go away and
               accept her “no” as definitive, for why should solicitousness for her health and
               well-being not be indicative of a more general wish to respect her choices? To this
               much, Austen gives Fanny reason and the logic remains intact, so that of the many
               jokes in play here, one is that she would like him better—and might be prepared to
               accept him—if he would only give up his pointed attention, and another is on the
               reader who, eager for Crawford’s chances, was prepared to take Fanny’s
               reconsideration of his qualities as a sign of her warming to him as a lover. </p>
            <p>So in the previous chapter perhaps nothing disposes Fanny toward Henry more favorably
               than his declining her father’s invitation to join them for Saturday dinner. Here too
               there are too many jokes fully to unpack, for where Fanny seems to overestimate his
               delicacy (as women are always supposed to be doing according to the gendered ideology
               of gentility), the concluding contrastive judgment, whether Austen’s or her own, only
               continues to consign him to the damned who will never be worthy of her hand: if she
               is right to want to spare him, it is only on account of his vices: <quote><p
                     rend="noCount">Before they parted, she had to thank him for another pleasure,
                     and one of no trivial kind. Her father asked him to do them the honour of
                     taking his mutton with them, and Fanny had time for only one thrill of horror,
                     before he declared himself prevented by a prior engagement. He was engaged to
                     dinner already both for that day and the next; he had met with some
                     acquaintance at the Crown who would not be denied; he should have the honour,
                     however, of waiting on them again on the morrow, &amp;c. and so they
                     parted—Fanny in a state of actual felicity from escaping so horrible an evil! </p>
                  <p rend="noCount">To have had him join their family dinner-party and see all their
                     deficiencies, would have been dreadful! Rebecca’s cookery and Rebecca’s
                     waiting, and Betsey’s eating at table without restraint, and pulling every
                     thing about as she chose, were what Fanny herself was not yet enough inured to,
                     for her often to make a tolerable meal. <emph>She </emph>was nice only from
                     natural delicacy, but <emph>he</emph> had been brought up in a school of luxury
                     and epicurism. (472)</p></quote> Finally there is a further joke in the
               discretion with which the narration leaves open whether Henry reads Fanny’s distress
               on her face and decides to decline the invitation accordingly, or whether he really
               does already have another engagement and is, as usual, putting his pleasure first—a
               miniature allegory of the difficulty of telling discretion from selfishness that
               informs the plot as a whole. </p>
            <p>Indeed if Fanny deludes herself at the end of Chapter 11 of Volume III (since at this
               moment Crawford has no thought of giving her up and indeed never will have such a
               thought), the plot will soon prove her correct in supposing that “he would not much
               longer persevere in a suit so distressing to her.” Not until the final chapter does
               Austen step in to account for this arbitrary lapse, in an unusually extended exercise
               in counterfactual fiction where the verb “persevere” once again appears, this time in
               the conditional mood: <quote><p rend="noCount">Could he have been satisfied with the
                     conquest of one amiable woman’s affections, could he have found sufficient
                     exultation in overcoming the reluctance, in working himself into the esteem and
                     tenderness of Fanny Price, there would have been every probability of success
                     and felicity for him. His affection had already done something. Her influence
                     over him had already given him some influence over her. Would he have deserved
                     more, there can be no doubt that more would have been obtained; especially when
                     that marriage had taken place, which would have given him the assistance of her
                     conscience in subduing her first inclination, and brought them very often
                     together. Would he have persevered and uprightly, Fanny must have been his
                     reward—and a reward very voluntarily bestowed—within a reasonable period of
                     Edmund’s marrying Mary. </p>
                  <p rend="noCount">Had he done as he intended, and as he knew he ought, by going
                     down to Everingham after his return from Portsmouth, he might have been
                     deciding his own happy destiny. (540)</p></quote> “Reward” is the same chilling
               word reserved for Marianne in <title level="m">Sense and Sensibility</title> in the
               thoughts of her sister and mother, who with the maternal narrator thus conspire to
               sacrifice her to the double demands of fortune and virtue represented by Colonel
               Brandon’s long-suffering deserts.<note xml:id="ftn14" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  n="14">Thus Elinor “felt that to <emph>his</emph> sufferings and <title level="m"
                     >his</title> constancy far more than to his rival’s, the reward of her sister
                  was due” (<title level="m">Sense and Sensibility</title> 379); “They each felt his
                  [Col. Brandon’s] sorrows, and their own obligations, and Marianne, by general
                  consent, was to be the reward of all” (429). </note> Austen’s repeated use of it
               here suggests that Henry’s reformation, however satisfying as a tale of moral
               redemption, would not have been worth the price of Fanny’s prostitution. At the same
               time, Austen rarely lays it on so thick, and in her haranguing of Henry for so
               completely if mindlessly ruining this alternative ending, we can read unease over the
               arbitrariness with which she has sprung her heroine from a plot from which Fanny
               herself could not so easily have extricated herself, since her giving ground in
               forming the hope that he would go of his own accord would have given him his first
               real grounds for hoping in the first place. </p>
            <p>Or so it would have gone were Fanny and Henry Stendhalian characters. Instead, Austen
               shows Henry extracting himself from a resolution metonymical of his proposal to
               Fanny, in a sentence that ironically produces the gentled sequence of
               deferral-turned-desertion and postponement-become-abandonment for which Fanny wishes,
               a movement parsed over three mental decisions among which Austen’s narrator finally
               does not decide: delay, performance by other means, cancellation: <quote>But he was
                  pressed to stay for Mrs. Fraser’s party; his staying was made of flattering
                  consequence, and he was to meet Mrs. Rushworth there. Curiosity and vanity were
                  both engaged, and the temptation of immediate pleasure was too strong for a mind
                  unused to make any sacrifice to right; he resolved to defer his Norfolk journey,
                  resolved that writing should answer the purpose of it, or that its purpose was
                  unimportant—and staid. (540-41)</quote> The repeated resolution (not to do x
               today, not to do it directly/in person, not to do it at all) finally does not resolve,
               and the last somewhat unsettling “or” amounts to a kind of shrug of the shoulders on
               Austen’s part: she does not care to know which way out Henry finally took, as all or
               any would have been sufficient.</p>
            <p>“Men owe us what we imagine they will give us. Forgive them this debt” (Weil, <title
                  level="m">Gravity and Grace</title> 9). In one breath Simone Weil makes an
               outrageous claim—there is nothing we cannot legitimately ask of others, or to put it
               in novelistic terms, “the schoolgirl is owed nothing less than what she imagines men
               will give her”— and in the next retracts it. I deliberately invoke the figure of the
               adolescent girl, simultaneously more exacting and less demanding than her adult
               parents who have entered into contract with one another, for in both its content and
               movement Weil’s thought follows the high-flown gestures of Stendhalian heroines: “A
               beloved being who disappoints me. I have written to him. It is impossible that he
               should not reply by saying what I have said to myself in his name” (Weil 9). The
               reader is not told just how the man has let her down or how she has excused him to
               herself. The novel that Weil here leaves unwritten, and that I have been suggesting
               in this essay Cavell’s famously uncontrolled prose often steps in to write, would
               concern the state of the man (the mortal?) who has been both accused and absolved of
               his insufficiency—from whom the secret of his having proven an illusion, unable to
               meet the other’s desire, has not been kept. </p>
            <p>I’d like to close with a passage that cuts the dialectic between the mildness of
               Fanny’s hopes and the extravagance of Weil’s, both of which can so easily shade into
               the coldness of no expectations at all. The passage finds Elizabeth Bennett (Fanny’s
               supposed anti-type) taking pleasure in the joke she imagines Darcy enjoying at her
               expense if he could, as she reflects on the irony of her changed feelings with
               respect to his earlier marriage proposal: <quote>What a triumph for him, as she often
                  thought, could he know that the proposals which she had proudly spurned only four
                  months ago, would now have been gladly and gratefully received! He was as
                  generous, she doubted not, as the most generous of his sex. But while he was
                  mortal, there must be a triumph. (<title level="m">Pride and Prejudice</title>
                  344)</quote> She imputes a cruelty, a laugh at her expense, for which she does not
               fault him. Perhaps such a going ahead of the other’s power of injury is all too
               readable according to the by now familiar reading of the disciplinary movement of
               Austen’s marriage-directed novels, where marriage is the reward for the wound the
               heroine inflicts upon herself and her narcissistic image of self-sufficiency. But
               such a reading hardly does justice to the multiple ironies of this fantasy of Darcy
               unable not to smile, powerless to resist his power over her, phrased as it is in the
               abstract form of the universal axiom. However one parses the thought—“it would take a
               god not to laugh at the errors of mortals”; “it would take superhuman strength not to
               find some pleasure in the weakness of the other”—one hardly begins to approach the
               riddle of a sentence that here finally does what it says and achieves a
               triumph—unassigned in Elizabeth’s mind because non-culpable, free of personal guilt,
               but in another sense unassigned because belonging to the immortal hand that writes
               the sentence and whose particular triumph is precisely to leave in doubt the reality
               of a triumph its human protagonist so decisively asserts, on the basis of
               finding her lover mortal.</p>
            <div type="citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>
               <p rend="noCount">Austen, Jane. <title level="m">Emma</title>. Ed. Richard Cronin and
                  Dorothy McMillan. New York: Cambridge UP, 2005.  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Mansfield Park</title>. Ed. John Wiltshire.
                  New York: Cambridge UP, 2005. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Pride and Prejudice</title>. Ed. Pat Rogers.
                  New York: Cambridge UP, 2006.  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Sense and Sensibility</title>. Ed. Edward
                  Copeland. New York: Cambridge UP, 2006.  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Austin, J.L. <title level="m">How to Do Things with Words</title>.
                  Cambridge, MA: Harvard UP, 1975. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. “A Plea for Excuses.” <title level="m">Philosophical
                     Papers</title>. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition. Ed. J.O. Urmson and G.J. Warnock. London:
                  Oxford UP, 1970. 175-204. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Banfield, Ann. <title level="m">Unspeakable Sentences: Narration
                     and Representation in the Language of Fiction</title>.
                  Boston: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1982. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Cavell, Stanley. <title level="m">The Claim of Reason:
                     Wittgenstein, Skepticism, Morality and Tragedy</title>. New York: Oxford UP,
                  1979. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">In Quest of the Ordinary: Lines of Skepticism
                     and Romanticism</title>. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1988. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">Philosophy the Day After Tomorrow</title>.
                  Cambridge, MA: Belknap Press of Harvard UP, 2005. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Cohn, Dorrit. <title level="m">Transparent Minds: Narrative Modes
                     for Presenting Consciousness in Fiction</title>. Princeton: Princeton UP, 1978.  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Critchley, Simon. <title level="m">Very Little . . . Almost Nothing:
                     Death, Philosophy, Literature</title>. New York: Routledge, 2004. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Ferguson, Frances. “Jane Austen, <title level="m">Emma</title>, and
                  the Impact of Form.” <title level="j">Modern Language Quarterly</title> 61.1
                  (2000): 160-180. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Finch, Casey, and Peter Bowen. “‘The Tittle-Tattle of Highbury’:
                  Gossip and Free Indirect Style in <title level="m">Emma</title>.” <title level="j"
                     >Representations</title> 31 (1990): 1-18.  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">François, Anne-Lise. <title level="m">Open Secrets: The Literature
                     of Uncounted Experience</title>. Stanford, CA: Stanford UP, 2008. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Lindstrom, Eric. “Austen and Austin.” <title level="j">European
                     Romantic Review</title> 22.4 (2011): 501-520.  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Miller, Andrew. “Perfectly Helpless.” <title level="j">MLQ</title>
                  63.1 (March 2002): 65-88. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Miller, D.A. <title level="m">Jane Austen, or the Secret of
                     Style</title>. Princeton: Princeton UP, 2003. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount"><title level="m">Oxford English Dictionary</title>. New York:
                  Oxford UP, 2011. Web. 31 May 2014.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Stendhal. <title level="m">Armance ou quelques scènes d’un salon de
                     Paris en 1827</title>. Ed. Henri-François Imbert. Paris: Garnier-Flammarion,
                  1967. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---.<title level="m">The Shorter Novels of Stendhal</title>. Trans.
                  C. K. Scott-Moncrieff. New York: Liveright Publishing Corporation, 1946.  Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Walker, Eric. <title level="m">Marriage, Writing, and Romanticism:
                     Wordsworth and Austen After War</title>. Stanford, CA: Stanford UP, 2009. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">Weil, Simone. <title level="m">Gravity and Grace</title>. Trans.
                  Emma Craufurd. New York: Routledge, 1995. Print.</p>
               <p rend="noCount">---. <title level="m">La pesanteur et la grâce</title>. Paris:
                  Librairie Plon, 1988.  Print.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
