<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Romantic Frictions</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
				<title level="a">About this Volume</title>
				<editor>Theresa M. Kelley</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
					<name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>about</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
					Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2010-11-01">November 1, 2010</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p rend="noCount">Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be
						downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
						unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching,
						and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
						amended.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on
						Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only
						in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as
						expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in
						any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors
						and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization
						should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
					<p rend="noCount">By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the
						following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p rend="noCount">Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in
						order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that
						of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
						elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
						resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the
						only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of
						course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our
						conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">About this Volume </title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Romantic Frictions:</title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
								Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2010-10-15">October 15, 2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p rend="noCount">All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for
						"," for ", ' for ', and ' for '.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p rend="noCount">Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been
						typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p rend="noCount">Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been
						indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p rend="noCount">&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound
						sign</p>
					<p rend="noCount">All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces,
						etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
					12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
						on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>David Rettenmaier</name>
				<date>2011-06-28</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="paratext">
				<head>About this volume</head>
				<p rend="noCount">This volume of <title level="j">Romantic Circles Praxis
						Series</title> includes an editor's introduction by <ref
						target="#KelleyAbout">Theresa M. Kelley</ref>, essays by <ref
						target="#DuncanAbout">Ian Duncan</ref>, <ref target="#FavretAbout">Mary A.
						Favret</ref>, <ref target="#O'QuinnAbout">Daniel O’Quinn</ref>, <ref
						target="#RowlinsonAbout">Matthew Rowlinson</ref>, <ref target="#JagerAbout"
						>Colin Jager</ref>, and <ref target="#KhalipAbout">Jacques Khalip</ref>.</p>

				<!-- Long volume abstract goes here -->
				<p rend="noCount">In recent decades skirmishes about how to read literature and
					culture have at times polarized critics, who find themselves identified, or
					identify themselves, with distinct critical dispositions toward either
					historicism or toward some version of poststructuralist writing, in particular
					deconstruction, supposed to be suspicious of historicism for espousing an
					empiricist, neo-positivist perspective on the past. What emerges from this
					standoff can seem comical or simply bizarre as one side imagines the other as
					its constitutive other, and as such productive of readings in which something is
					missing. Deconstructive and poststructural readers who ground their readings in
					philosophical argument and rhetorical nuance are at the very least bemused by
					the focus on detail in new historicist readings or the large gestures of
					cultural studies readings. In reply historicist and cultural critics find the
					lacunae in arguments from philosophical points of departure damaging to the
					lived temporality of writing and culture. Although this dispute animates more
					than one moment of literary study (it has become more marked in Victorian
					studies), its most sustained version has concerned Romanticism, understood
					variously since the 1980s as the disputed subject of new historicism and
					deconstruction.</p>

				<p rend="noCount">Whatever else it is, Romanticism arises in a moment of
					extraordinary and divisive recognition of differences among races, peoples, and
					political programs. And at least since the 1980s, the era has remained the focus
					of critical dissent as deconstructive, new historicist and other critical
					arguments debated whose Romanticism was theirs. This debate has in turn helped
					to shape public understanding of how we read literature and culture now as an
					enterprise strangely and contentiously divided between thinking about the work
					of language or the character of historical difference as though each goal could
					be separated from the other. This opposition is strangely rigid, easy to
					caricature and, as importantly, easy to dismiss. What gets lost in this critical
					antagonism is the shimmer of historical and philosophical friction in
					Romanticism itself and in compelling Romantic criticism in the last decade.</p>

				<p rend="noCount"><title level="m">Romantic Frictions</title> emphasizes this
					important critical turn, which supposes that the pressure of Romantic difference
					is as much historical and cultural as it is philosophical and theoretical and
					that it is ongoing in critical discourse. So positioned, these essays address
					the rub of critical differences as the work at hand as well as the work that
					Romanticism itself frequently performed. Hearing critical voices rather than
					taking stands, these essays stage frictions that make Romanticism engaging for
					modern readers, precisely because this era and its modern critics remind us of
					the value of difference as the work of thought in time and culture. The essays
					in <title level="m">Romantic Frictions</title> find in Romanticism what
					philosophical modernity has often found there: a disposition to recognize
					oppositions that cannot be squared or resolved precisely because they constitute
					the ongoing work of culture and writing. Such frictions are embedded in a
					shifting temporal moment whose inner complexity is similarly textured such that
					neither history nor philosophy assumes a master (and fictional) disguise. Both
					are instead crosscut and assembled in ways that sustain an inner friction that
					invites being read.</p>

				<!-- Change name of encoder here -->
				<div type="section">
					<head>About the Design and Markup</head>
					<p rend="noCount">This volume was TEI-encoded by David Rettenmaier and Michael
						Quilligan, site managers for Romantic Circles. Laura Mandell transformed the
						TEI files into HTML by using modified versions of the transforms provided by
						the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml">TEI</ref>. TEI renders text
						archival quality for better preservation and future access. This is the
						first <title level="j">RCPS</title> issue to be so encoded.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">The image associated with this volume is "A Group of
						Stapelias" from Robert John Thornton's <title level="m">Temple of Flora, or,
							Garden of the botanist, poet, painter, and philosopher</title> (1812).
						 The original may
						 be found <ref target="http://bit.ly/pllA3e">here</ref>.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">The HTML pages do not use frames but rather make extensive use
						of stylesheets for layout and presentation. The site works best when viewed
						with Mozilla Firefox v. 3, Netscape 4.0, Internet Explorer 4.0, or higher,
						or a comparable browser; earlier browsers may not display everything
						properly.</p>
				</div>

				<div type="section">
					<head>About the Romantic Circles Praxis Series</head>

					<p rend="noCount">The <title level="j">Romantic Circles Praxis Series</title> is
						devoted to using computer technologies for the contemporary critical
						investigation of the languages, cultures, histories, and theories of
						Romanticism. Tracking the circulation of Romanticism within these
						interrelated domains of knowledge, <title level="j">RCPS</title> recognizes
						as its conceptual terrain a world where Romanticism has, on the one hand,
						dissolved as a period and an idea into a plurality of discourses and, on the
						other, retained a vigorous, recognizable hold on the intellectual and
						theoretical discussions of today. <title level="j">RCPS</title> is committed
						to mapping out this terrain with the best and most exciting critical writing
						of contemporary Romanticist scholarship.</p>
				</div>

				<!-- Contributor bios here -->
				<div type="section">
					<head>About the Contributors</head>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Ian Duncan<anchor xml:id="DuncanAbout"/></hi>
						is Florence Green Bixby Professor of English at University of California,
						Berkeley. He is author of the award-winning <title level="m">Scott’s Shadow:
							The Novel in Romantic Edinburgh</title> (Princeton, 2007) and <title
							level="m">Modern Romance and Transformations of the Novel: The Gothic,
							Scott, Dickens</title> (Cambridge, 1992), co-editor of <title level="m"
							>Scotland and the Borders of Romanticism</title> (Cambridge, 2004) and
						editor of James Hogg’s <title level="m">Winter Evening Tales</title>
						(Edinburgh, 2002) and several novels (including Scott’s <title level="m">Rob
							Roy</title> and <title level="m">Ivanhoe</title> and Hogg's <title
							level="m">Confessions of a Justified Sinner</title>) and a co-edited
						anthology of <title level="m">Travel Writing 1700-1830</title> for Oxford
						World’s Classics.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.duncan.html">go to essay</ref>]</p>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Mary A. Favret<anchor xml:id="FavretAbout"
							/></hi> is Professor of English literature at Indiana
						University-Bloomington, where she specializes in literature and culture of
						the eighteenth-and nineteenth-centuries, especially British Romanticism. The
						author of <emph>Romantic Correspondence: Women, Politics and the Fiction of
							Letters</emph> (Cambridge, 1993) and co-editor of <emph>At the Limits of
							Romanticism</emph> (Indiana, 1994), she has published many scholarly
						articles, most recently in <emph>Modern Language Quarterly</emph> and
							<emph>English Literary History</emph>. She is curently at work on a book
						project about modern wartime in British Romanticism.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.favret.html">go to essay</ref>]</p>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Colin Jager<anchor xml:id="JagerAbout"/></hi>
						is Associate Professor of English at Rutgers University, where he is
						currently co-director of the “Mind and Culture” seminar at the Center for
						Cultural Analysis.  His articles have appeared in <emph>Modern Language
							Quarterly</emph>, <emph>Public Culture</emph>, <emph>Theory and Event,
						</emph>and <emph>Literature Compass.</emph>  <emph>The Book of God:
							Secularization and Design in the Romantic Era</emph> (University of
						Pennsylvania Press) appeared in 2006.  He edited "Secularism,
						Cosmopolitanism, and Romanticism" for <emph>Romantic Circles Praxis</emph>
						in 2008, and he has forthcoming articles on Charles Taylor, on literary
						enchantment, and on pedagogy.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.jager.html">go to essay</ref>]</p>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Theresa M. Kelley<anchor xml:id="KelleyAbout"
							/></hi> is Marjorie and Lorin Tiefenthaler Professor of English at
						University of Wisconsin, Madison. She is the author of <emph>Wordsworth’s
							Revisionary Aesthetics </emph>(Cambridge, 1988), co-editor with Paula
						Feldman of <emph>Voices and Countervoices:</emph>
						<emph>Romantic Women Writers</emph> (New England, 1995), and<emph>
							Reinventing</emph>
						<emph>Allegory</emph> (Cambridge, 1997), which won the South Central Modern
						Language Association award for best scholarly book of that year. Her
						articles have appeared in <emph>ELH, Studies in Romanticism</emph>,
							<emph>European Romantic Review</emph>, <emph>Nineteenth-Century
							Literature</emph>, and she has contributed essays to <emph>Romantic
							Science</emph> (SUNY, 2003), <emph>Cambridge Companion to
							Allegory</emph> (Cambridge, 2009) and <emph>Language without Soil:
							Adorno and Late Philosophical Modernity</emph> (Fordham,
							2009).<emph> </emph>She has just finished writing <emph>Clandestine
							Marriage</emph>, on the presence of botany, as figure and material
						culture, in Romanticism.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.kelley.html">go to essay</ref>]</p>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Jacques Khalip<anchor xml:id="KhalipAbout"
							/></hi> is associate professor of English and Modern Culture and Media
						at Brown University. He is the author of <title level="m">Anonymous Life:
							Romanticism and Dispossession</title> (Stanford, 2009), and co-editor of
							<title level="m">Releasing the Image: From Literature to New
							Media</title> (Stanford, 2011). His current book manuscript, <title
							level="m">Dwelling in Disaster</title>, considers Romantic and
						post-Romantic explorations of extinction and wasted life.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.khalip.html">go to essay</ref>]</p>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Daniel O'Quinn<anchor xml:id="O'QuinnAbout"
							/></hi> is an Associate Professor in the School of English and Theatre
						Studies at the University of Guelph. He is the author of <emph>Staging
							Governance: Theatrical Imperialism in London, 1770-1800</emph> (The
						Johns Hopkins University Press, 2005). He has co-edited the <emph>Cambridge
							Companion to British Theatre, 1737-1840</emph> (2007) with Jane Moody
						and edited <emph>Travels of Mirza Abu Taleb Khan</emph> for Broadview Press
						(forthcoming Winter 2008). His articles on the intersection of race,
						sexuality and class in Romantic culture have appeared in various journals
						including <emph>ELH</emph>, <emph>Studies in Romanticism</emph>, <emph>Texas
							Studies in Literature and Language</emph>, <emph>European Romantic
							Review</emph>, and <emph>Romantic Praxis</emph>.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.oquinn.html">go to essay</ref>]</p>

					<p rend="noCount"><hi rend="bold">Matthew Rowlinson<anchor
								xml:id="RowlinsonAbout"/></hi> is Associate Professor in the
						Department of English and Centre for Theory and Criticism, University of
						Western Ontario. He is the author of <emph>Tennyson’s Fixations:
							Psychoanalysis and the Topics of the Early Poetry</emph> (Virginia,
						1994) and essays on Victorian culture, capitalism, Marx and Jacques Derrida.
						He is welcomed to this volume as the disciplinary emblem of Romanticism’s
						differences with Victorian culture.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.rowlinson.html">go to
						essay</ref>]</p>

				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
