<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Romantic Frictions</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
				<title level="a">Abstracts</title>
				<editor>Theresa M. Kelley</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
					<name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>abstracts</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
					Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2010-11-01">November 1, 2010</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p rend="noCount">Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be
						downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
						unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching,
						and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
						amended.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on
						Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only
						in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as
						expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in
						any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors
						and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization
						should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
					<p rend="noCount">By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the
						following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p rend="noCount">Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in
						order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that
						of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
						elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
						resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the
						only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of
						course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our
						conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Abstracts</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Romantic Frictions:</title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
								Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2010-10-15">October 15, 2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p rend="noCount">All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for
						"," for ", ' for ', and ' for '.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p rend="noCount">Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been
						typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p rend="noCount">Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been
						indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p rend="noCount">&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound
						sign</p>
					<p rend="noCount">All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces,
						etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
					12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
						on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Mike Quilligan</name>
				<date>2010-06-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="paratext">
				<head>Abstracts</head>
				<p rend="noCount"><quote rend="center"><ref target="#KelleyAbstract">Theresa M.
							Kelley</ref> | <ref target="#DuncanAbstract">Ian Duncan</ref> | <ref
							target="#FavretAbstract">Mary A. Favret</ref> | <ref
							target="#O'QuinnAbstract">Daniel O'Quinn</ref> | <ref
							target="#RowlinsonAbstract">Matthew Rowlinson</ref> | <ref
							target="#JagerAbstract">Colin Jager</ref> | <ref
							target="#KhalipAbstract">Jacques Khalip</ref>
					</quote></p>

				<!-- Authors, titles, and abstracts here -->
				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="KelleyAbstract"/>Theresa M. Kelley</hi>,
							<title level="a">Introduction</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">In recent decades skirmishes about how to read literature and
						culture have at times polarized critics, who find themselves identified, or
						identify themselves, with distinct critical dispositions toward either
						historicism or toward some version of poststructuralist writing, in particular
						deconstruction, supposed to be suspicious of historicism for espousing an
						empiricist, neo-positivist perspective on the past. What emerges from this
						standoff can seem comical or simply bizarre as one side imagines the other as
						its constitutive other, and as such productive of readings in which something is
						missing. Deconstructive and poststructural readers who ground their readings in
						philosophical argument and rhetorical nuance are at the very least bemused by
						the focus on detail in new historicist readings or the large gestures of
						cultural studies readings. In reply historicist and cultural critics find the
						lacunae in arguments from philosophical points of departure damaging to the
						lived temporality of writing and culture. Although this dispute animates more
						than one moment of literary study (it has become more marked in Victorian
						studies), its most sustained version has concerned Romanticism, understood
						variously since the 1980s as the disputed subject of new historicism and
						deconstruction.</p>
					
					<p rend="noCount">Whatever else it is, Romanticism arises in a moment of
						extraordinary and divisive recognition of differences among races, peoples, and
						political programs. And at least since the 1980s, the era has remained the focus
						of critical dissent as deconstructive, new historicist and other critical
						arguments debated whose Romanticism was theirs. This debate has in turn helped
						to shape public understanding of how we read literature and culture now as an
						enterprise strangely and contentiously divided between thinking about the work
						of language or the character of historical difference as though each goal could
						be separated from the other. This opposition is strangely rigid, easy to
						caricature and, as importantly, easy to dismiss. What gets lost in this critical
						antagonism is the shimmer of historical and philosophical friction in
						Romanticism itself and in compelling Romantic criticism in the last decade.</p>
					
					<p rend="noCount"><title level="m">Romantic Frictions</title> emphasizes this
						important critical turn, which supposes that the pressure of Romantic difference
						is as much historical and cultural as it is philosophical and theoretical and
						that it is ongoing in critical discourse. So positioned, these essays address
						the rub of critical differences as the work at hand as well as the work that
						Romanticism itself frequently performed. Hearing critical voices rather than
						taking stands, these essays stage frictions that make Romanticism engaging for
						modern readers, precisely because this era and its modern critics remind us of
						the value of difference as the work of thought in time and culture. The essays
						in <title level="m">Romantic Frictions</title> find in Romanticism what
						philosophical modernity has often found there: a disposition to recognize
						oppositions that cannot be squared or resolved precisely because they constitute
						the ongoing work of culture and writing. Such frictions are embedded in a
						shifting temporal moment whose inner complexity is similarly textured such that
						neither history nor philosophy assumes a master (and fictional) disguise. Both
						are instead crosscut and assembled in ways that sustain an inner friction that
						invites being read.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.kelley.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="DuncanAbstract"/>Ian Duncan</hi>, <title
						level="a">The Trouble with Man: Scott, Romance, and World History in the Age of Lamarck</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">Sylvan the giant captive Ourang-Outang is only the most
						spectacular figure in an array of monsters, prodigies, and other anomalous
						characters who trouble the categories not just of culture, gender, ethnicity
						and race but of humanity as a species in Walter Scott's late romance <title
							level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> (1831). Dismissed by most
						commentators as a bizarre effusion of Scott’s dotage, <title level="m">Count
							Robert of Paris</title> sets its scene decisively outside the
						developmental continuum specified for “the classical form of the historical
						novel” by Georg Lukács. Eleventh-century Constantinople is scarcely the
						scene of “our own” past, a setting that may provide “a concrete prehistory
						of the present” (<title level="m">The Historical Novel</title> 269). It
						is doubly divided from modern British readers: by the schism between the
						Greek and Roman churches, which cast Byzantium as the decadent shadow of a
						more vigorous “western civilization”; and by the Ottoman conquest of 1453,
						which cut off the Greek empire from the progressive path to modernity. J. H.
						Alexander’s new edition of <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris
						</title>(Edinburgh, 2006), restoring extensive passages that were cut by
						Scott’s executors, allows us to see more clearly than was hitherto possible
						the novel’s philosophical investment in alien histories, alien origins. </p>
					<p rend="noCount">Among the passages published for the first time is a
						conclusion in which Scott acknowledges the unprecedented, experimental
						character of what is “probably the last of my fictitious compositions”
						(362). The quest for “novelty at whatever rate” has driven him to “lay his
						scene in distant countries, among stranger nations, whose manners are
						imagined for the purpose of the story – nay, whose powers are extended
						beyond those of human nature.” Scott’s prime example of a romance that goes
						beyond human nature is “a late novel . . . by the name of Frankenstein”
						(363). Scott had reviewed <title level="m">Frankenstein </title>for <title
							level="m">Blackwood’s </title>in 1818, and a new edition of the novel,
						revised by Mary Shelley, was published just over one month after he
						completed <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> (and less than two
						months before its publication). On Scott’s own authority, then, this essay
						will read <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> not as a historical
						novel but as a work of anthropological science fiction. Scott’s late romance
						reveals the link between the historical novel and science fiction to be more
						intimate than we might have thought, genetic as well as analogical, soon
						after the foundation of both genres (<title level="m">Waverley</title>,
							<title level="m">Frankenstein</title>) in British Romanticism. </p>
					<p rend="noCount">The name of that link, “man,” designates the philosophical
						problematic of <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> and marks the
						novel’s station not just at the end of Scott’s career but at the end of a
						century-long project of cultural modernization, the so-called Scottish
						Enlightenment. In 1739 David Hume had given that project a name, “the
						science of man.” By the 1770s it seemed as though history had become
						established as the discipline best equipped to realize the science of man,
						in conjectural histories of society, of manners and institutions, the arts
						and sciences, as well as of particular nations. It was the attempt to
						totalize these projects, to write the history of man as a species that laid
						bare a fault-line in the secular category of “man”&#8212;a fault-line
						constituted by its biological foundation. “The Human Species is in every
						view an interesting subject,” wrote Lord Kames in the preface to his <title
							level="m">Sketches of the History of Man</title> (1774): however, “there
						is still wanting a history of the species, in its progress from the savage
						state to its highest civilization and improvement.” “The subject of this
						volume is the History of Man, by which I mean, not what is commonly called
						History, that is the History of Nations and Empires, but the History of the
						Species Man”: thus Lord Monboddo, introducing the fourth volume of his
							<title level="m">Antient Metaphysics</title> (1795). These best-known of
						Scottish essays in the history of man as a species<hi> </hi>are notorious
						for their disruption of the category they invoke: Kames for his argument
						that humankind consists of different species (originally unified but then
						marked with biological as well as linguistic difference after Babel),
						Monboddo for his insistence that the mysterious great ape, the Orang-Outang,
						is man in his natural state, lacking only the artificial acquirement of
						language. For these accounts, it seems, “man” signifies at once too much and
						too little. By the time Scott was writing <title level="m">Count Robert of
							Paris</title>, in 1830-31, the trouble with man had blown up into a
						scandal. Amid a rising tide of mainly French morphological speculation on
						the transmutation of species, Jean-Baptiste Lamarck had cited the orang-utan
						as a human prototype&#8212;not just a type of natural man but a figure for man’s
						animal origins and the mutability of species. Lamarck’s work was diffused
						across British literature by the controversy that peaked in the early 1830s,
						in endorsements by “Edinburgh Lamarckians” such as Robert Jameson and Robert
						E. Grant, as well as in refutations, most notably by Charles Lyell in the
						second volume of <title level="m">Principles of Geology</title> (published
						one month after <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>, in January
						1832).</p>
					<p rend="noCount">
						<title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> finds its imaginative opening
						in the contemporary crisis of world history and the science of man. Scott’s
						Constantinople swarms with different creeds, nations, races and species, in
						which the boundaries between nation and race and species, and between human
						and non-human species, shift and blur. The main figure for this
						boundary-flux is the Orang-Outang, who, among his other accomplishments,
						understands instructions given in Anglo-Saxon and kills off the principal
						villain of the story. The newly restored text of <title level="m">Count
							Robert of Paris</title> allows us to see that various forms of
						biological difference (including sexual as well as racial and species
						difference) are everywhere in play in the novel. <title level="m">Count
							Robert</title> earns its place beside <title level="m"
							>Frankenstein</title>, if we understand Shelley’s novel (following
						Maureen McLane’s analysis in <title level="m">Romanticism and the Human
							Sciences</title>) as enacting a radical critique of the “specifically
						anthropological discourse of man” that underwrites the newly-won autonomy of
						imaginative literature in British Romanticism. Scott’s Constantinople opens
						a new kind of setting for a new kind of historical romance: the cosmopolis
						or world-city as conjectural arena for the natural history of man. Within
						this radically heterodox imaginary space, <title level="m">Count Robert of
							Paris</title> explodes the monogenetic trajectories of national progress
						charted in the Scottish Waverley Novels for a fantastic exploration of the
						multiplicity of developmental paths and forms that humankind might take. </p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.duncan.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="FavretAbstract"/>Mary A. Favret</hi>,
							<title level="a">Field of History, Field of Battle</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">Over the course of the eighteenth-century, Great Britain built
						a formidable military power stoked in no small part by financial instruments
						devised not by merchants but by the state. "The ability of government
						administrators to establish the routine by which revenues were collected,
						money raised and supplies requisitioned," writes historian John Brewer,
						"could make the difference between victory and humiliation." The rise of the
						"fiscal-military state" strengthened both British military forces and the
						state itself to an unprecedented degree. The financial, even clerical mode
						of waging war gained extraordinary value over the course of the
						eighteenth-century; hardly visible to the public at large, their effects
						were felt more than they were seen. New modes of taxation and deficit
						spending "put muscle on the bones of the British body politic, increasing
						its endurance, strength and reach" (xvii). Brewer's magisterial account
						deliberately turns attention away from military exploits and heroes, even
						away from devastating violence, to focus on the driest aspects of a nation
						dedicated to its martial power: taxes, book-keeping, numbers. In doing so,
						his account translates a system of fragile abstractions into corporeal
						tissue, converting what might be dead matter&#8212;the bare bones of the field
						of history or the field of battle&#8212;into a robust "body politic." More
						curious perhaps, and a sign of the uneasy passage of numbers to bodies, is
						Brewer's acknowledgement that the fictive body is also a feeling one:
						"humiliation," rather than defeat per se, is the haunting alternative to
						British victory.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">The figurative conjunction and conversion of numbers and flesh
						under the banner of war remains familiar. Harder to analyze in these verbal
						maneuvers is the level of sentience involved: what can the bodies born of
						numbers feel? The form of modern war emergent in the eighteenth century via
						taxes and debt financing is allied with other emergent regimes associated
						with numbers and finance: to what degree did the force of numbers amplify,
						dampen or otherwise transform the feeling body? If, as Brewer suggests, the
						economic repercussions of war in this period "are difficult to measure," how
						much more difficult is measurement when it tries to align what one
						contemporary called "the system of war" with the nervous system (xxi)? I
						would like to argue for a particular emphasis and delineation in the
						Romantic period on feeling numbers, especially among a group of
						reform-minded tinkers: Bentham, Godwin and Shelley&#8212;often in conversation
						with non-reformists such as Malthus. Heirs to and subjects of the fiscal
						military state, commenting both during and after the cataclysmic global wars
						with France that opened the new century, these writers unravel the neat
						allegory that Brewer paints, where the numbers of state finance and the
						cells of human bodies appear neatly woven together in the history of war.
						They employ numbers, by contrast, that tax the body to the point of
						disintegration so that, in fact, only numbers are left to register feeling. </p>
					<p rend="noCount">Following recent critical studies on numbers and finance
						capital by Mary Poovey and Ian Baucom; and studies of the history of affect,
						I consider Romantic debates on the numbers of war, and how reformists
						developed philosophical and rhetorical instruments to convert a system of
						value so closely associated with and productive of imperial warfare, into a
						system of feeling numbers that resists and works to disintegrate the fiction
						of the robust body politic. My aim is less to show how these writers argued
						against the system of numbers, but rather how they embraced and
						reconstituted numbers, insisting on the correspondence between pained and
						suffering bodies and state accounting, pushing that correspondence for its
						affective yield. In these cases, it is difficult and perhaps
						counter-productive to decide whether the appeal to numbers by opponents of
						the "war system" can be read as irony or complicity. "In the scale of just
						calculation," observes James Callender, a reformist forced to leave Britain
						for his criticism of Britain's war policies, "the most valuable commodity,
						next to human blood, is money." In his tirade against the "war system,"
						Callender literally seethes with numbers. Here is just his concluding
						flourish: “The question to be decided is, are we to proceed with the war
						system? Are we, in the progress of the nineteenth-century, to embrace five
						thousand fresh taxes, to squander a second five hundred millions sterling,
						and to extirpate twenty millions of people?” (8) The question that motivates
						my essay concerns what "just calculation" might mean in this view of
						history. I argue for war as a particularly potent site, indeed, perhaps the
						most potent and generative site for friction between universals and
						particulars, between theoretical (or in this case, numerical) systems and
						those forces (in this case, feeling or affect) that accompany as much as
						they disrupt such systems. The putative "difference" between calculation and
						sentience may be more complex than conventional accounts of Romanticism have
						led us to believe, especially when we are asked to respond to something like
						an unembodied sentience. </p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.favret.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="O'QuinnAbstract"/>Daniel O'Quinn</hi>,
							<title level="a">Of Extension and Durability: Romanticism’s Imperial
							Re-Memberings</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">William Hodges’s <title level="m">Travels in India During the
							Years 1780, 1781, 1782 and 1783</title> (1793) is a text literally
						structured by war. Hodges’s travels and his narrative are repeatedly
						interrupted by armed conflict between the forces of the East India Company
						and resistant native powers across the subcontinent. The particular
						conflicts in question did not go well for the British and the humiliating
						loss at Pollilur not only raised questions regarding Warren Hastings’s
						bellicosity, but also haunted representations of British rule in India until
						the final defeat of Tipu Sultan in 1799. In spite of the fact that the
							<title level="m">Travels</title> appears to be a pro-Hastings document,
						published in London at the turning point in the impeachment proceedings
						against the former Governor-General of Bengal, the narrative disjunctions
						instantiated by these conflicts destabilize Hodges’s explicit argument that
						British governance in the region is not only benevolent, but also far
						superior to prior examples of Moslem rule. The aim of this paper is to
						demonstrate how the text’s figural economy–both textual and visual–attempts
						to ameliorate the narrative disjunctions which everywhere threaten to
						disclose the Company’s precarious claim to sovereignty. Through a close
						analysis of Hodges’s figuration of good and bad governance in the region,
						the argument will isolate precisely how his–and by extension, the
						Company’s--historical predicament erupts into the text and call in to
						question the very models of governmentality figured forth in his remarkable
						rendering of the banyan tree.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Michel Foucault, in his essay “Governmentality”, defined
						“Government as the right disposition of things”. From the period immediately
						prior to the passing of the Regulating Act to the East India Company Charter
						Act, the hybridity of the East India Company generated significant
						controversy regarding the appropriate form and quality of colonial rule.
						Hodges’s text engages with this problematic by presenting figures of the
						right disposition of men and things. The most important of these, the banyan
						tree, is the subject of an extensive textual description and also one of the
						volumes most accomplished engravings. In the text, the tree offers shade and
						sustenance to all who come under its canopy and it is metaphorically linked
						to Hastings’s management of Indian affairs. Its vitality and above all its
						naturalness accrue to the governmentality of the Company and thus it
						ostensibly stands as a figure of prosperity, hope and stability in a time of
						war and economic uncertainty. It also stands in marked contrast to Hodges
						similarly iconic description of the ruins of Agra and especially of Acbar’s
						tomb later in the text. As ruins architectural traces of a similarly ruined
						Mughal empire, these descriptions ostensibly testify to the fundamental
						inability despotic powers to rule effectively. Akbar’s tomb is especially
						important in this regard because it is Akbar’s name itself, as rendered on
						the mausoleum that operates as the ultimate contrast to the banyan tree. In
						other words, a dead name, an almost Wordsworthian epitaph, figures forth the
						disappearance and obsolescence of entire period in Indian history and in its
						place, Hodges offers a living thing. What interests me about this contrast
						is that in both cases the historical obfuscations depend upon key slippages
						in the distinction between word and image, between living and dead, between
						name and metaphor.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">My essay’s concluding gesture demonstrates how the visual
						renderings of the banyan tree and of architectural ruins attempt to contain
						or regulate what amounts to a crisis in figuration. Of particular importance
						is the way Hodges’s image engages with prior images, most notably in Picart,
						which link the tree to suspect forms of sexuality. At the heart of Hodges
						engraving is a resonant act of visual surrogation which figures forth a
						remarkable fantasy of phallic Company rule well before the East India
						Company fully consolidated its power in the region. In other words, one can
						discern within the relationship between textual figuration and the visual
						strategies of the engravings the kind of “wishful thinking” or self-delusion
						that C. A. Bayly has identified as a crucial element of British governance
						prior to and during the imposition of the Permanent Settlement.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.oquinn.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="RowlinsonAbstract"/>Matthew
						Rowlinson</hi>, <title level="a">Allegory and Exchange in the Waverley
							Novels</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">This essay will propose that for an historical understanding
						of Scott’s fiction—or Romantic texts more generally—we should read them not
						as representations but rather as objects of exchange that embody social
						labor. The historically specific forms of the exchanges in which they took
						part and of the equivalents in which their value was realized determined the
						texts’ formal traits, which when this determination is ignored have the
						appearance of unmotivated play. The essay will offer its critical practice
						as an example to show that by a formalist reading of Scott’s fiction we can
						gain an historical understanding of textual production in the years of
						British publishing’s takeoff into capitalism. This reading will attend above
						all to the topic of signature, to the differentiations of text and paratext,
						and to those of writing as material practice and as abstraction, both as
						motifs in the Waverley novels and as problems in their social production and
						circulation.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">In Marx, capital is formally a moment of self-referentiality
						in the system of mediations that is a money economy. As capital money
						appears to lose the mediating relation to other commodities that normally
						defines it, and to relate only to itself in a process for which Marx gives
						the elementary formula M->M. The project of <title level="m">Capital</title>
						is to dissolve this appearance of capital’s identity. In discussing Scott,
						however, we are concerned with an historical moment at which that identity
						has scarcely yet been constituted. Scott wrote at a time and in a place
						where the money supply was in practice extremely heterogeneous and the
						question of money’s identity was a hotly debated topic in political economy. </p>
					<p rend="noCount">My main theoretical claim in this essay is that the
						indeterminacy of the money form for which Scott exchanged his labor as a
						novelist is allegorized in traits of the novels themselves. I will make this
						case principally through a reading of <title level="m">The Antiquary</title>
						(1816), the third Waverley novel and one of the most playfully
						self-referential. In this novel the inhomogeneity of money and the
						difficulty of recognizing it is a recurrent topic; two of the novel’s
						subplots turn on representations of transactions in the form M->M as comedies
						of error. In one, the Tory Baronet Sir Arthur Wardour becomes the dupe of a
						German swindler, who in exchange for an investment of “dirty Fairport
						banknotes” promises him “pure gold and silver, I cannot tell how much!" In
						the other, Wardour’s comic foil, Jonathan Oldbuck, the antiquary of the
						title, pays in good money for what he takes to be curious old coins, only to
						find that what he has purchased, though old, is a still-current instance of
						Scottish token coinage. Money, far from providing a uniform standard of
						value, becomes the novel’s principal instance of irreducible difference. </p>
					<p rend="noCount">Monetary difference in <title level="m">The Antiquary</title>
						certainly allegorizes cultural and political difference; elsewhere in
						Scott’s work, in <title level="m">The Letters of Malachi
							Malagrowther</title> (1826), written to defend Scots’ use of small
						denomination banknotes where the British system used coin, this allegory
						becomes explicit. The Scottish monetary system is defended not as superior
						to others, but on the grounds of difference itself. The frugality of a paper
						circulation that does not withdraw any useful commodity from circulation is
						explained as the expression of a frugal national character, formed by a
						harsh climate and poor land. </p>
					<p rend="noCount">This essay argues, however, that the monetary difference that
						repeatedly disrupts exchange within the diegesis of <title level="m">The
							Antiquary</title> also corresponds to formal traits of the text that do
						not readily lend themselves to culturalist interpretations of the kind that
						Scott himself pioneered. The uncertain boundary between what is and what is
						not money in the novel is the expression of a specific conjuncture in the
						historical development of capital and also an instance of a general
						problematic of the textual boundary that pervades the Waverley novels, with
						their serial form, indistinguishable protagonists, and extensive textual
						periphery in Scott’s introductions, prefaces, notes and other apparatus.
						When money is represented in <title level="m">The Antiquary</title> as
						bearing effaced or illegible signatures the novel incorporates within itself
						another instance of one of its own formal traits, framed as it is by the
						long performance of his own anonymity that Scott carried on before finally
						acknowledging in 1827 that he was the author of the Waverley novels. These
						formal traits of the Waverley novels, I will show, are determined by the
						historically specific forms of exchange by which the value of Scott’s labor
						was realized and ultimately transformed into capital.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.rowlinson.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="JagerAbstract"/>Colin Jager</hi>, <title
							level="a">Can We Talk About Consciousness Again?: (Emergence, Natural
							Piety, Wordsworth)</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">Talk about consciousness has largely disappeared from Romantic
						studies and, indeed, from literary studies more generally. As a symbol of
						this disappearance we might look to Harold Bloom’s edited volume <title
							level="m">Romanticism and Consciousness</title> (1970). While the volume
						was officially dedicated to the proposition that to talk about Romanticism
						simply <title level="m">was</title> to talk about consciousness, its
						inclusion of Paul de Man’s proto-deconstructive essay “Intentional Structure
						of the Romantic Image” in fact marked the beginning of the end of the
						association between Romanticism and consciousness. Sometime later de Man
						could retrospectively mark his own deconstructive turn as a break, however
						imperfect, from consciousness-talk. Noting the emphasis on “rhetorical
						terminology” in his landmark essay “The Rhetoric of Temporality,” de Man
						writes in 1983: “[t]his terminology is still uncomfortably intertwined with
						the thematic vocabulary of consciousness … that was current at the time, but
						it signals a turn that, at least for me, has proven to be productive.” One
						could note other similar turns at about this same time, not only within the
						“Yale School” and its turn away from phenomenology (Geoffrey Hartman and J.
						Hillis Miller) but also for example in Lacoue-Labarthe and Nancy’s <title
							level="m">Literary Absolute</title> (1978).</p>
					<p rend="noCount">Meanwhile, the historicism that has dominated Romantic studies
						for the past-quarter century has likewise had little patience with
						consciousness talk, which, particularly under the influence of Marx and
						Engels’s <title level="m">German Ideology</title>, it has tended to identify
						with “false consciousness.” The Frankfurt School, from Horkheimer and Adorno
						through to Habermas, has also been suspicious of consciousness, for largely
						cognate reasons. </p>
					<p rend="noCount">The end result of these powerful intellectual movements has
						been to deprive students of literature in general, and of Romanticism in
						particular, of a vocabulary for describing what goes on in the mind as
						anything other than a series of effects produced by some other structure,
						such rhetoric, history, or ideology. </p>
					<p rend="noCount">There are, of course, many good reasons to be skeptical about
						consciousness-talk, and this essay is not intended as a jeremiad. Rather, I
						seek here to remark upon an ironic countermovement in intellectual history,
						namely that just as consciousness-talk was disappearing from literary study
						it was re-emerging in the disciplines of cognitive science and analytic
						philosophy of mind. The result of this re-emergence has been an
						extraordinarily rich body of work—empirical and conceptual—on consciousness
						over the past 20 years: a rich body of work about which literary scholars,
						with one or two exceptions, has had nothing to say. It is that lack of
						conversation, the missed opportunity, which my essay dwells upon.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">One immediate objection to any effort in this direction is
						that reintroducing consciousness will result in mind-body dualism, and this
						result needs to be avoided for a variety of political and intellectual
						reasons. A stronger version of this claim is that the Romantic writers
						themselves were anti-dualist, but that this fact went unappreciated until
						the advent of deconstructive and historicist criticism. Talking about
						consciousness again would thus be like turning back the clock. And yet
						almost all cognitive scientists and philosophers of mind writing today agree
						that consciousness-talk and materialism are not mutually exclusive. Indeed,
						this is precisely the issue around which much of the current conversation
						circles: whether a non-reductive physicalism is possible, and what it would
						look like. The mind-body problem, that is to say, remains just that: a
						problem. One implication of this claim is that it may be impossible <title
							level="m">not</title> to talk about consciousness. Any position on the
						mind body-problem (which would include virtually any theory of how
						literature produces meaning, as Knapp and Michaels demonstrated a number of
						years ago in “Against Theory”) is also implicitly a theory of consciousness,
						even if a strictly negative one. There is value, therefore, in getting such
						hidden theories out into the open.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">My essay examines two approaches to the question of
						consciousness that have lately caught the attention of Romanticists. The
						first approach is a neurological one. The strong version of this approach is
						that because the mind is identical to the brain, consciousness is an
						illusion (though perhaps an evolutionarily necessary one). This is sometimes
						referred to as “eliminative materialism,” and it is a popular position among
						neuroscientists (Francis Crick, Christophe Koch) and some philosophers
						(Daniel Dennett). Alan Richardson’s <title level="m">British Romanticism and
							the Science of Mind</title> (2001), which argues for what Richardson
						calls the “embodied mind,” is considerably influenced by eliminative
						materialism. I will critique Richardson on the grounds that his
						neurologically-derived model cannot ultimately find a place for
						representation: a problem for any discussion of literary meaning, and (a
						larger claim) for discussions of culture in general.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">The second approach is emergence theory, which has a longer
						track record (stretching back to the nineteenth century) but is currently
						less popular among cognitive scientists and philosophers. Neither bees nor
						ants possess consciousness, and yet a bee-hive or an ant colony could be
						said to possess consciousness; in much the same way, emergence theory
						proposes that consciousness “emerges” from lower-level self-organizing and
						self- modifying systems. Some properties emerge from a physical substrate in
						a way that cannot be explained from the perspective of that substrate (eg.
						from the perspective of physics), nor are those properties reducible to the
						properties of their physical parts. Emergence has one decided advantage: the
						issue of phenomenal experience (“qualia”) is a problem for eliminative
						materialism (David Chalmers calls this the “hard problem”), but it is not a
						problem for emergence theory. Thus emergence seems a more promising route
						for discussions of cognitive science and literature, since it makes room for
						discussions of representation and of culture, as Alan Liu has recently
						demonstrated in his consideration of Romanticism and creative destruction. </p>
					<p rend="noCount">Emergence theory faces a problem, however, that eliminative
						materialism avoids: causation. This includes both bottom-up causation (from
						physical property to mental property) and top-down causation (whether a
						mental property can change the organization of its own physical substrate).
						Confronting this problem, Samuel Alexander, the late nineteenth-century
						emergence theorist, hit upon a phrase that ought to interest any
						Romanticist. The mystery of causation, Alexander wrote, had simply to accept
						with “natural piety.” My paper ends, then, with a consideration of
						Wordsworth’s “My Heart Leaps Up” in the context of emergence theory. </p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.jager.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="KhalipAbstract"/>Jacques Khalip</hi>,
							<title level="a">The Ruin of Things</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">"I see around me here / Things which you cannot see: we die,
						my Friend, / Nor we alone, but that which each man loved / And prized in his
						peculiar nook of earth / Dies with him, or is changed." </p>
					<p rend="noCount">Speaking to the narrator of <title level="m">The Ruined
							Cottage</title>, Armytage perceives what Adorno and Horkheimer call
						“disaster triumphant”: the invisible and intangible things of the destroyed
						environment, or things which in their utter lack of specificity and waste
						define the circulation of sentimental value that the poem has traditionally
						been thought to sustain. Part of that value depends precisely on this waste
						or decay that the poem proposes; after all, these things are not simply
						ghostly revenants but half-material entities on their way to death. Like
						Margaret, like the broken objects outside the cottage, and finally, like
						Armytage and the narrator, all things break down in the disaster that the
						poem paints, and their differences are rehydrated by its lines of sympathy,
						“in spite of things silently gone out of mind and things violently
						destroyed” (Preface). And yet, if Romanticism has often been read as
						synonymous with discourses of humanism, personhood, and community, how
						should we read Wordsworth’s insistence that we not look away from the
						disaster, from things in their states of destruction <title level="m">and
						</title>difference? And more specifically, what would it mean to think of
						persons as different things themselves? In this paper, I want to consider
						the non-pathological and transformative effects produced by disaster—that is
						to say, how apocalypticism in certain Romantic poems is denatured or
						flattened out to the point where “disaster triumphant” expresses new forms
						of non-triumphal, wasted life that evoke different ethical versions of
						social vulnerability. I will work toward a ruined cottage as the place where
						Wordsworth explores the hospitality of dwelling in the rubble of disaster;
						in other words, disaster as not the pessimistic obliteration of
						enlightenment promise, but rather as a kindly reimagination of sociality
						without a future. </p>
					<p rend="noCount">The spectral quality of things unseen echoes the commodity
						form itself which, as David Simpson has argued, describes not simply
						things-in-themselves but things as they leave the world. Although Wordsworth
						appears to be striving for a language of “thingification” in his scenes of
						disaster, he tries to think through a different kind of object relations
						that is not reducible to the logic of the commodity. The kind of interest in
						disaster that a poem like <title level="m">The Ruined Cottage</title>
						appears to evoke is not simply a rehumanization of our relationship with
						things in the world, but rather an unworking or <title level="m"
							>desoeuvrement</title> of our modes of being, troubling the kinds of
						economies which shuttle persons and things between durability and
						transience, gain and loss, wealth and waste. I trace how persons live
						through and are readily thingified in the disaster, and why the desire to
						treat persons <title level="m">as things</title> becomes a necessary
						component of Romantic modernity—to re circulate persons in an aesthetic
						economy that cannot bear to possess anything, that treats persons as <title
							level="m">res nullius</title>, and would have us literally waste life. </p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.khalip.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
