<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Romantic Frictions</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">The Trouble with Man: Scott, Romance, and World History in the Age of
               Lamarck</title>
            <author>
               <name>Ian Duncan</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">Kelley, Theresa M.</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.duncan</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2010-11-01">March 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">The Trouble with Man: Scott, Romance, and World
                     History in the Age of Lamarck</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Ian</forename>
                        <surname>Duncan</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Romantic Frictions:</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-03-01">March 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#226;&#8364;&#339;,"
                  for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>Mike Quilligan</name>
            <date>2010-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>
               
               <title level="a">The Trouble with Man: Scott, Romance, and World History in the Age
                  of Lamarck</title>
            </head>
            <byline>
               <docAuthor>Ian Duncan</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>University of California, Berkeley</affiliation>
            </byline>
            <div>
               <head>I</head>
               <p>What was Walter Scott thinking when he wrote <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>?
                  The last but one of the Waverley novels breaks the decorum of “the classical form
                  of the historical novel,” first of all, with its setting. Constantinople, the end
                  of the eleventh century: far outside the developmental continuum through which the
                  “classical form of the historical novel,” according to Lukács, should render its
                  “concrete prehistory of the present” (269). Scott’s readers would have understood
                  the Byzantine Empire as doubly cut off from the path to modernity—by the schism
                  between the Greek and Roman churches, which made Byzantium the decadent shadow of
                  a more vigorous western civilization, and then by the Ottoman Conquest of 1453.
                  The cast of characters conforms less to a set of historical types than to one of
                  those fantastic oriental taxonomies we read about in Borges. Its specimens include
                  Greeks, Turks, Normans, Varangians, Moors, Scythians, a homicidally irascible
                  warrior-princess, a philosopher nicknamed “the Elephant,” a real elephant, a
                  tiger, a mechanical lion, and a giant orangutan named Sylvan. Scott bedevils the
                  historical novel—his signature genre—with an alien history and alien races and
                  species. </p>
               <p>Scott composed <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris </title>in fits and starts between
                  December 1830 and September 1831. He was harassed by ill health, including a
                  serious stroke, and by disagreements with his publisher, Robert Cadell, and his
                  executor and son-in-law, John Gibson Lockhart. Just over one year later he was
                  dead. Critics have not hesitated to diagnose the excesses and irregularities of
                     <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> as symptoms of encroaching apoplexy—the
                  cloudy effusion of Scott’s dotage, the decline and fall of the Author of
                     <title level="m">Waverley</title>.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="1">See, e.g., Hobsbaum: “Everyone who has not
                     read <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> . . . knows it to be unreadable” (153).
                  </note> Much of the incoherence of the published novel is due to Cadell and
                  Lockhart, who cut and rewrote Scott’s manuscript as it went to press. J. H.
                  Alexander’s new restoration of <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> for the
                  Edinburgh Edition of the Waverley Novels allows us to read it, at last, in
                  something like the form the author intended.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="2">See Alexander;
                     Gamerschlag.</note> Among the passages published for the first time is an
                  epilogue in which the ailing Scott reflects on the experimental character of what
                  he thought might be “the last of my fictitious compositions” (<title level="m">Count Robert
                     of Paris</title> 362). The quest for “novelty at whatever rate” has driven him
                  outside the usual ground of historical fiction, “domestic nature,” to “lay his
                  scene in distant countries, among stranger nations, whose manners are imagined for
                  the purpose of the story—nay, whose powers are extended beyond those of human
                  nature” (362). Invention crosses a geographical and racial limit at which the
                  “manners” that are governed by human nature turn into “powers” that exceed it. As
                  examples of romances that go beyond human nature Scott cites Robert Paltock’s
                     <title level="m">The Life and Adventures of Peter Wilkins</title> (1751), a tale of a
                  sailor shipwrecked on an island of flying people, and “a late novel, also, by the
                  name of Frankenstein, which turns upon a daring invention, . . . the discovery of
                  a mode by which one human being is feigned to be capable of creating another”
                  (363). </p>
               <p>Of the two prototypes, it is clearly <title level="m">Frankenstein</title> that grips Scott’s imagination. He had written one of the few appreciative reviews of
                     <title level="m">Frankenstein</title>, for <title level="m">Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</title> in
                  1818; the present reference may have been prompted by advertisements for the
                  forthcoming <title level="m">Bentley’s Standard Novels</title> edition, revised by Mary
                  Shelley, published one month after he completed <title level="m">Count Robert of
                  Paris</title>, in October 1831. On Scott’s own authority, it seems, we are to read
                     <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> not so much as a historical novel than as a
                  work of anthropological science fiction. Here at the foundation of both genres in
                  British Romanticism, with <title level="m">Waverley</title> and <title level="m">Frankenstein</title>, the
                  link between them is revealed to be genetic as well as analogical.</p>
               <p> The name of that link, “man,” identifies the philosophical question posed in
                     <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>. It marks the work’s historical station not
                  just at the end of Scott’s career but at the end of the philosophical project of
                  Enlightenment, and specifically of the historical and anthropological turn that
                  project had taken in eighteenth-century Scotland. In 1739 David Hume had given the
                  project a name: “the science of MAN” (Hume 42). “There is no
                  question of importance, whose decision is not compriz’d in the science of man,”
                  Hume wrote: “In pretending to explain the principles of human nature, we in effect
                  propose a compleat system of the sciences built on a foundation almost entirely
                  new, and the only one upon which they can stand with any security” (43). The
                  science of man would also supply a foundation for that modern, post-metaphysical
                  upstart among literary genres, the novel. Hume’s contemporary Henry Fielding
                  justified the “new province of writing” with the claim that it could provide a
                  complete, authentic representation of “<title level="m">Human Nature</title>” (Fielding 30,
                  68). The philosophical prestige attached to human nature would outweigh such
                  defects as the novel’s lack of a classical genealogy, its identification with a
                  mass market and with women readers, and so on. Reinforced by developments in the
                  technology of fictional realism, human nature would remain the guarantee of an
                  otherwise suspect genre for at least a generation after Charles Darwin’s decisive
                  restructuring of a post-Enlightenment human science in <title level="m">The Descent of
                     Man</title> (1871). </p>
               <p>By the last third of the eighteenth century, meanwhile, Scottish philosophers had
                  elected history as the discipline best equipped to realize the science of man, in
                  conjectural histories of society, of manners and institutions, and of the arts and
                  sciences, as well as of particular nations. It was the attempt to totalize these
                  inquiries, to write the history of man as a species, which laid bare a fault-line
                  in the category’s foundation. “The Human Species is in every view an interesting
                  subject,” affirmed Lord Kames, in the preface to his <title level="m">Sketches of the History
                     of Man</title>; however, “there is still wanting a history of the species, in
                  its progress from the savage state to its highest civilization and improvement”
                  (Home I: 1). “The subject of this volume is the <title level="m">History of Man</title>,”
                  wrote Lord Monboddo, introducing the fourth volume of <title level="m">Antient
                     Metaphysics</title>, “by which I mean, not what is commonly called History, that
                  is the History of Nations and Empires, but the History of the Species Man”
                  (Burnett 1795: 1). These best-known of Scottish essays in the history of man are
                  notorious for their disruption of the category they invoke: Kames for his
                  contention that mankind consists of different species, branded with physiological
                  as well as linguistic difference; Monboddo for his insistence that the mysterious
                  great ape, the Orang-Outang, is man in his natural state, lacking only the
                  artificial acquirement of speech. For these accounts, it seems, “man” signifies at
                  once too much and too little.</p>
               <p> Kames’s and Monboddo’s cues are taken up with a vengeance in <title level="m">Count Robert
                     of Paris</title>. In Scott’s Constantinople—pullulating with different sects,
                  nations, races, species—the boundaries between race and species, and between human
                  and non-human species, melt and blur. The main figure for this boundary-flux is
                  Sylvan, the Orang-Outang, who (among other accomplishments) speaks his own
                  “unintelligible” language and understands Anglo-Saxon. Sylvan’s role has been well
                  noted by the few critics who have discussed <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>.
                  Graham McMaster reads the orangutan as an extreme declension of the noble savage,
                  in a symbolic antithesis between nature and art (214-15), while Clare Simmons
                  reads him as the “Romantic symbol of a loss of belief in human nature” (21). Their
                  accounts frame “nature” as primarily a moral rather than a biological category in
                  the novel. The newly restored text makes clear as never before, however, Scott’s
                  pervasive play with forms of biological difference, including sexual as well as
                  racial and species difference, in this most bizarre of all his works. Sylvan is
                  only the most conspicuous figure in a horde of prodigies and monsters which
                  overwhelms the traditional boundaries of “man.” Like <title level="m">Frankenstein</title>,
                     <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> opens to scrutiny the “specifically
                  anthropological discourse of man” which underwrote, according to Maureen McLane,
                  the newly-won autonomy of “literature” in British Romanticism as a distinctively
                  human praxis (10-13, 84-108).</p>
               <p> Key to what McLane calls the “ideological biologization of species difference” in
                     <title level="m">Frankenstein</title> (107), played out through a Malthusian discourse of
                  territory and population, is that novel’s speculative reach beyond a national
                  geography. Victor Frankenstein travels beyond the habitable limits of Europe, to
                  an alpine glacier and the Arctic Ocean, while the monster proposes the settlement
                  of his new race in the deserts of South America. This sublime planetary range
                  accommodates Shelley’s radical speculation on the potentiality for other races,
                  other species, to challenge human dominion and human uniqueness. The
                     <title level="m">mise-en-scène</title> of <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>, while less
                  spectacularly that of an early nineteenth century world-horizon, marks an
                  analogous abandonment of the geography of national history as well as of that
                  history’s philosophical foundation, a unified human nature. Scott’s Constantinople
                  instantiates a new kind of setting for a new kind of historical romance: the
                  cosmopolis, or world-city, as conjectural arena for a post-Enlightenment world
                  history—the natural history of man.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>II</head>
               <p>Recent scholarship has focused on the national contexts of Scott’s work, in the
                  legacies of Scottish Enlightenment moral philosophy and historiography, in British
                  Romanticism, and in the early nineteenth-century rise of Scottish fiction.<note
                     place="end" n="3">The direction was set by the most influential works in the
                     field in the 1990s: see Ferris and Trumpener. More recently, see Duncan;
                     Gottlieb; Jones; Lincoln; Mack; McCracken-Flesher; McNeil; Wickman; the essays
                     in Davis, Duncan and Sorensen; and in Duff and Jones.</note> This emphasis has
                  fortified a traditional preference for the novels that take their subject matter
                  from Scottish history, especially the great series of novels on the modernization
                  of Scotland, from <title level="m">Waverley</title> (1814) to the third series of <title level="m">Tales
                     of My Landlord</title> (1819; with the supplement of <title level="m">Redgauntlet</title>,
                  1824). The romances after <title level="m">Ivanhoe</title> (1820), with their miscellaneous
                  British, European and Asiatic settings, remain comparatively neglected. An
                  intermittent but decisive widening of scope across Scott’s career, from the
                  philosophical domain of national history to that of world history, remains largely
                  unexamined. Forecast as early as Scott’s second novel <title level="m">Guy Mannering</title>
                  (1816), with its Gypsies and off-stage Indian episodes, that shift of scope is
                  fully established in <title level="m">Ivanhoe</title>, in which dispossessed Saxons, Norman
                  warlords, Jews, returning Crusaders and their Moorish slaves contend in the
                  ancient forests of twelfth-century England; it is further developed in <title level="m">The
                     Talisman</title> (1825), a tale of the Crusaders in Palestine,<title level="m"> </title>and
                     <title level="m">The Surgeon’s Daughter</title> (1827), partially set in South India on the
                  eve of the second Mysore War. The critical attention recently paid to Scott’s
                  Oriental fictions has tended to frame them within the geopolitical horizon of
                  British Empire, whether in proleptic analogy (<title level="m">Ivanhoe</title>, <title level="m">The
                     Talisman</title>) or historical actuality (<title level="m">Guy Mannering</title>, <title level="m">The
                     Surgeon’s Daughter</title>).<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="4">See, e.g., Wallace; Watt;
                     Lincoln, 89-120.</note> The case for reading <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>
                  within this national and imperial field of historical-geographical reference is
                  harder to sustain. Far from being part of British imperial history, Constantinople
                  was “a seat of universal empire” (<title level="m">Count Robert</title> 4)—and a rival
                  universal empire, involving a rival conception of universal empire, at that. </p>
               <p> The next section of this essay will consider the symbolic status of the world
                  city, a new and vexed topos in Great Britain by the 1820s. But before we inquire
                  what Scott meant by setting his novel in eleventh-century Constantinople, let us
                  ask: Why Paris? Why should he have highlighted Paris, not
                     Constantinople,<title level="m"> </title>in the title of a romance of the late Byzantine
                  Empire? Fifteen years after Waterloo, Paris might have ceded geopolitical primacy
                  to London: but it could still lay claim to being capital city of the ascendant
                  domain that Pascale Casanova has called the “world republic of letters.” From the
                  late seventeenth century onwards, according to Casanova, Paris established itself
                  as the western capital of “international literary space” in its first modern
                  formation, the Enlightenment republic of letters, with the French language as its
                  universal medium (11, 67-73). In its ideology as well as its practical diffusion
                  beyond France the republic of letters was universal, cosmopolitan, pre-nationalist
                  (87). It was in a reaction against the cosmopolitan dominance of French that a
                  second developmental stage of world literary space took shape at the end of the
                  eighteenth century: the proliferation of distinctively national literatures, which
                  Casanova calls “the Herder effect,” otherwise known as Romanticism (75-79). </p>
               <p>Casanova perfunctorily acknowledges the eighteenth-century rise of a rival British
                  literary empire and pays next to no attention to Scotland. Nevertheless her
                  analysis frames Scotland as a highly interesting case, one which we may
                  extrapolate through Tom Nairn’s influential account of Scotland’s anomalous
                  relation to the historical pathways of modernization and nationalism in his book
                     <title level="m">The Break-up of Britain</title>. Scotland’s project of cultural
                  modernization, the Scottish Enlightenment, depended on the establishment of what
                  Murray Pittock has called a “separate public sphere” of letters and science in the
                  Lowland university towns (13). Distance from the seat of government (after the
                  1707 Act of Union) made possible Scotland’s modern entry into “world literary
                  space,” even as Anglo-British assimilation provided ideological cover. Rather than
                  exemplifying the binary antagonism between core and periphery analyzed in the
                  second part of Casanova’s study, Scottish literature made itself modern in a
                  triangulation with rival centers, London and Paris. While the Scottish literati
                  harnessed English as the linguistic vehicle of Enlightenment, they sought to
                  integrate their philosophical projects with the European republic of letters of
                  which Paris was the capital city. If the Scots invented British literature, as a
                  strong line of recent scholarship has argued,<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="5">See Crawford 1992; Crawford 1998.</note> it was to annex
                  it to that Paris-based horizon of world literary space—over and against a London
                  that remained relatively provincial in literary and philosophical terms even as it
                  was achieving global geopolitical supremacy. </p>
               <p> Scott’s fiction did not promote a separatist Scottish national destiny according
                  to the Herderian model. Rather than the Anglo-British absorption with which he has
                  often been charged, though, Scott extended the Enlightenment project of an
                  integration of Scottish literature within the larger domain of European
                  literature, the “world republic of letters”—although (to be sure) that domain was
                  very different in 1830 from what it had been before 1800, or from what it had
                  been, for that matter, in 1814 or 1819. This integration took place largely
                  through the medium of French translation, as recent scholarship on Scott’s
                  European reception has shown. French versions of the Waverley novels, by
                  Auguste-Jean-Baptiste Defauconpret, provided the texts for their diffusion into
                  other national literatures, and foreign authors who adapted Scott’s example, such
                  as Manzoni and Pushkin, read him in that language.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="6">See
                     Casanova 146; Barnaby; Maxwell, “Scott in France”.</note> The many operatic
                  versions of Scott, including Donizetti’s <title level="m">Lucia di Lammermoor</title>, were
                  based on French stage versions adapted from Defauconpret rather than on Scott’s
                  originals. Scott helped create the conditions for this massive French-mediated
                  reception across world literary space by actively engaging continental, especially
                  French, literary traditions in his novels; in his new book on the European
                  historical novel, Richard Maxwell makes a convincing case for the genre’s
                  articulation along a Franco-Scottish axis, from Mme de Lafayette and Prévost
                  through Scott to Hugo and Dumas. Scott, in short, belonged to French literature,
                  and thence to the world republic of letters, quite as much as he did to Scottish
                  and British traditions.</p>
               <p>Meanwhile, late-Enlightenment Paris incubated the most extreme developments of
                  that general project of the republic of letters: the Science of Man. It was in
                  Paris, more definitively than in London or Edinburgh, that formulations of the
                  natural history of man exposed the deep trouble with man as a universal category,
                  as what had been the putatively unified project of Enlightenment (unified in its
                  theoretical articulations rather than in practice) splintered into competing
                  systems, disciplines and ideologies. By the time Scott began work on <title level="m">Count
                     Robert of Paris</title> in 1830, the trouble had blown up into scandal. The
                  eccentric conjectures of Kames and Monboddo had been overtaken by more
                  comprehensive and radical theories emanating from the world capital of
                  Enlightenment, where materialist declensions of the science of man accompanied the
                  revolutionary reframing of man as a universal political subject. Amid a rising
                  tide of morphological speculation on the origins of life and the transmutation of
                  species, Jean-Baptiste Lamarck cited the orangutan as a human prototype—not just a
                  type of natural man, but a figure for man’s animal genealogy.</p>
               <p>Although it was not translated into English until the twentieth century, the
                  arguments of Lamarck’s <title level="m">Philosophie zoologique</title> (1809) were well known
                  in British scientific circles, above all in Edinburgh, which was the center for
                  advanced physiological thought in Britain until the founding of the University of
                  London (on Scottish principles) in the late 1820s. In the decade after Waterloo
                  (the era of the ascendancy of the Waverley novels) Scottish medical graduates
                  flocked to Paris, where they imbibed the controversial philosophical anatomy of
                  Lamarck, Xavier Bichat and Geoffroy St. Hilaire, and brought the new science back
                  with them to Edinburgh. As James Secord has shown, “the earliest favorable
                  reaction to Lamarck in a British scientific periodical” appeared in an anonymous
                  article in the <title level="m">Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal</title> in 1826. This was
                  the period when the young Charles Darwin was studying at Edinburgh; both Darwin’s
                  mentor, Richard Edmond Grant, and Robert Jameson, the Regius Professor of Natural
                  History, have been identified as the author of the article.  Grant, a far more radical figure than Jameson, was appointed in 1828 to the
                  new chair of Natural History at London, where his Lamarckian enthusiasm stoked the
                  fires of French philosophical anatomy and democratic politics in the age of
                     Reform.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="7">On Darwin, Jameson and Grant, see Desmond
                     398-402; Browne 69-88.</note> However, Secord makes a persuasive case that
                  Jameson, not Grant, wrote the article. Jameson belonged to the moderate Tory
                  Edinburgh establishment (Scott knew him); his even-handed comments on Lamarck
                  elsewhere, and his journal’s attentiveness to the latest scientific developments
                  in France and Germany, indicate the presence of “a wider circle of Scottish
                  naturalists interested in evolution” (15-17). Secord suggests that it was the
                  tolerance for Lamarckian transformationism in respectable Edinburgh—rather than
                  its vogue in radical London—that provoked Charles Lyell’s high-profile refutation
                  in the second volume of <title level="m">Principles of Geology</title>, published just one
                  month after <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> in January 1832. Lyell ridicules
                  the “progressive scheme” promoted by Lamarck, whereby “the orang-outang . . . is
                  made slowly to attain the attributes and dignity of man” (193). <title level="m">Principles
                     of Geology</title> proposed an influential solution to the late-Enlightenment
                  crisis of world history as the history of man: that of a detour around the history
                  of man, that minefield of radical and infidel speculation, altogether. Translating
                  the discourse of history from the human sciences onto the world considered as a
                  physical system (as in James Hutton’s <title level="m">Theory of the Earth</title>), Lyell
                  proposed a history of the earth from which human origins were sedulously excluded
                  (a strategy that Darwin would imitate in the <title level="m">Origin of Species</title>).<note
                     place="foot" resp="editors" n="8">See Rudwick 6, 158-60.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>III</head>
               <p>
                  <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> finds its imaginative opening in the
                  contemporary crisis of world history and the science of man, of which the
                  epicenter was Paris—the forum of a once progressive, now decadent Enlightenment.
                  Conservative British ideologues had cast France as the source of an absolutist and
                  then revolutionary cosmopolitanism against which local, organic forms of national
                  identification could be mobilized (e.g., in Spain).<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="9">See
                     Newman; Colley.</note> After 1815, according to Jon Klancher, a new conception
                  of the cosmopolis or “world city”—imperial, modern, the ganglion of
                  deterritorializing networks of capital as well as of corrosive new demographic and
                  ideological forces—had superseded the old-regime cosmopolitanism of the republic
                  of letters.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="10">Klancher; see also Langan.</note> So Scott’s
                  title means what it says: the Constantinople of <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>
                  situates a fantasia on the multinational, heterodox world city, the decadent
                  capital of the Enlightenment human sciences. Now, <title level="m">circa</title> 1830, that
                  discursive domain is falling apart, its relation to historical futurity cast in
                  doubt. If the progressive claims of Enlightenment had been discredited by the
                  terrorist meltdown of the French Revolution and its Napoleonic sequel, now a
                  second French Revolution threatens the restoration of the old regimes prescribed
                  at the Congress of Vienna. Revolution—with its claim on a political reinvention of
                  the human—has re-entered modernity to establish itself as a normal rather than a
                  singular event. Meanwhile Catholic Emancipation has legitimated a domestic
                  heterodoxy at home in Britain, and Reform, specter of a homegrown revolution,
                  lowers on the horizon. The world city accommodates not an “end of history” (see
                  Christensen) but its disintegration.</p>
               <p>The opening paragraphs of <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> reflect upon the
                  decadence of artificially restored empires. Scott compares Constantine’s New Rome
                  with “a new graft . . . taken from an old tree,” bound by an organic fatality to
                  resume an internal chronology of decline (<title level="m">Count Robert</title> 3-4). The
                  world-city is overflowing with heterogeneous creeds, nations, races, and species,
                  while alien hosts (Crusaders, Moors, Turks, Scythians) besiege it from without.
                  The mix of competing monotheisms overlays strange heresies (including, in a
                  canceled episode, Manicheans, 367-77) and Pagan survivals, such as the “brutal
                  worship of Apis and Cybele,” decayed from a state religion into popular
                  superstition (89). More than once, Scott compares Byzantine court ceremony with the
                  “court of Pekin” (7, 147), drawn into the geopolitical horizon of British
                  knowledge through the embassies of Lord Macartney (1792-94) and Lord Amherst
                     (1816).<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="11">Scott may have had an intimate informant in his
                     friend Basil Hall, who accompanied Amherst’s expedition and published a
                        <title level="m">Voyage to Loo-Choo, and Other Places in the Eastern Seas, in the Year
                        1816</title> (1817), reprinted as the first title in <title level="m">Constable’s
                        Miscellany</title> (1826).</note>
               </p>
               <p> One effect of this monstrous distention of world space is a diffusion or
                  fragmentation of historical time, in which we lose any sense of a unitary
                  direction along which history might be unfolding. <title level="m">Count Robert of
                     Paris</title> thwarts readers’ expectations that the western Crusaders, for
                  instance, might represent a romantic futurity—associated with individualist
                  virtues of honour and courage—that will supersede the orientalized decadence of
                  the Byzantines, according to the “clash of civilizations” and “nature versus art”
                  schemata that some critics have detected in the novel (e.g. McMaster). Such an
                  historical destiny is not made apparent in <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>, in
                  which the Emperor Alexius successfully manages the Crusaders and diverts the
                  threat they represent. (Scott’s informed readers would have known, of course,
                  about the sack of Constantinople in the Fourth Crusade as well as the Ottoman
                  conquest, but the novel refrains from harping on these future catastrophes.) The
                  eponymous Count Robert and his warrior-bride Brenhilda, formidable and glamorous
                  on their first appearance, prove worse than useless in the novel’s plot.
                  Brenhilda’s valour culminates in a grotesque Amazonian duel with the historian
                  Anna Comnena, in which she succeeds only in endangering her own pregnancy. Count
                  Robert, despite an outburst of action-hero alacrity in the middle of the story,
                  accomplishes nothing towards the resolution of the various predicaments he crashes
                  into. He does not even keep his promise to rescue the noble captive Ursel; that
                  task is taken care of by the Emperor, in one of Scott’s virtuoso essays in
                  anticlimax. Byzantine policy triumphs over Crusader prowess, however much the
                  Western narrator might profess contempt for the former and admiration for the
                  latter. The Emperor’s disavowed virtuosity consists above all in rhetoric, a
                  crafty linguistic excess, aligned with the supervening practice of the Author of
                  <title level="m">Waverley</title>. The narrator’s mockery of the “fair historian” Anna Comnena, sealed with
                  a formal parody of her <title level="m">Alexiad</title> in the fourth chapter, frames the open
                  secret of their stylistic affinity. “Scott moves to become what he beholds,” notes
                  Jerome McGann; since “[his] own style has over the years grown increasingly
                  elaborate and formulaic[,] [t]o pastiche Comnena’s prose . . . is to fashion a
                  critical measure of his own” (124)—ornate, murky, “Byzantine” indeed.</p>
               <p> Any sense of a governing historical progress or developmental direction is
                  exploded into a multitude of competing paths. The world-city opens up for the
                  imagination alternative modes and directions besides the progressive model of
                  Enlightenment conjectural history, supposed to structure particular national
                  destinies. Scott’s opening rendition of the <title level="m">translatio imperii</title>, as a
                  civilizational grafting that reiterates an inexorable process of decay instead of
                  a renovation, has already been mentioned. Later, we learn how the Anglo-Saxon
                  rebels who sought refuge in the greenwood after the Norman Conquest “made a step
                  backwards in civilisation, and became more like their remote ancestors of German
                  descent, than they were to their more immediate and civilized predecessors. . . . Old
                  superstitions had begun to revive among them,” drained however “of the sincere
                  belief which was entertained by their heathen ancestors” (<title level="m">Count
                     Robert</title> 209). Scott reimagines Robin Hood and his band—mythic figures
                  from his own <title level="m">Ivanhoe</title>—as inauthentic and degenerate. At the same time
                  these “Foresters,” natural Malthusians, regulate their population by chaste
                  practices of “moderation and self-denial” (210). It appears that those who regress
                  from civilization to the woods, as a consequence of world-historical defeat, are
                  better able to constitute a virtuous organic community than those who have not yet
                  left the woods.</p>
               <p>Volume Two of <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> closes with a striking instance
                  of what the narrator calls “retrograde evolution” (255). The Crusaders have
                  crossed the Bosphorus to the Asian shore on their way to Jerusalem, after swearing
                  an oath “never to turn back upon the sacred journey.” When they learn that Count
                  Robert and his bride are in trouble back in Constantinople, they must figure out a
                  way to rescue them without breaking their oath. “Are we such bad horsemen, or are
                  our steeds so awkward, that we cannot rein them back from this to the
                  landing-place at Scutari?” one of them suggests: “We can get them on shipboard in
                  the same retrograde manner, and when we arrive in Europe, where our vow binds us
                  no longer, the Count and Countess of Paris are rescued” (253). The inhabitants of
                  Scutari are duly treated to the spectacle of a column of knights riding their
                  horses backwards onto the transport barges.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>IV</head>
               <p>The Crusaders’ “retrograde evolution” is a grotesquely literal acting-out of a
                  developmental dynamic or potential that pulls at the various histories, destinies
                  and identities entangled in <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>. History is not
                  bound to move forward—whatever forward might mean; it might fall backwards, or
                  slide sideways, or go off in some other, unheard-of direction. It is not only
                  progress that is at stake, more than ever discredited by its Lamarckian
                  application to an evolutionary account of natural history. Scott’s Constantinople
                  accommodates an imaginary breakup of the monogenetic developmentalism that (this
                  novel lets us see) has underpinned the national history addressed in the great
                  sequence of his Scottish Waverley novels. “Monogenesis” designates the orthodox
                  anthropological principle that all humans are descended from a common origin and
                  thus comprise a single race or species. The principle governs the ideology of
                  unified development, or a shared single history, which a particular people or
                  nation, such as Scotland, must join on the path to modernity.</p>
               <p>In those key reflections on his art, the prefatory chapter to<title level="m">
                     Waverley</title> and the dedicatory epistle to <title level="m">Ivanhoe</title>, Scott cites
                  a universal human nature, constant across all differences of time and place, as
                  the philosophical basis for the kind of novel he is writing: 
                  <quote>Considering
                     the disadvantages inseparable from this part of my subject, I must be
                     understood to have resolved to avoid them as much as possible, by throwing the
                     force of my narrative upon the characters and passions of the actors;—those
                     passions common to men in all stages of society, and which have alike agitated
                     the human heart, whether it throbbed under the steel corslet of the fifteenth
                     century, the brocaded coat of the eighteenth, or the blue frock and white
                     dimity waistcoat of the present day. . . . It is from the great book of Nature,
                     the same through a thousand editions, whether of black letter or wire-wove and
                     hot-pressed, that I have venturously essayed to read a chapter to the public.
                        (<title level="m">Waverley</title> 5-6)</quote> 
                  In observing the sameness of “the
                  passions . . . in all stages of society,” the historical novel advertises itself
                  as a faithful edition of “the great book of Nature.” The gap between past and
                  present in <title level="m">Waverley</title>—“sixty years since”—becomes a gulf of six
                  centuries, rather more difficult to navigate, in <title level="m">Ivanhoe</title>: <lb/>
                  
                  <quote>What
                     I have applied to language, is still more justly applicable to sentiments and
                     manners. The passions, the sources from which these must spring in all their
                     modifications, are generally the same in all ranks and conditions, all
                     countries and ages; and it follows, as a matter of course, that the opinions,
                     habits of thinking, and actions, however influenced by the peculiar state of
                     society, must still, upon the whole, bear a strong resemblance to each other.
                     Our ancestors were not more distinct from us, surely, than Jews are from
                     Christians[.] (<title level="m">Ivanhoe</title> 19-20)</quote> 
                  
                  The story that follows turns
                  the proposition into a profoundly uncomfortable question: How distinct are Jews
                  from Christians? In drawing an equivalence between the diachronic difference
                  between ourselves and our ancestors and the synchronic difference between Jews and
                  Christians, Scott alludes to the scriptural resolution of that equivalence,
                  whereby an archaic Jewish dispensation is redeemed into an enlightened Christian
                  one. Ethically speaking, however—that is, viewed with an enlightened disregard for
                  dogma—Rebecca the Jewess turns out to be more chivalrous and a better Christian
                  than any of the Christian knights in <title level="m">Ivanhoe</title>. She speaks more
                  eloquently than anyone for a humane futurity. She is more human than “our
                  ancestors.” All the same she is exiled from the proto-national community, the
                  English destiny, evoked at the novel’s close. </p>
               <p>The sublime widening of historical distance in <title level="m">Ivanhoe</title>, and that
                  novel’s disintegration of “England” into a welter of alien ethnicities and castes,
                  look forward to the more radical experiment of <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>,
                  which opens up a “polygenetic” potentiality of evolutionary trajectories and
                  forms, enabled by its setting of a world-city severed both from western religious
                  orthodoxy and from the developmental path to modernity. Polygenesis, the heterodox
                  doctrine that humankind consists of different races or species with separate
                  origins, had been broached in Scotland by Kames in his <title level="m">Sketches of the
                     History of Man</title>. Addressing the question “whether there are different
                  races of men, or whether all men are of one race without any difference but what
                  proceeds from climate or other external cause,” Kames concluded that “there are
                  different species of men as well as of dogs” (Home I: 3, 20). Species
                  differentiation occurred, along with linguistic differentiation, as “an immediate
                  change of bodily constitution” after the fall of the Tower of Babel (I: 76).
                  Polygenetic speculation was becoming increasingly current in advanced scientific
                  thought by the late 1820s and 1830s, undermining what had been a monogenetic
                  orthodoxy, until it informed an ascendant racial science in mid-nineteenth century
                  Britain and the USA. (The most notorious polygenetic thesis, <title level="m">The Races of
                     Men: A Fragment</title> (1850), would issue from a Scottish pen—that of Robert
                  Knox, the radical anatomist tainted by the Burke and Hare scandal in 1828-29,
                  classmate of Robert E. Grant and one of Scott’s <title level="m">bêtes noires</title>. The
                  actual terms, monogenesis and polygenesis, would not be formulated until the
                     1860s.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="12">See Stepan; on Knox see Desmond 77-80, 388-89;
                     Kitson (who argues that Knox’s polygenetic views were not characteristic of
                     Romantic-period thinking about race). </note>)</p>
               <p> The weight of polygenetic conjecture is felt throughout <title level="m">Count Robert of
                     Paris</title>. By the logic of “retrograde evolution,” cultural difference seems
                  always to be on the point of falling into racial difference, and racial difference
                  falling into species difference—since, as Buffon, Monboddo and others
                  acknowledged, the terms race and species have no clear definition in the
                     period.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="13">See Burnett 1774: I: 313-17. </note> “Race” is
                  a problem everywhere in the novel, its status and boundaries the objects of
                  constant interrogation. Count Robert, Hereward the Varangian, and Anna Comnena
                  dispute whether or not the Normans and Franks are the same people (<title level="m">Count
                     Robert</title> 142-43). Alexius lectures Brenhilda on the clash of civilizations
                  memorialized in the <title level="m">Iliad</title>: “the offences of Paris were those of a
                  dissolute Asiatic; the courage which avenged them was that of the Greek Empire”
                  (195). The character of his own Greek Empire, more dissolute and Asiatic than
                  heroic, belies this racialized distinction.</p>
               <p> Most striking is the novel’s set of limit cases of human racial difference. The
                  first of these is instantiated (predictably) by Africans, reduced to slavery and
                  subject to a not-always-specified physical deformation. (Mutes and eunuchs seem to
                  share the same kind of disability.) The philosopher Agelastes holds forth
                  hypocritically on the separate status of “the race of Ham” as justification for
                  their enslavement (128). His slave Diogenes rebukes as “childish” Hereward’s
                  suspicion that he might be the devil, and ironizes the signs of his own
                  difference: <quote>“Thou objectest sorely to my complexion,” said the negro; “how
                     knowest thou that it is, in fact, a thing to be counted and acted upon as a
                     matter of reality? Thy eyes daily apprise thee, that the colour of the sky
                     nightly changes from bright to black, yet thou knowest that this is by no means
                     owing to any habitual colour of the heavens themselves . . . How canst thou
                     tell, but what the difference of my colour from thine own may be owing to some
                     circumstance of a similar nature—not real of itself, but only creating an
                     apparent reality?” (90) </quote> Well might he ask, in a city where the
                  doctrinal difference between eastern and western Christianity has acquired a
                  biological, embodied cast, so that heterodoxy is expressed as a physical
                  deformity: the Orthodox Patriarch complains that, whereas the Greek cross exhibits
                  “limbs of the same length,” in the Latin cross an “irregular and most damnable
                  error prolongs the nether limb of that most holy emblem” (84).</p>
               <p>Disproportion of the limbs characterizes the most spectacular of the novel’s limit
                  cases, both of which involve a monstrous distortion of the human. The narrator
                  comments that in Constantinople “the race of the Greeks was no longer to be seen,
                  even in its native country, unmixed, or in absolute purity; on the contrary, there
                  were features which argued a different descent” (125). The reflection takes a
                  nightmarish turn: <quote>A party of heathen Scythians, presented the deformed
                     features of the daemons whom they were said to worship—that is, having flat
                     noses with expanded nostrils, which seemed to admit the sight to their very
                     brain; faces which extended rather in breadth than length, with strange
                     unintellectual eyes placed in the extremity; figures short and dwarfish, yet
                     garnished with legs and arms of astonishing sinewy strength, disproportioned to
                     their body. (125)</quote> Scott alludes to a legend cited in Gibbon’s
                     <title level="m">Decline and Fall</title>, according to which “the witches of Scythia . . . had
                  copulated in the desert with infernal spirits, and the Huns were the offspring of
                  this execrable conjunction” (qtd. in <title level="m">Count Robert</title> 525). The allusion
                  infects the novel’s anthropology with its conjecture of monstrous descent.<note
                     place="foot" resp="editors" n="14">Sutherland, reading the Scythians and the Orang-Outang as
                     figures of “degeneration,” invests <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> with a
                     later nineteenth-century preoccupation (343-44).</note> The combination of
                  “strange unintellectual eyes” with nostrils that admit “sight to [the] very brain”
                  suggests, meanwhile, a weird short-circuiting of a human physiology of
                  vision-based cognition—a topic that recurs elsewhere in <title level="m">Count Robert of
                     Paris</title>.</p>
               <p> The novel’s main exhibit of what Nancy Armstrong has called “the polygenetic
                     imagination” <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="15">Armstrong refers to late-Victorian Gothic romances by H.
                     Rider Haggard and Bram Stoker, flourishing in the imperial heyday of scientific
                     racism.</note>
                  is Sylvan the Orang-Outang: a creature that wears “the form
                  of a human being” yet stands eight feel tall, like Frankenstein’s monster, with
                  “limbs . . . much larger than humanity” (<title level="m">Count Robert</title> 169-70). Sylvan
                  represents a more up-to-date challenge to the monogenetic ground-plan of
                  philosophical history than fables of miscegenation with devils. In admitting
                  Orang-Outangs to fully human status as “a barbarous nation, which has not yet
                  learned the use of speech,” Monboddo contradicted his principal source, Buffon,
                  who insisted that the creature was “nothing but a real brute, endowed with the
                  external mark of humanity, but deprived of thought, and of every faculty which
                  properly constitutes the human species” (Burnett I: 270-312 (270); Buffon X: 37).
                  Buffon acknowledges however that this verdict relies on faith in a “divine spirit”
                  which has endowed humanity with reason and language—since physical evidence alone
                  would compel us to regard the orangutan “as a variety of the human species” (X:
                     27).<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="16">Buffon was following the lead of Linnaeus amid a
                     long-standing controversy; see Agamben’s summary of Enlightenment taxonomies of
                     the anthropoid ape and human, 23-27: “<title level="m">Homo sapiens</title> . . . is neither a
                     clearly defined species nor a substance; it is, rather, a machine or device for
                     producing the recognition of the human” (26).</note> Evicting the divine
                  spirit, Lamarck claimed the Orang-Outang as not just a human relative but a human
                  ancestor. This liminal being enjoyed a vogue in Romantic fiction, with versions by
                  Peacock, Hogg, and Poe, as well as Scott himself; more thoroughly than its
                  precursors, <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title> exploits the categorical confusion
                  and instability marked by the Orang-Outang in early nineteenth-century natural
                  philosophy, rather than endorsing any particular scientific theory (McMaster 212;
                  Simmons 25). Where various characters mistake Sylvan for the devil or a knight
                  transformed by witchcraft, the narrator is carefully equivocal. “The creature . . . it
                  would have been rash to have termed it a man,” he calls it (<title level="m">Count
                     Robert</title> 170): “the tremendous creature, so like, yet so very unlike to
                  the human form . . . the creature in question, whose appearance seemed to the
                  Count of Paris so very problematical, was a specimen of that gigantic species of
                  ape—if it is not indeed some animal more nearly allied to ourselves—to which, I
                  believe, naturalists have given the name of Ourang Outang” (171). A dozen years
                  earlier, Scott had alluded to the enigmatic status of the orangutan in his
                  depiction of pre-modern human communities in <title level="m">Rob Roy</title>—not to suggest
                  that the Highlanders are literally a sort of Caledonian apeman, or even a separate
                  race, but rather to conjure the possibility of a separate developmental path that
                  the novel begins to imagine (if only optatively) for them, in a departure from the
                  monogenetic British history invoked in <title level="m">Waverley</title>. Moderns and
                  primitives coexist within an imperial world order which sustains itself upon the
                  perpetuation of radical forms of difference.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="17">See Duncan
                     111-14.</note>
               </p>
               <p> Those forms of difference attain monstrous extremes in the “seat of universal
                  empire.” McMaster contends that the Orang-Outang belongs to a
                  conjectural-historical chain of versions of “natural man” in the novel, along with
                  Hereward the Forester (whose physical beauty, extolled in the opening episode, has
                  something grotesque about it) and Count Robert himself (McMaster 214-15). On the
                  other side of the species barrier, Simmons shows how the Emperor’s menagerie of
                  non-human beings—elephant, giraffe, tiger, clockwork lion—involves the orangutan
                  in a satirical “confusion between beasts, man-beasts, and man-made beasts”
                  (Simmons 27). To these we should add the human monsters in the novel that are
                  marked by another sort of biological difference, namely sexual difference. The
                  Countess Brenhilda is persistently characterized as “[s]omething between man and
                  woman” (<title level="m">Count Robert</title> 180), thanks to the “fantastic appearance of her
                  half-masculine garb” (133). It turns out that the warrior-woman is pregnant, even
                  as she takes up arms in the novel’s bizarre climax. Biology trumps habit:
                  Brenhilda faints before she can engage battle. The duel confirms the status of her
                  opponent, Anna Comnena, as a complementary freak, the bluestocking. Early on we
                  are told that intellectual activity has unsexed Anna: “she had somewhat lost the
                  charms of her person as she became enriched in her mind” (37). “A woman who is
                  pitiless, is a worse monster than one who is unsexed,” the Empress Irene (herself
                  something of a monster) upbraids her daughter (284).</p>
               <p>Meanwhile the appearance of the Scythians foreshadows uncanny crossings between
                  the human and demonic after all. In the course of a diatribe against Christian
                  “superstition,” Agelastes is surprised by the sudden intrusion of a figure
                  resembling “the Satan of Christian mythology, or a satyr of the heathen age”
                  (270). This turns out to be Sylvan, the Orang-Outang. Monboddo had accepted
                  satyrs, along with mermaids, men with tails, dog-headed men, and men with eyes in
                  their breasts, as legitimate varieties of humankind alongside the orangutan,
                  although Scott is alluding to a more modest conjecture that ancient accounts of
                  satyrs might have been based on travellers’ tales of great apes (Burnett 1784:
                  III: 254-64).<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="18">The identification of great apes as “the
                     satyrs of the ancients” goes back to Tyson; see Nash 16-41.</note> Sylvan’s
                  role as satyr will be confirmed at his last appearance in the novel, as closing
                  act to the tragi-comical sequence of combats. More consequential is his role here
                  (not for the first time) as the devil. Agelastes has just been scoffing at “the
                  Christian Satan,” whose “goatish figure and limbs, with grotesque features,” in
                  violation of the scriptural principle of monogenesis, represent a bad theology as
                  well as bad aesthetics and bad biology (<title level="m">Count Robert</title> 270). Sylvan
                  proceeds to throttle Agelastes, an event interpreted by the onlookers as “the
                  judgment of Heaven.” Certainly this is a startlingly abrupt explosion of poetic
                  justice. Agelastes is the worst of the book’s villains, a seditious freethinker,
                  just the sort of rogue who would be promoting evolutionary, polygenetic and other
                  materialist speculations for subversive political ends in Scott’s day. Yet Sylvan,
                  conjured up by Agelastes’ denunciation of the Christian Satan, realizes a
                  euhemeristic demystification of that improbable demon, in keeping with the
                  demystification of the heathen satyr: he is himself the grotesque hybrid that
                  Agelastes ridicules. Scott reinscribes the heterodoxy that is ostensibly being
                  punished, in the form of a complicated joke. The orangutan may not be the
                  devil—all the same, the devil may be nothing more than an orangutan.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>V</head>
                  <p>Whenever he shows up in <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>, Sylvan provokes
                     strange textual disturbances. His intervention in the tale sets off figural
                     mutations and slippages which trace a lateral or retrograde motion—an
                     associative logic not of science, of an empirically verifiable scheme of cause
                     and effect, but of something like dreamwork, of metaphor and metamorphosis: a
                     logic of romance. Consider the Orang-Outang’s second irruption into the novel,
                     which leads to the recasting of Hereward, a soldier in the imperial guard, as a
                     “Forester,” a virtuous version of the “man of the woods.” A beautiful young
                     lady rushes onto the scene with the Orang-Outang in pursuit. After chasing him
                     away Hereward recognizes his long-lost love, Bertha, who recognizes Hereward in
                     turn by the scar of a boar’s tusk on his brow. We find ourselves rapt into a
                     suddenly intensified zone or atmosphere of romance, charged with allusions not
                     just to the <title level="m">Odyssey</title> but (as Simmons points out) to <title level="m">The
                        Faerie Queene</title>, in which the chivalrous forester Sir Satyrane defends
                     virgins from giants and wild men. “Have I but dreamed of that monstrous ogre?”
                     Bertha asks. Hereward’s reassurance, “That hideous thing exists,” gives the cue
                     for the recognition scene and—true to the Odyssean analogue—a retrograde
                     narrative plunge to his youthful encounter with another “hideous animal” or
                     “monster,” the wild boar (208). The recognition scene generates, in turn, the
                     back-story of the Foresters, the Saxon insurgents who “made a step backwards in
                     civilization” and returned to the woods.</p>
                  <p> The regressive, oneiric, metamorphic logic of romance is sustained most
                     powerfully in the <title level="m">outré</title> sequence, midway through the novel, in
                     which Sylvan makes his first appearance. On this occasion the orangutan closes
                     rather than initiates the series of figural mutations. Invited to dinner at the
                     imperial palace, Count Robert is startled by the ramping of the Emperor’s
                     mechanical lion. He smashes its skull with a blow of his fist—clockwork cogs
                     and springs litter the floor. After the banquet, Robert wakes up (he has been
                     drugged) to find himself in an underground dungeon, where he is menaced by a
                     tiger—a real tiger, this time, not a mechanical one. Once again he reacts by
                     smashing its skull. Scott’s description renders the tiger, despite its reality,
                     more like an effect in a magic-lantern show—“two balls of red light”—than a
                     flesh-and-blood animal: “he gazed eagerly around, but could discern nothing,
                     except two balls of red light which shone from the darkness with a self-emitted
                     brilliancy, like the eyes of a wild animal while it glares upon its prey”
                     (161). This apparition generates the voice of a fellow prisoner, invisible in
                     the darkness, who informs Robert that <title level="m">his</title> eyeballs have been put
                     out with red-hot irons. The mutilation of eyes or tongues (or, less explicitly,
                     genitals), in a metonymic chain of disfigurements that recurs across the novel,
                     marks the victim’s removal from fully human status. Deprived of the organs of
                     speech or vision, he is reduced to a mere body, to “bare life,” the condition
                     of a beast or slave. (The prisoner’s name, “Ursel,” also recalls “bear,” the
                     anthropomorphic beast of the woods that historically precedes the theriomorphic
                     man of the woods, the Enlightenment orangutan.) So at last the grotesque
                     semi-human captive, Sylvan, makes his appearance, babbling strange sounds
                     that—in the absence of his tribe—may or may not constitute a language.</p>
                  <p> What logic moves this strange narrative sequence, with its delirious
                     transitions and transformations, its cryptic series of antitheses? Mechanical
                     animal versus living animal; animal eyes without body versus a human body
                     without eyes; the man bereft of the endowment of humanity (vision) versus the
                     animal that possesses it (language). These symbolic oppositions recapitulate
                     the historical set of conjectures about the essential distinction between
                     humans and animals which informed the Enlightenment project of the “science of
                     man”: from the Cartesian account of the animal as machine, through the
                     empiricist abstraction of a vision-based cognition, to the Romantic investment
                     in language as the uniquely human property.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="19">See Thomas
                        30-41; Agamben 33-37. </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The set of conjectures resurfaces, recombined, near the end of the novel. The
                     captive Ursel turns out not to have been blinded after all. Released from
                     prison, high on a terrace overlooking the city, he experiences a return of
                     vision that is scarcely less traumatic than an actual blinding: <quote>His
                        eyeballs had been long untrained by that daily exercise, which teaches us
                        the habit of correcting the scenes as they appear to our sight, by our
                        actual knowledge of the truth as it exists in nature. His idea of distance
                        was so confused, that it seemed as if all the spires, turrets and minarets
                        which he beheld, were crowded forward upon his eyeballs, and almost touching
                        them. With a shriek of horror, Ursel turned himself to the further side[.]
                        (295)</quote> This particular instance of “retrograde evolution”—from
                     blindness to a sight that bears the violent effect of blindness—does not so
                     much look forward (for example, to the urban agoraphobia of the view from
                     Todgers’s in Dickens’s <title level="m">Martin Chuzzlewit</title>) as back: to the Platonic
                     allegory of enlightenment as emergence from a cave. Scott’s formulation however
                     is radically empiricist rather than platonic; it recalls the conjecture on the
                     reality of pigment with which the slave Diogenes taunts his interlocutors,
                     quoted earlier. If the operation of the senses is plastic rather than fixed,
                     subject to conditioning, neither is it the case that “our actual knowledge of
                     the truth as it exists in nature” precedes any sensory input. Cognition and
                     physical organization, rather, shape one another in a process of experimental
                     “correction.”</p>
                  <p>Shortly afterwards the narrator recurs to this moment, in the reaction of the
                     conspirator Nicephorus Briennius to the reversal of his plans: <quote>The
                        pardoned Caesar . . . found it as difficult to reconcile himself to the
                        reality of his situation as Ursel to the face of nature, after having been
                        long deprived of enjoying it; so much do the dizziness and confusion of
                        ideas, occasioned by moral and physical causes of surprise and terror,
                        resemble each other in their effects on the understanding. (322)</quote>
                     Nicephorus suffers what is more explicitly a narrative vertigo, as he discovers
                     himself to be a character in a plot when he had imagined himself to be the
                     author of it. His “dizziness and confusion” mirror the dizziness and confusion
                     that perturb readers of <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>. Only, as readers of
                     a novel, we are apt to experience that perturbation—the regression from a
                     conditioned blindness to a vision that is itself blinding—as sublime effects of
                     an aesthetic enjoyment, rather than as sensory distress.</p>
                  <p> Scott’s late romance does not attempt to pacify the turmoil afflicting the
                     “science of man” <emph>circa</emph> 1830 into any fixed knowledge. We are not
                     to look in these pages for a determination, even an allegorical one, of the
                     taxonomic status of man as a race or species. “In our culture,” writes Giorgio
                     Agamben, “man has always been thought of as the articulation and conjunction of
                     a body and soul, of a living thing and a <title level="m">logos</title>, of a natural (or
                     animal) element and a supernatural or social or divine element. We must learn
                     instead,” he adds, “to think of man as what results from the incongruity of
                     these two elements, and investigate not the metaphysical mystery of
                     conjunction, but rather the practical and political mystery of separation”
                     (16). Scott’s novel, through the techniques peculiar to fiction, begins that
                     work of disarticulation. The uncanny underground apparition of “two balls of
                     red light,” at once juxtaposed with and detached from the prisoner who believes
                     he has been blinded, constitutes the reflective core of <title level="m">Count Robert of
                        Paris </title>—the figure for vision, metonymically dislodged, as mark of the
                     reader’s gaze. Here, disoriented from a daylight logic of cause and effect,
                     flung deepest into a delirium of romantic adventure, we catch a glimpse of
                     ourselves: neither as human countenances nor organic bodies but as dislocated
                     perceptual fragments embedded in a meaning-generating apparatus, the literary
                     work. What we are seeing is the reflection of our own vision, bloodshot with
                     passionate amazement and with the sheer effort to see—reading in the dark.<note
                        place="foot" resp="editors" n="20">An early version of this essay was presented at the 2007
                        International Scott Conference; I thank Caroline Jackson-Houlston and the
                        community of Scott scholars for their feedback. For responses to later
                        drafts I thank Kevis Goodman, Maureen McLane, Matthew Ochiltree and Meg
                        Russett.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>
               <listBibl>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Agamben, Giorgio</author>
                        <title level="m">The Open: Man and Animal</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Attell, Kevin</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2004</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Alexander, J. H</author>
                        <title level="a">Essay on the Text</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Scott, Walter</author>
                        <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Alexander, J.H.</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Edinburgh University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">381-439</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Armstrong, Nancy</author>
                        <title level="m">How Novels Think: The Limits of British Individualism from
                           1700-1914</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Barnaby, Paul</author>
                        <title level="a">Another Tale of Old Mortality: The Translations of
                           Auguste-Jean-Baptiste Defauconpret in the French Reception of
                           Scott</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Pittock, Murray</editor>
                        <title level="m">The Reception of Sir Walter Scott in Europe</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Continuum</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">31-44</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Browne, Janet</author>
                        <title level="m">Charles Darwin: Voyaging</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1995</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Buffon, Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de</author>
                        <title level="m">Natural History, General and Particular, by the Count de Buffon: The History of Man and Quadrupeds</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Smellie, William</editor>
                        <edition>20 vols</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cadell and Davies</publisher>
                           <date>1812</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Burnett, James, Lord Monboddo</author>
                        <title level="m">Antient Metaphysics, Volume Third: Containing the History
                           and Philosophy of Men</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cadell</publisher>
                           <date>1784</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Burnett, James, Lord Monboddo</author>
                        <title level="m">Antient Metaphysics, Volume Fourth: Containing the History
                           of Man</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Bell &amp; Bradfute</publisher>
                           <publisher>Cadell</publisher>
                           <date>1795</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Burnett, James, Lord Monboddo</author>
                        <title level="m">Of the Origins and Progress of Language</title>
                        <edition>Second edition</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Balfour</publisher>
                           <publisher>Cadell</publisher>
                           <date>1774</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Casanova, Pascale</author>
                        <title level="m">The World Republic of Letters</title>
                        <editor role="translator">DeBevoise, M. B</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2004</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Christensen, Jerome</author>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism at the End of History</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2000</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Colley, Linda</author>
                        <title level="m">Britons: Forging the Nation, 1707-1837</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New Haven</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Yale University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1992</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Crawford, Robert</editor>
                        <title level="m">The Scottish Invention of English Literature</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1998</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Crawford, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">Devolving English Literature</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                           <date>1992</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Desmond, Adrian</author>
                        <title level="m">The Politics of Evolution: Morphology, Medicine and Reform
                           in Radical London</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                           <date>1989</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Duff, David</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Jones, Catherine</editor>
                        <title level="m">Scotland, Ireland, and the Romantic Aesthetic</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Lewisburg, PA</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Bucknell University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Duncan, Ian</author>
                        <title level="m">Scott&#8217;s Shadow: The Novel in Romantic
                           Edinburgh</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Ferris, Ina</author>
                        <title level="m">The Achievement of Literary Authority: Gender, History and
                           the Waverley Novels</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Ithaca</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cornell University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1991</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                 
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Fielding, Henry</author>
                        <title level="m">Tom Jones, the History of a Foundling</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Stern, Simon</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Bender, John</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford World&#8217;s Classics</publisher>
                           <date>1996</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Gamerschlag, Kurt</author>
                        <title level="a">The Making and Unmaking of Sir Walter Scott&#8217;s <title
                              level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Studies in Scottish Literature</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">15</biblScope>
                           <date>1980</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">95-123</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Gottlieb, Evan</author>
                        <title level="m">Feeling British: Sympathy and National Identity in Scottish
                           and English Writing, 1707-1832</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Lewisburg, PA</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Bucknell University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Hobsbaum, Philip</author>
                        <title level="a">Scott&#8217;s &#8216;Apoplectic&#8217; Novels</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Alexander, J.H</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Hewitt, David</editor>
                        <title level="m">Scott and his Influence</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Aberdeen</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Association for Scottish Literary Studies</publisher>
                           <date>1983</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">149-56</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Home, Henry (Lord Kames)</author>
                        <title level="m">Sketches of the History of Man</title>
                        <edition>Second edition</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Strahan, Cadell, Creech</publisher>
                           <date>1788</date>
                           <biblScope type="vol">4 vols</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Hume, David</author>
                        <title level="m">A Treatise of Human Nature</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Mossner, Ernest C.</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Harmondsworth</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Penguin</publisher>
                           <date>1984</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Jones, Catherine</author>
                        <title level="m">Literary Memory: Scott&#8217;s Waverley Novels and the
                           Psychology of Narrative</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Lewisburg, PA</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Bucknell University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2003</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Kitson, Peter J</author>
                        <title level="a">Coleridge and &#8216;the Ouran utang Hypothesis&#8217;:
                           Romantic Theories of Race</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Coleridge and the Science of Life</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Roe, Nicholas</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2001</date>
                           <biblScope>91-116</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Klancher, Jon</author>
                        <title level="a">Discriminations, or Romantic Cosmopolitanisms in
                           London</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Chandler, James</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Gilmartin, Kevin</editor>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Metropolis: The Urban Scene of British Culture,
                           1780-1840</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">65-82</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Lamarck, Jean Baptiste de</author>
                        <title level="m">Philosophie zoologique ou exposition des
                           consid&#233;rations relatives &#224; l'histoire naturelle des animaux,
                           &#224; la diversit&#233; de leur organisation et des facult&#233;s qu'ils
                           en obtiennent</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Dentu</publisher>
                           <date>1809</date>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2 vols</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Langan, Celeste</author>
                        <title level="a">Venice</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Metropolis: The Urban Scene of British Culture,
                           1780-1840</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Chandler, James</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Gilmartin, Kevin</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">261-69</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Lincoln, Andrew</author>
                        <title level="m">Walter Scott and Modernity</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Edinburgh University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Luk&#225;cs, Georg</author>
                        <title level="m">The Historical Novel</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Mitchell, Hannah</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Mitchell, Stanley</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
                           <date>1983</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Lyell, Charles</author>
                        <title level="m">Principles of Geology</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Secord, James A.</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Penguin</publisher>
                           <date>1997</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Mack, Douglas S</author>
                        <title level="m">Scottish Fiction and the British Empire</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Edinburgh University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Maxwell, Richard</author>
                        <title level="a">Scott in France</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Pittock, Murray</editor>
                        <title level="m">The Reception of Sir Walter Scott in Europe</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Continuum</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">11-30</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Maxwell, Richard</author>
                        <title level="m">The Historical Novel in Europe, 1650-1950</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2009</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>McCracken-Flesher, Caroline</author>
                        <title level="m">Possible Scotlands: Walter Scott and the Story of
                           Tomorrow</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>McGann, Jerome</author>
                        <title level="a">Walter Scott&#8217;s Romantic Postmodernity</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Scotland and the Borders of Romanticism</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Davis, Leith</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Duncan, Ian</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Sorensen, Janet</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2004</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">113-129</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>McLane, Maureen</author>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and the Human Sciences: Poetry, Population, and
                           the Discourse of the Species</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2000</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>McMaster, Graham</author>
                        <title level="m">Scott and Society</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1981</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>McNeil, Ken</author>
                        <title level="m">Scotland, Britain, Empire: Writing the Highlands,
                           1760-1860</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Columbus</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Ohio State University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Nairn, Tom</author>
                        <title level="m">The Break-Up of Britain: Crisis and Neo-Nationalism</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>New Left Books</publisher>
                           <date>1981</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Nash, Richard</author>
                        <title level="m">Wild Enlightenment: The Borders of Human Identity in the
                           Eighteenth Century</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Charlottesville</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Virginia Press</publisher>
                           <date>2003</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Newman, Gerald</author>
                        <title level="m">The Rise of English Nationalism: A Cultural History,
                           1740-1830</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>St. Martin&#8217;s</publisher>
                           <date>1987</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Pittock, Murray</author>
                        <title level="m">Scottish and Irish Romanticism</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Rudwick, Martin S</author>
                        <title level="m">Bursting the Limits of Time: The Reconstruction of
                           Geohistory in the Age of Revolution</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Scott, Walter</author>
                        <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Alexander, J.H</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Edinburgh University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Scott, Walter</author>
                        <title level="a">Frankenstein</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
                           <date>20 March/1 April 1818</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">613-620</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Scott, Walter</author>
                        <title level="m">Ivanhoe</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Duncan, Ian</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1996</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Scott, Walter</author>
                        <title level="m">Rob Roy</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Duncan, Ian</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1998</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Scott, Walter</author>
                        <title level="m">Waverley</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Garside, P.D</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Edinburgh University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Secord, James A</author>
                        <title level="a">Edinburgh Lamarckians: Robert Jameson and Robert E
                           Grant</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Journal of the History of Biology</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">24</biblScope>
                           <biblScope type="no">1</biblScope>
                           <date>1991</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">1-18</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Simmons, Clare</author>
                        <title level="a">A Man of Few Words: The Romantic Orang-Outang and
                           Scott&#8217;s <title level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Scottish Literary Journal</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">17</biblScope>
                           <biblScope type="no">1</biblScope>
                           <date>1990</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">21-34</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Stepan, Nancy</author>
                        <title level="m">The Idea of Race in Science: Great Britain,
                           1800-1960</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Macmillan</publisher>
                           <date>1982</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Sutherland, John</author>
                        <title level="m">The Life of Walter Scott: A Critical Biography</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Blackwell</publisher>
                           <date>1995</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Thomas, Keith</author>
                        <title level="m">Man and the Natural World: Changing Attitudes in England
                           1500-1800</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Penguin</publisher>
                           <date>1983</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Trumpener, Katie</author>
                        <title level="m">Bardic Nationalism: The Romantic Novel and the British
                           Empire</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1997</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Tyson, Edward</author>
                        <title level="m">Orang-Outang, sive Homo Sylvestrus: or, The Anatomy of a
                           Pygmy Compared with that of a Monkey, an Ape, and a Man</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Bennet and Brown</publisher>
                           <date>1699</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Wallace, Tara Ghoshal</author>
                        <title level="a">The Elephant&#8217;s Foot and the British Mouth: Walter
                           Scott on Imperial Rhetoric</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">European Romantic Review</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">13</biblScope>
                           <biblScope type="no">3</biblScope>
                           <date>2002</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">311-23</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Watt, James</author>
                        <title level="a">Scott, the Scottish Enlightenment, and Romantic
                           Orientalism</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Davis, Leith</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Duncan, Ian</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Sorensen, Janet</editor>
                        <title level="m">Scotland and the Borders of Romanticism</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2004</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">94-112</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Wickman, Matthew</author>
                        <title level="m">The Ruins of Experience: Scotland&#8217;s
                           &#8220;Romantick&#8221; Highlands and the Birth of the Modern
                           Witness</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
