<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Romantic Frictions</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">Introduction</title>
            <author>
               <name>Theresa M. Kelley</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">Theresa M. Kelley</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.kelley</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2010-11-01">March 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Introduction</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Theresa M.</forename>
                        <surname>Kelley</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Romantic Frictions:</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-03-01">March 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#226;&#8364;&#339;,"
                  for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>                         <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>                         <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>                         <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>                         <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2010-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay" n="1">
            <head>
               
               <title level="a">Introduction</title>
            </head>
            <byline>
               <docAuthor>Theresa M. Kelley</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
               <!-- <email>tkelley@wisc.edu</email> -->
            </byline>

            <p> The essays in this volume insist that irresolvable frictions mark Romanticism in its
               time and in our critical present. They do so by lingering with dubieties that fissure
               Romantic writing about its own historical moment and by insisting on surprising and
               difficult alignments between Romantic historiography and contemporary theory and
               philosophy. In doing so, these essays convey what it means to think about Romanticism
               in our present time. Beginning with <name ref="DuncanIan">Ian Duncan</name>’s reading
               of the problem of man and species in <name ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name>’s later
               fiction and the waning of the Scottish Enlightenment, the collection moves from
               writing committed to a nuanced grasp of the difficulties embedded in the relay
               between difficult histories and texts to writing as complexly committed to
               philosophical readings of Romanticism. Across this array of critical dispositions,
               these essays describe aspects of Romantic writing that render it both difficult and
               difficult to leave behind. </p>
            <p>In her meditation on the proximity or distance with which Romantics write about the
               “field of war,” <name ref="FavretMary">Mary Favret</name> recognizes a parallel
               impulse in the way contemporary scholars and theorists remove scholarly concepts from
               particular events and especially suffering. <name ref="O'QuinnDaniel">Daniel
                  O’Quinn</name> argues for a critical triangulation between the British loss of
               America, its assorted defeats and victories in India and the formal, aesthetic
               contours of poems about trees that evoke, or are made to evoke, national interests.
                  <name ref="RowlinsonMatthew">Matthew Rowlinson</name>’s double interrogation of
                  <name ref="ScottWalter">Walter Scott</name>’s anonymity as both a matter of
               authorship and financial credit argues that a Lacanian allegory of <name
                  ref="MarxKarl">Marx</name>’s Capital inhabits the folds of credit and debt in
                  <name ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name>’s financial rise and fall. <name
                  ref="JagerColin">Colin Jager</name> argues for a return to thinking about Romantic
               consciousness by way of recent cognitive theory concerning emergence, which supposes
               that the mind’s difference from and proximity to body and world can be postulated but
               not fully known. Reading contemporary philosophical writing about disaster and ruin
               beside <name ref="WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</name>’s poetry, <name
                  ref="KhalipJacques">Jacques Khalip</name> argues that <title level="m">The Ruined
                  Cottage</title> lingers with disaster in ways that urge a non-apocalyptic poetic
               turn toward the ordinary, barely sheltered conditions of living and dying. Considered
               together, these six essays insist on textual remainders of the stubborn frictions
               that mark Romanticism then and now. </p>
            <p> They do so in significant measure by turning away from an earlier, still influential
               critical supposition that thinking about historicism and thinking about theory are
               mutually exclusive operations. In too many conferences and not a few essays, this
               suspicion is sustained by looking past the frictions between things, events, cultures
               and theories that constitute Romanticism’s problematic sense of itself, hoping
               instead to see a Romanticism that does one thing or the other. <note place="foot"
                  n="1" resp="editors">
                  <name ref="ChaiLeon">Leon Chai</name> recapitulates the history of this critical
                  divide in <emph>Romantic Theory: Forms of Reflexivity in the Revolutionary
                     Era,</emph> 264-270. <name ref="ChaseCynthia">Cynthia Chase</name> presents a
                  brief, nuanced account of the divide in her “Introduction,”
                     <emph>Romanticism,</emph> 1-4, 31-35. <name ref="PfauThomas">Thomas Pfau</name>
                  argues for a philosophically oriented Romanticist criticism in “Reading beyond
                  Redemption: Historicism, Irony, and the Lessons of Romanticism,"<emph>The Lessons
                     of Romanticism</emph>, 1-37 and and in occasional bouts with historicist
                  critics in <emph>Romantic Moods,</emph> 337-39. Essays in <emph>Repossessing the
                     Romantic Past </emph>present the new historicist side of the divide. </note>
               The essays in this volume instead convey how these two aspects of Romanticism are,
               even in opposition, complexly bound to the problems and dubieties they inhabit. </p>
            <p>It is the claim of this introduction and collection that Romanticism is anything but
               schematically divided into round and square, and much more like a field of forces
               bent on fissuring and proliferating itself. This impulse works against the desire for
               a system that neatly bifurcates itself so that historicists might sit at one table
               and theorists at another, preferably in different rooms. I allude here to the
               cultural habits of scholarly conferences, but also to a wider impulse that would
               understand the interrogation of history as traduced by its inner empiricism and those
               of theory as traduced by a love of philosophy and concept that sorts ill with
               thinking about historiography. Both dispositions slight the traffic between history
               and philosophy or theory within Romantic writing; for that reason, they also miss a
               compelling way forward for contemporary writing about Romanticism.</p>
            <p>That way is through, not around, frictions between and within these perspectives.
               Precisely because it deals with material traits and efforts to manage distinctions,
               Romantic biological classification suggests how the friction between specimens,
               species traits and higher taxa kept distinctions in play even as nineteenth-century
               taxonomists sought to order them into a fixed system. In the end, taxonomists could
               not settle on one system to explain all possible relationships among natural kinds
               not so much because the ongoing discovery of biological plentitude outpaced efforts
               to classify them (taxonomists were and still are tireless), but because that
               plenitude could not be mapped adequately by a single systematic. <name
                  ref="DarwinCharles">Charles Darwin</name>’s definition of <emph>species</emph> as
               whatever his fellow biologists agreed was a species registers both the problem of
               biological classification and his diplomatic non-solution, inasmuch as many of his
               contemporaries could not agree on what the term <emph>species</emph> meant or even on
               whether it was a viable concept.<note place="foot" n="2" resp="editors">
                  <name ref="DarwinCharles">Darwin</name>, <emph>Origin of Species</emph>, 38.
               </note> A century after Linnaeus, the effort to create a fixed system of stable
               species and kingdoms of nature had met its other, a spirit of differentiation that
               could imagine, like James Hutton’s theory of the earth, no prospect of an end. </p>
            <p>As a principle of botanical investigation that goes back to Aristotle and Cesalpino,
               differentiation is the centrifugal engine working inside taxonomic inquiry. Nearly as
               soon as the Linnaean system was more or less accepted in the second half of the
               eighteenth century as standard practice for botanical taxonomy, taxonomists began to
               devise what Antoine de Jussieu and his successors called the “Natural System.” In all
               its incarnations prior to <name ref="DarwinCharles">Darwin</name>’s <title level="m"
                  >Origin of Species</title>, the Natural System recognized multiple affinities
               among plant characters or traits such that there might be both a primary taxonomic
               home based on one structural similarity and many more affine relationships that might
               well cut across recognized species, families and even genera, as the ascending plant
               orders were then described. </p>
            <p>Although Jussieu and others believed that the Natural System would eventually, when
               complete, record a continuous series of creation, the work of differentiation
               produced more species, subspecies, varieties in one direction and more families and
               genera and orders, even multiple plant kingdoms, in another, and all within the
               domain of what we have called the Romantic view of nature, a phrase that says nothing
               about the complexity of that nature, taking comfort instead in a sentimentalizing
               category that asks little of us and less about how Romantics thought about what
               nature might include. A-P. de Candolle, the Swiss taxonomist who consolidated the
               Natural System, concluded that Nature is not a continuous series but rather that
               there are leaps or gaps in nature that taxonomy cannot bridge. De Candolle’s
               recognition makes taxonomic differentiation a grounding principle instead of an
               unwelcome outsider. In his study of the history of plant systematics in the
               nineteenth century, Peter Stevens includes some of the cognitive maps or schematics
               which taxonomists devised to represent, or try to represent, different and at times
               competing taxonomic relationships. None of them worked. If finding one that worked
               forever were really the only game in town, the history of systematics right up to
               present work in evolutionary and then cladistic analysis would seem pointless. In
               recent decades the kingdoms of nature have divided yet again, to accommodate
               plant-like groups that now appear to be something else and to belong somewhere else,
               in a kingdom of their own that is neither plant nor animal. </p>
            <p> What this history of biological systematics conveys is the logical and conceptual
               necessity for an ongoing friction, admittedly provisional and probably impermanent,
               between local, material evidence and competing schematics for their meaning. Whether
               or not any single systematic will suffice is less important than what each finds and
               tries to gather up into a conceptual frame that is adequate to the array of
               differences it tries to gather together. The work of finding and mapping,
               conceptualizing the relationships among singularities or differences always turns up
               something to be worked at, debated, and by such means kept on the table, not shunted
               off into a corner where it cannot cause trouble, where its difference becomes or is
               claimed to be monstrous. Indeed, the taxonomic inquiry that paid close attention to
               so-called botanical monsters did so because their very difference suggested a
               mechanism or operation otherwise hidden and thus in need of attention. </p>
            <p> The parable suggested by the cascading array of frictions among natural kinds and
               human systematic for thinking about Romanticism is perhaps obvious, but so much the
               better. Attention to the on-going work of differentiation leads to friction, constant
               friction, between objects of inquiry and the structures used to map those objects.
               Competing systematics are all the better because they fight for what should be
               counted or not. The ensuing friction is good for heat and perhaps some light. Even so
               for the friction between those who emphasize Romanticism’s cultural historiography
               and those who emphasize its philosophy, literature and aesthetics. In one sense, this
               divide splits Romantic writing in remarkably artificial ways, choosing to ignore the
               degree to that body of writing persistently worked across these terrains. But in
               another sense, this disciplinary divide unfolds and expands a deeper set of frictions
               within Romanticism, and within our critical understanding of what this term and era
               entail, between the historical and the local and the abstract or philosophical. What
               rightly emerges from these frictions is a sharp reminder that efforts to read
               Romanticism as a smoothly articulated, undifferentiated field or period have often
               and quite rightly found it difficult, even rough going. </p>
            <p> For <name ref="DerridaJacques">Jacques Derrida</name>, <name ref="deManPaul">Paul De
                  Man</name> and <name ref="LyotardJean-François">Jean Lyotard</name>,
                  <emph>différance</emph> gathers to itself the work of friction by preserving
               notice of the singularity of persons and events that disrupts systematic,
               generalizing projects. For de Man, difference is the work figures do to undo unitary
               reading and meaning. For <name ref="DerridaJacques">Derrida</name>, difference
               prompts the philosophical demand to unsettle claims to absolute knowledge. The
               political and institutional force of this project is, as <name
                  ref="LyotardJean-François">Jean François Lyotard</name> has argued, apparent when
               one considers who or what might be said to be just. <note place="foot" n="3"
                  resp="editors"><name ref="DerridaJacques">Derrida</name>, <title level="m">Of
                     Grammatology, </title>and “Force of Law: The ‘Mystical Foundation of
                  Authority’,” <title level="m">Deconstruction and the Possibility of
                     Justice</title>, 3-67; de Man, “Rhetoric of Tropes,” <title level="m"
                     >Allegories of Reading</title> , 103-18; <name ref="LyotardJean-François"
                     >Lyotard</name>, <title level="m">The Differend</title> and <name
                     ref="CurtisNeal">Neal Curtis</name>, <title level="m">Against Autonomy: <name
                        ref="LyotardJean-François">Lyotard</name>, Judgement and
                  Action</title>.</note>
               <name ref="PlotnitskyArkady">Arkady Plotnitsky</name> observes that singularity,
               chance, and contingency trouble the effort to create a system or concept that would
               subsume differences. <note place="foot" n="4" resp="editors"><name
                     ref="PlotnitskyArkady">Plotnitsky</name>, “Difference,” <title level="m"
                     >Glossalalia</title>, 51-74. “Singularity” has become a watchword in its own
                  right. See <name ref="ClarkTimothy">Timothy Clark</name>, <title level="m">The
                     Poetics of Singularity</title> and <name ref="AttridgeDerek">Derek
                     Attridge</name>, <title level="m">The Singularity of Literature</title>.</note>
            </p>
            <p><name ref="NancyJean-Luc">Jean-Luc Nancy</name> emphasizes the difficulty that haunts
               efforts to preserve singularity as a concept. In <title level="m">The Inoperable
                  Community</title> he distinguishes, after <name ref="HegelGeorgWilhelmFriedrich"
                  >Hegel</name> and via <name ref="HegelGeorgWilhelmFriedrich">Hegel</name> after
                  <name ref="GoetheJohannWolfgangvon">Goethe</name>, the individual from
               singularity: whereas the individual, like the annual plant that is the subject of
                  <name ref="GoetheJohannWolfgangvon">Goethe</name>’s <title level="m">Metamorphoses
                  of Plants</title>, dies, what is singular remains so in part because its identity
               is secured by its antithetical yet also implicated relation to community, which <name
                  ref="NancyJean-Luc">Nancy</name> characterizes as the “socially exposed
               particularity” that <name ref="MarxKarl">Marx</name> sought to preserve against the
               “socially imploded generality” that Capitalism uses to put singularity in its place.
                  <note place="foot" n="5" resp="editors"><name ref="NancyJean-Luc">Nancy</name>,
                     <title level="m">The Inoperative Community</title>, 59; <name
                     ref="GoetheJohannWolfgangvon">Goethe</name>, <title level="m">Metamorphosen der
                     Pflanzen</title>. <name ref="RajanTilottama">Tilottama Rajan</name> examines
                  the philosophical itinerary of singularity from <name
                     ref="HegelGeorgWilhelmFriedrich">Hegel</name> to <name ref="NancyJean-Luc"
                     >Nancy</name> in "System and Singularity From Herder to Hegel," <title
                     level="j">European Romantic Review</title> , 137-49; "Dis-Figuring
                  Reproduction: Natural History, Community, and the 1790s Novel," <title level="j"
                     >The New Centennial Review,</title>: 211-52; and "The Unavowable Community of
                  Idealism: Coleridge and the Life Sciences," <title level="j">European Romantic
                     Review,</title> 395-416.</note> The philosophical problem of aligning
               singularity with community is suggested by <name ref="NancyJean-Luc">Nancy</name>’s
               return to this topic in <title level="m">The Sense of the World,</title> where
               singularity or “one” means necessarily “some ones <emph>and</emph> some others, or
               some ones with other ones.” To claim, as <name ref="NancyJean-Luc">Nancy</name> then
               does, that what mediates between singularity and community is a “transcendent
               curiosity” <note place="foot" n="6" resp="editors"><name ref="NancyJean-Luc"
                     >Nancy</name>, <title level="m">The Sense of the World</title>, 71 and
                  73.</note> on either side seems at once profoundly attractive and Romantic. It too
               is also a philosophical move that consolidates and categorizes what is singular. </p>
            <p>The task of thinking about Romanticism as an historical moment urges resistance to
               this move. In foregrounding the “irreducible inequality” of difference in the
               sensible world, <name ref="DeleuzeGilles">Gilles Deleuze</name> indicates how the
               resistant logic of historical or cultural difference might derive from the
               phenomenal, event-ridden domain of Romantic history. His remark that “everything
               bathes in its difference” <note place="foot" n="7" resp="editors"><name
                     ref="DeleuzeGilles">Deleuze</name>, <title level="m">Difference and
                     Repetition</title>, 222 and 243.</note> conveys what Romantics experienced, a
               world in which friction, not unity or closure, was the work at hand. The rub of
               difference is at work in the global theater of race and variety; in the politics and
               economics of scarcity during a time of war <note place="foot" n="8" resp="editors"
                     ><name ref="FavretMary">Mary Favret</name>, “War in the Air,” <title level="j"
                     >MLQ,</title> 531-59. </note> ; in debates about whose religion or gender or
               race qualifies individuals to be counted as persons or members of a body politic; and
               in scientific, philosophical and literary efforts to resist, accommodate, mark or
               eradicate such differences. </p>
            <p>Despite Romantic and post-Romantic efforts, then, to posit the unity of the one life,
               as Samuel Coleridge argued one night in 1797, singularity and difference, whether
               found in rocky outcroppings, <note place="foot" n="9" resp="editors"><name
                     ref="StaffordBarbara">Barbara Stafford</name>, <title level="m">Voyage into
                     Substance: Art, Science, Nature and the Illustrated Travel Account
                     1760-1840.</title>
               </note> plant species or recalcitrant human individuals, articulate the eruptive,
               discontinuous temporality of event and aesthetic response with which Romanticism
               works against the grain of a Burkean system of inheritance that imagines itself
               governing history and its remains. From this perspective, to provide one example, it
               becomes easier to notice how <name ref="ScottWalter">Walter Scott</name>’s <title
                  level="m">Waverley</title> retrospectively tracks fissures in the 1707 Union of
               Scotland and England in ways that do not constitute fictional corroboration of that
               political union as accomplished without remainder. <note place="foot" n="10"
                  resp="editors">On <name ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name>, compare <name
                     ref="TrumpenerKatie">Katie Trumpener</name>, <title level="m">Bardic
                     Nationalism</title> with <name ref="DuncanIan">Ian Duncan</name>, “Hume, <name
                     ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name> and the ‘Rise of Fiction’,” <title level="j"
                     >Angles on the English-Speaking World,</title> 63-76 and “Authenticity Effects:
                  The Work of Fiction in Romantic Scotland,” <title level="j">SAQ,</title>
                  93-116.</note>
            </p>
            <p> If Romantic forms, including Coleridge’s, are as often ruins as not, as Thomas <name
                  ref="McFarlandThomas">McFarland</name> argued, <note place="foot" n="11"
                  resp="editors"><name ref="McFarlandThomas">McFarland</name>, <title level="m"
                     >Romanticism and the Forms of Ruin </title>and <name ref="WolfsonSusan">Susan
                     Wolfson</name>, “Reading for Form,” <title level="j">MLQ</title>. </note> such
               formal difficulties specify the enabling rhythm of Romantic writing, a rhythm
               articulated in the midst of a jostling of events and an inclination toward dissent
               that no writer or philosopher of the age could quell. The view of Romanticism
               entailed by framing its event and discourse horizons as marked by difference
               evidently responds to a long-standing debate about what Romanticism is or was.
               Looking back on that debate in the early 1990’s, <name ref="ParkerMark">Mark
                  Parker</name> remarked, “perhaps we have come to a place where an ironic
               counterhistory of Romanticism, one less intent on closure, one more alive to the
               accidents and contingencies of descent, as at once possible and necessary.”<hi
                  rend="sup">
                  <note place="foot" n="12" resp="editors"><name ref="ParkerMark">Mark
                     Parker</name>, “Measure and Countermeasure: The Lovejoy-Wellek Debate and
                     Romantic Periodization,” in <title level="m">Theoretical Issues in Literary
                        History</title>, ed. David Perkins, 247. </note>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p> Although the debate about whether Romanticism exists or whether it is not one but
               many typically concludes by not concluding as critics speak for, against or somewhere
               in the middle of this question, its persistence is instructive. In separate
               assessments, <name ref="ParkerMark">Parker</name> and Thomas Vogler note the stubborn
               resistance that the debate about what Romanticism is (or whether it exists) presents
               to fixed chronologies and conceptual boundaries. They also note the equally stubborn
               critical desire to recognize Romanticism as a viable category and event. From A. O.
               Lovejoy and René Wellek, who began this twentieth-century debate, to critics in the
               near present, Romanticism either names a category that is convenient, perhaps even
               valuable, or it registers the impossibility of such a category and period
               designation. </p>
            <p> As the disputed middle of this long debate, Romanticism names a conceptual and
               historical manifold that repays critical attention less for its sureties that for its
               inner resistance to coherence. As a period or event horizon, it is not defined by a
               single leading indicator like the French Revolution (although this event evidently
               does matter, in manifold directions), <note place="foot" n="13" resp="editors"><name
                     ref="BrownMarshall">Marshall Brown</name>, “Romanticism and Enlightenment,”
                     <title level="m">The Cambridge Companion to Romanticism</title>, ed. Stuart
                  Curran, 44-47. Essays in <title level="m">The Age of Cultural Revolutions: Britain
                     and France, 1750-1820</title>, ed. <name ref="JonesColin">Colin Jones</name>
                  and <name ref="WahrmanDror">Dror Wahrman</name>, argue that the idea of revolution
                  requires a longer and broader trajectory. See, for instance, the editors’
                  “Introduction: An Age of Cultural Revolutions?,” 1-16 and <name
                     ref="ChandlerJames">James K. Chandler</name>, “Moving Accidents: The Emergence
                  of Sentimental Probability,” 137-170. </note> but by the jostling presence of many
               temporalities, different levels of momentum, and different moments of intensity. In
               one direction, which its writers certainly promoted, Romanticism enters a new era,
               one characterized for a time by the prospect of freedom as the projected ground of
               poetic imagination and Romantic prophecy. <note place="foot" n="14" resp="editors"
                     ><name ref="BalfourIan">Ian Balfour</name>, <title level="m">The Rhetoric of
                     Romantic Prophecy</title>.</note> Reading this era as a “hot chronology”—<name
                  ref="Lévi-StraussClaude">Claude Lévi-Strauss</name>’s term for those cultures that
               appear at certain moments to develop more quickly than others—<name
                  ref="ChandlerJames">James Chandler</name> evokes both to the Romantic sense that
               time and events had speeded up and to the modern critical desire to read Romanticism
               as hurrying toward the future it imagined. <note place="foot" n="15" resp="editors"
                  >In <title level="m">The Savage Mind </title><name ref="Lévi-StraussClaude"
                     >Lévi-Strauss</name> argues that there exists an “uneven development” among
                  societies such that some exhibit “hot chronologies” while others do not, 259.
                  Although he is wary of the primitive /civilized subplot of <name
                     ref="Lévi-StraussClaude">Lévi-Strauss</name>’s phrase, in <title level="m"
                     >England in 1819 </title><name ref="ChandlerJames">James Chandler</name> uses
                  it to characterize Romantic writers’ sense of the quickened pace of their era,
                  68-69. <name ref="KoselleckReinhart">Reinhart Koselleck</name> emphasized the
                  broad European conviction that the French Revolution introduced an “accelerated
                  tempo which seemed to open up a new and different age” in <title level="m">Futures
                     Past: On the Semantics of Historical Time</title>, 59. </note> Yet <name
                  ref="Lévi-StraussClaude">Lévi-Strauss</name>’s phrase invokes more than a hint of
               a progressive, evolutionary bias in which a neo-<name
                  ref="HegelGeorgWilhelmFriedrich">Hegel</name>ian march of world and spirit moves
               forward, away from the “cold” chronology of primitive cultures and “the savage mind.”
               Such a view ignores too easily the extent to which Romanticism’s global interests
               permeated other cultures and sustained a retrograde preference for slavery for some,
               even in the midst of imagining freedom for all. That this was so Romantics were well
               aware. Centrifugal pressures that challenged the myth of a consolidated Britain
               during the era reveal how fragile and how fractured the era also looked to those who
               lived it. <note place="foot" n="16" resp="editors"><name ref="NairnTom">Tom
                     Nairn</name>, <title level="m">The Break-Up of Britain: Crisis and
                     Neo-nationalism, </title>86; <name ref="DuncanIan">Ian Duncan</name>,
                  “Primitive Inventions: <title level="m">Rob Roy</title>, Nation, and World
                  System,” <title level="j">Eighteenth-Century Fiction</title>, 82 and “Authenticity
                  Effects,” 103. </note>
            </p>
            <p> As a category, a moment, and a matrix of ideas and contentions, Romanticism suggests
               how we might think about periodization without putting aside the need to historicize
               in precisely the differential manner conveyed by the echo of <name
                  ref="JamesonFredric">Fredric Jameson</name>’s dictum “always historicize.”<hi
                  rend="sup">
                  <note place="foot" n="17" resp="editors"><name ref="JamesonFredric"
                     >Jameson</name>, <title level="m">The Political Unconscious,</title> 9.</note>
               </hi> As a culture and discourse that stretch across these extremes, Romanticism may
               well be what it looks like—an era under construction and inhabited by transient
               figures who cannot locate themselves at home or even in those putatively houseless
               woods near Tintern Abbey. In this Romanticism, singularity and contingency belong to
               the concept they animate and yet, as <name ref="HegelGeorgWilhelmFriedrich"
                  >Hegel</name> and <name ref="DerridaJacques">Derrida</name> differently
               acknowledged, <note place="foot" n="18" resp="editors"><name ref="GaschéRodolphe"
                     >Rodolphe Gasché</name>, <title level="m">Inventions of Difference,</title>
                  171-98.</note> these traits also make the concept, here Romanticism, tremble from
               within. This, rather than a posited conceptual stability, is the event horizon of
               Romantic history and philosophy. Even <name ref="HegelGeorgWilhelmFriedrich"
                  >Hegel</name>, who argued for a Romantic moment and spirit that could resolve
               earlier historical and philosophical shortcomings, found himself confronting a time
               whose “instability, …tearing, [and] passage,” as <name ref="NancyJean-Luc">Jean-Luc
                  Nancy</name> puts it, is the strange fundament of history. <note place="end"
                  n="19"><name ref="NancyJean-Luc">Nancy</name>, <title level="m"><name
                        ref="HegelGeorgWilhelmFriedrich">Hegel</name></title>, 27. </note>
            </p>
            <p> If Romanticism is marked by frictions among competing definitions all the way down,
               as <name ref="LovejoyArthurO">A. O. Lovejoy</name>’s frustrated account of the
               discrimination of Romanticisms implied, those frictions, along with those among
               readers and critics, need to be on the table. Romantic writing and culture is shot
               through with local and material, literary and cultural frictions that anticipate its
               modern critical identity, pungently declared in <name ref="RancièreJacques">Jacques
                  Rancière</name>’s study of what he calls “<emph>mésentente</emph>,” usually
               translated as “disagreement,” but closer in spirit to an idea of fundamental discord,
               arising from different grounds and premises. <name ref="RancièreJacques"
                  >Rancière</name> argues that to think about justice and the aesthetics of
               politics, we must first grant the irreconciliability of certain arguments, no matter
               how much we may hope or image their congruence. Under the sign of
                  <emph>mésentente</emph>, Romanticism might be characterized as an historical
               moment when singularity, chance, and contingency become the work of the day. This
               claim is not a staging ground for an easy settling into commonality; it argues
               instead for recognizing that friction is always about several, discordant
               possibilities. The cultural and political frictions that <name ref="TsingAnna">Anna
                  Tsing</name> describes among inhabitants, national programs and global capitalism
               in modern Indonesia takes another shape in the Romantic era, when revolution, war,
               and imperial advance prompted occasions for thinking about as well as trying to
               ignore fundamental disputes. <note place="foot" n="20" resp="editors"><name
                     ref="RancièreJacques">Jacques Rancière</name>, <title level="m">La Mésentente:
                     Politique et Philosophe; </title>English translation, <title level="m"
                     >Dis-agreement: politics and philosophy</title>, trans. Julie Rose; <name
                     ref="TsingAnna">Anna Lowenhaupt Tsing</name>, <title level="m"
                     >Friction.</title>
               </note> Kept in play instead of pushed off to the side, friction and irresolvable
               disagreement remind us that relationships among singularities or differences always
               turn up something to be worked at, debated, and by such means kept on the table, not
               shunted off into a corner where it cannot cause trouble, or dismissed as something
               monstrous and thus categorically inadmissable. </p>
            
            <p>Viewed this way, Romanticism specifies competing refractions of time and event within
               or inside its pulsating chronology(ies). What counts as Romanticism is not who gets
               there first or last, or even who or what goes in reverse or forward, but the way that
               its differences jostle for attention. That said, the frictions that mark out the
               space of Romanticism suggest that its nature or definition has more flow than edge.
               This apparent weakness offers a surprising advantage: it transforms a persistent
               feature of Romanticism—its holding together of extremes like those <name
                  ref="BlakeWilliam">Blake</name> imagines as contraries, or extremes of scale in
               Romantic visual representation, or the polarities that separate <name
                  ref="BurkeEdmund">Burke</name>’s political assumptions from <name
                  ref="PaineThomas">Paine</name>’s—into tensile strength. Paradoxically,
               Romanticism becomes more flexible and commanding as a category to the degree that it
               does not expend itself in an effort to seal its borders. The essays in this volume
               insist on what this Romanticism looks like, in its time and in our critical moment. </p>
            <p> In the first essay <name ref="DuncanIan">Ian Duncan</name> addresses the
               instabilities of Romantic and Enlightenment classifications of the species of man in
               a reading of <name ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name>’s penultimate novel, <title
                  level="m">Count Robert of Paris</title>, as a work that thoroughly overturns
               Romanticism’s sense of its futurity as well as its past. Whereas <title level="m"
                  >Waverley</title>, the first of the Waverley novels, could be read to argue for
               the shared national histories of Scotland and England, an outcome shadowed but not
               undone by its internal ironies, not the least of them concerning the heroic status of
               its reckless English hero, <title level="m">Count Robert</title> raises many more
               questions than <title level="m">Waverley</title> had put in abeyance, beginning with
               “man,” the biological category the later novel leaves in shreds, even as it undoes
               most of the traits that <name ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name> is said to have
               established for the historical novel. Reaching back to a time and a place
               (Constantinople at the close of the eleventh century) that are at once too far off
               from Scotland and so Byzantine in style and manner that critics have suggested <name
                  ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name> was slipping even as he wrote the novel that he
               (mistakenly) believed would be his last, <title level="m">Count Robert</title>
               replies, and puts an end to the great project of the Scottish Enlightenment, the
               science of man. A novel uncertain of its own genre or species, and rife with species
               that put the solidity and superiority of that of “man” in question, <title level="m"
                  >Count Robert</title> looks backwards in ways that challenge Romantic hopes for
               the future. This eastern metropolis presents a hodgepodge of species and nations
               that make different claims on the idea of man, none more so that the Ourang-Utan
               Silvan, who speaks a dialect all its own and understands Anglo-Saxon. In the bloated
               world space and anarchically polygenetic array of peoples and species of <name
                  ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name>’s fictionalized Constantinople, Romantic hopes for
               historical progress stumble on the limitations of their own view of racial and
               species difference. As the logic of the historical novel shifts in <name
                  ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name>’s most phantasmagoric fiction, knights imagine
               retrograde motions that bizarrely undo the forward momentum of Crusade campaigns.
                  <name ref="DuncanIan">Duncan</name>’s account of the worlds <name
                  ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name> evokes in <title level="m">Count Robert</title>
               insists on instabilities within the historiographic projections of the Scottish
               Enlightenment that turn essentially on problems with the category of man signaled by
               Lord Kames’s notice of the species of men and pursued by Lamarck. </p>
            <p>
               <name ref="FavretMary">Mary Favret</name>‘s essay takes up the phrases “field of
               history” and “field of battle” to consider the metaphoric slide from event and
               persons to concept and figure that each phrase imagines or seeks. Whereas Scottish
               Enlightenment historiography had supposed that writing about war required the distant
               perspective conveyed by understanding and describing battles as scenes on the field
               of history, the relative safety of such metaphors seemed by the end of the eighteenth
               century, a time of near constant warfare for England and its allies, as <name
                  ref="FavretMary">Favret</name> puts it, little more than “wishful thinking” or
               worse, insofar as its call for dispassionate observation suggested that blood and
               suffering seen at close range were not the stuff of which history is made. <name
                  ref="FavretMary">Favret</name> uses this friction between distance and metaphors
               that preserve that distance and what war looks like up close to query contemporary
               theory and criticism, beginning with Michel Foucault’s argument that history and
               historiography are war. For although Foucault insists that these terms should not
               become just figures, they nonetheless do as Foucault’s use of them slides toward
               intellection, away from the experience of war or, for that matter, of history.
               Recognizing the importance of <name ref="KoselleckReinhart">Reinhardt
                  Koselleck</name>’s notice of the incompatibility between history at the micro
               level—that is all that happens in fine grain detail or however much of it we can
               capture—and the macro level—which tells grander, concept driven stories about fields
               of history—<name ref="FavretMary">Favret</name> argues that thinking about
               Romanticism historiographically frequently risks or assumes the status of a
               macrohistory by taking up the dispassionate and distant vantage point on “details”
               for which theory speaks. <name ref="BarbauldAnnaLaetitia">Anna L. Barbauld</name>,
                  <name ref="FavretMary">Favret</name> observes, reverses this tendency in “Dialogue
               in the Shades,” charging History with reckoning and limiting what happens to the
               mortal body. Barbauld’s refusal of dispassionate distance and the kind of history
               writing that occurs at a distance specifies an enduring friction within Romantic
               historiography and contemporary criticism between concept and event, human lives and
               grand designs. </p>
            <p>
               <name ref="O'QuinnDaniel">Daniel O’Quinn</name> assesses the figural connection
               between distinct but uncomfortably intertwined British war zones: the Mysore state of
               India in the decades when the East India Company’s military forces repeatedly battled
               Tipu Sultan for control of lower India and North America, where British military
               forces spectacularly failed to manage the colonies. <name ref="O'QuinnDaniel"
                  >O’Quinn</name> argues that half a globe away from each other, America and Asia
               constitute a cultural and historical imaginary for the British, who use triumphs in
               one arena to forget defeats in the other. This curious triangulation moves in this
               essay by way of figure and specifically figures of trees, Cowper’s destroyed British
               oak versus the Indian Banyan tree which William Hodges reimagines in <title level="m"
                  >Travels in India</title> not as the symbol of Indian monstrous proliferation, but
               as one protected by the British army, whose troops are sheltered there and shelter
               others. The difference between the way Hodges wishes to read the banyan and earlier
               readings that identified its proliferation of trunks with a suspect sexuality
               constitute, argues <name ref="O'QuinnDaniel">O’Quinn</name>, a crisis in
               representation. For although Hodges’s banyan redirects this earlier iconography to
               claim the banyan as a proleptic figure for the spread of Company rule well before the
               East India Company had fully consolidated its power in the region, that argument also
               exposes the “wishful thinking” or self-delusion that C. A. Bayly has identified as a
               crucial element of British governance prior to and during the imposition of the
               Permanent Settlement. <name ref="O'QuinnDaniel">O’Quinn</name> reads both Cowper’s
               Oak and Hodges’s Banyan as figures whose ironies register the give and take (one
               battle won here, another lost there) of British nationalist identity and imperial
               desire. This “global historic dynamic” requires reading across both the
               geographic and cultural terrains each figures. Romantic historiography by way of
               figure here makes visible and linked arguments that might otherwise appear to be
               isolated claims about America or India under British eyes. Whereas both <name
                  ref="FavretMary">Favret</name> and <name ref="O'QuinnDaniel">O’Quinn</name> are
               concerned with what figures do, <name ref="O'QuinnDaniel">O’Quinn</name> contends
               that some figures reveal a larger cultural imaginary than one might otherwise
               glimpse. </p>
            <p><name ref="RowlinsonMatthew">Matthew Rowlinson</name>’s argument about <name
                  ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name>’s fiction, anonymity and capital takes up an
               intriguing middle ground in the collection. <name ref="RowlinsonMatthew"
                  >Rowlinson</name> offers on an astute and detailed understanding of how <name
                  ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name> relied on Scots systems of credit and finance that
               required the anonymity of authorship that he famously insisted on and played with,
               like money in the bank. <name ref="RowlinsonMatthew">Rowlinson</name> reads the
               uncertainty about what is and what is not money in <name ref="ScottWalter"
                  >Scott</name>’s <title level="m">Antiquary</title> as one instance of a problem of
               textual boundary that recurs in the Waverley novels, with their serial form,
               indistinguishable protagonists, and the extensive textual periphery of introductions,
               prefaces, notes and other apparatus. By such turns, <name ref="ScottWalter"
                  >Scott</name>’s fictional voices create the simulacrum of capital in ways that
               anticipate the role of Capital in <name ref="MarxKarl">Marx</name>’s analysis as a
               Lacanian marker for the real in a symbolic order. Yet the point of <name
                  ref="RowlinsonMatthew">Rowlinson</name>’s essay is not simply that <name
                  ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name> anticipates <name ref="MarxKarl">Marx</name>, but
               rather that its riveting historiographic evidence discloses a deeply economic
               rationale for <name ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name>’s mystic and permutable anonymity
               and, further, that this highly fictive circulation of identities conveys the
               allegorical character of <name ref="MarxKarl">Marx</name>’s Capital and the author
               “Walter Scott” among his various fictive voices, frequently leaked identities. Moving
               between <name ref="ScottWalter">Scott</name>’s publishing history, Scottish finance,
                  <name ref="MarxKarl">Marx</name>, Lacan, and back, <name ref="RowlinsonMatthew"
                  >Rowlinson</name> tracks the work of allegory and credit such that the distinction
               between historiography and theory remains, but their conjoined work becomes more
               telling.</p>
            <p>
               <name ref="JagerColin">Colin Jager</name> takes up the question of Romantic
               consciousness, an inquiry that recent work on Romanticism has either put aside or
               taken up in ways that he contends are less productive than they might be. Much of the
               essay considers developments in cognitive theory that literary scholars of
               Romanticism have only partly begun to read. He identifies two recent approaches to
               consciousness: neurological arguments which regard mind as a synonym for the brain
               and emergence theory, which has a longer track record (stretching back to the
               nineteenth century) but does not claim to answer the “hard question” of cognition,
               how mind is related to world or more precisely how we can physically know that the
               mind has consciousness. Using examples that recur in recent accounts of emergence and
               cognition, <name ref="JagerColin">Jager</name> notes that although neither bees nor
               ants possess consciousness, a bee-hive or an ant colony could be said to demonstrate
               the kinds of collective and individual organization we might understand as necessary
               activities from which consciousness would emerge. Lower-level self-organizing and
               self-modifying systems such as <name ref="GoetheJohannWolfgangvon">Goethe</name>
               found in plant development and many other Romantic writers found in different animals
               and insects would constitute, then, physical evidence of activities from which
               consciousness might emerge. What is arresting about this argument, <name
                  ref="JagerColin">Jager</name> emphasizes, is its tentativeness, its capacity to
               rest, as Keats urged, in doubt and uncertainty. This attitude, <name ref="JagerColin"
                  >Jager</name> suggests, recalls too <name ref="WordsworthWilliam"
                  >Wordsworth</name>’s “natural piety,” a phrase <name ref="FrançoisAnne-Lise"
                  >Anne-Lise François</name> uses to imagine a Romantic environmentalist ethic
               poised to stand back and think about what might emerge in us that is, however
               indistinctly or problematically, from nature.<note place="foot" n="21" resp="editors"
                     ><name ref="FrançoisAnne-Lise">François</name>, "’O Happy Living Things’:
                  Frankenfoods and the Bounds of <name ref="WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</name>ian
                  Natural Piety,” 42-70.</note>
               <name ref="JagerColin">Jager</name> argues via emergence theory for a more tentative
               theoretical disposition that is less commanding than the habits of mind <name
                  ref="FavretMary">Favret</name> questions.</p>
            <p>
               <name ref="KhalipJacques">Jacques Khalip</name>’s concluding essay argues for a
               dwelling with ruin and disaster that begins by asking this question about the story
               of Margaret and Armytage as narrator in <name ref="WordsworthWilliam"
                  >Wordsworth</name>’s <title level="m">Ruined Cottage</title>: how can poetry and
               reading dwell with the non-normative effects unleashed by disaster to discover forms
               of non-triumphal, wasted life? <name ref="KhalipJacques">Khalip</name> addresses this
               question via Martin Heidegger’s shadowed notion of being as persisting in ruin, Rem
               Koolhaas’s vision of the accumulated wreckage of modern life, Maurice Blanchot’s
               insistence that disaster cannot be forgotten but must be lived with, and the strange
               hospitality that <name ref="DerridaJacques">Derrida</name> urges for our relation to
               the nonhuman, the vegetable, and the dead. With these arguments engaged, <name
                  ref="KhalipJacques">Khalip</name> returns to the “harassed unrest” of <name
                  ref="WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</name>’s Margaret. Working from a very
               different point of departure, shadowed as much by the Holocaust as it is by Romantic
               wartime, <name ref="KhalipJacques">Khalip</name> finds very different ground to
               return readers, as do <name ref="FavretMary">Favret</name> and <name ref="DuncanIan"
                  >Duncan</name>, to a Romantic poetics that cannot turn from suffering, the wasting
               of human life, the instability of bodies and species in the kingdoms of nature. <name
                  ref="KhalipJacques">Khalip</name> insists on unsatisfied hermeneutic economy that
               theorizing at times seeks to offer: in exchange for this suffering, here is a theory
               of war or peace that will make up the difference. The elegy of the <title level="m"
                  >Ruined Cottage</title>, as <name ref="KhalipJacques">Khalip</name> puts it,
               “disasters the payments ordinarily recouped by acts of mourning.” It is an open
               question, I think, and was for <name ref="WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</name> as
               well, whether elegy can do even this much without denying loss. </p>
            <p>
               <name ref="KhalipJacques">Khalip</name>’s unremitting theoretical exploration of what
               doesn’t tidy up, what doesn’t find an easy settlement in Romantic writing shares with
               other authors in this collection a reading of Romanticism that lingers with its
               instabilities and doubts. Each of these essays takes up its own position along a
               continuum in which historiographic and theoretical interests lie, unevenly
               distributed, with several opportunities for friction between critical practices. None
               is assimilable in argument or method to the others. All six essays nonetheless insist
               on reading Romanticism for its frictions.</p>

            <div type="Citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>
               <listBibl>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Attridge, Derek</author>
                        <title level="m">The Singularity of Literature</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                           <date>2004</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Balfour, Ian</author>
                        <title level="m">The Rhetoric of Romantic Prophecy</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2002</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Brown, Marshall</author>
                        <title level="a">Romanticism and Enlightenment</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">The Cambridge Companion to Romanticism</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Curran, Stuart</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1993</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">25-47</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Chai, Leon</author>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Theory: Forms of Reflexivity in the Revolutionary
                           Era</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Chase, Cynthia</author>
                        <title level="a">Introduction</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Harlow, Essex</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Longman</publisher>
                           <date>1993</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Chandler, James K</author>
                        <title level="m">England in 1819</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                           <date>1998</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                 
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Chandler, James K</author>
                        <title level="a">Moving Accidents: The Emergence of Sentimental
                           Probability</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">The Age of Cultural Revolutions: Britain and France,
                           1750-1820</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Jones, Colin</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Wahrman, Dror</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Los Angeles and Berkeley</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of California</publisher>
                           <date>2002</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">137-170</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Clark, Timothy</author>
                        <title level="m">The Poetics of Singularity</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Edinburgh University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2004</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Curtis, Neal</author>
                        <title level="m">Against Autonomy: Lyotard, Judgement and Action</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Aldershot, Hampshire</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>
                           <date>2001</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Darwin, Charles</author>
                        <title level="m">Origin of Species</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Beer, Gillian</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1996</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Deleuze, Gilles</author>
                        <title level="m">Difference and Repetition</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1994</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>de Man, Paul</author>
                        <title level="a">Rhetoric of Tropes</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Allegories of Reading</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New Haven</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Yale University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1979</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">103-18</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Derrida, Jacques</author>
                        <title level="a">Force of Law: The ‘Mystical Foundation of
                           Authority’</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Deconstruction and the Possibility of Justice</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Cornell, Drucilla</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Rosenfeld, Michel</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Gray, David</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                           <date>1992</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">3-67</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Derrida, Jacques</author>
                        <title level="m">Of Grammatology</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Spivak, Gayatri</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1974</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Duncan, Ian</author>
                        <title level="a">Hume, Scott and the ‘Rise of Fiction’</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Angles on the English-Speaking World</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">3</biblScope>
                           <date>2003</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">63-76</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Duncan, Ian</author>
                        <title level="a">Authenticity Effects: The Work of Fiction in Romantic
                           Scotland</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">SAQ</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">102:1</biblScope>
                           <date>Winter 2003</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">93-116</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Duncan, Ian</author>
                        <title level="a">Primitive Inventions: <title level="m">Rob Roy</title>,
                           Nation, and World System</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Eighteenth-Century Fiction</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">15:1</biblScope>
                           <date>October 2002</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">81-102</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Favret, Mary</author>
                        <title level="a">War in the Air</title>
                        <title level="j">MLQ</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">61:1</biblScope>
                           <date>December 2004</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">531-59</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>François, Anne-Lise</author>
                        <title level="a">’O Happy Living Things’: Frankenfoods and the Bounds of
                           Wordsworthian Natural Piety</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Diacritics</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">33:2</biblScope>
                           <date>Summer 2003</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">42-70</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Gasché, Rodolphe</author>
                        <title level="m"> Inventions of Difference</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass.</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1994</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>


                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Glen, Heather</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Hamilton, Paul</editor>
                        <title level="m">Repossessing the Romantic Past</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Goethe, J. W. von</author>
                        <title level="m">Metamorphosen der Pflanzen</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Steiner, Rudolf</editor>
                        <edition>6th edition</edition>
                        <edition>1790 rpt</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Verlag Freies Geistesleben</publisher>
                           <date>1992</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Jameson, Fredric</author>
                        <title level="m">The Political Unconscious</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Ithaca, N.Y.</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cornell University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1981</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <!-- Note: In html, two authors is producing three hyphens and a comma -->
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Jones, Colin</author>
                        <author>Wahrman, Dror</author>
                        <title level="a">Introduction: An Age of Cultural Revolutions?</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <ref target="#JW">
                        </ref>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="pp">1-16</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                     
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct xml:id="JW">
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Jones, Colin</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Wahrman, Dror</editor>
                        <title level="m">The Age of Cultural Revolutions: Britain and France,
                           1750-1820</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Los Angeles and Berkeley</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of California Press</publisher>
                           <date>2002</date>
                           
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  
                  

                  


                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Koselleck, Reinhart</author>
                        <title level="m">Futures Past: On the Semantics of Historical Time</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Tribe, Keith</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2004</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Lyotard, Jean François</author>
                        <title level="m">The Differend</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Van Den Abbeele, Georges</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Minneapolis</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Minnesota University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1988</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>McFarland, Thomas</author>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and the Forms of Ruin</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1984</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Nairn, Tom</author>
                        <title level="m">The Break-Up of Britain: Crisis and Neo-nationalism</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>New Left Books</publisher>
                           <date>1981</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <!-- Note: -->
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Nancy, Jean Luc</author>
                        <title level="m">The Inoperative Community</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Connor, and Trans. Peter</editor>
                        
                        <editor role="editor">Garbus, Lisa</editor>
                        
                        <editor role="editor">Holland, Michael</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Sawhney, Simon</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Minneapolis</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Minnesota Press</publisher>
                           <date>1991</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Nancy, Jean Luc</author>
                        <title level="m">Hegel: The Restlessness of the Negative</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Minneapolis</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Minnesota Press</publisher>
                           <date>2002</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Nancy, Jean Luc</author>
                        <title level="m">The Sense of the World</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Librett, Jeffrey S.</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Minneapolis</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Minnesota Press</publisher>
                           <date>1997</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Parker, Mark</author>
                        <title level="a">Measure and Countermeasure: The Lovejoy-Wellek Debate and
                           Romantic Periodization</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Theoretical Issues in Literary History</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Perkins, David</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Harvard UP</publisher>
                           <date>1991</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">227-47</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Pfau, Thomas</author>
                        <title>Reading beyond Redemption: Historicism, Irony, and the Lessons of
                           Romanticism</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">The Lessons of Romanticism</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Pfau, Thomas</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Gleckner, Robert F.</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Durham, NC</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1998</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">1-37</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Pfau, Thomas</author>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Moods</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Plotnitsky, Arcady</author>
                        <title level="a">Difference</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Glossalalia</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Wolfreys, Julian</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                           <date>2003</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">51-74</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Rajan, Tilottama</author>
                        <title level="a">System and Singularity From Herder to Hegel</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">European Romantic Review</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">11:2</biblScope>
                           <date>2000</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">137-49</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Rajan, Tilottama</author>
                        <title level="a">Dis-Figuring Reproduction: Natural History, Community, and
                           the 1790s Novel</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The New Centennial Review</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2:3</biblScope>
                           <date>2002</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">211-52</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Rajan, Tilottama</author>
                        <title level="a">The Unavowable Community of Idealism: Coleridge and the
                           Life Sciences</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">European Romantic Review</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">14:4</biblScope>
                           <date>2003</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">395-416</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Rancière, Jacques</author>
                        <title level="m">La Mésentente: Politique et Philosophe</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Éditions Galilée</publisher>
                           <date>1995</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Rancière, Jacques</author>
                        <title level="m">Dis-agreement: politics and philosophy</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Rose, Julie</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Minneapolis</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Minnesota Press</publisher>
                           <date>1999</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>



                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Stafford, Barbara</author>
                        <title level="m">Voyage into Substance: Art, Science, Nature and the
                           Illustrated Travel Account 1760-1840</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass.</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
                           <date>1984</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Trumpener, Katie</author>
                        <title level="m">Bardic Nationalism</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1997</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Tsing, Anna Lowenhaupt</author>
                        <title level="m">Friction</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Wolfson, Susan</author>
                        <title level="a">Reading for Form</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">MLQ</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">61:1</biblScope>
                           <date>March 2000</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">1-16</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
