<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Romantic Frictions</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">The Ruin of Things</title>
            <author>
               <name>Jacques Khalip</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">Theresa M. Kelley</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.khalip</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2010-11-01">March 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">The Ruin of Things</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Jacques</forename>
                        <surname>Khalip</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Romantic Frictions:</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-03-01">March 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#226;&#8364;&#339;,"
                  for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>                         <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>                         <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>                         <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>                         <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2010-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay" n="7">
            <head>
               
               <title level="a">The Ruin of Things</title>
            </head>
            <byline>
               <docAuthor>Jacques Khalip</docAuthor>
               <affiliation>Brown University</affiliation>
            </byline>

            <epigraph>
               <quote>The disaster is the gift; it gives disaster: as if it took no account of being
                  or not-being. It is not advent (which is proper to what comes to pass): it does
                  not happen. And thus I cannot ever happen upon this thought, except without
                  knowing, without appropriating any knowledge. Or again, is it the advent of what
                  does not happen, of what would come without arriving, outside being, and as though
                  by drifting away? The posthumous disaster? <lb/>
               - Maurice Blanchot (5)
               </quote>
            </epigraph>
            <epigraph>
               <quote>Junkspace features the tyranny of the oblivious: sometimes an entire Junkspace
                  comes unstuck through the nonconformity of one of its members; a single citizen of
                  an another culture—a refugee, a mother—can destabilize an entire Junkspace, hold
                  it to a rustic’s ransom, leaving an invisible swath of obstruction in his/her
                  wake, a deregulation eventually communicated to its furthest extremities... <lb/>
               Rem Koolhaas (180) 
               </quote>
            </epigraph>
            <p>At first glance, my remarks in this essay improvise on Adorno and Horkheimer’s
               pronouncement at the beginning of <title level="m">Dialectic of the
                  Enlightenment</title> that “Enlightenment, in the widest sense of progressive
               thought, has always aimed at liberating men from fear and installing them as masters.
               Yet the fully enlightened earth radiates disaster triumphant” (3). Their narrative of
               the perilous debris of secularized knowledge—the “disenchantment of the
               world”—negatively offers up the glimmer of waste for critical speculation. Indeed,
               the <title level="m">Dialectic</title>’s critique of progressivism shores up remnants
               of various projects that lie in the wake of thought’s destruction and division,
               leaving readers in the headlights of the very forms of political, social, and
               cultural subjugation they were meant to overcome: “the Enlightenment has extinguished
               any trace of its own self-consciousness. The only kind of thinking that is
               sufficiently hard to shatter myths is ultimately self-destructive” (4). </p>
            
               <p> In what follows, however, I do not propose a therapeutic Romantic response to the
                     <title level="m">Dialectic</title>’s claims; rather, I invert Adorno and
                  Horkheimer in order to explore how the aesthetic, cognitive, and ethical
                  vocabularies of ruination and disaster (what Adorno will himself refer to as
                  “damaged life”) provide ways for <emph>dwelling with </emph>the non-normative and
                  transformative effects unleashed <emph>by</emph> disaster—that is to say, how
                  palpable strains of apocalypticism in certain Romantic texts are denatured or
                  flattened out to the point where “disaster triumphant” isn’t merely synonymous wth
                  the denigration of thought, but rather suggests new conditions of intelligibility
                  and complex forms of non-triumphal, wasted life. “I see around me here/Things
                  which you cannot see: we die, my Friend,/Nor we alone, but that which each man
                  loved/And prized in his peculiar nook of earth/Dies with him, or is changed.”
                     (<title level="m">Ruined</title> 67-71).
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="1">All references to the poem are to this
                        edition and to the MS.D version, unless otherwise noted. </note>
                   In <title level="m">The Ruined Cottage</title>, Armytage hews an imaginary
                  path through disaster: he perceives the intangible things of his littered
                  environment as figures of reasoning that do not cease to generate unnatural
                  visualizations and understandings. Here, ruins are less triumphalist memorials
                  than wasted terrains that deviate from the normative circulations of sentimental
                  value which the poem has traditionally been thought to sustain at a premium. In an
                  article to which I will return, the architectural theorist Rem Koolhaas has
                  imagined such scorched scenes as “Junkspace”—aesthetically residual stuff, the
                  “apotheosis, or meltdown” of modernization’s enlightened programs of construction:
                  “If space-junk is the human debris that litters the universe, Junk-Space is the
                  residue mankind leaves on the planet” (175). This postmodern proliferation of
                  immanent spaces, which Koolhaas diagnoses as one of the designs of late
                  capitalism, homogenizes and conglomerates things that are readily discarded or
                  treated as underway to being remaindered: “Continuity is the essence of Junkspace;
                  it exploits any invention that enables expansion, deploys the infrastructure of
                  seamlessness: escalator, air-conditioning, sprinkler, fire shutter, hot-air
                  curtain. . .” (175). Risking anachronism, this architectural “stuff” leaks out of
                     <title level="m">The Ruined Cottage</title>’s own continuities of accumulation
                  and regress, progress and memorialization, which are treated as leftover and
                  exposed to exploitation. The poem begs its ruins to be read differently
                     <emph>as</emph> junk, as “oblivious” spaces of conditioned freedom and
                  “collision” where to look upon disaster is to see and meditate on the deviant
                  mutability of persons and things. Part of the value of identifying such inhumanism
                  and understanding why it countermands the nostalgia, melancholy, and frustration
                  ordinarily associated with modernity’s angst depends on how we perceive the
                  disaster that the poem proposes; after all, these things are not simply ghostly
                  revenants but half-material entities on their way to death. Like Margaret, like
                  the broken objects around the cottage, and finally, like Armytage and the
                  narrator, all things break down in the poem and are rehydrated by its muted lines
                  of sympathy. And yet, if Romanticism has often been read as synonymous with
                  discourses of humanism, personhood, and community, how should we read Wordsworth’s
                  insistence that we must attend to the waste, to things in their various states of
                  destruction? And what would it mean to think of persons as things themselves? The
                  trancelike inhumanism of the spear-grass vision that concludes the poem evokes a
                  disastrous reticence that suffuses Wordsworth’s thought, and in this essay, I want
                  to work toward a ruined cottage as the place where Wordsworth explores the
                  hospitality of dwelling in the rubble of disaster—in other words, disaster
                     <emph>not</emph> as the pessimistic obliteration of enlightenment promise, but
                  rather as a bleak and elegant reimagination of sociality without a future. </p>
            

            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>Harassed Unrest</head>
               <p>In “Building Dwelling Thinking,” Heidegger states that: ‘“Mortals dwell in that
                  they receive the sky as sky. They leave to the sun and the moon their journey, to
                  the stars their courses, to the seasons their blessing and their inclemency; they
                  do not turn night into day nor day into a harassed unrest” (150). What
                     <emph>is</emph> harassed unrest? Is it a state lacking in peace, an imposed
                  disruption of everyday life, or the place of disaster? When Wordsworth exclaims in
                     <title level="m">Home at Grasmere</title> that “yon ethereal vault/And this
                  deep Vale” will give us the sense of finding ourselves as “The Inmates not
                  unworthy of their home/The Dwellers of their Dwelling” (<title level="m"
                     >Poems</title> 642-648), is he referring to a way of dwelling in
                     <emph>un</emph>harassed rest? (We might also recall, for example, Wordsworth’s
                  wish in “Tintern Abbey” that Dorothy’s mind “shall be a mansion for all lovely
                  forms,/Thy memory be as a dwelling-place/For all sweet sounds and
                     harmonies”[<title level="m">Poems</title> 140-142]). For the author of <title
                     level="m">Home at Grasmere</title>, how to live or, more importantly, how to
                  dwell essentially conveys the insight of pastoral <emph>otium</emph>: that “being”
                  is about how one occupies or remains, stops or tarries as a figure in a space that
                  neither precedes nor emerges out of one’s control. “Dwelling” sounds like a
                  parrying move of sorts against the “multitude of causes unknown” blunting everyday
                  life—England’s military-industrial proliferation, war, famine, poverty, amongst
                  other elemental matters of late eighteenth-century European life (Wordsworth,
                     <title level="m">Literary</title> 21). In <title level="m">Home at
                     Grasmere</title>, Wordsworthian dwelling emerges as a defensive habitat—the
                  ruling figure of contained, domesticated housing or sheltering where to live is to
                  coincide (to prove “not unworthy”) with place and purpose. Finding a home marks a
                  singular attempt on the poet’s part to avoid disasters that would demolish
                  dwelling entirely. </p>
               <p>Heidegger etymologically traces <emph>dwelling</emph> to mean “to stay in a
                  place…to be at peace, to be brought to peace, to remain at peace…preserved from
                  harm and danger, preserved from something, safeguarded. To free really means to
                  spare” (149), and his gloss captures the wistful ambivalence within Wordsworth’s
                  thought which shuttles between containment and anxious openness at all costs: to
                  dwell means to reprieve the imagination from the very stimulations that seek to
                  exploit it—to grant or relinquish a spot to its state of rest, ostensibly without
                  any design of its own. Dwelling, then, is less about home than it is (as Heidegger
                  states) about a thinking and building, a securing of ontological place by allowing
                  it to remain unoccupied or unused. </p>
               <quote><lg>
                     <l rend="#indent6"> In such strength</l>
                     <l>Of usurpation, in such visitings</l>
                     <l>Of awful promise, when the light of sense</l>
                     <l>Goes out in flashes that have shown to us</l>
                     <l>The invisible world, doth greatness make abode,</l>
                     <l>There harbours whether we be young or old. </l>
                     <l>Our destiny, our nature, and our home</l>
                     <l>Is with infinitude, and only there;</l>
                     <l>With hope it is, hope that can never die,</l>
                     <l>Effort and expectation, and desire,</l>
                     <l>And something evermore about to be.</l>
                     <l> (<emph>Prelude</emph> 6.532-542)
                           <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="2">I refer to the 1805 poem. In the
                              1850 version, “nature” is replaced with “being’s heart.” </note>
                        
                     </l>
                  </lg></quote>
               <p>In this passage from <title level="m">The Prelude</title>, the imagination does
                  indeed “make abode” as it exchanges its power over and against reason, but it is
                  less concerned with housing authorial power than with deflecting an infinitude
                  which lies “only there” in the most minimal sense of being a space out of reach,
                  rather than an inaccessibility that gestures to a transcendental beyond. The
                  ambiguities in Heidegger’s thoughts, like Wordsworth’s, turn on the question of
                  how and why dwelling must be “brought to peace”: that is to say, is peace an
                  original condition of place—the <emph>placing</emph> of place—that must be
                  reestablished through a violence that is inextricable from its accomplishment? Or
                  is it a horizon-event left to be discovered through “building” which spares and
                  preserves a spot of rest? Insofar as “securing” is also a “building” for
                  Heidegger, dwelling is a motile gathering of place, a recycling act in view of
                  what he calls the fourfold (earth, sky, gods, mortals). All four of these
                  reciprocally coalesce in dwelling, and nothing is misplaced. “Dwelling preserves
                  the fourfold by bringing the presencing of the fourfold into things. But things
                  themselves secure the fourfold <emph>only when</emph> they themselves
                     <emph>as</emph> things are let be in their presencing” (151). Fretful dwelling
                  is thus <emph>undwelling</emph>—it means a crisis with presencing the fourfold,
                  with its arrangement—an incapacity to let things be. For Heidegger, the “real
                  plight of dwelling lies in this, that mortals search anew for the nature of
                  dwelling, that they <emph>must ever learn to dwell.</emph> What if man’s
                  homelessness consisted in this, that man still does not even think of the
                     <emph>real</emph> plight of dwelling as <emph>the</emph> plight?” (161)
                  Heidegger’s post-war reflections on dwelling and world-homelessness might be
                  thought of as reparative attempts at living: they generate or <emph>build</emph>
                  forms of life that might dwell without coercion and harassment, not by changing
                  what the world is, but by experiencing its openness as a condition of thinking
                  about it otherwise. The difference for Wordsworth, however, in a poem like <title
                     level="m">The Ruined Cottage</title> and <emph>not</emph>
                  <title level="m">Home at Grasmere</title>, is that in the former text he
                  specifically dwells in the disastering of the fourfold. Wordsworth thinks about
                  how dwelling in the ruins of unrest brings changes in sociality that are rendered
                  unreal in a landscape dominated by scarcity.</p>
               <p>How to dwell then in disaster? The absence of a precise definition (whether
                  scientific, medical, social, aesthetic) imposes limits and demands a recalibration
                  of its meanings. According to the <emph>Center for Research on the Epidemiology of
                     Disaster </emph>(<emph>CRED</emph>), disaster “is a situation or event which
                  overwhelms local capacity, necessitating a request to a national or international
                  level for external assistance.” The <title level="m">OED</title>’s
                  definition—“Anything that befalls of ruinous or distressing nature; a sudden or
                  great misfortune, mishap, or misadventure; a calamity”—reflects the World Health
                  Organization’s emphasis on “extraordinary response from outside.” Disaster thus differs from other variants like crisis, emergency, or
                  catastrophe by virtue of a system of scale and disproportionate intensity: the
                  DEEP Center, for example, emphasizes an “imbalance between the demands of the
                  disaster event and the capacities of the affected community to respond.” Disaster is a relational description of an excess of
                  potentiality and the vulnerabilities produced by and within an environment
                  rendered non-holistic. It forces bodies and objects to collide; rather than evoke
                  a verticalizing sense of obligation and suspension by that which is “evermore
                  about to be,” it intimates that any marked awareness of an alteration of events is
                  at base perspectival—a change in position that outdoes the capacity to properly
                  define and respond to it. As Marie-Hélène Huet reminds us of the etymology of the
                  word, <emph>désastre</emph> (from the stars) or <emph>disastro</emph> also signals
                  a particular displacement or dislocation vis-à-vis the sky—a betrayal or
                  disownment by the cosmos: “However, the word ‘disaster’ has not always designated
                  a catastrophic event. Initially it was not a noun by a past participle. In other
                  words, there was no disaster per se, ony the experience of disaster—one was
                  ‘disastered’…In disaster, the very space humans occupy in relation to the stars is
                  destabilized; they are uprooted from their place in the cosmos and cast adrift”
                  (18, 19). As a spatial coincidence of hazard <emph>with</emph> vulnerability,
                  disaster provokes reflections on the possibilities of living under and
                     <emph>through</emph> conditions undesirable—a reshifting of the hierarchization
                  of knowledge in view of a change in placement. It is, in other words, a radical
                  change in perspectives on dwelling. Trauma theory, for example, treats disaster as
                  a kind of specialized knowledge of the modern habitus—something that is understood
                  by its unknownness, or the mind’s hospitality to formations it cannot anticipate
                  in advance.
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="3">See Terada’s “Living” for a
                        non-traumatic exploration of discovering possibility in ruination.</note>
                   And new historicist criticism of a certain traumatic variety has taught us
                  to uncover these disasters, whether real or imagined, as in some way doubly dismal
                  and displaced: they are hidden by forms of literary obscuration that blunt the
                  “historical” underscorings of place. What these approaches share, however, is an
                  attentiveness to the uncovering of referentiality as a material revelation of the
                  states of life, and they equally treat disaster’s critical magnitude as the payoff
                  for an enrichment of knowing in the face of loss: in other words, what resonates
                  in some of these accounts is the recovery of unwanted knowledge as generative and
                  non-privative. If we accept this, we might risk precluding narratives of
                  non-development that disaster evokes in non-differential terms. For Maurice
                  Blanchot, for example, disaster brings forms of perceptual awareness that cannot
                  be easily shared or drawn into acceptable use because they shortcircuit desires to
                  dwell with <emph>oneself</emph>: <quote>The question concerning the disaster is a
                     part of the disaster: it is not an interrogation, but a prayer, an entreaty, a
                     call for help. The disaster appeals to the disaster that the idea of salvation,
                     of redemption might not yet be affirmed, and might, drifting debris, sustain
                     fear. The disaster: inopportune. (13) </quote> The question of the disaster is
                  implicitly about dwelling—as a non-reciprocal appeal, it reflects on how to live
                  with unrest while refusing to consent to outside response. For Blanchot, the
                  ability to think is synonymous with a capacity to <emph>not</emph> exclude
                  difficulty—to forestall the expectation of what is “evermore about to be,” or what
                  is cognitively expected of the unknown when it is construed as inevitable. On the
                  one hand, disaster appears to read like a structure of desire (like love, risk,
                  mourning), but even more for Blanchot, the disaster figures for the
                  non-affirmation of hope, a plea that can never be attested to nor secured. It is a
                  state of displacement, of non-affective dwelling that fails to imitate a
                  relational stance toward salvation or redemption because neither can be properly
                  anticipated. To believe in them is to erroneously seize upon each as structures of
                  promised opportunity. <quote>The disaster ruins everything, all the while leaving
                     everything intact. It does not touch anyone in particular; ‘I’ am not
                     threatened by it, but spared, left aside. It is in this way that I am
                     threatened; it is in this way that the disaster threatens in me that which is
                     exterior to me—an other than I who passively become other. There is no reaching
                     the disaster…To think the disaster (if this is possible, and it is not possible
                     inasmuch as we suspect that the disaster is thought) is to have no longer any
                     future in which to think it. (1)</quote> A number of thoughts emerge in this
                  tightly-knit fragment: how does disaster “ruin everything” while changing nothing
                  at the same time? And how can one speak of the disaster if it touches no one “in
                  particular”? Blanchot’s fragmentary descriptions undo the privileging aspects of
                  reference: to consider disaster as both preserving and destroying (to echo
                  Shelley’s west wind) is to denature any demonstrative sense of its meaning. It
                  intimates that progressive transformation is evanescent or slight or, moreover,
                  that disaster is an inertia, something passively imponderable. Disaster is
                  posthumous: it “neither is, nor is it not”
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="4">This is Ann Smock’s gloss in her
                        introduction to <title level="m">The Writing of the Disaster</title>
                        (x).</note>
                   an event over which a <emph>present</emph> judgment can be rendered because
                  the temporality of its occurrence is always belated. Since one cannot know “what
                  comes to pass,” disaster attenuates revelation to the point of translating
                  knowledge of <emph>an </emph>experience into knowledge of the
                     <emph>afterlife</emph> of that experience. The difference between stasis and
                  change, human and non-human, is thus neutralized by an ethics of reading that
                  erases the experience of thinking of such difference as something felt to be
                  discovered <emph>within</emph> the self, something made recognizable by the
                  temporalization of a narrative that distributes events and their perception as
                  seemingly successive and accountable. To be left untouched or to dwell
                     <emph>as</emph> untouched means to go without registering the slightest kind of
                  acknowledgment, the unaffective or non-traumatic impression that occurs by virtue
                  of the fact that there is <emph>no one there to be touched by it in the first
                     place</emph>. A “bond/Of brotherhood is broken” when a “human hand” does not
                  touch the stillness it had earlier sought to disturb. The British geographer Nigel
                  Clark has argued that the very desire to define disaster as “an event that makes a
                  difference” is to reduce it to historical or social determinants, and thus do
                  conceptual damage to the virtual materializations it unleashes: “Is it really
                  ‘difference’ if we conceive of the disaster as a making manifest of
                  vulnerabilities that could and should have been visible prior to the event; if the
                  disaster serves primarily to reveal, re-inscribe and retrench pre-existing
                  hierarchies and structures? And for whom is it a disaster, if in the very event of
                  disrupting and unravelling a spatial or geographic order, it turns out to
                  authorise the discourse that speaks of disruption and unravelling of spatial and
                  geographic orders?” (1132-1133.) Difference can mark too easily an emerging
                  pattern of articulation, of revelation and necessary sequence—it compels a
                  relentless sameness, a rewinding of time to maintain repetition and inertia. By
                  contrast, disaster is an unwilled, unseeable, and <emph>indifferent</emph>
                  eventfulness, a “dwelling-with” so deeply ruined that its non-apparency marks a
                  resistance to its claims. Although Blanchot’s cryptic descriptions mystify the
                  term to the point of rendering it uninterpretable, it is important to recall how
                  the question <emph>of</emph> disaster is always an entreaty to speak well of it.
                  “Everything is the disaster” is an injunction to dwell with and not look away from
                  oneself, and others, in ruin.</p>
               <p>When Wordsworth speaks of the “fretful dwellings of mankind” at the beginning of
                  the <title level="m">Two-Part Prelude</title>, he does so by way of what Timothy
                  Morton has called an “ambient poetics”: a surrounding, reverberating environment
                  of co-existence, rather than a marker or mere spot of time (Morton 22). Both the
                  1805 and 1850 <title level="m">Prelude</title> repeat this passage with a
                  teleological inflection that marks out the eventual home of Wordsworth’s poetic
                  ambition. But instead of further amplifying these gladdening descriptions, I want
                  to suggest a counter-Wordsworthian reading that turns especially on the withdrawal
                  of personal will in favor of passive acceptance and receipt of unassumed
                  itineraries: <quote><lg>
                        <l rend="#indent6"> I might advert</l>
                        <l>To numerous accidents in flood or field,</l>
                        <l>Quarry or moor, or ’mid the winter snows,</l>
                        <l>Distresses and disasters, tragic facts</l>
                        <l>Of rural history, that impressed my mind</l>
                        <l>With images to which in following years</l>
                        <l>Far other feelings were attached—with forms</l>
                        <l>That yet exist with independent life,</l>
                        <l>And, like their archetypes, know no decay. </l>
                        <l> (<title level="m">Two-Part Prelude</title> 1. 279-287)</l>
                     </lg></quote> In this passage, which was not reproduced in the subsequent 1805
                  and 1850 versions of <title level="m">The Prelude</title>, Wordsworth speaks of
                  “distresses and disasters” as causal breaks, events that are neither anticipated
                  by nor fulfill the experiences that precede them. Wordsworth’s disaster is closer
                  to Deleuze’s theory of the event, for whom the event is not anything in particular
                  but rather a virtualization of material possibilities that are always occurring:
                  “The event is not the state of affairs. It is actualized in a state of affairs, in
                  a body, in a lived, but it has a shadowy and secret part that is continually
                  subtracted from or added to its actualization: in contrast with the state of
                  affairs, it neither begins nor ends but has gained or kept the infinite movement
                  to which it gives consistency” (<title level="m">What is Philosophy</title> 156).
                  The Deleuzian event is a disastrous irruption that is not to be confused with the
                  actual occurrence precipitated by the event itself. It is always belatedly
                  captured by the literary which doesn’t represent it but rather
                     <emph>expresses</emph> it, not symptomatically but almost metabolically
                  “counter-effectuating” the event (159). In this sense, Wordsworth’s distresses and
                  disasters effect a non-pathological counter-effectuation: they permit a moment of
                  freedom, an allusion to a virtuality of experience that won’t reduce the meaning
                  of the disaster to the facticity of life. The “images to which in following
                  years/Far other feelings were attached” certainly conjure a Humean reading of the
                  image as a mechanism between sense and mind to which feeling incrementally
                  attaches and in turn embellishes thought. But what Wordsworth also seems to
                  suggest is that the images of “Distresses and disasters, tragic facts/Of rural
                  history” which merge into “independent life” subsequently outlive, metaphorically,
                  the real casualties out of which they come, not as naturalized copies or
                     <emph>eidolons</emph> that rival reality, but which exist apart as simulacra
                  requiring a violent dissemination in order to be reborn again. Rather than see
                  such images as redemptive breakaways from disaster, Wordsworth points here to the
                  mind <emph>not</emph> working to therapeutically overcome disaster (recuperating
                  itself outside of these disasters and metastisizing out of it); rather, it is
                  passively fascinated by the images’ endurance, “like archetypes,” in spite of the
                  mind’s own individuation. If the disaster does signal a difference in the speaker,
                  it is one which emerges with insignificant detail: “that what we feel of sorrow
                  and despair/From ruin and from change, and all the grief/The passing shews of
                  being leave behind,/Appeared an ideal dream that could not live/Where meditation
                  was” (520-524); But at the same time, disaster also brings to awareness a life
                  that somehow dwells under conditions that leave it to compose or decompose itself
                  anew. If dwelling, for Heidegger, is an overcoming of “harassed unrest” that opens
                  one up to and gathers the fourfold, Wordsworth’s “disasters” point to a kind of
                  life whose unrest <emph>is</emph> unharassed, non-coercive, and non-apocalyptic.
                  It scatters the fourfold. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>Irreparable</head>
               <p>What if we were to conceive of the disasters of the past as pulverizing our
                  standard forms of attachment? Because disasters are silently happening all around
                  us, what would it mean to insist that our response should not be one of sudden
                  regrouping, but of welcoming the unwanted changes that a form of disastrous
                  hospitality commits on our moral exchanges, undoing our models of personhood, and
                  transforming us into debris, waste, and ruin? Derrida writes after Kant that
                  hospitality is a right or duty rather than an affective form of philanthropy
                  because it is an obligation that challenges the seeming “naturalness” of our
                  sentimental attachments: “it already broaches an important question, that of the
                  anthropological dimension of hospitality or the right to hospitality: what can be
                  said of, indeed can one speak of, hospitality toward the non-human, the divine,
                  for example, or the animal or vegetable; does one owe hospitality, and is that the
                  right word when it is a question of welcoming-–or being made welcome by-–the other
                  or the stranger as god, animal or plant?” (4) Hospitality in fact concerns the
                  question of unrestful dwelling because it won’t let the sky or the earth simply
                  be—it marks the torquing between identities, the queering of our relation to the
                  non-human, of the person to the vegetable. As inmates of dwellings, we should
                  begin to read Wordsworth’s poetry as reflecting on the forms of dwelling afforded
                  in the face of conditions that are, to say the least, intolerable and
                  inhospitable. </p>
               <p> When Armytage points to the scene of disaster at the beginning of <title
                     level="m">The Ruined Cottage</title>, he gestures to the “cheerless spot” where
                  the fourfold is at once gathered <emph>and</emph> disseminated, where disaster is
                  kept open as a question over the ruins of a poem that has often been read as an
                  act of reparative memorialization.
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="5">See Schor and Fosso. </note>
                   In keeping with Clark’s definition, I want to suggest that the ruins
                  Wordsworth attends to closely resemble an “event of disrupting and unravelling,”
                  and are linked to his antirepresentational preoccupation with disaster’s ruination
                  of the gains of pastoral elegy. <title level="m">The Ruined Cottage</title> thus
                  doesn’t simply rehumanize our relationship with things in the world; instead, it
                  marks an unworking or <emph>désoeuvrement</emph> of things, and troubles the kinds
                  of economies that shuttle persons and things between durability and transience,
                  gain and loss, wealth and waste. The elegy, in other words, <emph>does not
                     give</emph>, and similarly does not owe (after Derrida): it disasters the
                  payments ordinarily recouped by acts of mourning that assure normative dwelling
                     “evermore.”
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="6">My thinking here is indebted to
                        Freedgood’s manuscript, “That People Might Be Like Things and Live.” </note>
                   On the one hand, of course, <title level="m">The Ruined Cottage</title> does
                  seek to sublimate grief into what Joel Faflak calls a “desire for moral
                  management” (“Was it”), creating pathetic fallacies which substantialize and
                  organize emotions already resistant to duration (“The Poets in their elegies and
                  songs/Lamenting the departed call the groves,/They call upon the hills and streams
                  to mourn,/And senseless rocks, nor idly; for they speak/In these their invocations
                  with a voice/Obedient to the strong creative power/Of human passions” [73-79]).
                  But there are always “Sympathies…//More tranquil” (79-80) in the sense of being
                  non-reciprocal, that do not instrumentalize streams and rocks in order to make
                  them weep: while the poem’s opening rehearsal of the history of elegiac address
                  seeks to re-cite (and re-assert) its precedence over a world of things, it also
                  exhumes the “senselessness” of a triadic encounter laid waste in a leftover world.
                  As Paul J. Alpers has noted, the intertextual echoes of Vergilian eclogue in the
                  poem work less to develop a dark antipastoralism than to script a new mode of
                  pastoral poetry that literally digs up the “bare Common” of its initial setting,
                  and reconfigures it in new encounters and experiences where “the question of
                  whether and how the earth is a fit habitation for human beings” (267) persists
                  throughout the Romantic junkspace, where disaster makes the difference between
                  change and death imperceptible. Indeed, as we are soon brought to a “ruined house,
                  four naked walls/That stared upon each other,” the poem implies that any kind of
                  ethical response to this spot will be measured in terms of how well we look upon
                  (rather than away from) the ruins—a different kind of pedagogical approach,
                  moreover, that risks changing everything and nothing, eliding being with
                  non-being.</p>
               <p>
                  <title level="m">The Ruined Cottage</title> in fact begins with a scene of
                  lugubrious oversaturation in the world, a wasting away of time that defines the
                  narrator’s own way of being which, from the outset, is beset by “no rest” (23).
                  This unrest of dwelling is characterized by intellectual distraction and barely
                  recorded somatic movements: “careless limbs beside the root/Of some huge oak whose
                  aged branches make/A twilight of their own” (11-13), or just after, the speaker
                  toiling “With languid feet which by the slipp’ry ground/Were baffled still” (20).
                  Unlively feet here are baffled into stillness and continue, as Wordsworth
                  suggests, to be baffled by a groundlessness the poem asks us to accept as its
                  state of unrest—the unraveling of our own being into a baffled stillness of
                  matter. Armytage, as numerous critics have noted, is signaled as ruined or
                  thing-like himself: “his hat/Bedewed with water-drops, as if the brim/Had newly
                  scooped a running stream. He rose/And pointing to a sunflower, bade me climb/The [
                  ] wall where that same gaudy flower/Looked upon the road” (49-54). The MS. B
                  version of the poem seems to overhaul this reification by inserting the as-yet
                  unnamed pedlar’s self-narrative early on in the poem as an exemplary biography: as
                  a “chosen son” (MS. B 76), the pedlar is described as entirely of a piece with the
                  natural landscape, giving “moral life” to “every natural form, rock, fruit, and
                  flower,/Even the loose stones that cover the highway” (80-82). The pedlar is
                  individualized in the very act of his own self-discerning capacities to overcome
                  the psychoanalytic frustration of Margaret’s abjection through philosophical
                  narrative and moral therapy, or what Faflak elsewhere describes as the “conflict
                  between a desire for a system that will discipline the aberrant empirical
                  phenomena of psychic life and his fascination with those phenomena” (“Analysis”): <quote><lg>
                        <l> Some called it madness—such it might have been,</l>
                        <l> But that he had an eye which evermore</l>
                        <l> Looked deep into the shades of difference</l>
                        <l> As they lie hid in all exterior forms,</l>
                        <l> Which from a stone, a tree, a withered leave,</l>
                        <l> To the broad ocean and the azure heavens</l>
                        <l> Spangled with kindred multitudes of stars,</l>
                        <l> Could find no surface where its power might sleep,</l>
                        <l> Which spake perpetual logic to his soul,</l>
                        <l> And by an unrelenting agency</l>
                        <l> Did bind his feelings even as in a chain. <lb/> (MS.B., 93-103). </l>
                     </lg></quote> Aesthetic contemplation here mingles with a relentless moral
                  uncovering of difference: the eye’s vigilance over the environment repetitively
                  binds or “chains” it to assent to things that do not rest. These surfaces
                  differentiate themselves as phenomena that coherently assemble the world’s
                  facticity. But the pedlar’s look is not quite so self-absorbed and
                  self-discerning: the biographical insert in MS.B literally “frame[s]” (104)
                  Armytage so as to suggest that even in solitude, he is never detached from the
                  “perpetual logic” that enchains him to all things. Indeed, the perpetuity of his
                  thought serializes him into a landscape where he is dispersed into the scenic
                  abstractions of “surface” and “shades.” Ocular power is scattered through a kind
                  of ever-metamorphosing formalism. When Armytage exclaims in the MS.D version of
                  the poem that at the “hour of deepest noon…/This hour when all things which are
                  not at rest/Are chearful…Why should a tear be in an old man’s eye?” (187-192), his
                  apparently stalled response over “feeding on disquiet” divests thought from
                  thinker and contagiously passes it onto the poet who, on looking on the pedlar’s
                  face, feels “that simple tale/[Pass] from my mind like a forgotten sound,”
                  (203-204). The moment of forgetfulness is less one of sympathetic resemblance than
                  a strange example of sfumato, or a literal <emph>inhumanizing</emph> of the face
                  to the point where what is perceived is several disfigurations away from the
                  object or person beheld. “[L]ooking round/Upon that tranquil ruin” (217-218), the
                  poem reverses the compulsion to gaze upon things as if they were subject to
                  coerced judgment. A different kind of unanticipated perception develops, a
                  low-grade suspended attentiveness or distracted “looking away” that recalls what
                  Rei Terada has studied as phenomenophilia—a love for “emigrating” or fleeting
                  things. Such a love runs counter to the usual normativity of appearances foisted
                  upon us by the social world (<title level="m">Looking</title>).</p>
               <p>Alan Bewell has noted that “Wordsworth’s ‘ruined cottage’…should be read not only
                  in terms of the discourse of the picturesque, but also as part of that ‘alien’
                  landscape of death that first emerged in his poetry with <title level="m"
                     >Salisbury Plain</title>,” and the poem moves further into an astonishingly
                  bleak poetic vision that reduces the picturesque almost to the level of still life
                  (124-5). As Harold Bloom wrote years ago (37-52), Wordsworth’s cinematic
                  Romanticism consists of a preternatural zooming in on the world: the poem unfurls
                  a series of time-lapse vignettes that contrast the barest inklings of movement
                  with interminable motionlessness, effecting a degradation of the narrative’s
                  kinetic pull to the point where the hypersensations afforded by the elegy are
                  shown to be utterly external to the form itself. In other words, the poem
                  demonstrates how perception is negotiated <emph>through</emph> a poetic
                  materiality that in turn abstracts sensation and leaves behind virtual, corroded
                  images of things “at peace,” or things that “presence” the world and dwell insofar
                  as they cannot be normatively reinhabited: <quote><lg>
                        <l rend="#indent6">…When I stooped to drink,</l>
                        <l>A spider’s web hung to the water’s edge,</l>
                        <l>And on the wet and slimy foot-stone lay</l>
                        <l>The useless fragment of a wooden bowl;</l>
                        <l>It moved my very heart… (88-92)</l>
                     </lg></quote>
                  <quote><lg>
                        <l rend="#indent6">…[Margaret] is dead, </l>
                        <l>The worm is on her cheek, and this poor hut,</l>
                        <l>Strippd of its outward garb of houshold flowers,</l>
                        <l>Of rose and sweet-briar, offers to the wind</l>
                        <l>A cold bare wall whose earthy top is tricked</l>
                        <l>With weeds and the rank spear-grass. She is dead,</l>
                        <l>And nettles rot and adders sun themselves </l>
                        <l>Where we have sate together while she nurs’d </l>
                        <l>Her infant at her breast. (108-111)</l>
                     </lg></quote> As the speaker “stoops,” the spider web also hangs, while the
                  bowl lies on the “foot-stone” in the same way as the worm is “on” Margaret’s
                  cheek. In these instances, one gesture appears to set off the energy of another in
                  a Rube Goldberg-like process. Material figure hits against material figure with
                  the slimmest sense of tangible action, and the effects of this lyric movement are
                  in turn abstracted into the arc of disuse that degrades the image into a rubble of
                  representation. What kind of durability does Wordsworth lend a character like
                  Margaret, who is at once utterly obsolete, subject to decay, while also movingly
                  thing-like? As Adam Potkay has noted, Romantic writers frequently point to the
                  “thing” as a term that is not always reducible to sociological and materialist
                  readings: neither commodity, fetish, nor concrete object, the “things we cannot
                  see” disturb the gap between person and thing, self and other, and offer a
                  challenging ecological ethics.
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="7">See Potkay. </note>
                   Such things, in their utter disposability, are images of what remains
                  uncontaminated by time and hence resistant to any restorative, differential
                  desire. The lingering waste of the poem doesn’t ripen, but rather remains
                  unyielding to any future prospects—it is literally the “no future,” the
                  superfluity of stuff that glimmers in a history of disaster that divests the poem
                  of any redeemable conditions.
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="8">I allude here to Edelman. </note>
                  
               </p>
               <p>In this way, the elegy, while lamenting the substitution of non-human for human
                  life, is a form that is as powerfully <emph>retro</emph> as it is retrospective,
                  memorializing and reanimating the poem’s Wordsworthian kitsch in order to bring to
                  light what Benjamin calls the “revolutionary energies that appear in the
                  ‘outmoded’ ” (210). Elegy’s sweep here detotalizes the scene of recovery: rather
                  than rescue memory and figure, elegiac deviance plows and erodes sentimentalism to
                  the point of producing veritable kitsch or detritus. Put another way, the poem
                  returns objects from misuse by “gathering” them up <emph>as</emph> things subject
                  to no one at all: <quote><lg>
                        <l>Her cottage in its outward look appeared</l>
                        <l>As chearful as before; in any shew</l>
                        <l>Of neatness little changed, but that I thought </l>
                        <l>The honeysuckle crowded round the door</l>
                        <l>And from the wall hung down in heavier wreathes,</l>
                        <l>And knots of worthless stone-crop started out</l>
                        <l>Along the window’s edge, and grew like weeds</l>
                        <l>Against the lower panes. I turnd aside</l>
                        <l>And stroll’d into her garden.—It was chang’d:</l>
                        <l>The unprofitable bindweed spread his bells </l>
                        <l>From side to side and with unwieldy wreaths</l>
                        <l>Had dragg’d the rose from its sustaining wall</l>
                        <l>And bent it down to earth; the border tufts—</l>
                        <l>Daisy and thrift and lowly camomile</l>
                        <l>And thyme—had straggled out into the paths</l>
                        <l>Which they were used to deck. Ere this an hour</l>
                        <l>Was wasted. (305-321)</l>
                     </lg></quote> This disastrous overturning of the dwelling-with of objects,
                  persons, and spaces in Wordsworth’s poem predictably recalls a fallen Eden, but it
                  is more to the point that Armytage’s words turn the materiality of the environment
                  into a text of disastrous interconnectivity. The rose suffocates under the violent
                  pressures of the bindweed; combined, the two effect a <emph>junkimage</emph>, a
                  residual poetic perception. Rose and bindweed serve as topological points of
                  mediation which “gather” just as well as they disaster the various intimacies the
                  passage seeks to render adjacent. Much like the passage where the narrator stoops
                  to drink the water, here agency is several times relocated from honeysuckle to
                  stone-crop, weed, bindweed, rose, chamomile, thyme—none of which are isolated
                  things unto themselves, but “objects” that only mean insofar as they are brought
                  into a web of proximation by the pedlar’s visualized narration. In just this way,
                  pastoral ruination veers away from psychologizing lament, and produces a different
                  kind of figural traffic. </p>
               <p> As Armytage, the poem’s bewildered documentarian, casts his eye on the <title
                     level="m">Grey Gardens</title>-like world of Margaret’s desuetude, he creates
                  and <emph>transforms</emph> the cottage’s past and present. The infinitesimal
                  alternation between stoppage and motion unleashed by the scene of disaster is of a
                  piece with the unworking of images which moulder in their own inoperative pathetic
                  fallacies, and the strangely atemporal, stop-motion description of things that
                     <emph>do not move,</emph> much like the “insidious half-life” of Koolhaas’s
                  Junkspace: “Aging in Junkspace is nonexistent or catastrophic; sometimes an entire
                  Junkspace—a department store, a nightclub, a bachelor pad—turns into a slum
                  overnight without warning: wattage diminishes imperceptibly, letters drop out of
                  signs, air-conditioning units start dripping, cracks appear as if from otherwise
                  unregistered earthquakes; sections rot, are no longer viable, but remain joined to
                  the ﬂesh of the main body via gangrenous passages” (180). The “catastrophic”
                  upsets of junkspace plot time to be at once stopped <emph>and</emph> contracted to
                  the point where change is instantaneous with presence. Junkspace thus spatializes
                  the destructivity of endless movement and the excessive remains it jettisons:
                  while space changes, junk accumulates but is relocated to different foci or lines
                  of sight that turn habitation into an ethics of reading, or reading
                     <emph>as</emph> a dwelling in states of disrepair between being and non-being
                  where things cannot be appropriated. </p>
               <p> Raimonda Modiano has identified this de-instrumentalization of things as a
                  feature of eighteenth-century picturesque, where human figures, like their
                  non-human opposites, are ambiguously caught between prospect and property, and in
                  turn are frequently depicted as <emph>found</emph> objects: “It is an object which
                  has no known owner or if the owner is known, he or she is either unlocatable or
                  out of reach. Because this object is not given by someone, a relationship with it
                  incurs no obligation and fosters no dependency, as in gift exchange. On the
                  contrary, this object guarantees the discoverer’s independence for it asks nothing
                  and invites no attachments” (212-213).
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="9">Also see Mitchell and Collins.</note>
                   Thus the picturesque economizes a non-reciprocal form of gift-giving that
                  assumes the found object as the ungiven gift. The strangeness of <title level="m"
                     >The Ruined Cottage</title> lies precisely in this emphasis on the foundness of
                  things <emph>as if there were no prior authorship nor ownership</emph>: things are
                  seemingly returned as unrepaired and not to be used, or as gifts never put into
                  circulations of exchange or obligation. While their affective kitschiness
                  nostalgically recalls the commodified literary history out of which they have
                  emerged—as Karen Swann has taught us, they are almost certainly Gothic ephemera
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="10">See Swann. </note>
                  —the elegy just as convincingly organizes the broken bowl, Margaret, her
                  child, the spear-grass, and the cottage itself as things found <emph>in</emph> a
                  limbic state between being for another and being for themselves. Like Van Gogh’s
                  peasant shoes, what we see are the traces of <emph>inhuman</emph> objects rid of
                  their wearers or dwellers, poetic fallacies that occur without the error of human
                  intention. These things are specifically <emph>irreparable</emph> in Giorgio
                  Agamben’s sense of the word: they “are consigned without remedy to their
                  being-thus, that they are precisely and only their <emph>thus</emph>…[for these
                  things] there is literally no shelter possible, that in their being-thus they are
                  absolutely exposed, absolutely abandoned” (39). For Agamben,
                  this irreparability is a quality of what he calls its “being that is always
                  already given in modality, that <emph>is</emph> its modalities. It is not
                     <emph>thus</emph>, but rather it is <emph>its</emph> thus” (92). The
                  “being-thus” of the irreparable imagines being not in terms of essence, state, or
                  condition, but in an “abandoned” excessiveness, a mode of “ecstatic dwelling,” as
                  Kate Rigby calls it (“Ecstatic”). Like disaster, Agamben’s sense of the
                  “irreparable” throws into high relief a form of sociality that is borne out of a
                  decommodified and desacralized world—in other words, inoperative communities freed
                  from universal judgment (“if the sensible world was ordered to fit the dignity and
                  the habtation of imperfect humans, then what sense can that world have when those
                  humans arrive at their supernatural destination?” [39]). Persons and things will
                  “thus” not be expropriated; they are the stuff of an ontological desuetude that is
                  intensely careless and negatively “<emph>capable of not not-being</emph>”
                  (40).</p>
               <p> It is customary to note how the poem’s narration of Margaret’s wartime
                  destruction is tempered by both the speaker and by Armytage, but what is less
                  remarked on is how the moral helplessness of tending for her—of letting the
                  disaster literally shift things before our eyes—is less a form of resignation than
                  a thingifying counter-effect of Armytage’s trances: to cede to the “passing shews
                  of being” is to be desubjectified, to enter the space from “ruin and from change”
                  where the elegy’s pathic distractions express the degree to which the speakers
                  themselves have become utterly irreparable: “ ‘I turned away/And walked along my
                  road in happiness’ ” (524-525), says Armytage, his joy as impotent as the grief
                  that “traced” (502) the “secret spirit of humanity” surviving “’mid the calm
                  oblivious tendencies/Of nature, ‘mid her plants, her weeds, and flowers”
                  (503-505). While criticism has often focused on this image of “humanity” as an
                  ideological purification of the humanness of Margaret, what often goes unsaid is
                  how the poet’s blessing of Margaret’s thingification in fact marks the point where
                  the rubble is asserted as having a spooky perspective all by itself: as an object
                  of care and not appropriation, the rubble is hospitably turned away from because
                  in this refusal of identification, a refusal of the viral nature of sympathetic
                  co-existence, a different kind of non-recognitional “ministering” is formed. Such
                  distractions signify a life that is neither subjective nor objective, between
                  being and non-being; it is a life that is rendered superfluous, or irreducible to
                  its biopoliticized specificity—a dwelling in a disastrous or ruined mode that
                  hears a gothic ecology of warbling linnets, singing thrushes “and other melodies”
                  (533) that are as mechanized as the friendship between pedlar and poet. The
                  elegy’s final musicality, moreover, recalls the thick silence of Keats’s “To
                  Autumn,” but even more, the emphasis on the “evening resting-place” literally
                     <emph>evens out</emph> the dwelling of poet and Armytage to the point where by
                  now, we watch them mutate to the point of failing, <emph>as figures</emph>, to
                  bear witness anymore to the human. Armytage falls into just this inhumanizing
                  trance when he speaks of how “so familiarly/Do I perceive her manner and her
                  look/And presence, and so deeply do I feel/Her goodness, that not seldom in my
                  walks/A momentary trance comes over me/And to myself I seem to muse on one/By
                  sorrow laid asleep or borne away,/A human being destined to awake/To human life,
                  or something very near/To human life, when he shall come again/For whom she
                  suffered” (365-375). The Christianizing redemption of these last lines
                  notwithstanding, Armytage’s trance also compels him (and us) to attend to the way
                  in which Margaret’s life becomes superfluous in the sense of becoming disposable,
                  not knowing whether she sleeps or is borne away, or to which “life,” human or not,
                  she is to awake. The interpassivity of her actions—suffering for Christ—suggests
                  that her own waiting is less expectation than a process of strange erosion
                  compelled by the elegy itself, one undertaken not in order simply to better
                  translate Margaret into the ground or virtualize her into the “secret spirit of
                  humanity” amid plants, weeds, and flowers, but rather to have us attend to her
                  indistinction, to a life that is not quite human—a “passing shew” that has yet to
                  awaken into <emph>a</emph> human life because she never experienced humanity in
                  the world at all. </p>
               <p> Affixed to this site, Armytage compulsively “clings” to Margaret’s ghostly
                  materiality as if she were a machine that spun him out into existence. In this
                  “tale of silent suffering, hardly clothed/In bodily form, and to the grosser
                  sense/But ill adapted, scaracely palpable/To him who does not think” (233-236),
                  narrative propulsion does seem to become, as Davd Simpson has powerfully argued, a
                  spectralized commodity itself that produces virtual figures and environments
                  hovering between tangibility and phantom-like invisibility—states of “bare life”
                  that testify to the buying and selling of mortality (<title level="m"
                     >Wordsworth</title>). But at the same time, Margaret’s thingification occurs
                  while she “wastes [her] time” (352), thus congealing her in debris and preventing
                  any investment in what Alan Liu has called the poem’s “capitalization upon
                  inhumanity” (325). Indeed, it isn’t clear if the commodification of labor has even
                  begun: Margaret’s “pac[ing] through many a day/Of the warm summer, from a belt of
                  flax/That girt her waist spinning the long-drawn thread” (459-462), which
                  foreshadows her eventual demise into a spirit of humanity, seems like a mode of
                  profligate dalliance. Deleuze would call this aspect of Wordsworth’s poem its
                     <emph>éspace</emph>
                  <emph>quelconque</emph>, or “whatever space”—a space denuded of human
                  participation, that endures not simply as the remnant of human life, but of life
                  itself in its state of desertion (<title level="m">Cinema</title>). After all,
                  garbage is precisely that which is prohibited, that which we ought not look at.
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="11">See Yaeger: “the binary trash/culture
                        has become more ethically charged and aesthetically interesting than the
                        binary nature/culture. In a world where nature is dominated, polluted,
                        pocketed, eco-touristed, warming, melting, bleaching, dissipating, and
                        fleeing toward the poles—detritus is both its curse and its alternative.
                        Trash is the becoming natural of culture, what culture, eating nature, tries
                        to cast away. In the midst of simulacra, it is also a substance in which we
                        can encounter decay and mortality” (339).</note>
                   And because we <emph>do</emph> look at it here, Wordsworth points to the
                  poem’s mise–en–scène, to the unrestful dwelling in rubbish that is brought into
                  the poem’s foreground as the environment that sticks around and cannot be
                  redeveloped. Although biblical images like the broken bowl imply a certain
                  predestined fulfillment of catastrophic prophecy, Wordsworth’s writing
                  concentrates on such images <emph>as</emph> rubbishy, irreparable
                     <emph>ready-unmades</emph> that block any kind of recuperating
                  interpretation—what Alphonso Lingis, in another context, calls “the empty
                  endurance of the void” (21). What Wordsworth points to, in my view, is
                  uncomfortably compelling: a reading of disaster in terms of a grief without grief,
                  a hope without hope, and a style of extraindividual, catastrophic aestheticization
                  that dwells beyond elegy. If <title level="m">The Ruined Cottage</title> evokes a
                  singular inhumanism in its lines of sympathetic attachment, it just as well
                  concentrates on the less palatable moments of unrest where the vulnerability of
                  persons catalyzes a kind of disastrous thought—one which turns women into things
                  and men into ruins. Persons are readily thingified, and the desire to treat
                  persons as things becomes a necessary component of Romantic modernity—to
                  recirculate persons in an aesthetic economy that cannot bear to possess or dwell
                  with anything, that treats persons as <emph>res nullius</emph>, and would have us
                  literally waste life.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>
               <listBibl>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Adorno, Theodor</author>
                        <author>Max Horkheimer</author>
                        <title level="m">Dialectic of Enlightenment</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Verso</publisher>
                           <date>1997</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Agamben, Giorgio</author>
                        <title level="m">The Coming Community</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Hardt, Michael</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Minneapolis</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Minnesota Press</publisher>
                           <date>1993</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  
                  
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Alpers, Paul J</author>
                        <title level="m">What is Pastoral?</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                           <date>1996</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  
                  
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Benjamin, Walter</author>
                        <title level="a">Surrealism: The Last Snapshot of the European
                           Intelligentsia</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Jephcott, Edmund</editor>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Selected Writings: Volume 2, 1927–1934</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Jennings, Michael</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Eiland, Michael</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Smith, Gary</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Belknap/Harvard University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1999</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">207–21</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Bewell, Alan</author>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Colonial Disease</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2000</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Blanchot, Maurice</author>
                        <title level="m">The Writing of the Disaster</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Smock, Ann</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
                           <date>1995</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Bloom, Harold</author>
                        <title level="a">Visionary Cinema of Romantic Poetry</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">The Ringers In The Tower: Studies in Romantic
                           Tradition</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                           <date>1971</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">37-52</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title><ref target="http://www.cred.be/">Center for Research on the
                              Epidemiology of Disaster (CRED)</ref></title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date type="access">2011-5-10</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Clark, Nigel</author>
                        <title level="a">Living Through the Tsunami: Vulnerability and Generosity On
                           a Volatile Earth</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Geoforum</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">38</biblScope>
                           <date>2007</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">1127-1139</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Collins, Douglas</author>
                        <title level="a">The Found Object</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Willamette Journal</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">1.1</biblScope>
                           <date>1983</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">43-74</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title><ref target="http://www.deep.med.miami.edu/x314.xml">The Deep
                              Center</ref></title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date type="access">2011-5-10</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Deleuze, Gilles</author>
                        <title level="m">Cinema: The Movement-Image</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Tomlinson, Hugh</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Habberjam, Barbara</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Minneapolis</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Minnesota Press</publisher>
                           <date>1989</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Deleuze, Gilles</author>
                        <author>Félix Guattari</author>
                        <title level="m">What is Philosophy?</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Tomlinson, Hugh</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Burchell, Graham</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1994</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Derrida, Jacques</author>
                        <title level="a">Hostipitality</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Angelaki</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>December 2000</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">3-18</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Edelman, Lee</author>
                        <title level="m">No Future: Queer Theory and the Death-Drive</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Durham</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2004</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Faflak, Joel</author>
                        <title level="a"><ref target="http://www.erudit.org/revue/ron/1999/v/n16/005883ar.html"
                              >Analysis Interminable in the Other Wordsworth</ref></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Romanticism On the Net</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date type="update">November 1999</date>
                           <date type="access">2011-5-10</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Faflak, Joel</author>
                        <title level="a">‘Was it for this?’: Romantic Psychiatry and the Addictive
                           Pleasures of Moral Management</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Pleasure: Disciplined Delights in British
                           Literary Culture, 1780-1830</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Faubert, Michelle</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Schmid, Tom</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York and London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Palgrave</publisher>
                           <date>forthcoming</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Fosso, Kurt</author>
                        <title level="a">Community and Mourning in William Wordsworth’s <emph>The
                              Ruined Cottage</emph>, 1797-1798</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Studies in Philology</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>Summer 1995</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">329-345</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Freedgood, Elaine</author>
                        <title level="u">"That People Might Be Like Things and Live."</title>
                     
                     
                        <imprint>
                           <publisher>Unpublished ms.</publisher>
                           <date>2009.</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Heidegger, Martin</author>
                        <title level="a">Building Dwelling Thinking</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Poetry, Language, Thought</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Hofstadter, Albert</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Perennial</publisher>
                           <date>1971</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">143-161</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Huet, Marie-Hélène</author>
                        <title level="a">The Face of Disaster</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Yale French Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">111</biblScope>
                           <date>2007</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">7-31</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Koolhaas, Rem</author>
                        <title level="a">Junkspace</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">October</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>Spring 2002</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">175-190</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>


                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Lingis, Alphonso</author>
                        <title level="a">Catastrophic Times</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Time and Value</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Lash, Scott</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Quick, Scott</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Roberts, Scott</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Blackwell</publisher>
                           <date>1998</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Liu, Alan</author>
                        <title level="m">Wordsworth: The Sense of History</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1988</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Mitchell, W.J.T</author>
                        <title level="a">Founding Objects</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">What Do Pictures Want?</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">111-124</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Modiano, Raimonda</author>
                        <title level="a">The Legacy of the Picturesque: Landscape, Property, and the
                           Ruin</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">The Politics of the Picturesque: Literature, Landscape and
                           Aesthetics since 1770</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Copley, Stephen</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Garside, Peter</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1994</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">196-219</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Morton, Timothy</author>
                        <title level="m">Ecology Without Nature: Rethinking Environmental
                           Aesthetics</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Potkay, Adam</author>
                        <title>Wordsworth and the Ethics of Things</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">PMLA </title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">123:2</biblScope>
                           <date>2008</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">390-404</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Rigby, Kate</author>
                        <title level="a">Ecstatic Dwelling</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Angelaki</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>August 2004</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">117-143</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Schor, Esther</author>
                        <title level="m">Bearing the Dead: The British Culture of Mourning from the
                           Enlightenment to Victoria</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1994</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Simpson, David</author>
                        <title level="m">Wordsworth, Commodification, and Social Concern</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2009</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Swann, Karen</author>
                        <title level="a">Suffering and Sensation in <title level="m">The Ruined
                              Cottage</title></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">PMLA</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>January 1991</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">83-95</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Terada, Rei</author>
                        <title level="a">Living a Ruined Life: De Quincey Beyond the Worst</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">European Romantic Review</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>April 2009</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">177–186</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Terada, Rei</author>
                        <title level="m">Looking Away: Phenomenality and Dissatisfaction, Kant to
                           Adorno</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2009</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Wordsworth, William</author>
                        <title level="a">Preface to <title level="m">Literary Ballads, with Other
                              Poems</title> (1800)</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Literary Criticism of William Wordsworth</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Zall, Paul M.</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
                           <date>1966</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">15-32</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Wordsworth, William</author>
                        <title level="m">The Poems: Volume One</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Hayden, John O.</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Penguin</publisher>
                           <date>1977</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Wordsworth, William</author>
                        <title level="m">The Prelude: 1799, 1805, 1850</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Wordsworth, Jonathan</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Abrams, M.H.</editor>
                        <editor role="editor">Gill, Stephen</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Norton</publisher>
                           <date>1979</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Wordsworth, William</author>
                        <title level="m">The Ruined Cottage and The Pedlar</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Butler, James</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Ithaca</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cornell University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1979</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                 
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>World Health Organization</author>
                        <title level="a"><ref target="http://www.who.int/en/">Hospitals Networking
                              in Disaster</ref></title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date type="access">2011-5-10</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Yaeger, Patricia</author>
                        <title level="a">The Death of Nature and the Apotheosis of Trash; or,
                           Rubbish Ecology</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">PMLA</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>March 2008</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">321-339</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
