<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">An Interview with Anne Mellor</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <author>
               <name>Anne Mellor</name>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <name>Roxanne Eberle</name>
            </editor>
            <editor role="editor">Roxanne Eberle</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">praxis.2013.eberle_intro</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce3070</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
               Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-04-01">April 1, 2013</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be
                  downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching,
                  and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
                  amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on
                  Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only
                  in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as
                  expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in
                  any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors
                  and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization
                  should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the
                  following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                        without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                        other than their current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in
                  order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that
                  of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
                  elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
                  resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the
                  only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of
                  course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our
                  conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Introduction</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Mellor</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Roxanne</forename>
                        <surname>Eberle</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" type="main">An Interview with Anne Mellor</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <editor>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Roxanne</forename>
                        <surname>Eberle</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2013-04-01">April 1, 2013</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>APEX used utf-8 codes for quotation marks, hyphens, and all
               special characters; except in the introduction, "hi rend="ital" has been used
               for titles.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
               10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smcap" scheme="css">font-variant:small-caps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5 #g18"/>
            <keywords scheme="http://www.rc.umd.edu/#tags">
               <list>
                  <item>Abstract here</item>
                  <item>Anne Mellor</item>
                  <item>Interview</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2013-03-19</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
         <head>Introduction</head>
         <byline>
            <docAuthor>Roxanne Eberle</docAuthor>
         <affiliation>University of Georgia</affiliation>
         </byline>
         <dateline>March 4, 2013</dateline>
         <p>Once upon a time (or so the story goes) only six male poets made up the field of British Romanticism, but in the mid-1980s, born out of the body of Anglo-American feminist scholarship, poststructuralism, and French psychoanalytical criticism, there emerged a counter narrative of literary production and achievement in the period. Anne Mellor was at the forefront of a group of scholars intent upon the recovery and critical engagement of Romantic women writers either neglected (Mary Wollstonecraft and Mary Shelley), misplaced (Jane Austen) or simply forgotten (Anna Barbauld, Charlotte Smith, Felicia Hemans, Letitia Landon, and myriad others). </p>
         <p>In the interview that follows, Mellor recounts her determined commitment to rethinking Romanticism through the lens of gender. Already the author of several books and articles on canonical male figures, including <title level="m">Blake’s Human Form Divine</title> (1974) and <title level="m">English Romantic Irony</title> (1980), the second stage of Mellor’s career began in 1988 with Routledge’s dual publication of <title level="m">Mary Shelley: Her Life, Her Fiction, Her Monsters</title> and <title level="m">Romanticism and Feminism. </title>The first volume set about reconsidering the literary output of Mary Shelley and was central in recovering her as a powerful author in her own right, rather than as William Godwin’s daughter or Percy Bysshe Shelley’s wife. <title level="m">Romanticism and Feminism</title> introduced readers to Mellor’s concept of masculine and feminine romanticism in a collection of essays on both male and female Romantic authors penned by influential critics including Stuart Curran, Alan Richardson, and Susan Wolfson. </p>
         <p>With the publication of <title level="m">Romanticism and Gender </title>(1993) and <title level="m">Mothers of the </title>
            <title level="m">Nation: women’s political writing in England, 1780-1830</title> (2000), Mellor offered scholars of the period critical analysis of texts long neglected (most notably perhaps Charlotte Smith’s novels and Letitia Landon’s poetry), even as she posed questions meant to urge readers towards further engagement with thorny critical questions: What difference <title level="m">does</title> gender make? What constituted a woman’s authority in the period, as author and social activist? Why shouldn’t we reclaim Hannah More as well as Mary Wollstonecraft?</p>
         <p>I first met Anne Mellor in 1986 as a graduate student at UCLA. It was impossible not to be caught up in her enthusiasm and she quickly swept away my preconceptions of the Romantic period. Although I had entered graduate school intent upon studying Virginia Woolf and Modernism, Anne’s lively seminars and vibrant commitment to this radically new concept of Romanticism changed my direction, as it would many others. </p>
         <p>The interview that follows took place about a year ago on a very sunny March afternoon in the living room of Anne’s Los Angeles home, which has also been the meeting place of the UCLA Romantic Study Group. We ranged widely over many topics, from Anne’s education and career to her thoughts about the current state of Romanticism, particularly in regards to feminist literary criticism and the ongoing recovery of women writers. Throughout our conversation Anne generously acknowledged her own teachers, even as she frequently brought recent work of her own students into the discussion. Although joyfully anticipating retirement, her continuing enthusiasm about classroom engagement was evident and she was deep into planning her first Jane Austen course. As I write this introduction several months later, Anne has taught her first Austen course, been honored by peers at NASSR, MLA and the Clark Library, and is more set then ever on a busy retirement. And yet, as the interview reveals, she retains her commitment to further developing our still relatively new narrative of Romanticism. In the audio clips attached to the transcription, Anne’s intellectual curiosity resonates, as her voice continues to prompt the reader to return to the texts, the archives, and the critical concerns of Feminist Romanticism. In Anne’s case “retirement” can only be considered a misnomer; her prodigious scholarly publication ensures that her voice will continue to change stories of Romanticism for all of us.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

