<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Romanticism, Forgery and the Credit Crunch</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
				<title level="a">Abstracts</title>

				<editor role="editor">Ian Haywood</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor,</resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
					<name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>abstracts</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
					Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
						or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
						purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
						use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
						are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
						with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
						permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
						requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
						forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
						conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
						them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
						have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
						Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
						continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
						a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
						use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Abstracts</title>

					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Romanticism, Forgery and the Credit Crunch</title>
						<title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
								Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2011-12-01">December 1, 2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for
						&#226;&#8364;&#339;," for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
						keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
						such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
						been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
					12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
						on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
				<keywords scheme="http://www.rc.umd.edu/#tags">
					<list>
						<item>[abstract] </item>
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Michael Quilligan</name>
				<date>2011-11-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="paratext">
				<head>Abstracts</head>
				<p rend="noCount"><quote rend="center"><ref target="#HaywoodAbstract">Ian
							Haywood</ref> | <ref target="#MilesAbstract">Robert Miles</ref> | <ref
							target="#BenchimolAbstract">Alex Benchimol</ref> | <ref
							target="#DickAbstract">Alex J. Dick</ref> | <ref target="#GroomAbstract"
							>Nick Groom</ref></quote></p>

				<!-- Authors, titles, and abstracts here -->
				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="HaywoodAbstract"/>Ian Haywood</hi>,
							<title level="a">Paper Promises: Restriction, Caricature, and the Ghost
							of Gold</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">The surge of scholarly interest in Romantic literary forgery
						has overlooked the impact of financial forgery on Romantic-era politics and
						culture. This essay uses James Gillray’s <title level="m">Midas</title>
						(1797) and William Hone and George Cruikshank’s <title level="m">Bank
							Restriction Note</title> (1819) as the basis for an investigation of the
						cultural and political repercussions of the 1797 Bank Restriction Act. The
						decision of Pitt’s government to end payment in gold and flood the economy
						with paper money was deeply unpopular. To begin with, it was seen as an act
						of fiscal incompetence and incontinence, as can be seen in Gillray’s
						scatological vision of Pitt as an inverted Midas figure showering the nation
						with cheap banknotes. Secondly, the Restriction Act led to a massive hike in
						executions for banknote forgery. The Bank of England’s prosecution of
						lower-class offenders provoked a public outcry at both the unreality of
						paper money and the harshness of the penal code. Cruikshank and Hone’s
						response to this controversy was the Bank Restriction Note, a mock banknote
						in which the normal symbols of the state have been replaced with macabre
						gallows humour. The essay concludes by proposing that caricature (sheets of
						paper satire) was the perfect medium for ridiculing the dubious authenticity
						of paper currency which was no longer anchored in the ‘real’ value of gold
						and silver.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.haywood.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="MilesAbstract"/>Robert Miles</hi>, <title
							level="a"><title level="m">Emma</title> and Bank Bills: Romanticism and
							Forgery</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">In his review of <title level="m">Emma</title> Walter Scott comments that Harriet
						Smith’s "facile affections" are transferred "like a bank bill by
						indorsation." The metaphor is doubly apt: it sums up Harriet while pointing
						to a peculiar feature of Austen’s <title>Emma</title>—its reliance on economic language
						to prosecute its themes. This reliance is not accidental but an expression
						of a fundamental aspect of Romantic-era culture: the consistent
						juxtaposition of contingency with an imagined "gold standard" that gives
						such contingency meaning. This essay argues that Jane Austen’s <title level="m">Emma</title> offers the reader a complex reflection on the
						interpenetration of economic and aesthetic systems of value that developed
						in the aftermath of the suspension of cash payments in 1797.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.miles.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="BenchimolAbstract"/>Alex Benchimol</hi>,
							<title level="a">Knowledge Against Paper: Forgery, State Violence and
							Radical Cultural Resistance in the Romantic Period</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">This essay firstly examines the strategy of radical education
						in the early nineteenth-century plebeian public sphere around the issue of
						paper money, illustrated by William Cobbett in his article series "Paper
						Against Gold," published in the <title level="j">Political Register</title>
						during 1810-11. Cobbett’s role as a counter-hegemonic intellectual in the
						series and the conception of popular knowledge it championed is highlighted,
						in part through his attempts to expose the complex workings of the wider
						financial system he described as a "place . . . of a sort of mysterious
						existence; a sort of Financial Ark; a place not, perhaps, to be touched, or
						even seen." The second part of the essay demonstrates how this form of
						critical publicity was transformed in the postwar years into an active
						project of resistance against the worst abuses of the paper money system,
						culminating in Cobbett’s "puff out" campaign in the <title level="j"
							>Register</title> to materially undermine Bank of England paper currency
						and T.J. Wooler’s print protests in <title level="j">The Black Dwarf</title>
						directly confronting the enforcement of the "bloody code" in the capital
						forgery trials of late 1818. This postwar print campaign against the paper
						money system illustrates key aspects of the wider radical intellectual
						project in the plebeian public sphere, highlighting how the radical press
						"converted" popular public debate into a new form of cultural currency in
						the Romantic period, a currency that emblematized a continuing concern for
						the material welfare of its readers and listeners in the face of a corrupt
						and bloody political and economic system.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.benchimol.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="DickAbstract"/>Alex J. Dick</hi>, <title
							level="a">Walter Scott and the Financial Crash of 1825: Fiction,
							Speculation, and the Standard of Value</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">Although radicals and economists had been attacking the fiscal
						“speculation” of the credit economy since the seventeenth century as akin to
						forgery and theft, many conservative commentators on Britain’s financial
						affairs embraced it as the source of the heroic and imaginative power of
						debt and credit. This essay reads Walter Scott’s <title level="m">Letters of
							Malachi Malagrowther and The Chronicles of the Canongate</title> as
						“speculative” responses to the financial crisis of 1825. Following a period
						of intense economic expansion, primarily in Latin America and mostly based
						on highly speculative development plans, and facing a sudden loss of
						confidence in the banking sectors, the British government and the Bank of
						England tested various forms of economic diversification. Rather than
						assuming total responsibility for the new debt loads, the banks, supported
						by legislation, converted it into a variety of repayment and deposit schemes
						in smaller institutions, including, for the first time, bank branches. But
						in Scotland, such schemes also entailed replacing an autonomous and thriving
						financial community. In the letters, Scott attempts to revive the idea of
						“speculation”—which I define as both an act of imagination and an act of
						seeing—against English models of economic diversification. <title level="m"
							>Chronicles</title> documents the failure of this speculative economy
						and replaces it with a tenuous if critical mode of socio-economic
						comparison.</p>
					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.dick.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

				<div>
					<head><hi rend="bold"><anchor xml:id="GroomAbstract"/>Nick Groom</hi>, <title
							level="a">Afterword: Forgery and the Credit Crunch</title></head>

					<p rend="noCount">This essay summarizes the essays in the collection. It places
						them in the context of recent work in authenticity studies, Romanticism, and
						the history of legal and financial forgery, and remarks on the current
						economic situation. The account concludes with suggestions for further
						avenues of research.</p>

					<p rend="noCount">[<ref target="praxis.2011.groom.html">go to
						essay</ref>]<lb/></p>
				</div>

			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
