<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Romanticism, Forgery and the Credit Crunch</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a">Paper Promises: Restriction, Caricature, and the Ghost of
               Gold</title>
            <author>
               <name>Ian Haywood</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">Ian Haywood</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.haywood</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Paper Promises: Restriction,
                     Caricature, and the Gghost of Gold</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Ian</forename>
                        <surname>Haywood</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Romanticism, Forgery and the Credit Crunch</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-12-01">December 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#226;&#8364;&#339;,"
                  for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
            <keywords scheme="http://www.rc.umd.edu/#tags">
               <list>
                  <item>This essay takes fresh look at the cultural and political impact of the Bank
                     of England’s suspension of cash payments between 1797 and 1821. The policy was
                     controversial for two main reasons: it led to a huge increase in executions for
                     making or handling fake banknotes, and it exposed the fictional core of the
                     capitalist faith in credit. I argue that of all Romantic cultural forms, it was
                     caricature—a “phoney” symbolic economy of plundered identities - which made the
                     most apposite, spectacular and intriguing response to this crisis of
                     representation.</item>
                  <item>Romanticism</item>
                  <item>forgery</item>
                  <item>caricature</item>
                  <item>credit</item>
                  <item>executions</item>
                  <item>Bloody Code</item>
                  <item>James Gillray</item>
                  <item>George Cruikshank</item>
                  <item>William Hone</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>Michael Quilligan</name>
            <date>2011-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <div type="essay">
            <head>
               <title level="a">Paper Promises: Restriction, Caricature, and the Ghost
                  of Gold</title>
            </head>

            <byline><docAuthor>Ian Haywood</docAuthor><affiliation>Roehampton
                  University</affiliation></byline>
            <div type="section">
               <head> </head>
               <p>The topic of literary forgery in the eighteenth century and Romantic period has
                  become something of a boom industry in the last few decades.<note place="foot"
                     resp="editors" n="1">From the list of studies in the Works Cited, see the
                     following: Haywood, <title level="m">The Making of History</title> and <title
                        level="m">Faking It</title>; Stafford; Gaskill; Baines; Ruthven; Groom,
                        <title level="m">Forger’s Shadow</title>; Groom, <title level="a"
                        >Romanticism and Forgery</title>; Russett; Lee, <title level="a"
                        >Forgeries</title>; Lee, <title level="m">Romantic Liars</title>;
                     Constantine; Lynch; Garvey; Miles; and Malton.</note> Since I published my own
                  studies on this theme in the 1980s (<title level="m">The Making of History</title>
                  and <title level="m">Faking It</title>), scholarly interest in this area has
                  burgeoned and has contributed much to the remapping and redefining of literary
                  history in this period. One reason for this renaissance is undoubtedly that the
                  eighteenth century is so rich in primary sources. The literary forgeries of the
                  “big three” still continue to fascinate scholars: I refer here of course to James
                  Macpherson, who invented an ancient Scottish epic poet called Ossian; Thomas
                  Chatterton, the boy wonder of Bristol who fabricated a series of poems and other
                  documents supposedly written in the fifteenth century; and William Henry Ireland,
                  who “discovered” a new play by Shakespeare, <title level="m">Vortigern and
                     Rowena</title>. Some of the scholarly interest in these figures and other
                  forgers has been motivated by nationalistic affiliations: the “Ossianic Celtic
                  revival” has produced solid studies by, among others, Fiona Stafford and Howard
                  Gaskill, while Mary Ann Constantine has recently championed the Welsh antiquarian
                  scholar-forger Iolo Morganwg (Edward Williams). Other work has perhaps been
                  stimulated by post-Foucauldian concerns about the vexed yet intriguing
                  relationship between creative authorship, originality, and authenticity. As Debbie
                  Lee notes in her chapter on <title level="a">Forgeries</title> in <title level="m"
                     >Romanticism: An Oxford Guide</title> (and this inclusion is itself symptomatic
                  of the resurgence I am describing), “One of the things impostors and forgers make
                  strikingly clear is the period’s idolatrous worship of authenticity and truth”
                  (521). Chief among the iconoclasts determined to expose Romanticism’s “idolatrous
                  worship of authenticity and truth” is Nick Groom, whose book <title level="m">The
                     Forger’s Shadow</title> (2002) represents the most sophisticated and searching
                  re-evaluation of the impact of forgery on our conceptions of authorship and
                  authenticity. Groom goes so far as to state that Romanticism “(for want of a
                  better term) would have been very different without literary forgery—indeed it may
                  not have recognisably existed at all” (<title level="m">Forger’s Shadow</title>
                  15); hence the subtitle of his book, <title level="a">How Forgery Changed the
                     Course of Literature.</title></p>
               <p>Groom’s book, together with recent studies by Debbie Lee, Margaret Russett, Jack
                  Lynch and Robert Miles provide clear evidence that forgery studies have expanded
                  well beyond those paradoxically-defined “original” fakes of the Big Three
                  (supposedly ancient or renowned works of the past actually authored in the present
                  and as such qualifying as new, “valid” creative texts). Forgery now embraces
                  aspects of canonical authors’ poetic practice (such as plagiarism), but
                  increasingly there is an interest in the colourful cases of exotic hoaxes and
                  imposture, a tradition which begins with the sprightly career of the “Formosan”
                  rogue George Psalmanazar. Indeed, the Romantic impostor has graduated into the
                  heroic performer of Butlerian, transgressive gender and identity politics, most
                  notably in the examples of Joanna Southcott (who claimed to be the bride of
                  Christ) and the servant Mary Wilcox/Baker, alias “Princess Caraboo of Javasu.” As
                  Groom remarks on Debbie Lee’s <title level="m">Romantic Liars: Obscure Women who
                     became Impostors and Challenged an Empire</title> (2006), “Lee’s impostors are
                  women who disguised themselves to create social opportunities, which they lacked
                  through gender and class prejudice” (<title level="a">Romanticism and
                     Forgery</title>). This cast of Romantic impostors continues to grow and is not
                  restricted to one gender. One important and lively figure whom Lee overlooks and
                  who takes the theme of forgery into the furthest regions of the British Empire is
                  George Barrington, a celebrated “Prince of pickpockets” who was transported to
                  Australia in 1791 where he supposedly wrote several pioneering biographical
                  accounts of Botany Bay and New South Wales. As Nathan Garvey’s excellent study
                  shows, these influential books were actually fabrications produced by unscrupulous
                  publishers cashing in on Barrington’s celebrity. </p>
               <p>As these examples demonstrate, the subversive credentials of forgery continue to
                  generate historical curiosity and scholarly passions. In Groom’s words, literary
                  forgers are “by turns spectral, mad, illegitimate and elusive; vilified,
                  criminalised, excluded from the canon” ("Romanticism and Forgery"). However, one
                  area of Romantic forgery which remains under-explored is financial forgery; to be
                  precise, the massive counterfeiting of banknotes which emerged from the credit
                  crisis of the Romantic period. The contemporary tone of the phrase “credit crisis”
                  is quite intentional, as there are some striking (if depressing) parallels between
                  the collapse of faith in paper money which occurred in the early nineteenth
                  century and the current desperate measures to restore faith in an international
                  monetary system based on credit and colossal levels of national debt. In one sense
                  this recurrence attests to Romanticism’s failure to prevent credit becoming (in
                  Brantlinger’s words) “a basic, unavoidable aspect of modern money and modern
                  economic processes” (139) yet, as Brantlinger’s fine study shows, the Romantic
                  period saw some of the most illuminating analyses of credit by both its supporters
                  (such as Coleridge) and its radical critics (such as Blake, Cobbett and Shelley)
                  (114-35). The stakes were extremely high: the controversy about credit struck not
                  only at the roots of national wealth and security but also at the emerging idea of
                  culture as a civilising force which both resisted and transcended commercialism.
                  “Paper” was therefore a massively ambiguous symbol of both the fraudulent power of
                  the state and the democratic medium of print culture and the press. If the problem
                  for Romantic writers was to try to reconcile this contradiction, one course of
                  action was relatively easy: if “paper” was illusory and dangerous, critics of
                  credit could restate their faith in “real” gold and silver. But a remaining
                  concern for “currency radicals” (Poovey 220) was that the rejection of what
                  Cobbett called the “paper promises” of a debt-ridden system did not necessarily
                  reveal a new source of value outside the (dis-credited) economy: what would be the
                  literary or cultural manifestation of the absent gold standard? Hence the Romantic
                  credit crisis may well have sharpened and deepened the Romantic quest for an
                  “egotistical sublime” and a redemptive concept of culture uncontaminated by
                  materialism, conformity and commodification (Williams, chapters 1-2).</p>
               <p>However, it was not the suspension of cash payments alone but another controversy
                  which pushed the paper-money scam to the forefront of public debate: the
                  spectacular increase in the number of executions for forgery. It was the severity
                  of Britain’s “bloody” penal code which heightened and inflamed public opinion
                  about the invidious connections between paper money and unreformed political
                  power. This theme has been neglected by scholars of both Romantic forgery and the
                  credit crisis, so it is to be hoped that the essays in this volume will open up
                  some new lines of investigation and provide some interesting case studies. For
                  opponents of paper money the public execution of hundreds of lower-class victims
                  of petty forgery crimes (the handling of fake one-pound banknotes) was a
                  spectacular display of the evils of an unreformed state which relied on a credit
                  economy to pursue its goals. As the essays in this volume show, the shockwaves of
                  these judicial crimes reverberate throughout the literature and culture of the
                  Regency period and beyond—all that is needed are the methodological sensors to
                  detect the tremors.</p>
               <p>My own interest in Romantic financial forgery takes up in a quite literal way the
                  idea that forgery spectacularized the contradictions of the credit economy. The
                  anti-hero of my essay is not the literary forger or bravura impostor but the
                  spectral figure of the engraver: the generic producer of, on the one hand, both
                  genuine and counterfeit currency and, on the other, the “shadow” economy of
                  popular graphic caricatures. By giving the forgery controversy a visual turn, I
                  show that Romantic-period anxieties about authenticity and value achieved a form
                  of visual apotheosis through the “formidable” power of the caricaturist (and the
                  source and significance of that word “formidable” will be revealed later). I
                  propose that Romantic-period caricature actually flourished within the credit and
                  forgery crisis, finding a fertile cultural climate for its own paper economy of
                  “fake” or falsifying representations, and exploring in an inimitably effective way
                  the dubious logic of a system built on “paper promises.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Romanticism and Restriction</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <quote>
                     <lg type="stanza">
                        <l rend="#indent2"> Of Augustus and Rome</l>
                        <l rend="#indent2">The poets still warble</l>
                        <l rend="#indent2">How he found it of brick</l>
                        <l rend="#indent2">And left it of marble.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
                  <quote>
                     <lg type="stanza">
                        <l rend="#indent2">So of Pitt and of England</l>
                        <l rend="#indent2">Men may say without vapour</l>
                        <l rend="#indent2">How he found it of gold</l>
                        <l rend="#indent2">And left it of paper.<note place="foot" resp="editors"
                              n="2">Cited Ehrman, 11.</note>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </epigraph>
               <p>On 25 February 1797, “a day which will long be remembered”, according to William
                  Cobbett (149), Prime Minister William Pitt went to see the King for an emergency
                  meeting. The country was in a state of national alarm, as news had just arrived of
                  a French invasion at Fishguard. In fact this turned out to be easily repelled
                     (<ref target="../images/figure1.jpg">Figure 1</ref>), but the incident forced
                  Pitt to consider an option he had resisted for some time. Fearing that there would
                  be a run on the Bank of England which would in turn damage the financing of the
                  war against France, he persuaded the King to issue (what turned out to be) a
                  momentous decree: starting immediately, the Bank would no longer issue specie
                  (cash or metal currency) in exchange for paper banknotes. The Bank Restriction
                  Act, as it later passed into law, is a somewhat misleading title, as it actually
                  led to a massive expansion of paper money. Specifically, the Act authorized the
                  mass production of new £1 and £2 banknotes to replace the withdrawn specie, and it
                  was this literal cheapening of the currency which would prove to be so disastrous
                  in its social consequences. The explosion of paper money was seized on immediately
                  by James Gillray, the period’s leading caricaturist. In his wonderful print <title
                     level="m">Midas</title>, published just a few weeks after Restriction came into
                  force (<ref target="../images/figure2.jpg">Figure 2</ref>), Pitt is shown as a
                  colossus squatting over the Rotunda of the Bank of England which serves him like a
                  toilet. From both his rear end and his mouth Pitt is showering the Bank with the
                  new low denomination notes which also make up his paper crown. We will return to
                  this image throughout this essay as it forms one of the most iconic responses to
                  the credit crisis, matched only by George Cruikshank’s <title level="m">Bank
                     Restriction Note</title> which we will meet shortly. Note that Gillray
                  foregrounds Pitt’s megalomania and plays down the culpability of the Bank:
                  obviously, at this very early stage he could not have foreseen the Bank’s role in
                  securing convictions for forgery and the ensuing public outrage this engendered.
                  Originally, Restriction was meant to last only six months, but as the credit
                  crisis persisted the Act was renewed continually until specie payment was
                  eventually reintroduced in 1821, by which time the national debt was an
                  astonishing £854 million, or 2.7 times the national income (O’Brien 179). During
                  its 24-year reign (which dovetails quite neatly with a large slice of the Romantic
                  period), Restriction provoked a storm of controversy which is still under-valued
                  in Romantic studies. Though the topic is mentioned in a number of books on
                  forgery, the issue of forgery remains marginal in the seminal studies of the role
                  of credit in British culture.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="3">See:
                     Brantlinger, chapters 2-3; Dick, “‘The Ghost of Gold’”; Malton, <title
                        level="m">Forgery, Fiscal Trauma, and the Fauntleroy Case</title>;
                     Gallagher, 17-19.</note> But in light of the fact that, as Margot Finn notes,
                  an “aversion to paper money” was “deeply rooted in Georgian England” (80) this
                  theme clearly deserves more exploration.</p>
               <p>There were two major problems with Restriction. The first was that it seemed to
                  undermine the very system of credit which it was supposedly safeguarding. Charles
                  James Fox called the stoppage of cash payments “the first day of our national
                  bankruptcy” (Richard, 1: 84). But, as we shall see, the Restriction crisis
                  actually exposed deeper contradictions which had bedevilled the British “financial
                  revolution” from its inception in the Restoration period (Dickson, chapters 1-2).
                  The second problem with Restriction was more visible and sensational: London (the
                  primary zone within which the new low denomination Bank of England notes
                  circulated) saw a massive increase in executions for forgery.<note place="foot"
                     resp="editors" n="4">The problem was focused on London as this was the main
                     zone within which Bank of England notes circulated. Outside of London most
                     people used the notes of private or “country” banks; these were still issuing
                     their own notes in the early twentieth century.</note> This catastrophe had
                  three main causes. First, the vulnerability and gullibility of the lower classes
                  who were unused to dealing with banknotes.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="5"
                     >Even one of the Restriction Act’s most fervent admirers had to admit that the
                     enforced introduction of banknotes into the “common class of people” could
                     cause “tumultuous proceedings” (Thornton, 114). According to Jerome
                     Christensen, a review of Thornton's book in the first issue of the <title
                        level="j">Edinburgh Review</title> was the first recognition of the
                     “revolutionary” impact of paper money on English history (619).</note> Before
                  this time forgery had been largely a white-collar crime. The best-known
                  eighteenth-century forger was probably the Reverend William Dodd, who was executed
                  in June 1777 for forging the signature of his former pupil Lord Chesterfield on a
                  banknote valued at £4,000. Despite Dr Johnson coming to his aid and writing his
                  pleas for clemency, and despite a large petition of 30,000 signatures in his
                  favour, Dodd went to the gallows. As Boswell puts it in his <title level="m">Life
                     of Johnson</title>, Dodd had committed “the most dangerous crime in a
                  commercial country” (828). </p>
               <p>The second contributing factor to the rise in Restriction forgery was the poor
                  quality of the banknotes which made them easily counterfeited (<ref
                     target="../images/figure3.jpg">Figure 3</ref>). The third factor was something
                  which Gillray could not have foreseen: the ruthlessness of the Bank of England -
                  the “head of all circulation” - in prosecuting offenders.<note place="foot"
                     resp="editors" n="6">The Bank was called the “head of all circulation” by the
                     Secret Committee of the House of Lords, April 1797 (cited in Ehrman, 7).</note>
                  Indeed, the Bank employed a team of lawyers at great expense to ensure
                  prosecutions. The statistics are dramatic: the period 1783-97 saw only four
                  prosecutions for forgery, but 1797-1821 (the Restriction period) saw over 2000
                  prosecutions and over 300 executions. The Bank spent thousands of pounds to secure
                  these executions, and in some years such as 1819 this amounted to more than was
                  lost through forgery (McGowen para 4). Almost one third of all executions at this
                  time were for forgery, but the vast majority of these were concentrated in the
                  post-Napoleonic war period, when economic depression and demobilization of
                  thousands of troops and sailors produced ever greater incentives for the forger
                  (Handler, <title level="a">Forging the Agenda</title>). When the government
                  reneged on the original promise to abolish Restriction after six months of peace
                  (which eventually came in 1815), public hostility to the growing body count of
                  convicted forgers and handlers (or “utterers”) became vitriolic. James Mackintosh
                  spoke in parliament of the “course of guilt and blood which had followed the
                  stoppage of cash payments”<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="7">Cited in
                     Handler, <title level="m">Forging the Agenda</title>, 256.</note> while Henry
                  Brougham railed at the “human sacrifices to the Moloch of Paper Credit.”<note
                     place="foot" resp="editors" n="8">Henry Brougham, review of <title level="m"
                        >Returns of Prosecutions and Convictions for Forging Notes of the Bank of
                        England from 1783 to 1813</title>, <title level="j">Edinburgh Review</title>
                     1818; cited in Dick, <title level="a">The Ghost of Gold,</title> 390.</note>
                  The resurgent radical press—perhaps drawing on memories of similar injustices
                  against the plebeian body, such as the Waltham Black Acts against poaching, or the
                  widespread practice of press-ganging and crimping - persistently and sensationally
                  exposed the injustices of the forgery trials. Thomas Wooler’s <title level="m"
                     >Black Dwarf</title> declaimed that “<emph>homicide</emph> has been
                     <emph>legalized</emph>” to defend “the <emph>paper bubbles</emph> which are
                  dignified with the name of <emph>currency</emph>” (2 [9 September 1818], 561). In
                  1818, when almost 30,000 fake banknotes were in circulation, public sympathy for
                  the hapless plebeian forger led to numerous acquittals.<note place="foot"
                     resp="editors" n="9">See <title level="m">Black Dwarf</title>, 2 [23 September
                     1818], 593-601, 2 [9 December 1818], 769- 775; <title level="j">Times</title>,
                     9 December 1818. For a fuller discussion of <title level="m">Black
                        Dwarf</title>’s campaigning zeal, see Alex Benchimol’s essay in this
                     volume.</note> Doubts were also expressed about the competence of the Bank of
                  England in recognising a fake from the real banknote. As early as 1814 an
                  anonymous caricature called <title level="m">A Peep into the Rag Shop in
                     Threadneedle Street</title> highlighted this theme. The print shows a poor
                  forger pleading with Bank of England directors who are examining a bank note. As
                  the speech bubbles make clear, behind their callous bluster is dire ineptitude: <quote>
                     <emph>“Upon my soul I have my doubts but at all events—we had better declare it
                        bad.”<lb/> “Take him out Thomas !!! he has a d----d hanging lok.”<lb/> “Away
                        with the Vagabond! Do you think we sit here for nothing!”</emph>
                  </quote> By the late 1810s, therefore, forgery was no longer, in Handler’s words,
                  a “uniquely subversive” crime which undermined what William Wilberforce called the
                  “vital principle of a commercial nation”, but a dramatic exposure of the
                  eighteenth-century “bloody code” (Handler, <title level="a">Forging the
                     Agenda,</title> 264, 263). The response of both the Bank of England and the
                  government to this barrage of criticism was characteristically insensitive: rather
                  than campaigning for leniency, they both launched inquiries aimed at finding a
                  foolproof or “inimitable” design for the banknote. However, the clamour of public
                  opinion was proving to be a formidable force and in 1819 official moves began to
                  review both Restriction and capital punishment.</p>
               <p>There could have been no timelier a moment than January 1819, therefore, for the
                  radical publisher William Hone and the leading Regency caricaturist George
                  Cruikshank to issue their own “inimitable” contribution to the Restriction
                  controversy. The <title level="m">Bank Restriction Note</title> and its companion
                  piece the <title level="m">Bank Restriction Barometer</title> (<ref
                     target="../images/figure4.jpg">Figures 4</ref> and <ref
                     target="../images/figure5.jpg">5</ref>) were published just days after the Bank
                  of England’s inquiry concluded that a forgery-proof design had to be robust enough
                  to withstand the “formidable power of imitation” of the engraver (<title level="j"
                     >Times</title>, 27 January 1819). Hone and Cruikshank undoubtedly appreciated
                  this ironic tribute to their joint production, as the <title level="m">Bank
                     Restriction Note</title> takes the form of a mock-submission to the
                     inquiry.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="10">See Patten 1: 146-7. Hone
                     claimed that he composed the basic visual design for the <title level="m">Bank
                        Restriction Note</title> and though Patten is sceptical about this claim he
                     speculates that Hone may well have designed the companion print <title
                        level="m">Bank Restriction Barometer</title>. See also 1: 157-8, 186.</note>
                  Unlike earlier satirical banknotes which resembled actual counterfeits (<ref
                     target="../images/figure6.jpg">Figure 6</ref>), the Hone-Cruikshank caricature
                  is more than just a “formidable” imitation which exposes the flimsy authenticity
                  of the original. By using visceral and witty gallows symbolism, Hone and
                  Cruikshank inscribed into the banknote the catastrophic social consequences of its
                  circulation: what <title level="m">Black Dwarf</title> called the “blood-cemented
                  fabric of paper currency” (2 [14 October 1818], 611). Reminiscent of the “blood
                  sugar” anti-slavery propaganda of the 1790s, the <title level="m">Bank Restriction
                     Note</title> defamiliarizes and demonizes everyday consumption, transforming
                  banknotes into emblems of blood money: satirically, this is their true appearance
                  and true value (the Bank’s role as surrogate executioner is evidenced by the
                  replacement of its clerks’ signature with that of Jack Ketch, the notorious
                  hangman of the 1680s).</p>
               <p>The national calamity of Restriction can be gauged by comparing Gillray’s
                  efflorescent vision of paper-money inflation with Hone and Cruikshank’s single
                  banknote: with hindsight, Pitt becomes an apocalyptic monster of destruction,
                  spewing out seemingly innocuous and ephemeral scraps of paper which are actually
                  seeds of future calamity. Put another way, Pitt is spreading his malign influence
                  over the Bank to ensure its compliance in devastating the lower classes, those
                  absent or proleptic victims of the new dispensation (Pitt puts John Bull in the
                  Rotunda but he is clearly incongruous). The Midas legend is brilliantly if
                  ironically apt, as the new notes will bring death to those who touch them and
                  ‘restrict’ the body politic in the most debased way possible. Seen in conjunction
                  with Cruikshank’s caricature, the full significance of the catastrophic
                  transformation of “value” under Restriction becomes terrifyingly apparent. In a
                  series of mock-mythic metamorphoses, a whole national narrative of modernity and
                  progress is unravelled: gold transmutes into paper, paper into its forged
                  “shadow”, and this phantom form of circulation is re-incarnated into the “blood”
                  of the nation, an inverted symbol of national well-being. The function of currency
                  as both the literal and symbolic signifier of national wealth and security is
                  systematically dis-credited by satirically re-encoding its semiotic processes as
                  both fantastical and lethal—as if currency is the Gothic alter-ego of caricature
                  itself.</p>
               <p>The Hone-Cruikshank prints were an instant success and undoubtedly contributed to
                  raising or inflaming public awareness about the evils of both paper money and
                  capital punishment.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="11">The British Museum has
                     a copy of the Bank Restriction Note in its display of paper currency.</note>
                  Significantly, it was in 1819 that Peel’s Act finally promised the restoration of
                  specie payment by 1823 (though this was achieved by 1821, when Britain formally
                  adopted the gold standard), and during the same year a parliamentary inquiry into
                  capital punishment focused on forgery as one of the main reasons for reforming
                  Britain’s harsh penal code. In his old age Cruikshank claimed that his print had
                  single-handedly led to the abolition of the death penalty for forgery 13 years
                  later, an exaggeration though a forgivable one.<note place="foot" resp="editors"
                     n="12">See Handler, “Forgery and the End of the ‘Bloody Code’”; Hackwood, 199,
                     201-3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But the spectacular achievements of the <title level="m">Bank Restriction
                     Note</title> should not be allowed to overshadow the quiet power of its
                  companion print the <title level="m">Bank Restriction Barometer</title>. Clearly,
                  this print takes a different approach to its companion piece’s mimetic wit. At
                  first sight the <title level="m">Barometer</title> appears to be a simple visual
                  illustration of the radical argument that over-investment in paper currency leads
                  to national ruin, but the satirical dynamic is more complex than this. Many
                  viewers in 1819 would have recognised that the print was a close parody of the
                  Evangelical spiritual barometer of the late eighteenth century (<ref
                     target="../images/figure7.jpg">Figure 7</ref>). In the caricature, the salutary
                  function of the vertical scale is inverted: the overheated economy replaces
                  sublime spiritual redemption and the gravitational security of gold replaces the
                  sins of the flesh (and note that novel reading is calibrated at minus 40!). This
                  parodic allusion makes clear that the satirical target of the <title level="m"
                     >Barometer</title> is the quasi-religious “faith” in paper money which, as we
                  shall see, both underpinned and troubled the “financial revolution” from its
                  Williamite origins. But the process of allusion does not end there, as the
                  spiritual barometer first appears in Hogarth’s anti-Methodist caricature <title
                     level="m">Enthusiasm Delineated</title> (<ref target="../images/figure8.jpg"
                     >Figure 8</ref>). The echo of Hogarth is, I believe, a self-authorizing
                  reference to the English caricature tradition which first accrued substantial
                  cultural authority by critiquing the new monied interest of the early eighteenth
                  century. Like the fake banknote, the satirical print shadowed, mirrored and
                  exposed the new credit economy throughout its history.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Gold into Paper</head>
               <p>The Restriction controversy was the breaking point of an ideological instability
                  which lay at the heart of the paper money system. If the Romantic period was
                  haunted by what Shelley in <title level="m">The Mask of Anarchy</title> called the
                  “ghost of gold”,<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="13">As Ehrman shows, over
                     two thousand tons of copper coins were minted in the first three years of
                     Restriction (13), but low valuation copper coins did not carry the same
                     symbolic significance as the evanescent gold and silver. As John Clapham
                     remarks, “gradually the age became one of banknotes” (2: 4).</note> the earlier
                  eighteenth century was haunted by the transubstantiation of paper. When Charles
                  James Fox remarked that “the solidity of Notes consisted in their being
                  convertible into cash” (<title level="j">Times</title>, 1 March 1797), he
                  identified that magical process of transformation which underpinned the credit
                  economy and which could maintain the illusion that banknotes were “solid” rather
                  than ephemeral and insubstantial. To its many critics, Pitt’s Restriction Act of
                  1797 jeopardised the nation by undermining the system of credit and national debt
                  which it was supposedly trying to protect. It was this system of deferred payment
                  which lay behind the creation of the Bank of England in 1694 and which allowed
                  Britain to finance wars and imperial gains well beyond its actual stock of
                  bullion—as Roy Porter puts it succinctly, “Britannia”s wars were won on credit”
                  (132). The genius of the “financial revolution” was that it utilized the
                  foundational economic metaphor of circulation to naturalize and anthropomorphize
                     convertibility:<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="14">According to David
                     Trotter, the metaphor of circulation was the “vital principle” of the
                     eighteenth-century analysis of wealth (62). See also Klancher, 31-4.</note> In
                  this imaginary, paper money is the blood which periodically returns to the heart
                  (the Bank’s bullion), to be then pumped out into further circulation, revitalized
                  with “real” value. In the words of one of Thomas Love Peacock’s <title level="m"
                     >Paper Money Lyrics</title>: <quote>
                     <lg type="stanza">
                        <l rend="#indent2">The paper money goes about, by one, and two, and
                           five,</l>
                        <l rend="#indent2">A circulation like the blood, that keeps the land alive.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="15">“A Mood of My Own Mind”, in
                              Peacock, 16.</note>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote> According to the circulatory or anatomical model, the body politic
                  functions healthily so long as this flow of money is neither “restricted” nor
                  inundated: if one nightmare is economic starvation (as seen in the stereotype of
                  the emaciated French), the other danger—as Gillray imagines—is the inflationary
                  overproduction of worthless and wasteful currency. Another way to read Gillray’s
                     <title level="m">Midas</title> is as a scatological parody of the famous cover
                  illustration to Thomas Hobbes’ <title level="m">Leviathan</title> (<ref
                     target="../images/figure9.jpg">Figure 9</ref>): instead of the monarch
                  comprised of his people, Pitt’s body is a sack of secreted and hoarded gold; the
                  literal and symbolic wealth of the nation becomes the tyrant’s booty, replacing
                  citizens with financial chicanery (Pitt’s incontinent largesse also, unavoidably,
                  brings the current dis-credited euphemism “quantitative easing” to mind). However,
                  behind Gillray’s scatological effects lies a more acute point: by evoking the
                  Midas legend, Gillray exposed the alchemical delusions and perils of the myth of
                  convertibility—indeed, the critique was anticipated in a print of 1796 (<ref
                     target="../images/figure10.jpg">Figure 10</ref>) which shows Pitt as a
                  megalomaniac alchemist who is converting the national wealth into a throne for
                  himself. As Gillray understood, it was the magical properties of paper money which
                  mystified both economic and political power. Even political economists (whether
                  supportive or not) invariably resorted to pre-enlightenment tropes of what Marx
                  called “primitive economic superstition” (261): alchemy, allegory, magic, blind
                  allegiance. Debacles like the South Sea Bubble and the John Law Mississippi scheme
                  (both collapsed in 1720) fuelled the idea that paper credit was a powerful and
                  potentially dangerous illusion.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="16">In an
                     essay on Defoe, Srinivas Aravamudan notes of these debacles that “Paper was
                     chasing paper without proper collateral” (54).</note> Daniel Defoe referred to
                  paper money as a “chimera”; Thomas Mortimer called credit a “standing miracle in
                  politics, which at once astonishes and over-awes the states of Europe” while later
                  in the century Benjamin Franklin boasted that the “wonderful machine” of “paper
                  currency” (in this case the dollar) had enabled America to defeat Britain.<note
                     place="foot" resp="editors" n="17">Defoe is cited in Shell, 68; Mortimer is
                     cited in Dickson, 154. Defoe also called credit “Air Money,” anticipating both
                     Adam Smith and Gillray: see Lynch, 96. Such anxieties can even be found at the
                     inception of western responses to paper money. When Marco Polo reported that
                     paper money was used in the city of Cambaluc in China, he commented that the
                     Emperor must have a power like a “perfect alchemist” (cited in Shell, 13,
                     n.10). The 14th-century Chinese experiment in paper money collapsed after just
                     a few decades when the Ming dynasty’s attempt to replace metal with banknotes
                     resulted in hyper-inflation: see the discussion of the Ming banknote in the
                     Radio 4 series <title level="m">History of the World in One Hundred
                        Objects</title>.</note></p>
               <p>Like its over-valued material form, the ideological “miracle” of paper credit
                  required constant investment and re-investment. For all its glaring conceptual
                  weaknesses, the financial revolution became an epistemological revolution: in
                  Pocock’s words, the switch to deferred payment was a “momentous intellectual
                  event.” By locating value in an endlessly receding future, credit changed the
                  whole basis of the individual’s relationship with the state, replacing civic
                  humanist duty with an “imagined” community of desiring individuals.<note
                     place="foot" resp="editors" n="18">Pocock, 108 and chapter 6
                        <foreign>passim</foreign>. See also Torre, 4-5, 48, 162.</note> As
                  Brantlinger has shown, this destabilization of what Marx called species being
                  (though perhaps “specie being” is a more appropriate coinage in the current
                  context) both afflicted and empowered the literary imagination (114-35). At the
                  same time as the new monied interest became a regular target for satire, attempts
                  to relocate value outside of the paper economy proved to be difficult and often
                  equally reliant on cultural mythologies: Romanticism’s resort to primitivism
                  (Wordsworth’s “natural” language of the lower classes), and radical nostalgia
                  (Cobbett’s banknoteless past) are just two prominent examples.</p>
               <p>Alchemical or transubstantiational delusions were not the only obstacles
                  preventing the full assimilation of paper money into Enlightenment modernity. The
                  “momentous” transition to the credit economy was also undermined by the spectre of
                  forgery. This was both a literal and figurative threat. From its inception, paper
                  money was shadowed by forgery: the first fake banknotes appeared in 1695 within
                  months of the genuine issue.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="19">Mackenzie,
                     chapter 1. Jack Lynch refers colourfully to “a strange arms race between the
                     legitimate issuers of banknotes and the counterfeiters” (139).</note> But the
                  greater damage was ideological, as forgery exposed the essentially imaginary or
                  fictive status of the supposedly authentic original (and it is worth a reminder
                  that a banknote is of course a simulacrum, a copy of a non-existent originating
                  source; there is no such thing, except conceptually, as a unique, single banknote
                  from which copies (legal or illegal) are taken). As Paul Baines notes, “The whole
                  system could be typified by the forgery it naturally engendered” (14). Faced with
                  this perplexing intimacy between financial good and evil, the difference between
                  supporters and critics of the new “system” could only be theological: supporters
                  believed the fiction (or refused to question it), critics exposed it.</p>
               <p>A characteristically ambivalent attitude to paper money can be seen in Joseph
                  Addison’s third <title level="j">Spectator</title> essay (Saturday 3 March 1711).
                  The essay takes the form of an allegorical dream vision of the goddess Credit, a
                  deity who sits on a throne in the Bank of England, surrounded by “a prodigious
                  heap of bags of money” and pyramids of gold piled to the ceiling. It is likely
                  that Addison is alluding to the image of Britannia “sitting and looking on a Bank
                  on Money” which was the logo of banknotes from their earliest issue (Keyworth) and
                  which reassuringly emblematized the “real” value of the note in bullion. Hence
                  Addison likens Credit to the “Lydian king”; Credit can “convert whatever she
                  pleased into that precious metal”—in other words she is a transgendered Midas who
                  guarantees the nation’s wealth with her miraculous powers of transformation.
                  However, at the first sign of political and social unrest the goddess shrivels
                  into a skeleton, the bullion becomes “bags full of wind” and the gold changes into
                  “heaps of paper.” Only when order is restored is the goddess resuscitated and
                  restored to her former beautiful but “delicate” constitution (<title level="j">The
                     Spectator</title>, 1: 17-20). </p>
               <p>Addison’s nervous allegory of the politically unstable rise of paper rule (a “bag
                  full of wind”) was a vivid and influential expression of residual Enlightenment
                  scepticism towards the new faith of “speculative fantasy” (Nicholson 10).
                  Alexander Pope delivered a poetic broadside against the new orthodoxy in <title
                     level="m">Epistle III: To Allen Lord Bathurst</title> (1733-4): <quote>
                     <lg type="stanza">
                        <l rend="#indent2">Blest paper-credit! last and best supply! </l>
                        <l rend="#indent2">That lends Corruption lighter wings to fly! (Butt, 254;
                           lines 69-70)</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote> David Hume referred to paper credit as “counterfeit money” (173), while
                  Adam Smith in <title level="m">The Wealth of Nations</title> had to apologize for
                  using “so violent a metaphor” when he compared paper credit to “a sort of
                  waggon-way through the air”, a fantasy of elevated economic activity which he was
                  obliged to qualify by reworking Pope’s trope of tainted flight: <quote>The
                     commerce and industry of the country, however, it must be acknowledged, though
                     they may be somewhat augmented, cannot be altogether so secure, when they are
                     thus, as it were, suspended upon the Daedalian wings of paper money, as when
                     they travel about upon the solid ground of gold and silver. (1: 484)</quote> If
                  the Midas legend provided an aptly mythological vehicle for dramatising the
                  miraculous powers of convertibility, the Icarus myth added the elements of
                  ambition, risk and catastrophic failure. The perils of putting all the nation’s
                  financial eggs into the flimsy basket of credit became only too apparent in the
                  Gordon riots of June 1780. When the Bank of England was attacked, the country
                  faced the prospect of financial ruin: <quote> Let any rational mind figure to
                     itself the confusion that must have ensued, the ruin that would have been
                     spread, the distresses in which orphans, widows, natives, and foreigners,
                     persons of all ranks and conditions, in whatever station, in whatever
                     employment, would have been involved, by the annihilation of so many hundreds
                     of millions of property, and the total abolition of all public credit! Who can
                     but for a moment think on the danger, without looking up to heaven in grateful
                     acknowledgment to the Supreme Being for so signal a national deliverance?
                        (<title level="j">Gentleman’s Magazine</title>, 50 [July 1780], 312)
                  </quote> But if “public credit” narrowly survived the century’s worst outbreak of
                  civil disorder, it faced an even greater threat in the wake of French revolution.
                  On this occasion, the price to be paid for “national deliverance” was regarded by
                  many observers as unacceptably high. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="section">
               <head>John Bullion</head>

               <p>By the revolutionary 1790s, the idea that “public credit” faced an imminent
                  “Daedalian” disaster became a powerful rhetorical tool in anti-government writing.
                  In <title level="m">The Rights of Man</title> (1791-2), Thomas Paine noted that
                  the “English system of funding” was close to bankruptcy; in order to finance
                  overseas conflicts, Britain was “increasing paper till there is no money left”
                  (133). As the war-torn decade progressed and the national debt grew, Paine
                  realised that the principle of convertibility was about to collapse. From this
                  point on, radical discourse configured paper and gold as class enemies. In his
                  pamphlet <title level="m">Decline of the English System of Finance</title>,
                  published one year before Restriction in 1796, Paine predicted that gold and
                  silver were about to “revolt against depreciation and separate from the value of
                  paper”, in the process destroying the “popular delusion” of the credit system
                  (Foner, 2: 661, 651-2).<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="20">In one of the many
                     ripostes to Paine’s tract, Ralph Broome admitted that “In trusting to private
                     paper money, we certainly do very often trust to a shadow” (37).</note> The
                  Restriction Act must have seemed to many a fulfilment of this prophecy and a major
                  boost for the radical critique. The iconoclastic discourse of transparency
                  penetrated so deep into radical thought that it can even be found in a fugitive
                  document issued by the shadowy insurrectionary group the United Britons in 1799.
                  The document calls the English political system as an enormous “Fraud” and adds
                  that <quote> Amidst mock Contentions for Liberty, and real ones for Plunder,
                     [England] vainly imagined herself free, and was thereby induced to pay the
                     Interest of a Debt of greater Amount than the Value of the whole landed
                     Property of the Country, without reflecting that Bankruptcy, however late, must
                     be the consequence of an overstretched Credit. That Bankruptcy has arrived.
                        (<title level="m">Report of the Committee of Secrecy</title>,
                  68)</quote></p>

               <p>Alongside the oppositional analysis, caricature added its own distinctive
                  contribution to the debunking of credit by imagining a new national narrative of
                  conflict between the people and the government: John Bullion versus Paper Pitt. In
                     <title level="m">Bank Notes</title> (1 March 1797), Gillray’s first response to
                  the Restriction Act, John Bull is a hapless yokel caught between the insidious
                  “bullionist” temptations of the Jacobin Foxites and the spectacular “paper”
                  rip-off of Pitt and his ministers (<ref target="../images/figure11.jpg">Figure
                     11</ref>). Characteristically, Gillray mocks all three parties and leaves the
                  viewer uncertain about which is the greatest offence: Fox’s disloyalty, Pitt’s
                  tyranny, or Bull’s idiocy. Bull decides “a’ may as well let my Measter Billy hold
                  the Gold to keep away you Frenchmen, as save it, to gee it you, when ye come over,
                  with your domn’d invasion”, but this reluctant compliance with the lesser evil
                  does not defuse the satirical gusto with which Gillray depicts the “delusion” of
                  paper money: the stash of padlocked money bags beneath Pitt’s counter constitutes
                  both a mock-patriotic bulwark against the French and a new symbol of centralised
                  state power (hence in <title level="m">Midas</title> one such money bag is used
                  for Pitt’s body). The hapless Bull fails to notice that in the background
                  ministers are delivering sacks of increasingly low-denominational notes (including
                  one labelled “one shilling”). Their worthlessness is brilliantly echoed in Pitt’s
                  use of an inflationary scoop, a satirical inversion of the Bank of England’s
                  supposedly authoritative and measured release of currency into the economy. Seen
                  alongside <title level="m">Midas</title>, this print anticipates the dangerous
                  consequences of the Restriction Act for the plebeian classes: in another telling
                  touch, John Bull’s coat-buttons look perilously like gold coins, a tempting prize
                  for the voraciously asset-stripping government. Before very long, as we shall see,
                  the caricature narrative of John Bullion’s victimization will take on a much more
                  violent form.</p>
               <p>As the cases of forgery multiplied and Restriction became more and more unpopular,
                  the lethal rift between “real” money and paper “delusion” became increasingly
                  exposed in both radical polemic and the caricature imagination. The most
                  successful single radical intervention was almost certainly William Cobbett’s
                  bestseller <title level="m">Paper against Gold</title>, first published in his
                  newspaper the <title level="j">Weekly Register</title> as a series of open
                  letters, and subsequently issued in book form in 1815. Cobbett argued that only
                  “real money” had “real value” (96), but in stating this he was only echoing the
                  Bullion Committee report of 1810 which called cash payments the “natural and true
                  control” against paper inflation.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="21"><title
                        level="m">Report from the Select Committee on the High Price of
                        Bullion</title> (8 June 1810), cited in Cannan, 66. Poovey argues that
                     Cobbett used the mode of direct address to his readers as a way to subvert the
                     impersonal paper economy of commercial print culture (181-96).</note> This
                  re-naturalization of gold and demonization of paper gave an additional force to
                  Hone and Cruikshank’s debunking of the official iconography of the nation state in
                  their <title level="m">Restriction Bank Note</title>. Instead of depicting
                  Britannia staring at a beehive, a symbol of industriousness which replaced the
                  earlier pile of gold, the satirical Britannia is shown as an unnatural mother
                  eating her children, an apt illustration of the state’s dereliction of duty (<ref
                     target="../images/figure12.jpg">Figure 12</ref>). Reminiscent of the
                  liberticidal monsters of anti-Jacobin caricatures, this grotesque figure reveals
                  that such symbols of authority are now (in Cobbett’s words) a mere “paper promise”
                  of “real value” (98). As Gillray’s successor, Cruikshank was able to see the
                  Restriction narrative through to its grisly end: the cannibalistic Britannia is
                  the tragic climax to the paper assault on John Bullion. The bloated Midas has
                  transmuted into the vampiric mother, and forgery executions are both a literal and
                  symbolic destruction of the democratic body of the nation. </p>
               <p>A more optimistic note is struck in another caricature which Cruikshank issued in
                  January 1819. <title level="m">Johnny Bull and his Forged Notes!! or Rags and Ruin
                     in the Paper Currency</title> shows John Bull as a small tradesman rather than
                  a plebeian or yokel (<ref target="../images/figure13.jpg">Figure 13</ref>). He is
                  about to be arrested in his impoverished home for hoarding forged banknotes, but
                  as he says to the foppish inspector, “I took all these notes in the way of Trade—I
                  can’t tell Bad Good ones from Good Bad ones. Even those who issue them are
                  frequently mistaken &amp; have been deceived by Forgeries.” The debunking of paper
                  money is wittily conceived by reducing the bank notes to combustible paper—this is
                  now their only value. But the most important feature of this print is its
                  portrayal of the Bull family. Far from being abject, Johnny Bull is defiant,
                  sturdy, patriarchal and ruggedly masculine. He is the personification of the moral
                  gold standard, the “real value” of the national character, and he is protecting
                  his “little platoon” against a cowardly and intrusive government. His defiance
                  reflects the resurgent mass radicalism of the post-war years which later in 1819
                  will confront the repressive state apparatus at Peterloo. His self-belief is a
                  striking riposte to the more familiar caricature figure of a disempowered John
                  Bullion who is constantly duped, plundered and violated by a paper system of
                  taxes, bills and cheap banknotes. The most striking examples of this extreme
                  exploitation of John Bullion are probably Richard Newton’s <title level="m">The
                     New Paper Mill</title> and <title level="m">The Inexhaustible Mine</title>,
                  both published in 1797 as a response to Restriction (<ref
                     target="../images/figure14.jpg">Figures 14</ref> and <ref
                     target="../images/figure15.jpg">15</ref>). In <title level="m">The New Paper
                     Mill</title> Bull is being minced by Pitt into paper notes (presumably having
                  been stripped of his gold first, though allegorically Bull himself represents
                  “real” money); in the brutal Restriction age, Pitt’s mincer is the modern state’s
                  industrially efficient yet banal replacement for the alchemical bravura of
                  convertibility. <title level="m">The Inexhaustible Mine</title> is an
                  eye-catching, quasi-pornographic inversion of Gillray’s <title level="m"
                     >Midas</title>. John Bull’s spouting orifices are not scatologically rendered:
                  they are the result of a violation which conflates a gang-rape, a mugging and a
                  strip search. The image captures the repressive authoritarianism of
                  counter-revolutionary policy in the 1790s, a period in which “the spirit of
                  despotism” led to “invasions of privacy” (Barrell). With these images (and many
                  others) in mind,<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="22">See for example <title
                        level="m">John Bull at His Studies</title> (1799), <title level="m">The
                        British Lion</title> (1797), and William Holland, <title level="m">Political
                        Hocus Pocus</title> (1802).</note> Restriction and the ensuing prosecutions
                  for forgery can be understood as the latest components of a wider, interlocking
                  system of mystification, oppression and exploitation which relied on the state’s
                  monopoly of “paper” power. </p>
               <p>The state’s rationale for such infringements of civil liberty was that some
                  personal freedoms had to be surrendered if the nation was to be protected against
                  invasion and conquest. Unless John Bullion surrendered his specie and allowed more
                  paper money to circulate, Britain faced an unthinkable fate. If Britons found
                  cheap banknotes unpalatable, they should consider the Jacobin alternative: the
                  rule of the revolutionary French assignat (<ref target="../images/figure16.jpg"
                     >Figure 16</ref>). The assignat was the paper currency which the French
                  Assembly introduced in 1790 out of the proceeds of confiscated Church
                     property.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="23">See Taws for a discussion of
                     French counter-revolutionary caricatures of the assignat and the similarity
                     between these two forms of “authenticity and falsehood” (104).</note> The
                  policy quickly led to hyperinflation, and by the time the plates which printed the
                  assignat were publicly burned in February 1796, its value had depreciated by an
                  astonishing 95% (compared to about 30% for the pound in the Restriction period).<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="24">Buchan, 159. See also Ferguson, <title
                        level="m">The Cash Nexus</title>, 151-3.</note> For Edmund Burke, the
                  assignat was the epitome of Jacobin mischief and the arch enemy of the gold
                  standard. In Pocock’s opinion, it was the introduction of the assignat, and not
                  the invasion of the Queen’s bedchamber, which was for Burke “the central, the
                  absolute and the unforgivable crime of the Revolutionaries” (197). Throughout his
                     <title level="m">Reflections on the Revolution in France</title>, Burke rails
                  against the revolutionaries’ decision “to force a currency of their own fiction in
                  the place of that which is real” (261). He declaims that “So violent an outrage
                  upon credit, property, and liberty, as this compulsory paper money currency, has
                  seldom been exhibited” (226). Overall: <quote>everything human and divine
                     sacrificed to the idol of public credit, and national bankruptcy the
                     consequence; and to crown all, the paper securities of new, precarious,
                     tottering power, the discredited paper securities of impoverished fraud, and
                     beggared rapine, held out as a currency for the support of an empire, in lieu
                     of the two great recognized species [gold and silver] that represent the
                     lasting conventional credit of mankind, which disappeared and hid themselves in
                     the earth from whence they came, when the principle of property, whose
                     creatures and representatives they are, was systematically subverted. (126)<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="25">Brantlinger argues that Burke
                        conceived the “financial mysteries” of the State in sublime terms as a
                        “towering phallic menace” which “could only dimly be apprehended through
                        imagination and a suitably terroristic rhetoric” (108)—a useful gloss on
                        Gillray”s mock-sublime <title level="m">Midas</title>.</note>
                  </quote> Burke castigated English republicans and revolutionary sympathizers who
                  believed that England should follow the French example and worship the “idol of
                  public credit.” These misguided supporters of paper currency <quote>forget that,
                     in England, not one shilling of paper money of any description is received but
                     of choice; that the whole has had its origin in cash actually deposited; and
                     that it is convertible, at pleasure, in an instant, and without the smallest
                     loss, into cash again. (357-8)</quote> But as Tom Furniss notes, Burke’s method
                  of “projecting a negative aspect of Britain’s own financial revolution which had
                  haunted it from the beginning onto a radical ‘other’ across the channel” simply
                  reproduced those endemic anxieties about an economy based on what Furniss calls
                  “imagination” (241). So it is both ironic and poignant that Burke died in the year
                  in which Pitt introduced the English equivalent of the assignat (Gillray’s <title
                     level="m">Midas</title> illustrates this irony in the way in which the tiny
                  Jacobin demons swarming round Pitt’s head merge into banknotes). In Burke’s own
                  terms, paper money was no longer “convertible, at pleasure, in an instant, and
                  without the smallest loss, into cash again.”</p>
               <p>Yet by freeing paper money from convertibility and the gold standard, it could be
                  argued that Restriction was an unconscious act of modernization, as there was no
                  longer a pretence (or “delusion”) that paper and gold were related (this is surely
                  the case today in so far as no one believes the “promise” on British banknotes to
                  “pay the bearer” the equivalent in gold). By converting currency into
                  “imagination” rather than “real value”, the idea of value migrated into the
                  aesthetic realm, the realm of symbolic circulation. But if Romantic writers
                  remained troubled by the loss of the real, this was not the case for
                  caricaturists, whose work was premised on converting political events into an
                  alternative, parallel and usually controversial fantasy. In this sense,
                  caricature’s generically maverick and ungovernable aesthetics were more in tune
                  with a system of “fabricated pieces of paper”.<note place="foot" resp="editors"
                     n="26">P. B. Shelley, <title level="a">A Philosophical View of Reform,</title>
                     in Leader and O’Neill, 651. </note></p>
               <p>The efflorescent character of Gillray’s <title level="m">Midas</title> seems to
                  register this new creative opportunity. Unlike the macabre <title level="m">Bank
                     Restriction Note</title>, Gillray shows that Restriction was actually a dynamic
                  explosion of paper energy. It is as if Gillray found the idea of unconvertible
                  paper currency irresistible, despite the print’s overt political attack on Pitt’s
                  policy. Another way to think about this apparent celebration of paper circulation
                  is to consider how Gillray innovated upon and modernized his satirical sources, so
                  that we understand more clearly how Gillray constructed Pitt/Midas’s bizarre
                  anatomy. The most immediate influence on his fantasy is the figure of the
                  political colossus. This was a well-honed satirical technique which became popular
                  with attacks on Britain’s first Prime Minister Robert Walpole (<ref
                     target="../images/figure17.jpg">Figure 17</ref>) and quickly became a familiar
                  visual weapon with which to attack overweening ministerial ambitions such as those
                  of the Earl of Bute (<ref target="../images/figure18.jpg">Figure 18</ref>). Just a
                  few weeks before the introduction of Restriction, Gillray portrayed Pitt as a
                  colossus in <title level="m">The Giant Factotum Amusing Himself</title> (<ref
                     target="../images/figure19.jpg">Figure 19</ref>), so the novelty of <title
                     level="m">Midas</title> consisted of the change of venue (from parliament to
                  the Bank of England—a clear hint of the true source of the nation’s ills) and the
                  switch of satirical wit from bawdy pun (‘amusing himself’) to scatological
                  extroversion. For the latter effect, Gillray drew on another popular caricature
                  language in which politicians are depicted scatalogically if not always
                  gigantically. These prints visualize tyranny, patronage and sycophancy by showing
                  the powerful leader shitting or vomiting on hangers-on and suitors. The literary
                  sources of such earthy wit included Rabelais and Swift, but caricature could add
                  the unique extra frisson of visuality. Good examples include anti-Walpolian prints
                  such as <title level="m">The Political Vomit for the Ease of Britain</title> and
                     <title level="m">Idol Worship; or the Way to Preferment</title> (<ref
                     target="../images/figure20.jpg">Figures 20</ref> and <ref
                     target="../images/figure21.jpg">21</ref>) and James Aitken’s <title level="m"
                     >Public Credit, or the State Idol</title>—the latter shows Edmund Burke as the
                  arse-licker climbing the mired pole of preferment (<ref
                     target="../images/figure22.jpg">Figure 22</ref>). Where Gillray innovates on
                  such sources is his remarkable ability to show Pitt/Midas vacating and ingesting
                  at the same time; metaphorically, this strange physiology registers the credit
                  system’s simultaneous mystification and demystification of paper. As the
                  transparent torso shows, this colossus is anatomically far more agile than his
                  scatological predecessors: he is both hoarding and secreting money, an apt image
                  of “convertibility.” This in itself is a considerable artistic achievement, but
                  Gillray goes one step further in his visual dexterity and allusiveness. </p>
               <p>Another popular visual source for <title level="m">Midas</title> is the medieval
                  fantasy of the money devil, a diabolical yet faintly comic figure who exposes
                  greed and covetousness by raining coins onto people from all his orifices. The
                  genesis of this creature can be seen in Hieronymus Bosch’s <title level="m">Garden
                     of Earthly Delights</title>. Next to the so-called “Prince of Hell” (who sits
                  on a toilet-throne expelling people into a diabolical midden) there is a naked
                  rear end ejecting coins into the same pit, a clear association of lucre and
                  damnation. By the eighteenth century the money devil had become a familiar figure
                  in European and Russian caricatures, some of which Gillray may have known (<ref
                     target="../images/figure23.jpg">Figure 23</ref>). In <title level="m"
                     >Midas</title>, however, the cluster of coins which appear to be dropping from
                  Pitt’s posterior like the money devil are actually defying the laws of gravity;
                  they are being sucked up into Pitt/Midas’s torso while banknotes (the new
                  ‘easing’) now perform the lavatorial function—a brilliant realization of the
                  “delusion” of convertibility. As Marc Shell notes, “many people in the
                  eighteenth-century were used to seeing depictions of a coin-covered money devil”
                  but “they were more puzzled by paper money than by coin, so they were especially
                  leery of the new paper money devil’s graphic powers of production, or poesis”
                  (67). Gillray’s genius lies in his ability to imagine this new “poesis” and make
                     <title level="m">Midas</title> a satirical tribute to “the new paper money
                  devil’s graphic powers of production” rather than to the print’s ostensible theme,
                  the “goodness of guineas” (Cobbett, 204). </p>
               <p>This contradiction has a wider bearing on the fraught relations between
                  Romanticism and popularity. On the one hand, as already surmised, the loss of
                  “real” currency and the hike in forgery executions made many thinkers mistrustful
                  of the paper money system and for writers and artists these doubts may have
                  extended to the signifying power of “paper” more generally. Simon During describes
                  the post-Restriction mood for Romantic writers as a strange cocktail of
                  “fearfulness, unpredictability, opportunity and weightlessness” (339), perhaps
                  unintentionally echoing Adam Smith’s trope of credit’s perilous “Daedalian”
                  sublimity. Despite clinging to the secure “weight” of bullion, Romantic writers
                  were also impelled to explore new, relatively autonomous and self-authorizing
                  imaginative paradigms which could keep the vexed issue of the tainted paper
                  economy of print circulation and popularity at arm’s length. Though Shelley
                  ventured into Heavy Metal performances in his satires <title level="m">Oedipus
                     Tyrannus; Or Swellfoot the Tyrant</title> (which has a character called
                  “Banknotina”), <title level="m">Peter Bell the Third</title> (which characterises
                  paper money as expropriated bee-honey), and <title level="m">The Mask of
                     Anarchy</title> (which memorably styles the credit economy the “ghost of
                  gold”), such incursions into popular culture were rare.<note place="foot"
                     resp="editors" n="27">See Hogle, 236-9, Brantlinger 114-19. Significantly, none
                     of these texts was published in Shelley’s lifetime (<title level="m"
                        >Swellfoot</title> was published in 1820 but immediately suppressed), nor
                     was the “Philosophical View of Reform”, in which he expounded his critique of
                     credit at greatest length. For a discussion of Shelley’s currency radicalism,
                     which demanded the abolition of the national debt as a condition of returning
                     to the gold standard, see Connell, chapter 4.</note> On the other hand, radical
                  authors like Paine and Cobbett saw the teeming popularity of print circulation as
                  an opportunity for ideological subversion rather than state control. Despite all
                  the government’s efforts to suppress, regulate and neutralize radical writing in
                  the 1790s, Paine was still able to claim (with typical bravado) that Restriction
                  had been precipitated not by the alarm of a French invasion but by the panicky
                  response to cheap editions of his pamphlet <title level="m">Decline of the English
                     System of Finance</title> (Foner, 2: 1387-8). For Paine, cheap radical
                  literature operated like a phoney currency of economic espionage, overloading the
                  system to breaking point. Paper was a medium to be appropriated and carnivalized
                  rather than repressed, displaced or sublimated. When Cobbett asked his readers to
                  flood the market with fake banknotes, he recalled wryly that Pitt had considered
                  deluging France with fake assignats (<title level="j">Black Dwarf</title>, 2 [21
                  October 1818], 658-9); <title level="j">Cobbett’s Weekly Political
                     Register</title>, 22 August 1818). Like Paine, Cobbett’s phenomenal success
                  cocked a snoop at the new paper economy from within its own ranks: <title
                     level="m">Paper against Gold</title> sold around 150,000 copies, making it,
                  according to Spater, “probably the most widely read book ever written purely on
                  monetary questions” (1: 315). By converting currency into “imagination”, the
                  Restriction Act released its own critique and sowed the seed of its own
                  destruction.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="section">
               <head>The “formidable” caricaturist</head>
               <p>But it was the caricaturists, above all, who could have their Restriction cake and
                  eat it: caricature thrived in a cultural environment in which the boundaries
                  between the “real” and the phoney or fake were being so sensationally and publicly
                  challenged, eroded, undermined and continually flouted. Caricature had a
                  productively contradictory relation to Restriction forgery. To begin with, Horace
                  Walpole’s oft-quoted comment that “all the house of forgery are relations” was
                  much truer of engravers than writers. Walpole made this comment to rebut
                  accusations that his rejection of Chatterton’s request for patronage had led to
                  the latter’s suicide, but he was not alone in seeing a slippage from literary to
                  financial forgery. Joseph Ritson, for example, remarked that “a man who will forge
                  a poem, a line or even a word will not hesitate, when the temptation is greater
                  and the impunity equal, to forge a note or steal a guinea” (Ruthven, 57-9). In
                  fact there was little if no evidence to support this claim, whereas there was
                  abundant evidence that engravers were playing both sides of the law. As noted
                  earlier, the state both relied on and feared the “formidable power of imitation”
                  of the engraver. Ironically, the Bank of England subjected all submitted designs
                  for “inimitable” banknotes to a counterfeiting test by its own engravers: not one
                  design passed the test.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="28">The consensus was
                     that the new note should combine, in the words of the Society of Arts report
                     into Restriction forgery, the “highest perfection” of hand engraving with
                     “mathematical accuracy” of “engine engraving” (<title level="m">Report of the
                        Committee of the Society of Arts</title>, 10)—theoretically at least, this
                     fusion of high artistic standards and technological sophistication would put
                     the banknote beyond the reach and resources of the forger.</note> Equally
                  revealing is the fact that one of the eventual solutions to this problem, the use
                  of lithography, was first proposed by the well-known caricature print seller
                  Rudolph Ackermann, yet his suggestion was rejected as “a discovery as applied to
                  the subject of Forgery, infinitely more to be dreaded than encouraged” (cited in
                  Mackenzie, 61).</p>
               <p>This takes us the second aspect of caricature’s cultural power. Ackermann
                  undoubtedly knew that the single print caricature functioned like an alternative
                  currency, shadowing and transforming “official” history.<note place="foot"
                     resp="editors" n="29">Gary Dyer confirms that Regency caricature had a much
                     greater impact on “public perceptions” than literary satires (93).</note>
                  Moreover, society seemed to be imitating art. For critics of the unreformed
                  political system, Regency England had become a caricature of itself, consuming
                  rather than protecting its own children. No event showed this more clearly than
                  the Peterloo massacre of August 1819, an incident which lies at the heart of that
                  extraordinarily productive few years of Romantic literary output which James
                  Chandler (borrowing from Shelley) calls “England in 1819.” But what Chandler fails
                  to note is that these years also represent the crowning achievement of caricature.
                  It is surely no coincidence that the title page of Hone and Cruikshank”s
                  bestselling satire <title level="m">The Political House that Jack Built</title>
                  (1819) shows a pair of scales in which the pen of radicalism outweighs not just
                  Wellington’s sword but a bundle of unjust laws topped by “Bank Restriction” (<ref
                     target="../images/figure24.jpg">Figure 24</ref>). The image implies that
                  radical critique is the antithesis of Old Corruption’s mystifications, but there
                  could also be an allusion to the <title level="m">Bank Restriction Note</title> of
                  earlier that year. In other words, Cruikshank could be complimenting his own
                  “formidable” imitation of the forged banknotes which (in Baines’ words) were
                  “naturally engendered” by the paper money system and which functioned as an emblem
                  or synecdoche of unreformed political and social structures. This ability to
                  satirically copy a discredited copy of a discredited copy (caricature—forged
                  banknote—original banknote) is a paradigm of the way caricature used its
                  distinctive “imagination” and the medium of paper to critique the “real.”</p>
               <p>A third way in which caricature mimicked forgery was that the satirical copy had
                  to be sufficiently life-like so that public figures would be recognised. In
                  essence, this constituted a kind of identity theft in which counterfeit images
                  circulated in place of the original and without the original’s consent. Hone and
                  Cruikshank’s Duke of Wellington is simultaneously real and satirical, his
                  (modestly caricatured) visual identity determined by a few key features such as
                  the hook nose, oversize plumed hat and spurs. Ironically, many Georgian authority
                  figures were known to the public primarily through their caricature
                  representations (Charles James Fox would be the obvious example). As Gombrich and
                  Kris argue, graphic satire’s ability to steal an original identity and manufacture
                  phantom copies tapped into pre-Enlightenment superstitions about magical fetishes
                  which “annihilated” individuality. The reason why “portrait” or personalized
                  caricature appeared so late in history was not, they argue, due to the relaxing of
                  censorship; it has more to do with the secularization of society and the
                  desacralization of the image, its dissociation from actual necromancy. Once this
                  tendency merged with “political allegory”, the result was an explosive release of
                  anti-authoritarian visual aggression (14-17, 26-7). In Vic Gatrell’s words,
                  caricature was “a modernized form of an ancient effigy magic delivered against
                  otherwise unassailable enemies … [a] symbolic defilement anciently embedded in
                  ritual destructions of the defamatory image” (227). </p>
               <p>Relatively untouched by legal prosecutions, unburdened by the aesthetics of
                  originality, masterful in creating allegorical fantasies of politics and culture,
                  firmly embedded in reportage and print culture, the single print caricature
                  circulated like a shadow economy of symbolic representation, pumping out “phantom”
                  versions of political leaders, authority figures and celebrities.<note
                     place="foot" resp="editors" n="30">If Julie Carlson is correct to state that
                     Romantic celebrity was about “making a spectacle of one’s self” (503), then
                     caricature celebrity was about making a spectacle of a phantom other.</note>
                  Again, there is a useful parallel here with Marx’s theory of the quasi-divine,
                  transformative power of money which “turns real human and natural powers into
                  purely abstract representations, and therefore imperfections and tormenting
                  phantoms, just as it turns real imperfections and phantoms—truly impotent powers
                  which exist only in the individual’s fantasy—into real essential powers and
                  abilities” (378). Perhaps the final irony of the relationship between caricature
                  and forgery is that the restoration of “real value” in 1821 (which in practice
                  meant a return to convertibility and the abolition of the lethal £1 and £2 notes)
                  also marked the decline of the golden age of British caricature. After the success
                  of the campaign to support Queen Caroline, Cruikshank took a huge bribe from the
                  state and retired from the scene.</p>
               <p>Paper money, on the other hand, continued to be a controversial issue beyond the
                  Romantic period. In 1830, for example, just two years before the abolition of the
                  death penalty for forgery, the Northamptonshire peasant poet John Clare grumbled
                  that: <quote>The Speculator is looking for a new paper currency which placed a
                     false value on every species of his traffic &amp; thereby enables the cunning
                     to cheat the honest…I would have every bank issuing one pound notes (which is
                     but a shadow of a promise for a substance which the promiser has pocketed)
                     dependent as Branch banks on the Bank of England. (To John Taylor (1 February
                     1830); Storey, 498-500)</quote> The influence of Cobbett over the next
                  generation of radicals who formed the Chartist movement kept the discourse of
                  ‘paper against gold’ alive. In Thomas Doubleday’s satire <title level="m">The
                     Political Pilgrim’s Progress</title> (1839), for example, the hero Radical’s
                  main adversary Political Apollyon is a demon composed of paper money (<ref
                     target="../images/figure25.jpg">Figure 25</ref>). But given that forgery ceased
                  to be a capital offence in the early 1830s, the debunking of credit lost much of
                  its sensationalism.</p>
               <p>To conclude: if Niall Ferguson is correct to say that “Money is not metal. It is
                  trust inscribed” (Ferguson, <title level="m">The Ascent of Money</title>, 29-30),
                  then the key issue remains: who, or what do you put your trust in? If, to quote a
                  popular ditty, “One forgery makes a felon –Millions a statesman!” perhaps you
                  would be wise to invest in caricature. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="citation">
               <head>Works Cited</head>
               <listBibl>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Aravamudan, Srinivas</author>
                        <title level="a">Defoe, Commerce and Empire</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">The Cambridge Companion to Daniel Defoe</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Richetti, John</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Baines, Paul</author>
                        <title level="m">The House of Forgery in Eighteenth-Century Britain</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Aldershot</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>
                           <date>1999</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Black Dwarf</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>9 September 1818; 14 October 1818; 21 October 1818</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Boswell, James</author>
                        <title level="m">Life of Johnson</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Chapman, R. W.</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
                           <date>1970</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Brantlinger, Patrick</author>
                        <title level="m">Fictions of State: Culture and Credit in Britain,
                           1694-1994</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Ithaca</pubPlace>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cornell UP</publisher>
                           <date>1996</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Broome, Ralph</author>
                        <title level="m">Observations on Mr. Paine’s Pamphlet, entitled The Decline
                           and Fall of the English System of Finance</title>
                        <edition>Second Edition</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>J. Debrett</publisher>
                           <date>1796</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Buchan, James</author>
                        <title level="m">Frozen Desire: An Inquiry into the Meaning of Money</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Picador</publisher>
                           <date>1997</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Burke, Edmund</author>
                        <title level="m">Reflections on the Revolution in France</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Penguin</publisher>
                           <date>1976</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Butt, John</editor>
                        <title level="m">The Poems of Alexander Pope</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Methuen</publisher>
                           <date>1968</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Cannan, Edwin</author>
                        <title level="m">The Paper Pound of 1797-1821: A Reprint of the Bullion
                           Report</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>P. S. King and Son</publisher>
                           <date>1919</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Carlson, Julie</author>
                        <title level="a">Theatre, performance and urban spectacle [Chapter
                           21]</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Chandler, James</editor>
                        <title level="m">The Cambridge History of English Romantic
                           Literature</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>2009</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Christensen, Jerome</author>
                        <title level="a">Romantic Conspiracy in Britain</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">South Atlantic Quarterly</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">95</biblScope>
                           <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                           <date>Summer 1995</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">603-28</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Clapham, John</author>
                        <title level="m">The Bank of England</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>1944</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Cobbett’s Weekly Political Register</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>22 August 1818</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Cobbett, William</author>
                        <title level="m">Paper Against Gold</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>W. Cobbett</publisher>
                           <date>1815</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Connell, Philip</author>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism, Economics and the Question of
                           “Culture”</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
                           <date>2001</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Constantine, Mary Ann</author>
                        <title level="m">The Truth against the World</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cardiff</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Wales UP</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Dick, Alex J</author>
                        <title level="a">‘The Ghost of Gold’: Forgery Trials and the Standard of
                           Value in Shelley’s <emph>The Mask of Anarchy</emph></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">European Romantic Review</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="issue">18</biblScope>
                           <date>2007</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">381-400</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Dickson, P. G. M</author>
                        <title level="m">The Financial Revolution in England: A Study in the
                           Development of Public Credit 1688-1756</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Macmillan</publisher>
                           <date>1967</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>During, Simon</author>
                        <title level="a">Regency London [Chapter 14]</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Chandler, James</editor>
                        <title level="m">The Cambridge History of English Romantic
                           Literature</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>2009</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Dyer, Gary</author>
                        <title level="m">British Satire and the Politics of Style, 1789-1832</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>1997</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Ehrman, John</author>
                        <title level="m">The Younger Pitt: The Consuming Struggle</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Stanford UP</publisher>
                           <date>1996</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Ferguson, Niall</author>
                        <title level="m">The Cash Nexus: Money and Power in the Modern World,
                           1700-2000</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Allen Lane</publisher>
                           <date>2001</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Ferguson, Niall</author>
                        <title level="m">The Ascent of Money: A Financial History of the
                           World</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>The Penguin Press</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Finn, Margot</author>
                        <title level="m">The Character of Credit: Personal Debt in English Culture,
                           1740-1815</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>2003</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Foner, Eric</editor>
                        <title level="m">The Complete Writings of Thomas Paine</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>The Citadel Press</publisher>
                           <date>1969</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Furniss, Tom</author>
                        <title level="m">Edmund Burke’s Aesthetic Ideology: Language, Gender, and
                           Political Economy in Revolution</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>1993</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Gallagher, Catherine</author>
                        <title level="m">The Body Economic: Life, Death, and Sensation in Political
                           Economy and the Victorian Novel</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Princeton UP</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Garvey, Nathan</author>
                        <title level="m">The Celebrated George Barrington: A Spurious Author, the
                           Book Trade, and Botany Bay</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Sydney</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Hordern House</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Gaskill, Howard</author>
                        <title level="m">Ossian Revisited</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Edinburgh UP</publisher>
                           <date>1991</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Gentleman’s Magazine</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">50</biblScope>
                           <date>July 1780</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Gombrich, E.H.</author>
                        <author>Kris, E.</author>
                        <title level="m">Caricature</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Penguin</publisher>
                           <date>1940</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Groom, Nick</author>
                        <title level="m">The Forger’s Shadow</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Picador</publisher>
                           <date>2002</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Groom, Nick</author>
                        <title level="a"><ref
                              target="http://www.blackwell-compass.com/subject/literature/article_view?article_id=lico_articles_bpl485"
                              >Romanticism and Forgery</ref></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Literature Compass</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>August 2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Hackwood, Frederick William</author>
                        <title level="m">William Hone; His Life and Times</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>T. Fisher Unwin</publisher>
                           <date>1912</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Handler, Philip</author>
                        <title level="a">Forging the Agenda: The 1819 Select Committee on the
                           Criminal Laws Revisited</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Journal of Legal History</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">25</biblScope>
                           <date>2004</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">249–68</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Handler, Philip</author>
                        <title level="a">Forgery and the End of the ‘Bloody Code’ in early
                           nineteenth-century England</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Historical Journal</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">48</biblScope>
                           <date>2005</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">683–702</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Haywood, Ian</author>
                        <title level="m">Faking It: Art and the Politics of Forgery</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Brighton</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Harvester</publisher>
                           <date>1987</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Haywood, Ian</author>
                        <title level="m">The Making of History: A Study of the Literary Forgeries of
                           James Macpherson and Thomas Chatterton</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Associated UP</publisher>
                           <date>1986</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Hogle, Jerrold E</author>
                        <title level="m">Shelley’s Process: Radical Transference and the Development
                           of his Major Works</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
                           <date>1988</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Hume, David</author>
                        <title level="m">Essays and Treatises on Several Subjects</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>A. Millar</publisher>
                           <date>1758</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Keyworth, John</author>
                        <title level="a"><ref
                              target="http://www.bankofengland.co.uk/education/museum/exhibitions/securitybydesign.pdf"
                              >Security by Design: A closer look at Bank of England
                           notes</ref></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><ref
                              target="http://www.bankofengland.co.uk/education/museum/exhibitions/securebydesign.htm"
                              >Secure By Design</ref></title>
                        <imprint>
                           <publisher>Bank of England Museum</publisher>
                           <date>24 November 2011</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Klancher, Jon P</author>
                        <title level="m">The Making of English Reading Audiences, 1790-1832</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Madison</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Wisconsin Press</publisher>
                           <date>1987</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Lee, Debbie</author>
                        <title level="a">Forgeries [Chapter 32]</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Roe, Nicholas</editor>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism: An Oxford Guide</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Lee, Debbie</author>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Liars: Obscure Women who became Impostors and
                           Challenged an Empire</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Basingstoke</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Palgrave</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Lynch, Deidre Shauna</author>
                        <title level="a">Money and Character in Defoe’s fiction</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">The Cambridge Companion to Daniel Defoe</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Richetti, John</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Lynch, Jack</author>
                        <title level="m">Deception and Detection in Eighteenth-Century
                           Britain</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Farnham</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Mackenzie, A. D</author>
                        <title level="m">The Bank of England Note: A History of Its Printing</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>1953</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Malton, Sara</author>
                        <title level="a">Forgery, Fiscal Trauma, and the Fauntleroy Case</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">European Romantic Review</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">18</biblScope>
                           <date>2007</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">401-15</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Malton, Sara</author>
                        <title level="m">Forgery in Nineteenth Century Literature and Culture:
                           Fictions of Finance</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher>
                           <date>2009</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Marx, Karl</author>
                        <title level="m">Early Writings</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Livingstone, Rodney</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Benton, Gregor</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Penguin</publisher>
                           <date>1984</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>McGowen, Randall</author>
                        <title level="a">Managing the Gallows: The Bank of England and the Death
                           Penalty, 1797-1821</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Law and History Review</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">25</biblScope>
                           <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Miles, Robert</author>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Misfits</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Basingstoke</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Nicholson, Colin</author>
                        <title level="m">Writing and the Rise of Finance: Capital Satires of the
                           Early Eighteenth Century</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>1994</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>O’Brien, Patrick Karl</author>
                        <title level="a">Mercantilist Institutions for the Pursuit of Power without
                           Profit: The Management of Britain’s National Debt, 1765-1815</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Caselli, Fausto Piola</editor>
                        <title level="m">Government Debts and Financial Markets in Europe</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Pickering and Chatto</publisher>
                           <date> 2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Patten, Robert L</author>
                        <title level="m">George Cruikshank’s Life, Times and Art. Volume 1:
                           1792-1835</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Lutterworth</publisher>
                           <date> 1992</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Peacock, Thomas Love</author>
                        <title level="m">Paper Money Lyrics</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>C. and W. Reynell</publisher>
                           <date>1837</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Pocock, J. G. A</author>
                        <title level="m">Virtue, Commerce and History</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>1985</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Poovey, Mary</author>
                        <title level="m">Genres of the Credit Economy: Mediating Value in
                           Eighteenth- and Nineteenth-Century Britain</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Chicago UP</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Porter, Roy</author>
                        <title level="m">English Society in the Eighteenth Century</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Penguin</publisher>
                           <date>1982</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Report of the Committee of Secrecy of the House of Commons.
                           Ordered to be Printed 15th March 1799</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>J. Stockdale</publisher>
                           <date>1799</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Report of the Committee of the Society of Arts &amp;c.
                           Together with the Approved Communications and Evidence upon the Same,
                           Relative to the Mode of Preventing the Forgery of Banknotes</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Printed by Order of the Society</publisher>
                           <date>1819</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Richard, Henry, Lord Holland</author>
                        <title level="m">Memoirs of the Whig Party During My Time</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green and Longmans</publisher>
                           <date>1852</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Russett, Margaret</author>
                        <title level="m">Fictions and Fakes: Forging Romantic Authenticity</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Ruthven, K. K</author>
                        <title level="m">Faking Literature</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>2001</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Shell, Marc</author>
                        <title level="m">The Economy of Literature</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>John Hopkins UP</publisher>
                           <date>1993</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Shell, Marc</author>
                        <title level="m">Art and Money</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Chicago UP</publisher>
                           <date>1995</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Smith, Adam</author>
                        <title level="m">An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of
                           Nations</title>
                        <edition>Eighth Edition</edition>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">3 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>A. Strahan, T. Cadell</publisher>
                           <date>1796</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Spater, James</author>
                        <title level="m">William Cobbett: The Poor Man’s Friend</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                           <date>1982</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Stafford, Fiona</author>
                        <title level="m">The Sublime Savage: A Study of James Macpherson and the
                           Poems of Ossian</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Edinburgh UP</publisher>
                           <date>1988</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Spectator</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">8 vols</biblScope>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Longman, Dodsley, Law, Robson, et al</publisher>
                           <date>1797</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Storey, Mark</editor>
                        <title level="m">Letters of John Clare</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                           <date>1985</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Taws, Richard</author>
                        <title level="a">The Currency of Caricature in Revolutionary France</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Porterfield, Todd</editor>
                        <title level="m">The Efflorescence of Caricature, 1759-1838</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Farnham</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>
                           <date>2010</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Thornton, Henry</author>
                        <title level="m">An Inquiry into the Nature and Effects of Paper Credit of
                           Great Britain</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>J. Hatchard</publisher>
                           <date>1802</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Times</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <date>1 March 1797; 27 January 1819</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Torre, Jose R</author>
                        <title level="m">The Political Economy of Sentiment: Paper Credit and the
                           Scottish Enlightenment in Early Republican Boston, 1780-1820</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Pickering and Chatto</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Trotter, David</author>
                        <title level="m">Circulation: Defoe, Dickens, and the Economies of the
                           Novel</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Macmillan</publisher>
                           <date>1988</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Williams, Raymond</author>
                        <title level="m">Culture and Society 1780-1950</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Penguin</publisher>
                           <date>1976</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
               </listBibl>
            </div>

            <div type="figures">
               <head>List of Figures</head>
               <figure n="1">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure1Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc> James Gillray, <title level="m">The Table’s Turn’d</title> Published by
                     Hannah Humphrey, 4 March 1797. British Museum Satires 8992. Courtesy Trustees
                     of the British Museum. </figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="2">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure2Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc> James Gillray, <title level="m">Midas. Transmuting all into [Gold]
                        Paper</title> Published by Hannah Humphrey, 9 March 1797. British Museum
                     Satires 8995. Courtesy Trustees of the British Museum. </figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="3">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure3Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>Forged banknote from 1819. British Museum Eagleton 2011, 2012. Courtesy
                     Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="4">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure4Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>George Cruikshank, <title level="m">Bank Restriction Note</title>.
                     Published by William Hone, January 1819. British Museum Satires 13198. Courtesy
                     Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="5">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure5Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>George Cruikshank, <title level="m">Bank Restriction Barometer</title>
                     Published by William Hone, January 1819. British Museum Satires 13199. Courtesy
                     Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="6">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure6Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>Satirical banknote, valued two pence, made payable to “William
                     Pittachio”, one of Pitt’s many satirical titles. Published by S. W. Fores, 1
                     August 1807. British Museum Satires 10753.A. Courtesy Trustees of the British
                     Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="7">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure7Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>The Spiritual Barometer. Taken from the <title level="j">Evangelical
                        Magazine</title> 8 vols (London: T. Chapman, 1793-1800), 8 (1800): 526.
                     Courtesy British Library.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="8">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure8Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>John Ireland (after William Hogarth), <title level="m">Enthusiasm
                        Delineated</title> Published by Isaac Mills, 12 November 1795. British
                     Museum Satires 2426. Courtesy Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="9">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure9Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>Abraham Bosse, title page of Thomas Hobbes, <title level="m"
                        >Leviathan</title> (1653). British Museum Lothe 1307. Courtesy Trustees of
                     the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="10">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure10Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>James Gillray, <title level="m">The Dissolution, or The Alchymist
                        Producing an Aetherial Representation</title> Published by Hannah Humphrey,
                     21 May 1796. British Museum Satires 8805. Courtesy Trustees of the British
                     Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="11">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure11Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>James Gillray, <title level="m">Bank Notes.
                        Paper-money,-French-alarmists,-O, the Devil, the Devil!-Ah! Poor
                        John-Bull!!!</title> Published by Hannah Humphrey, 1 March 1797. British
                     Museum Satires 8990. Courtesy Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="12">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure12Thumb.jpg" width="153px"/>
                  <figDesc>George Cruikshank, <title level="m">Bank Restriction Note</title>
                     (detail).</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="13">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure13Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>George Cruikshank, <title level="m">Johnny Bull and his Forged Notes!! or
                        Rags and Ruin in the Paper Currency</title> Published by J. Sidebotham,
                     January 1819. British Museum Satires 13197. Courtesy Trustees of the British
                     Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="14">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure14Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>Richard Newton, <title level="m">The New Paper Mill or Mr Bull Ground
                        into 20 Shilling Notes</title> Published by Richard Newton 12 March 1797.
                     British Museum Satires 8998. Courtesy Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="15">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure15Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>Richard Newton, <title level="m">The Inexhaustible Mine</title> Published
                     by Richard Newton, 22 June 1797. British Museum Satires 9025. Courtesy Trustees
                     of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="16">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure16Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>Revolutionary French assignat, 1792. British Museum G68/17/3/5 Courtesy
                     Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="17">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure17Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>George Bickham the Younger, <title level="m">The Stature of a Great Man
                        or the English Colossus</title> Published by George Bickham the Younger,
                     1740. British Museum Satires 2458. Courtesy Trustees of the British
                     Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="18">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure18Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>Anon. <title level="m">The Colossus</title> Published 1767. British
                     Museum Satires 4178. Courtesy Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="19">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure19Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>James Gillray, <title level="m">The Giant Factotum Amusing
                        Himself</title> Published by Hannah Humphrey, 21 January 1797. British
                     Museum Satires 8980. Courtesy Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="20">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure20Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>Anon., <title level="m">The Political Vomit for the Ease of
                        Britain</title> Published in 1742. British Museum Satires 2531. Courtesy
                     Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="21">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure21Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>Anon. <title level="m">Idol Worship or the Way to Preferment</title>
                     Published 1740. British Museum Satires 2447. Courtesy Trustees of the British
                     Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="22">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure22Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>James Aitken, <title level="m">Public Credit, or the State Idol</title>
                     Published by William Dent, 3 June 1791. British Museum Satires 7872. Courtesy
                     Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="23">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure23Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>Anon. A Russian print of a money devil, c. 1800-1850. British Museum
                     Popular Prints Russian. Courtesy Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="24">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure24Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>George Cruikshank and William Hone, title page of <title level="m">The
                        Political House that Jack Built </title> Published by William Hone, 1819.
                     British Museum Satires 13292. Courtesy Trustees of the British
                     Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure n="25">
                  <graphic url="../images/figure25Thumb.jpg" width="375px"/>
                  <figDesc>Illustration to Thomas Doubleday, <title level="m">The Political
                        Pilgrim’s Progress</title>, published in <title level="j">The Northern
                        Liberator</title> 1839. Author’s collection.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
