<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Romanticism, Forgery and the Credit Crunch</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles PRAXIS Volume</title>
            <title level="a"><title level="m">Emma</title> and Bank Bills: Forgery and Romanticism</title>
            <author>
               <name>Robert Miles</name>
            </author>
            <editor role="editor">Ian Haywood</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
               <name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>praxis.2011.miles</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
            <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
            <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
            <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
          </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                  <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                     prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                  <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                     their current ones.</item>
               </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main"><title level="m">Emma</title> and Bank Bills: Forgery and Romanticism</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Robert</forename>
                        <surname>Miles</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Romanticism, Forgery and the Credit Crunch</title>
                  <title level="j">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-12-01">December 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#226;&#8364;&#339;,"
                  for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard</p>
               <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
            <keywords scheme="http://www.rc.umd.edu/#tags">
               <list>
                  <item>This essay argues that Jane Austen’s <title level="m">Emma</title> offers the reader a complex reflection on the
                     interpenetration of economic and aesthetic systems of value that developed
                     in the aftermath of the suspension of cash payments in 1797, an interpenetration that is itself constitutive of Romanticism.</item>
                  <item>Austen</item> 
                  <item>Emma</item> 
                  <item>Romanticism</item>
                  <item>political economy</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <date>2011-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the issue</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>
               <title level="a"><title level="m">Emma</title> and Bank Bills: Forgery and Romanticism</title></head>
            <byline><docAuthor>Robert Miles</docAuthor><affiliation>University of Victoria</affiliation></byline>
            <p>Reviewing Austen’s <title level="m">Emma</title> Walter Scott sums up the denouement
               like this: <quote>Mr. Woodhouse’s objections to the marriage of his daughter are
                  overpowered by the fears of housebreakers, and the comfort which he hopes to
                  derive from having a stout son-in-law resident in the family; and the facile
                  affections of Harriet Smith are transferred, like a bank bill by indorsation, to
                  her former suitor, the honest farmer, who had obtained a favourable opportunity of
                  renewing his addresses.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn1" place="foot" n="1">Walter
                     Scott, Review of <title level="m">Emma</title>, in Southam, 70. </note>
               </quote> Scott’s financial metaphor is deeply apt. In Emma’s speculative imagination,
               Harriet Smith is the illegitimate offspring of aristocratic, Whig capital, of
               “nobility or wealth,”<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn2" place="foot" n="2">Austen,
                     <title level="m">Emma</title>, 404. Subsequent references are cited
                  parenthetically in the text. </note> rather than what she proves to be, the
               natural daughter of a modest “tradesman” (403). Harriet’s history is introduced
               through what the reader will come to realize is free indirect discourse: “Harriet
               Smith was the natural daughter of somebody. Somebody had placed her, several years
               back, at Mrs. Goddard’s school, and somebody had lately raised her from the condition
               of scholar to that of parlour-boarder” (68). Somebody, or a nobody: the antithetical
               possibilities vary as we imagine the voice Emma’s, or Knightley’s, or, indeed,
               Emma’s, retrospectively, once chastened by experience. In the interim Harriet
               circulates like a bank bill whose questionable legitimacy is deepened by the facility
               of her transference. I shall be arguing that the financial metaphors that pervade
                  <title level="m">Emma</title>, including the one perceptively noted by Scott, are
               not a fortuitous aspect of the novel, but a product of forces that may be said to be
               constitutive of Romanticism itself. My argument is based on the following thesis: the
               conceptual field in which forgery finds itself placed is not Romanticism’s repressed
               secret but rather its enabling condition. In <title level="m">Emma</title>’s case,
               the suspicions that attach to readily-endorsed bank bills have their origins in a
               newly shaped “social imaginary” coming to terms with “discounting” (inflation), paper
               money, and unbacked securities: phenomena following on from the suspension of
               cash-payment in 1797. </p>
            <p>The term “social imaginary” derives from Charles Taylor’s <title level="m">Modern
                  Social Imaginaries</title>. Taylor’s ultimate aim in this book is to substantiate
               his thesis that we had best speak of multiple modernities rather than a single,
               uniform one; that <emph>pace</emph> the World Bank, putting in place a modern economy is not
               simply a matter of pulling on the usual policy levers. In each culture a unique
               social imaginary is at work, producing inevitable difference. The social imaginary
               refers to the way—analogous to Benedict Anderson and communities—we imagine a
               moral order, including that which legitimates it. Taylor aims to reveal the
               historical uniqueness of the social imaginary of the West over the last four hundred
               years, to those of us who live within it, where our social imaginary has become
               second nature, and unless prodded into introspection, invisible. </p>
            <p>The broad transition Taylor has in mind, is from “Platonic-modeled orders of
               hierarchical complementarity” to a contingent model whose “two main ends, security
               and prosperity, are now the principal goals of organized society (12, 13-14). In
               contradistinction to the former, “the modern order gives no ontological status to
               hierarchy or any particular structure of differentiation” (12). Taylor refers to
               modern liberalism rising from the natural law theories of Grotius and Locke, to the
               imagining of societies composed of equal free agents who pool sovereignty in order to
               advance individual goals, en masse. We tend to think of such individualism as
               inherently atomistic, but as Taylor notes, in its original conception private ends
               and public goods found themselves in a balanced, productive tension, as it is only
               through the latter (including, notably, security) that the former may be realized. </p>
            <p>If one were thinking of the modern, Western, moral order as a system, it would be
               “structuralist” in that no element would have an a priori meaning, but gains
               significance as it furthers or hinders the ultimate goals of prosperity and security.
               Originally the preserve of a few philosophers, the ideas underlying the modern
               Western order migrate “from one niche to many, and from moral theory to social
               imaginary” (6). However, remarkably, a third axis is at work. Summing up his
               distinctions, Taylor notes “that an idea of moral or political order can either be
               ultimate”, as in eschatology, “or for the here and now, and if the latter, it can
               either be hermeneutic or prescriptive” (7). The modern idea of order begins as a
               hermeneutic inquiry into the origin and nature of the “unquestioned legitimacy”
               underlying governments. But over time the “hermeneutic of legitimation” found in
               natural law theory travels along its axis towards prescription, so that notions of
               fundamental equality between social agents and the consensual nature of legitimacy
               become ethical constraints, taking on revolutionary force in the process. </p>
            <p>Taylor employs the term “social imaginary” because he wants to avoid the idealist
               pitfalls of “culture” and “ideology”, both of which he sees as covertly teleological.
               His definition is worth attending to: <quote>By social imaginary, I mean something
                  much broader and deeper than intellectual schemes people may entertain when they
                  think about social reality in a disengaged mode. I am thinking, rather, of the
                  ways people imagine their social existence, how they fit together with others, how
                  things go on between them and their fellows, the expectations that normally met,
                  and the deeper normative notions and images that underlie these expectations.
                  (23)</quote> Taylor’s project is emphatically not a history of ideas (although it
               may be mistaken for such at first glance). He does not believe that natural law
               theory accounts for, or explains, the Western modern order. The task of explanation,
               rather, would fall on why the theory moved along its “three axes” into the Western
               social imaginary, from few to many, abstraction to practice, hermeneutic to
               prescription. While Taylor argues that the materialist substrate is an essential part
               of the story, arguments predicated on materialism as the primum mobile inevitably
               traduce the complexity of the process. By the same token “culture” is an unhelpful
               metaphor, suggesting, as it does, something contained, with a singular axis of
               causality, of a medium in which agents act on objects (think petri dish). Taylor’s
               preferred term is “background”, a philosophical concept meaning “that largely
               unstructured and inarticulate understanding of our whole situation, within which
               particular features of our world show up for us in the sense they have. It can never
               be adequately expressed in the form of explicit doctrines because of its unlimited
               and indefinite nature”. Hence the need to speak of an “imaginary” rather than a
               “theory” (30). </p>
            <p> The Romantic era looms large in all of Taylor’s many accounts of the history of the
               instantiation of what is now a salient aspect of our social imaginary, something we
               familiarly know as the “economy“.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn3" place="foot" n="3"
                  >Besides <title level="m">Social Imaginaries</title>, see Taylor 1989 and 2007.
               </note> For Taylor it is a period of late transition and early consolidation, and
               therefore Janus faced. Thus <title level="m">Emma</title>, which contains at once
               “hierarchical complementarity” and the new moral order of equal acquisitive agents, a
               tension comically evident, as we shall discover, in Emma’s transparent snobbery. So
               when I say that in <title level="m">Emma</title> suspicions attaching to
               readily-endorsed bank bills ramify within a newly shaped “social imaginary”, I mean a
               process that goes very deep.</p>
            <p>The point can be illustrated through an argument Lynn Hunt makes about how, for the
               population at large, the French Revolution was mediated through the family romance
               (Hunt). Prior to the Revolution the king was commonly regarded as the father of the
               nation; by the same token his subjects were his children. The point Hunt stresses is
               that within the social imaginary the relationship pulsed with literal, rather than
               figurative, force. </p>
            <p>Within the Pre-Revolutionary mentality, legitimacy was a concrete affair, insofar as
               it could be materialized as blood. The shift to thinking of citizenship and state
               legitimacy in abstract terms, as matters of universal principles and rights, or,
               indeed, as the expression of Rousseau’s “general will”, was, indeed, revolutionary.
               In support of her argument Hunt provides evidence of the profound disorientation of
               the common citizenry, who felt bereft, indeed “orphaned”, by the king’s execution;
               they had severed connections with a visible “father”, and were now at sea with a host
               of abstractions. In Taylor’s terms the transition was from a previous model of
               “hierarchical complementarity”, concretely instantiated in the king’s body, haloed by
               an ontological investment, to a new order predicated on the universal human rights of
               equality, security and prosperity, so that we may concur with Saree Makdisi who
               argues, along with Burke, that Jacobins were the advanced guard of economic
               liberalism (Makdisi). The point of introducing Hunt’s perspective, is that it cues us
               into what this crisis in the social imaginary meant at the level of narrative: an
               explosion of stories of families and fathers, rebellions and repressions, unities and
               disunities, in which the paternal figure was divested of its ontological aura through
               the father’s endlessly repeated symbolic decapitation in the Gothic plots of the
               Minerva school; plots turning on sons and daughters somehow prevailing in their quest
               to marry in accordance with their emotional needs, rather than the family’s dynastic
               ambitions (Miles 2002). In Freudian terms, it’s as if contemporary readers
               administered their own talking cure, vicariously experienced through endless symbolic
               repetitions of the new order’s primal scene where abstract right was conceived (in
               the daughter’s stubborn adherence to her love), and the king’s body dispatched (in
               the father’s failure to impose his will), the whole psychomachia mediated through the
               cultural debris of an exploded feudal system. </p>
            <p>I want to argue that the change in the social imaginary attendant upon the suspension
               of cash payments was equally far reaching, as value lost its concrete embodiments in
               favour of abstract promises: where there used to be stamped portions of precious
               metal, there were now paper bank notes unsecured by specie. This was hardly a
               phenomenon anyone could have missed, who lived through it. Prior to the suspension
               country banks were prohibited from issuing notes smaller than five pounds, while the
               Bank of England had none smaller than ten. According to John Clapham’s history of the
               Bank of England, up until 1797 “Englishmen of the rank and file—wage-earners and
               small traders—knew little of paper money” (Clapham 2-3). Over a period of twenty
               years paper or its substitutes replaced traditional coins: “Gradually the age became
               one of bank notes and tradesmen’s tokens and Spanish dollars stamped with the head of
               King George III and put into circulation by the Bank in England” (Clapham, 4). There
               was an explosion of country banks, made possible by the relaxation in the rules
               governing the supply of money (an explosion involving Austen’s brother, Henry). The
               surge in the supply of money was in turn linked to a rapid cycle of boom and bust, of
               speculative fevers momentarily cured by bone-numbing recessions. The journals were
               filled with the “bullion controversy”—with the first finest hour of the dismal
               science, as it came to grips, conceptually, with the underlying causes of boom and
               bust, “inflation” and “deflation” (as yet, not the common currency of economic
               discussion). Meanwhile, the suspension was a forger’s charter. When bank notes were
               of large denomination, counterfeiting was difficult, as palming-off a dodgy note was
               an act you did up close and personal: only with the emergence of small notes in
               common and daily use could you anonymously slip them into circulation, and then
               disappear; hence, as Ian Haywood explains, the draconian practice of stringing up any
               unfortunate wretch insufficiently eagle-eyed to catch the minute signs of the
               counterfeiter’s art.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn4" place="foot" n="4">See
                  Haywood’s essay in this volume. </note> Before special paper, with unreproducible
               water-marks (let alone holograms) counterfeiters were on the whole even more skilled
               than their engraving counterparts in the treasury; and whatever the treasury could
               do, as regards intricate patterns and secret signs, the counterfeiters could do as
               well, if not better (Dick, 389). Hence one of the more unlikely public movements of
               the age: the societies forming for the prevention of the wholesale hanging of
               market-traders caught with bent bills. </p>
            <p>Romanticism—at any rate, Romantic ideology—may be understood as the dream of
               achieving permanent or transcendent value against a background of value rendered
               radically unstable and contested (McGann). In this respect forgery signifies the
               possibility of the endemic instability that fed the transcendental desires that
               peculiarly distinguish Romanticism. Although this is a version of the familiar story
               told about Romanticism—a story about the rise of secularization, with temporal
               theories of value replacing atemporal ones—the constitutive role of the bullion
               controversy (with its concomitant ills, such as the forgery epidemic) as a necessary
               condition for the historical rise of Romanticism has only recently been directly
               addressed, for example in Mary Poovey’s <title level="m">Genres of the Credit
                  Economy</title>, and in Alex Dick’s forthcoming <title level="m">Realms of Gold:
                  British Romanticism and the Standard of Value</title>.</p>
            <p>My aim is not to change prevailing notions of Romanticism so much as it is to change
               prevailing notions of forgery in relation to it, from forgery as Romanticism’s dark
               other (an expression of the critical imaginary understandably present in, for
               instance, Nick Groom’s ground-breaking 1994 issue of <title level="j"
                  >Angelaki</title> devoted to the subject) to forgery as a logically necessary
               constituent of Romanticism. In effect I am positing the interchangeability of two
               systems of value: the aesthetic, and the economic (see Thompson). As disciplines, or
               fields, aesthetics and economics both famously come into being (as regards their
               modern shape) around the same time: think, for instance, of Adam Smith’s <title
                  level="m">Wealth of Nations</title> (1776) and Lord Kames' <title level="m">The
                  Elements of Criticism</title> (1762). Each needs the other, to think itself into
               being.</p>
            <p>The hinge, linking the two systems, is forgery. In recent years there has been a
               great deal of critical interest in the history of literary forgery, an interest K.K.
               Ruthven links to “two intellectual developments in the final decades of the twentieth
               century”: “post-structuralist critical theory” and the “continuing anatomy of . . . 'the
               postmodern condition'“. The first forced a rethinking of traditional assumptions
               about “authorship, originality, authenticity and value” while the second
               fundamentally undermined commonsense apprehensions of the real and the simulated
               (Ruthven, 63). The eighteenth-century habit of positing the ideal of “original
               genius” axiomatically produced the allied condition of anxiety about its failure,
               which is to say, fakery, or, where it was with malice prepense, forgery.
               Post-structuralist critical theory certainly pounced on this hare, once set running;
               my aim, rather, is to take us back to a moment where a linkage was made, that now
               seems self-evident, but was hardly so at the time: the linkage, that is, between
               forgery in its dominant figurative sense (the unauthorized replication of bank
               notes), and a secondary one: the unauthorized replication of literary property.
               Originally a forger was simply a metal-basher, and forgery “the action or craft of
               forging metal”. So what connects the innocent act of making something (a poem, say,
               attributed to a long-dead poet), with the criminal act of counterfeiting bank bills?
               Blackstone in his <title level="m">Commentaries</title> (1769) appears to provide an
               answer: “the fraudulent making or alteration of a writing to the prejudice of another
               man’s right.”<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn5" place="foot" n="5">See the entry on
                  forgery in the <title level="m">Oxford English Dictionary</title>. </note> Prior
               to the suspension of 1797, most forged bills were to the detriment of a named
               individual, fraudulently endorsed (rather than to a faceless bank). Blackstone’s
               legal definition stretches to encompass both robbery through counterfeit bank notes,
               and the theft of literary property though imposition; both the Reverend Dodds, and
               Chatterton. But of course, only Dodds was stretched, and not just because Chatterton
               checked out early. The famous cases of literary forgery in the eighteenth century did
               not involve infringements of copyright “to the prejudice of another man’s right”.
               Rowley’s poems not having been previously published, the copyright could not have
               been snapped up by a publisher, so none was injured. The same was true of Ireland’s
               Shakespeare forgeries, where the worst that could be said, was that Ireland had
               trampled on Shakespeare’s “moral rights”, as later iterations of the copyright law
               would come to call the right of not having one’s work traduced, and its brand
               tarnished, by fraudsters; but in the 1790’s this concept lay in the future. When
               Horace Walpole famously claimed that all inmates of the house of forgery were
               relations, he was the one doing the stretching (see Baines). The circle he was
               drawing, was greatly in excess of what was then logically, or legally, possible. We
               do well to listen to natural contrarians, such as Cobbett, who is here righteously
               tearing strips off the fools who rounded on W. H. Ireland, once his ingenuity as a
               Shakespeare-basher was revealed: <quote>instantly the base wretches, from every
                  quarter, poured in upon him; instead of admiring his ingenuity, and apologising,
                  as well as they could, for their own folly, in having been Shakespeare-mad, they
                  pitched upon him, like tigers, called him a forger, called him an impostor, and
                  almost hunted him from the face of the earth.</quote> Cobbett continues:
                  <quote>With regard to Mr. Ireland, let these facts be borne in mind; that he was
                  no forger, no impostor, according to the usual meaning of those words; that he had
                  a perfect right to put forth the publications he put forth; that there was nothing
                  illegal and nothing immoral in any of his proceedings as to this matter; that
                  Doctors Wharton and Parr were deemed the two most learned men in the Kingdom; that
                  they declared and certified that it was their conviction that no human being could
                  write those manuscripts but Shakespeare; that when Mr Ireland was discovered to be
                  the real author, the whole band of literary ruffians fell upon him, and would have
                  destroyed him, if they had been able, with as little remorse as men destroy a mad
                     dog...<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn6" place="foot" n="6">The article is W.H.
                     Ireland’s obituary from Cobbett’s <title level="j">Register</title>, but is
                     pasted in, without date or page numbers, in British Library Manuscript BL 37,
                     831. </note>
               </quote> Cobbett is correct. “According to the usual meaning” of the word, Ireland
               was no forger. But in the minds of those hunting him down, like a mad dog, he was,
               because the concept of forgery had been stretched to link together the aesthetic with
               the monetary value the aesthetic generates (where the aesthetic is arbitrarily
               confined to a single, “original” source). From Cobbett’s perspective, these are
               heterogeneous notions yoked together by force. The “con” was not Ireland pretending
               to be Shakespeare, but the pretence of a rare and precious literary value only the
               cognoscenti could discern. Ireland’s true crime, Cobbett suggests, was his laying
               bare the pretence. </p>
            <p>One could say that mine is a secularization argument; that the late Enlightenment
               throws us into a state of irony, contingency, and subjectivity; and the hinged
               relationship between numismatic and literary forgery is just another indication that
               we are in the free-floating realm of shifting values. But I prefer to put it like
               this: the suspension of cash payments ushered in a period in which the modern
               economic cycle first began to intensify, a period, that is, of rapid capital growth,
               speculation, and savage retrenchments; it was one where paper replaced metal as
               common, circulating tokens of value; and where the economic discourse of value (on
               why, for instance, gold and silver have value in the first place: the common answer
               looping back to the scarcity-value attendant upon the limits of South American mines
               and the labour that worked them) infiltrates other discursive systems of value. All
               three developments altered the social imaginary, not least through the pervasive
               example of economic agents rising and falling, as the economy booms and busts, along
               with the allied lesson that the modern moral order presupposes deep interconnection
               and dependence. And I put it like that, because it is the best way of understanding
               something really peculiar about Jane Austen’s <title level="m">Emma</title>.</p>
            <p>And that is, that <title level="m">Emma</title> is a deeply meditated work on the
               same interpenetration of literary and economic systems of value that we found in
               Cobbett’s analysis of Ireland’s persecution. We can start with the fact that Highbury
               is sixteen miles South of London, in Surrey—insofar as Austen had a location in
               mind, it was Leatherhead, the epicentre of what is now the stockbroker belt. The
               obvious point—for contemporary readers, screamingly so—is that the Woodhouses are
                  rentiers.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn7" place="foot" n="7">Beth Tobin
                  speculates that the Woodhouse fortune “was most likely made by someone who retired
                  to Highbury, not far from London and its money market, where he could have bought
                  and sold stocks in corporations and colonialist ventures like the East India or
                  South Seas Companies, or lent money to the government for William III’s and Anne’s
                  wars” (Tobin 238).</note> In the following passage, the humour is very broad
               indeed. Emma is wondering to herself about what could have possessed Mr. Elton into
               imagining himself her equal: <quote>Perhaps it was not fair to expect him to feel how
                  very much he was her inferior in talent, and all the elegancies of mind. The very
                  want of such equality might prevent his perception of it; but he must know that in
                  fortune and consequence she was greatly his superior. He must know that the
                  Woodhouses had been settled for several generations at Hartfield, the younger
                  branch of a very ancient family—and that the Eltons were nobody. The landed
                  property of Hartfield certainly was inconsiderable, being but a sort of notch in
                  the Donwell Abbey estate, to which all the rest of Highbury belonged; but their
                  fortune, from other sources, was such as to make them scarcely secondary to
                  Donwell Abbey itself, in every other kind of consequence... (153)</quote> We never
               learn about these mysterious “other sources”—Emma is doubtless vague herself—but
               almost certainly the Woodhouses have their money in the funds: and like many others
               living the good life among England’s ancient gentry, they are but one or two
               generations removed from the trade in which they earned their pile, before “cashing
               out”. As Shinobu Minma observes, “we may assume that the progenitor of the Hartfield
               Woodhouses was a younger brother in a landed family, who entered trade, made his
               fortune, purchased the Hartfield estate (from the Knightleys no doubt) and settled in
                  Highbury.”<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn8" place="foot" n="8">Quoted in
                  Parrinder, 198. </note>
            </p>
            <p> Of course stock-jobbers and kindred scoundrels are always trying to cash-out: as the
               current joke has it, they made off, like Madoff. The eighteenth-century had their own
               word for the phenomenon: “realise”. Here is the OED defining the word: <quote>To
                  convert (securities, paper money, etc.) into cash, or (property of any kind) into
                  money. After F. <emph>réaliser</emph>, first used <emph>c</emph> 1719 in connexion
                  with the speculations over Law’s scheme,<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn9"
                     place="foot" n="9"> John Law’s Mississippi scheme in France was the inspiration
                     for the South Sea bubble. </note> in the sense of converting securities into
                  cash or permanently valuable property. Hence Johnson, perhaps influenced by the
                  phrase “real property”, gives as one sense of the word “To convert money into
                  land”; this, however, is unsupported by quotations.</quote> In Highbury, everyone
               is trying to realize themselves (apart from George Knightley, who has the opposite
               problem to contend with, of turning land to cash). Thus we learn that Mr Weston had
               “realized an easy competence—enough to secure the purchase of a little estate
               adjoining Highbury, which he had always longed for” (16). Buoyed by the unexpected
               profits of their London “House”, meaning business, the Coles are looking to realize
               their fortune, by buying property in Highbury and insinuating themselves into the
               best circles, to Emma’s chagrin. The obvious point, for a contemporary reader, is
               that Emma is drawing distinctions without a difference; or rather, the slight
               difference of the Woodhouses being superior to the Coles, by dint of cashing out a
               generation or two earlier.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn10" place="foot" n="10">For
                  a contemporary notice commenting on the middling nature of Highbury’s residents,
                  and the slight degree of social difference among them, see Anon (1816). </note>
               The irony is equally broad in this passage (Emma is explaining to Harriet why Robert
               Martin is not a desirable catch): <quote>“Well, and that is as early as most men can
                  afford to marry, who are not born to an independence. Mr. Martin, I imagine, has
                  his fortune entirely to make--cannot be at all beforehand with the world. Whatever
                  money he might come into when his father died, whatever his share of the family
                  property, it is, I dare say, all afloat, all employed in his stock, and so forth;
                  and though, with diligence and good luck, he may be rich in time, it is next to
                  impossible that he should have <emph>realised</emph> any thing yet.” (74) (my
                  italics).</quote> This is the second instance of “realize”, used in its modern,
               financial sense, found in the novel. Emma is speculating about Robert Martin’s
               speculation, his attempt at the “high farming” as it was called, that was then
               transforming British agriculture, as the speculative boom involved capital investment
               in land, in new farming methods that were reaping strong returns owing to the
               unprecedented high prices in corn.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn11" place="foot"
                  n="11">For instance, in 1815, Thomas Malthus observed that there had been "a great
                  consequent extension of cultivation and improvement," especially over the last
                  seven years: "the system of spirited improvement and high farming, as it is
                  technically called, has been principally encouraged by the progressive rise of
                  prices..." (Quoted Anon 1815, 493).</note> Or were the prices simply inflated? As
               Niall Ferguson points out, at around this time (just before the end of the Napoleonic
               wars) the Funds were a mere 60% of their historic value, undermined by inflation
               (Ferguson, 80). At the point of the novel’s writing, rentiers such as the Woodhouses
               are on their way down, while high farmers and capital speculators such as Robert
               Martin are on their way up. Emma notes this without quite taking it in (she predicts
               Robert Martin will be rich in time). </p>
            <p>How broad is the irony? “. . .his share of the family property . . . is . . . all afloat, all employed in his
               stock”. Note the pun on stock (obviously livestock, but also the financial variety).
               The pun develops the double meaning of Robert Martin as a high farmer (a passion he
               incidentally shares with Mr. Knightley), but it also brings out this latent irony:
               Emma is talking as the very thing she is: a speculator, who is, herself, the daughter
               of speculators (that is, business people), who have realised themselves, having
               cashed out.</p>
            <p>The novel has a word for this conjunction of the two senses of speculation: Emma,
               we are told, is an “imaginist...on fire with speculation and foresight!” (295). The
               conjunction is also evident in the novel’s core plot device, where Emma speculates on
               Harriet Smith’s origin. Emma prefers romance (Harriet is the natural daughter of a
               Merchant Prince, or Whig Grandee, someone, ideally, combining both nobility and
               wealth, so “bleaching” the stain of her dodgy origin [404]), but has to learn
               novelistic realism (Harriet’s father is a tradesman decent enough to remain
               anonymous). In its sly way, <title level="m">Emma</title> is also a novel about novel-writing. As someone who
               speculates, and predicts marriage, Emma is linked—at least theoretically—with the
               main business of the novel, of narrating marriage. When she takes on her protégé,
               Harriet Smith, the theoretical point becomes practical: in developing Harriet, Emma
               speculates through the medium of romance conventions, much as Catherine Morland does.
               She views the world through the prism of the wrong kind of novels. At the same time,
               the Harriet Smith romance encapsulates the main fear of Tory ideology: that feckless,
               irresponsible, illegitimate capital (engendered in the City) will be set lose to
               circulate freely, transforming the shires, by turning the social order upside down.
               With this allegorical dimension in mind, the gypsy episode is ironically inverted:
               the real menace, is not the raggedy offspring of a few tinkers, but Harriet Smith,
               the ambulatory bank note, the daughter of God-knows-who, who promises capital
               transformation (in Emma’s speculation), a threat further ironically intensified given
               the hero’s association with the Churchills. Frank Churchill, who gallantly disperses
               the gypsies, is the adopted son of the self-same class of Whig nabobs who are the
               putative parents of illegitimate Harriet. Where legitimacy is defined by land, a form
               of property where the social contract (of obligations and responsibilities, as well
               as privilege) is legible to all, capital has the taint of illegitimacy, or
               irresponsible pleasure. Frank himself generates the hugger-mugger Tory ideologues
               typically associated with large city fortunes. In other words, <title level="m"
                  >Emma</title> reprises the plot of <title level="m">Northanger Abbey</title> where
               a romance-addled heroine is unable to recognize the very thing that obsesses her when
               it’s in front of her face: in Emma’s case, the perils of new (City) money and
               marriage across class lines. Even as she spurns the Coles, as socially illegitimate
               new money, she promotes Harriet (its epitome). </p>
            <p>One could argue that Harriet is a counterfeit banknote, in that she is, from Emma’s
               perspective, a “fake”, but that is taking the allegory too far. The point, rather, is that two competing discourses inhabit the same space in the novel, and through the punning
               capacity of language, often the same words. You can try the experiment. Get an e-text
               of the novel and plug in “resources”, “speculate”, “improve”, “stock”, “credit”,
               “realize”: the terms recur, pointedly. The competing discourses are drawn from
               aesthetics and economics, where the correction of one kind of speculation (the
               economic) is linked to the improvement of another (novel-writing). </p>
            <p>Austen’s fascination with the dismal science arguably pervades her work, but most
               notably <title level="m">Emma</title>, <title level="m">Mansfield Park</title>, and
                  <title level="m">Sanditon</title>. It is not a sign of her famed Enlightenment
               realism; rather, it is where she is at her most Romantic, for it is through her
               economic interests that she finds a language for exploring a world where value is
               inescapably contingent. Contingent value is not thematized in her novels—rather it
               is part of the web-and-woof of a social imaginary that in a manner of speaking thinks
               itself out through the medium of her novels.</p>
            <p> I want to conclude by considering the aspect of the novel that most severely tries
               my interpretation: the idealization of Knightley and Donwell Abbey. The marriage
               between Emma and Knightley repairs the “notch” in the latter’s property, making it
               whole again, while her thirty thousand pounds is safely placed in the service of an
               ancient estate, the pinnacle of a “well-connected” community presumably stretching
               back to the English Reformation and the dissolution of the monasteries. In his brisk
               pedestrianism, frugal habits, and active concern for all the “citizens of Highbury”,
               Knightley appears to be the embodiment of the responsible, enlivening spirit that
               draws the community together, transforming it (through self-regulation) into a living
               example of the Tory ideal. Emma’s epiphany, when she strolls around Knightley’s
               grounds, as she escapes the wretched Mrs. Elton and her inane mercantile chatter,
               appears Austen’s own, ventriloquized by Edmund Burke: “It was a sweet view—sweet
               to the eye and the mind. English verdure, English culture, English comfort, seen
               under a sun bright, without being oppressive” (315). At the heart of this glorious,
               organic, vital media is a crucial representation of social relation: “The considerable
               slope, at nearly the foot of which the Abbey stood, gradually acquired a steeper form
               beyond its grounds; and at half a mile distant was a bank of considerable abruptness
               and grandeur, well clothed with wood; and at the bottom of this bank, favourably
               placed and sheltered, rose the Abbey-Mill Farm, with meadows in front, and the river
               making a close and handsome curve around it” (315). Knightley, and Robert Martin, the
               Abbey and the Abbey-Mill farm, seem chthonically present, as if spontaneously grown
               from the sinuous earth, as close as one can get, in a realist novel, to an
               instantiation of the ontic force of “hierarchical complementarity”. On this reading,
               the mysterious power that makes the English home counties the home counties of
               England, and nowhere else—continuous across space and time, a unique identity
               enduring through the aeons—is made manifest in the novel as the healing force that
               repairs notches in ancient estates, excludes frightful sorts like the Eltons, while
               lodging dangerous females (wild imaginists and ambulatory banknotes alike) snugly
               within the confines of appropriate marriages. </p>
            <p> This “heritage” fantasy is indisputably at work in the novel, but it works as one
               pole in irresolvable tension with another reality, of independent, and equal,
               economic actors, engaged in a mutual-aid society, as they seek to prosper in giddy
               financial times. For if <title level="m">Emma</title> was written at a time of faltering boom, it was quickly
               followed by a spectacular bust.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn12" place="foot" n="12"
                  >For the timing of the novel’s composition see Miles (2003-04). </note> Hence the
               stress on what Robert Martin and George Knightley have in common: an insatiable
               appetite for “information”, especially information relating to “improvement”—another of the novel’s key terms. “Improvement” resonates ironically in the text, as
               the watch word of enclosures, engrossments, and the capital transformation of land at
               a time of rising prices and rents: it’s what Robert Martin does with his sheep, and
               other farmers with oxen, and what Emma does with Harriet, even as Mr. Knightley
               wishes that Emma would exert more effort in her own reading, to improve herself. When
               Mr. Knightley says he can as “ill spare Robert Martin” (397) as his canny steward,
               William Larkins, he means, not the umbilical connection of master and tenant farmer,
               but a collaborator in their joint project of improving their lands and profits. The
               social imaginary in which <title level="m">Emma</title> ramifies, is a modern one of
               equal, mutually dependent actors where the older moral outlook exists as an outdated
               cast of mind satirized through Emma’s snobbery, and as an idealization ironically
               presented as just that: the era of “gold standards” has passed, and ever-shifting
               relation ushered in. As Alex Dick notes, the “gold standard” was first conceptualized
               in the course of the bullion controversy, at which point it was retrospectively
               projected onto the past, onto the era preceding the suspension of cash-payments in
               1797, as a fantasy of origin.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn13" place="foot" n="13"
                  >See the essay in this volume.</note>
            </p>
            <p>J.G.A. Pocock influentially argued that the rise of a polite and commercial society
               in the eighteenth century eclipsed the mentality in which land was automatically
               assumed to be the proper source of wealth and the true foundation of political
                  legitimacy.<note resp="editors" xml:id="ftn14" place="foot" n="14"> See Pocock, who
                  makes it clear that the ideal of a settled landed interest was a later
                  retrospective simplification of the past.</note> But as Beth Tobin notes, although
               this ideal had waned, it began to wax after the post-Waterloo economic crash as an
               ideological defence of the corn laws that were used to prop up farming prices, thus
               ensuring the continued pre-eminence of “land” in the British social imaginary (Tobin,
               249). At this juncture the ideological formation assumed its modern form: the Tory
               ideal of the “knights of the shires” as the true pillars of English society. <title
                  level="m">Emma</title> puts both things in play: the fantasy (the gold standard of
               “land”; Donwell Abbey; the immutabilities of rank) and its opposite (contingency; the
               stockbroker belt; permeable class). It is in this tension that Austen finds her
               Romantic irony.</p>

            <div type="citations">
               <head>Works Cited</head>

               <listBibl>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Anon</author>
                        <title level="a">Rev. of Thomas Malthus, <title level="m">Observations on
                              the Effects of the Corn Laws ... and The Grounds of an Opinion on the
                              Policy of Restricting the Importation of Foreign Corn</title></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Edinburgh Review</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">24. xlviii</biblScope>
                           <date>Feb. 1815</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">491-505</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Anon</author>
                        <title level="a">Rev. of <title level="m">Emma</title></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Champion</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">31</biblScope>
                           <date>1816</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">102-3</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Austen, Jane</author>
                        <title level="m">Emma</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Samuelian, Kristin Flieger</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Peterborough, Ontario</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Broadview Editions</publisher>
                           <date>2004</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Baines, Paul</author>
                        <title level="m">The House of Forgery in 18th‑Century Britain</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Aldershot</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>
                           <date>1999</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Clapham, John</author>
                        <title level="m">The Bank of England: A History. Volume 2: 1797-1914</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1966</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Dick, Alex. J</author>
                        <title level="a">'The Ghost of Gold': Forgery Trials and the Standard of
                           Value in Shelley's <title level="m">The Mask of Anarchy</title></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">European Romantic Review</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">18</biblScope>
                           <date>2007</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">381-400</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Ferguson, Niall</author>
                        <title level="m">The Ascent of Money: A Financial History of the
                           World</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Penguin Press</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Hunt, Lynn</author>
                        <title level="m">The Family Romance of the French Revolution</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Berkeley</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of California Press</publisher>
                           <date>1993</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Makdisi, Saree</author>
                        <title level="m">William Blake and the Impossible history of the
                           1790's</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                           <date>2003</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>McGann, Jerome</author>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Ideology: A Critical Investigation</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                           <date>1983</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Miles, Robert</author>
                        <title level="a">'A Fall in Bread': Speculation and the Real in <title
                              level="m">Emma</title></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">NOVEL: A Forum on Fiction </title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">37.1-2</biblScope>
                           <date>2003-04</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">66-85</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Miles, Robert</author>
                        <title level="a">1790’s: The Effulgence of Gothic</title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="m">The Cambridge Companion to Gothic Fiction</title>
                        <editor role="editor">Hogle, Jerrold E.</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2002</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">41-62</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Parrinder, Patrick</author>
                        <title level="m">Nation and Novel: The English Novel from its Origins to the
                           Present Day</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2006</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Pocock, J.G.A.</author>
                        <title level="m">Virtue, Commerce, and History: Essays on Political Thought
                           and History, Chiefly in the Eighteenth Century</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1976</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Poovey, Mary</author>
                        <title level="m">Genres of the Credit Economy: Mediating Value in
                           Eighteenth- and Nineteenth-Century Britain</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Chicago University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Ruthven, K. K.</author>
                        <title level="m">Faking It</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2001</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <editor role="editor">Southam, B. C.</editor>
                        <title level="m">The Critical Heritage: Jane Austen, Volume 1,
                           1811-1870</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Taylor and Francis</publisher>
                           <date>2005</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Taylor, Charles</author>
                        <title level="m">Sources of the Self: of the Self: The Making of Modern
                           Identity</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1989</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Taylor, Charles</author>
                        <title level="m">Modern Social Imaginaries</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Durham and London</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2004</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Taylor, Charles</author>
                        <title level="m">A Secular Age</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                           <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                           <date>2007</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Thompson, James</author>
                        <title level="m">Models of Value: Eighteenth-Century Political Economy and
                           the Novel</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <publisher>Durham and London</publisher>
                           <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                           <date>1996</date>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>

                  <biblStruct>
                     <analytic>
                        <author>Tobin, Beth Fowkes</author>
                        <title level="a">The Moral and Political Economy of Property in Austen’s
                              <title level="m">Emma</title></title>
                     </analytic>
                     <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Eighteenth-Century Fiction</title>
                        <imprint>
                           <biblScope type="vol">2.3</biblScope>
                           <date>1990</date>
                           <biblScope type="pp">234-35</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                     </monogr>
                  </biblStruct>
               </listBibl>

            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
